<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20061023.EN" lang="en" date="2006-10-23" place="Strasbourg" edition="OJ edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Resumption of the session">
    <intervention id="1-004" speaker_id="28267" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">I declare resumed the session of the European Parliament adjourned on Thursday 12 October 2006.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Approval of Minutes of previous sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Welcome">
    <intervention id="1-007" speaker_id="28267" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Ladies and gentlemen, I would like to inform you that we have a visit by a Delegation from the Japanese Parliament this afternoon and that that Delegation is in the official gallery, headed by Mr Tsushima Tuji, a great friend of Europe.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
      <p sl="unknown">The Delegation of our Japanese colleagues is taking part in the 27th interparliamentary meeting between the European Parliament and Japan.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">We have a long tradition of dialogue between the European Parliament and the Japanese Parliament. Initially it dealt with strictly commercial issues, but now it has branched out into many issues of concern to our respective people.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">We are delighted that our dialogue with Japan is being enhanced, within a context in which it is increasingly necessary for us to work together towards international security and stability.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">We welcome you, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Membership of committees and delegations: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. Signature of acts adopted under codecision: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Announcement by the President: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Relations between the European Union and Russia following the assassination of journalist Anna Politkovskaya (motions for resolution tabled)"/>
  <section id="creitem8" title="8. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem9" title="9. Petitions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem10" title="10. Transfers of appropriations: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="11. Texts of agreements forwarded by the Council: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem12" title="12. Action taken on Parliament’s resolutions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem13" title="13. Written declarations (Rule 116): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem14" title="14. Order of business">
    <intervention id="1-018" speaker_id="28267" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The final version of the draft agenda for the current part-session, as drawn up by the Conference of Presidents at its meeting of Thursday 19 October 2006 pursuant to Rules 130 and 131 of the Rules of Procedure, has been distributed. The following amendments have been proposed:</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Wednesday:</p>
      <p sl="unknown">In view of the large number of debates scheduled for Wednesday afternoon, and having sought the opinion of the political groups, I propose that we extend the debates until 6 p.m., rather than 5.30, and Questions to the Council will therefore take place between 6 and 7 p.m.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Are there are any comments?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-019" speaker_id="4535" name="Philip Bushill-Matthews" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, this is not the first time I have pointed out that whenever somebody suddenly wants to find some extra time from somewhere on the agenda, it always seems to be Question Time that is the victim. That is not fair. I believe that if Question Time starts half an hour later, it should continue for an extra half an hour at the end. That is my proposal.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-020" speaker_id="28267" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Good, I personally have no objection; we shall propose to the Council that it take part in Questions to the Council for an extra half an hour; that seems very appropriate.</p>
      <a text="(Parliament accepted the proposal)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-021" speaker_id="4560" name="Toine Manders" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="nl">Mr President, according to the agenda, an oral question was going to be put on the subjects of gambling policy and infringement procedures; on Thursday, for obscure reasons, the Conference of Presidents removed it from the agenda even though we had included it in the compromise and therefore had to delete the reference to the infringement procedures. The question is now off the table. I should like to propose making the Conference of Presidents’ meetings public in future, for then we could be given some insight into the reasons and arguments adduced by one side or the other in them. After all, we have also demanded that the Council’s meetings be made public too. I would therefore express the wish that the Conference of Presidents’ meetings be made public in future, so that we can avoid the underhand scheming that we are witnessing at the moment.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-022" speaker_id="28267" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Let us see whether your argument is justified. Are you saying that a question to the Council appeared on the agenda and that the Conference of Presidents decided to remove it?</p>
      <p sl="unknown">I shall ask the secretariat to look into what you have told us, and then we will see what we can do about it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-023" speaker_id="4538" name="Malcolm Harbour" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the remarks by my colleague, Mr Manders, did not come over very clearly via the interpretation. What we are talking about is a question to the Commission on gambling and relevant infringement procedures.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am a coordinator on the Committee on the Internal Market and Consumer Protection, as is Mr Manders. As the joint authors of this question, we understood that it was going to be on the agenda tonight when Mr McCreevy was here, and that was approved through the system. I am astonished to find that it has apparently been withdrawn at the request of the Conference of Presidents and I cannot understand why. Nobody has talked to me or Mr Manders as the authors of the question, or to any of my colleagues. Mr McCreevy from the Commission is ready to answer the question and yet for some inexplicable reason the Conference of Presidents has totally removed it from the agenda. Perhaps you can explain why?</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-024" speaker_id="28267" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Yes, the Conference of Presidents decided to remove this question from the agenda.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-025" speaker_id="4429" name="Robert Goebbels" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, I may be able to clarify things. I replaced Mr Schulz at the Conference of Presidents and I asked for this question, which is on this evening’s agenda, to be postponed until a later sitting so as to allow Parliament to take account of the new developments in this whole affair. The Conference of President granted this request.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-026" speaker_id="28267" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">All right, the Conference of Presidents will therefore once again look into including this question in a later plenary sitting.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-027" speaker_id="4538" name="Malcolm Harbour" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, could I request, as a matter of courtesy, that the committee responsible for preparing this question – which was voted on in committee – should be informed of concerns before they come to you, so that we have a chance to talk about it. After all, we are the ones who have asked for it. We spent a long time carefully drafting the question and the Commissioner is ready to answer it. So why was it taken off the agenda without any consultation? We are responsible in the committee for the questions and we do not expect the Conference of Presidents to overrule us unilaterally on a very technical matter.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-028" speaker_id="28267" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Excuse me, but the political groups, represented in the Conference of Presidents, are supposed to inform their members of the decisions taken by the Conference. You may not agree with it, but it is the decision that the Conference of Presidents has taken, and I cannot change it now; you must appreciate that I cannot rectify that decision. It is the responsibility of the political groups to inform their members of the decisions taken in the Conference of Presidents.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Let us return to the business for Wednesday: the Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance has asked for the addition of a Commission statement on nuclear safety, relating to the ongoing problems of the Forsmark reactors, a statement that would be followed by a debate which would conclude with a motion for a resolution.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Mr Turmes has the floor to explain this proposal.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-029" speaker_id="4432" name="Claude Turmes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, we should like to add an item to Wednesday’s agenda. In the light of the incident that took place at the Forsmark reactor in July, we should like to have a discussion with the Commission on nuclear safety. This House is divided over the issue of nuclear power, but, when it comes to safety, we all want to see a transparent debate on these issues.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-030" speaker_id="997" name="Francesco Enrico Speroni" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, without compromising – as Mr Turmes would have us do – the positions of those who are in favour or against nuclear power stations, I think that we should discuss these incidents, and whether or not they are serious.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-031" speaker_id="2295" name="Hannes Swoboda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, Mr Goebbels, we made it quite plain at the Conference of Presidents that we are very definitely in favour of this issue being discussed, but not during this part-session, since we have already had to move Question Time around within the agenda for lack of sufficient time with the Council. We will certainly back the Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance – or whoever it is who ends up asking for a debate – in getting this problem put on the agenda at a proper time. We are well aware of the problem, but our position is that it does not need to be debated this week.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-033" speaker_id="4432" name="Claude Turmes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I hope that other groups will support us if we put it back on the next agenda.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-034" speaker_id="28267" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">I cannot guarantee it; in any event, you will have to discuss it with them.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-035" speaker_id="2097" name="Giles Chichester" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, perhaps I could urge Mr Turmes to raise the matter in committee first, which might be the more appropriate route to take, rather than seeking to turn this matter into an urgency, when I suspect it is not. I would welcome the opportunity to have the matter discussed in committee first, before we burden the House with it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-036" speaker_id="28267" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">I am not going to give you the floor to reply, Mr Turmes. Please keep the communications required to ascertain when and how this issue should be dealt with outside of plenary.</p>
      <a text="(The order of business was thus established)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem15" title="15. One-minute speeches on matters of political importance">
    <intervention id="1-039" speaker_id="21918" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the one-minute speeches on matters of political importance.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-040" speaker_id="23746" name="Vytautas Landsbergis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="lt">At the end of the 19th century, the future of European fascism was born in Russia. The slogan was concise and clear: 'Beat the Jews! Save Russia!' More than a hundred years later, Russian political culture can be characterised by a similar slogan of hatred: 'Beat the Georgians! Save Russia!'</p>
      <p sl="lt">The words have become a weapon for the Russian President, Foreign and Defence Ministers and the Russian Duma. Officers of lower rank and fascist gangs of bullies favour the persecution. It is not new, since the murder of people with darker faces in the streets of Russian cities has become routine.</p>
      <p sl="lt">The European Union should employ its own slogan: 'Save Russia! Stop Russian Nazism!' Therefore, representatives of the Russian Government and democratic forces should be invited to discuss how the European Union can help today’s Russia to avoid a pervasive plague of xenophobia at our goodwill common legal environment conference.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-041" speaker_id="23807" name="Magda Kósáné Kovács" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="hu">The 2006 Nobel Peace Prize was given to Muhammad Yunus, a Bangladeshi economist, and to his Grameen Bank.</p>
      <p sl="hu">The decision of the Nobel Committee has not only given cause for rejoicing, but has also shown the way and given hope to those who are striving for a humane and peaceful world. Many of us believe that poverty and social exclusion are among the root causes of war and destructive impulses. There are people who are strangers in their own land, who have lost all human contact and the chance to feel at home in the world. Muhammad Yunus’ microcredit system is not simply charity, which often helps to alleviate the guilty conscience of the well-to-do. Rather, it lends money and makes cooperation possible, as well as restoring people’s faith in future opportunities.</p>
      <p sl="hu">We, as MEPs, should look upon this year’s Peace Prize as a challenge and a task. Poverty such as exists in Bangladesh may also be found in Europe. Let us consider again and again the potential for small steps, be they in credit, entrepreneurship or increasing knowledge, since small steps can take us a long way down the path towards human dignity.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-042" speaker_id="2155" name="Graham Watson" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, this is more in the form of a question to you. I am aware that Mr Borrell Fontelles wrote to Mr Barroso and Mr Vanhanen, requesting that they communicate the names and portfolios of the two new Commissioners from Bulgaria and Romania to this House by 23 October. I would like to know whether we have heard anything about that and whether we expect the names and portfolios to be communicated to us this week.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-043" speaker_id="21918" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">I do not personally have the information you requested. I shall try to find out from the President’s office.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-044" speaker_id="4432" name="Claude Turmes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, two weeks ago, there was a train crash on the line between Luxembourg and France. That crash left six people dead and a dozen injured. I should therefore like to offer my condolences to the victims’ families. After an accident such as that, we must move forward.</p>
      <p sl="fr">One of the problems on the cross-border railways is that their safety systems vary greatly from one country to the next. Luxembourg has a different system to Belgium, which itself has a different system to France, which has a different system to Germany. Luxembourg’s railways are therefore confronted with three different systems, in addition to their own.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The best solution, after this crash, is to increase the investment in the European safety system, ERTMS. I hope that the European Commission will make Luxembourg and the wider Luxembourg region a pilot region for the introduction of new systems and arrangements.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I also believe that the flagship train, namely the TGV that will link Paris to Luxembourg as from next year, which absolutely must be …</p>
      <a text="(The President cut off the speaker)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-045" speaker_id="28514" name="Kyriacos Triantaphyllides" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, the trial started in Turkey last week of three people responsible for translating a book by the American writer Noam Chomsky into Turkish. On the basis of section 301 of the Turkish Penal Code, the publisher, translator and publishing house are accused of causing public outcry and inciting hatred against Turks and of degrading democracy and the Turkish parliament.</p>
      <p sl="el">I remember that in plenary in September we discussed section 301 and the fact that Turkey should, at long last, comply with some of the values which the European Union stands for if it wishes to acquire the European profile it yearns for. One month later, we can see that nothing has changed and that Turkish intransigence continues unabated.</p>
      <p sl="el">I ask you therefore, Mr President, if we shall continue to watch this theatre of the absurd or if we shall strengthen democratic speech by condemning this new trial which infringes freedom of speech and human rights.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-046" speaker_id="23784" name="Janusz Wojciechowski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, yesterday in Italy demonstrations took place in protest against the forced labour camps in that country. I fully support the demonstrators, but I would also like to point out that in early September my group, the Union for Europe of the Nations Group, requested a debate on the situation of foreign workers in European Union Member States. This is not just an Italian problem; it also affects other countries, some more than others. This House cannot remain silent on the matter. We need to send out an unequivocal message. In particular, we should appeal to the Member States not to allow serious infringements of human rights to occur. That is what the citizens expect, which is all the more reason for Parliament not to remain silent. I am therefore asking once again that the debate called for by the UEN Group take place.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-047" speaker_id="28587" name="Georgios Karatzaferis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, President Borrell is due to visit Athens next week as part of an official programme. I should like to ask the President to find a little time, even just half an hour, to cross over from Parliament to the Parthenon, where he will see that some of the most beautiful creations of Phidias, the greatest artist of all times, are missing. The British have taken them. They are in the British Museum. It is unthinkable that these works from the Parthenon, which is one of the Seven Wonders of the World, should be outside the Parthenon.</p>
      <p sl="el">I therefore wish to ask President Borrell to visit it, to see this repellent site and to lobby with us for the return of the sculptures which the English derisorily refer to as 'the Marbles'. They are the sculptures of the Parthenon. I repeat: one of the Seven Wonders of the World, which has been 'butchered', from which pieces have been removed which today adorn the British Museum.</p>
      <p sl="el">I appeal to all cultured people for the sculptures to be returned to the place in which they were created, to the Acropolis, to a place which all cultured people should visit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-048" speaker_id="28372" name="Ryszard Czarnecki" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, over the last two years there have been occasions when serious differences of opinion have emerged between Mr Borrell, the President of the European Parliament, and many Polish MEPs, with the majority of Polish MEPs being critical of the President’s opinion of our country. Today, however, I have to thank the President for his stance at the recent Lahti Summit, and I know I speak on behalf of many other Polish MEPs. According to the French daily Libération, Mr Borrell was one of five European leaders who dared to voice criticism of Russia. In this he was joined by the President of Poland and the Prime Ministers of Sweden, Denmark and Latvia. I would like to thank Mr Borrell for stating that the Union will not trade human rights for energy. I would also like to thank him for questioning whether Russia is still democratic. Europe will remember these pronouncements by President Borrell, and the countries of Central and Eastern Europe will remember his courage. I would therefore like to thank the President in his own language: gracias, Señor Presidente .</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-049" speaker_id="2341" name="Michael Gahler" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, I wish to inform the House that the Ethiopian authorities, last Thursday, expelled two diplomats belonging to the EU delegation. This is in connection with the arrest of Yalemzewd Bekele, an Ethiopian member of the delegation’s staff, who is accused by the authorities of active opposition to the Ethiopian Government, and who had therefore attempted to flee to Kenya.</p>
      <p sl="de">A fortnight ago, in Addis Ababa, Glenys Kinnock and I met the two diplomats and Mrs Bekele, who is currently held in the Moyale prison, and we entertain the gravest concerns about the treatment she is receiving there. This case has also been brought to the attention of the UN’s special rapporteur on torture.</p>
      <p sl="de">I urge the Commission, as a matter of urgency, to take seriously its duty of care as an employer and provide Mrs Bekele with legal counsel. The troika should also travel from Addis Ababa to Moyale, assure themselves that Mrs Bekele is physically unharmed, and demand of the Ethiopian authorities that they clarify the accusations they are levelling against her. Our President should also write a letter to his Ethiopian counterpart.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-050" speaker_id="23808" name="Csaba Sándor Tabajdi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="hu">Today, we celebrate the 50th anniversary of the Hungarian Revolution of 1956. This is not solely a Hungarian celebration, but an international one: 56 Heads of State or Government have travelled to Hungary to celebrate this day with us. The significance of this event can be compared to the Prague Spring of 1968 and to the Polish Solidarity movement, for without these three historic events, the downfall of Soviet-style communism and the changes of regime in Central Europe in 1989 and 1990 would not have been possible. The Hungarian Revolution of 1956 is unique, however, for none of the other opposition movements involved armed battle against the Soviet army, and in no other instance did a country withdraw from the Warsaw Pact and declare its neutrality. The heroes of 1956 were united in the belief that a small nation could defeat a totalitarian superpower. In 1956 our request was: 'Back to Europe!' And in 2004, with Hungary’s accession to the European Union, the legacy of 1956 was fulfilled.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-051" speaker_id="4529" name="Sarah Ludford" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I want to ask the presidency of Parliament as well as MEPs across the spectrum to continue to press for the EU, as well as the UK authorities, to try to persuade President Musharraf of Pakistan urgently to use his powers to pardon or at least commute the sentence of Mirza Tahir Hussain.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mr Hussain is a dual British-Pakistani citizen who has been on death row for 18 years, convicted of a murder of which he has always protested his innocence. Indeed, he was only convicted in the Islamic Sharia courts after having been acquitted in the normal secular courts. We learned last week that the date for his execution had been postponed for another two months, putting it beyond the date this week when the heir to the British throne, the Prince of Wales, makes an official visit to Pakistan.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, I urge everyone to keep up their efforts to persuade President Musharraf to use his undoubted powers under the Constitution to resolve this situation in the sense of justice and not just postpone the execution.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-052" speaker_id="28407" name="Willy Meyer Pleite" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, I would urge the Commission and the Council — that is to say, the European Union — to express their concern to the Argentinean authorities about the fate of crucial witnesses in the ongoing trials aimed at tackling impunity and establishing responsibility for all illegal actions carried out during the dictatorship.</p>
      <p sl="es">One of these cases involves the disappearance of Jorge Julio López, who is crucial to the case against a Buenos Aires policeman, Miguel Etchecolatz, who was a torturer during the period of the dictatorship, the blackest period in the history of Argentina. This witness has been missing since September, and this has caused huge alarm amongst the many witnesses who must carry on testifying in order to reveal the truth and in order to ensure that no crime goes unpunished.</p>
      <p sl="es">I would therefore call upon the European Union to raise this specific case with the Argentinean authorities.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-053" speaker_id="28497" name="Gerard Batten" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, on 20 August 1989, on the River Thames, the gravel dredger Bowbelle collided with the pleasure cruiser Marchioness and 51 people lost their lives. That tragedy resulted in the Government implementing stricter safety requirements for those navigating on the River Thames.</p>
      <p sl="en">These safety regulations are now in danger of being diluted as a direct result of the Government’s intention to implement EU Directive 96/50/EC. The current United Kingdom standards will be replaced by much lower standards under a harmonised European boatmaster’s licence. However, this is not necessary, as the same directive allows, under Article 3(2), for Member States to apply exemptions on national waterways and issue boatmaster’s certificates under their own conditions.</p>
      <p sl="en">I therefore call on all United Kingdom MEPs to write to the Minister, Dr Stephen Ladyman, asking him, in the interests of higher safety standards on the River Thames, to apply the derogation allowed under the directive.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-054" speaker_id="28117" name="Jim Higgins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, if the Open Skies transport agreement for aviation is agreed between the United States and Europe, numerous benefits will flow: more routes, more competition and cheaper air fares – better all round for the traveller and the consumer. A major obstacle, namely, an objection on the European side to the exchange of passenger data with the United States, has now been overcome. However, there is another obstacle in relation to the ownership of airlines, which is causing major problems in the United States and has been objected to in Congress.</p>
      <p sl="en">In the meantime, the Irish Minister for Transport, Mr Cullen, is trying to get the Commission to agree to a one-to-one bilateral agreement between Ireland and the United States. I object to that on two fronts. Firstly, it will undermine the global trust of Open Skies; and secondly, it will do irreparable damage to Shannon Airport in Ireland, which has been the gateway for transatlantic travel. Until such time as there is a full global agreement, then no bilateral agreement should be concluded between Ireland and the United States. The Commission should reject it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-055" speaker_id="28175" name="Yannick Vaugrenard" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, for some time now, the influx of migrants has been portrayed as a seemingly unacceptable threat. This rhetoric has been taken up by the far right, which is perpetuating the confusion between crime and immigration and which is thriving in this area.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The fact is that these migrants are first and foremost victims: victims of the Mafia-like networks that become rich by bringing over men and women who want to build a future for themselves; and victims of European businessmen and slum landlords who prosper by enslaving a cheap workforce, in the former case, and by renting out insalubrious accommodation at exorbitant prices, in the latter case.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Faced with that, let us put all of the existing Community instruments into operation so that we can combat these sectors. Let us review the regulation that stipulates that asylum applications must be reviewed by the first Member State in which asylum seekers step foot, because that puts an unacceptable burden on countries in Southern and Eastern Europe. Furthermore, the overcrowded and inhuman transit camps are no longer acceptable.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Finally, let us have the objectivity and courage to say that Europe will need legal immigrants in order to compensate for its demographic deficit. Let us therefore move out of our political comfort zone, let us stop making facile ideological statements and let us clearly state that immigration can also represent an opportunity for Europe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-056" speaker_id="28572" name="Georgios Papastamkos" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, if we take stock of the Union's policy towards the countries of southeast Europe, focusing on the Western Balkans, we can see that it has had positive and negative results.</p>
      <p sl="el">Following the criticism directed at the strategy of further enlargement of the Union, which also concerns the Western Balkans, there is a feeling that the ability of the area in question to be heard by the European institutions has been impaired.</p>
      <p sl="el">I believe that, within the framework of parliamentary diplomacy, we have a responsibility to make the Union's strategy more cohesive, transparent and effective, so that the southern dimension of European policy becomes more visible.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-057" speaker_id="1708" name="Marie-Noëlle Lienemann" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, EADS and the industrial projects that this group comprises, including Airbus, make it one of the great flagships of Europe, an industrial flagship, the symbol of our future technology and capabilities. However, this business is in great difficulty. I shall not dwell on the reasons – including those to do with the way in which it has been managed – which may justify or explain some of its current difficulties, which, in turn, require effective remedies.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I shall emphasise, instead, the statements made by Airbus’s management team, who explain to us that, if the business is to be competitive, it will probably have to relocate or set up a number of its operations in the so-called ‘dollar’ currency area, for the sole reason that the euro/dollar exchange rate is putting one of the European Union’s most important cutting-edge sectors at a disadvantage. When questioned on this point, Mr Trichet has only one thing to say: ‘I do not have to explain myself regarding the exchange rate!’.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Do you not think, Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, that there is an urgent need to change Europe's monetary policy?</p>
      <a text="(The President cut off the speaker)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-058" speaker_id="23816" name="András Gyürk" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="hu">50 years ago today, revolution broke out in Hungary. The site of the first battle in the nascent struggle for freedom from Soviet oppression took place at the headquarters of Hungarian Radio. The rebels knew that, in addition to force, the system was built first and foremost upon lies. The symbol of those lies was the mouthpiece of the Communist Party, namely state radio. The battle ended with the victory of the revolutionaries, and therefore the radio station was able to broadcast the words that would later become a catchphrase: 'We lied at night, we lied during the day, we lied on every wavelength.'</p>
      <p sl="hu">Force and lies: these are what kept communism alive in Hungary, and these were the building blocks of oppression in the rest of the Soviet bloc as well. Although the Hungarian Revolution was crushed by the overpowering columns of tanks that rolled into the country, today we know that the events in Budapest, Prague and Gdansk did not happen in vain, and that the victims did not give their lives in vain. Thanks to them, Europe today is free and united.</p>
      <p sl="hu">However, in order to make sure that no system on our continent will ever be built on force and on lies again, we must remember. It is for this reason that my fellow Members and I have launched an initiative to make 4 November, the anniversary of the defeat of the Hungarian Revolution, a day of remembrance for the victims of communism in Europe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-059" speaker_id="28580" name="Panagiotis Beglitis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, on 29 August UN Secretary-General Kofi Annan tabled a study on violence against children by the independent expert Paulo Sérgio Pinheiro before the General Assembly.</p>
      <p sl="el">This study describes in the blackest terms the phenomenon of violence and child exploitation in the world, highlighting the serious infringements of the rights of the child. This study is a wake-up call for the collective conscience of mankind and a call to take action to defend fundamental humane principles and values.</p>
      <p sl="el">I believe, to take advantage of the presence here of Commissioner Frattini, that this UN study should be the subject of debate in the institutions of the European Union, especially the European Parliament, in conjunction with the recent communication from the European Commission on a European strategy for the rights of the child.</p>
      <p sl="el">The European Union must be at the vanguard of a common system of rules for the protection of children's rights which are binding on all the Member States.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-060" speaker_id="28571" name="Marie Panayotopoulos-Cassiotou" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, we have heard from reports in the media that an airline employee in the United Kingdom is being persecuted and may be dismissed, purely and simply because she was wearing a chain with a cross the size of a five-cent piece around her neck.</p>
      <p sl="el">We talk about democracy, freedom and justice as principles which must also be consolidated in candidate countries. We want to give Europeans and everyone living on this planet the security of knowing that they will not be persecuted on the grounds of freedom of expression – irrespective of whether that freedom is expressed by word or by outer garments – and, more importantly, that they will not be persecuted for their religious faith.</p>
      <p sl="el">In my country, 80% of the people are baptised and wear a cross their whole life. How can we demand respect for religious freedoms from candidate countries when we do not protect the possibility of there being such a simple expression of religion? I hope that the Commissioner will take steps …</p>
      <a text="(The President cut off the speaker)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-061" speaker_id="4282" name="Renate Sommer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, I would like to draw the House’s attention to an occurrence several days ago involving Polish border guards and a German cruise ship, the Adler Dania , which entered the Polish port of Swinemünde, whereupon three Polish customs officers, in civilian clothing and without any written authorisation, sought to confiscate all the vessel’s stocks of spirits. The captain responded to this by turning the vessel round and speeding back to Germany, with a Polish border protection force speedboat in hot pursuit and, moreover, firing off signal flares in the Adler Dania’s direction.</p>
      <p sl="de">It defies belief that this sort of thing can happen, but it appears from the letters I have received from those with personal experience of these things that this is not, regrettably, an isolated incident. There are recurrent problems at the borders within Europe with many new Member States and also with other neighbouring countries, involving such things as the arbitrary levying of charges and attempts at coercing travellers into paying them or else being denied entry to the country they wish to enter. I demand that action be taken to deal with this.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-062" speaker_id="28585" name="Diamanto Manolakou" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, a report by a US strategic analysis and study company states that Greek Cypriots and Greek soldiers missing since the invasion by the Turkish army of northern Cyprus were used as guinea pigs in industrial laboratories belonging to the Turkish army between 1984 and 1988.</p>
      <p sl="el">Given not only that Turkey continues to occupy the northern part of Cyprus, but also that it has never provided any information or details about the missing persons, and given that the relatives of the missing persons have been suffering for three decades now, I would ask Parliament to take the initiative of demanding that Turkey supply all the information it has on the missing persons, however awful it may be, so that this suffering can be brought to an end.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-063" speaker_id="28570" name="Ioannis Gklavakis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I have taken the floor because I wish to express my displeasure and concern about the future of Europe. I have always believed that one of the main objectives of the European Union was to protect children, to safeguard their education and health and ensure they grow up to be rounded human beings.</p>
      <p sl="el">I wish to express my acute displeasure about the establishment in Holland of the paedophile party, a party whose basic objectives are to legalise sexual intercourse between adults and children over 12 years of age and to legalise possession of child pornography for personal use. In a Europe which is growing old, in a Europe in which the institution of the family is growing weaker by the day, in a Europe in which morals and customs and traditions are disappearing, the establishment of this party looks like a bomb in the foundations of the European construct.</p>
      <p sl="el">I call on us all to oppose it. I propose that the European Parliament table a request to the Finnish Presidency to have the paedophile party abolished. If we want a European Union with a future and prospects, we must primarily and above all protect our children.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-064" speaker_id="4482" name="Rodi Kratsa-Tsagaropoulou" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I have just returned from a visit to Lebanon with a feeling of optimism about the new situation in the area, but also with a greater awareness of the challenges which we all face. LIFE is returning to the south. Houses have been patched up and people are returning to live at home or with relatives pending reconstruction with the help of the government and donors, among which Hezbollah is playing an important part.</p>
      <p sl="el">The presence of the Lebanese army and UNIFIL forces is providing security and satisfaction to the citizens and, I must say, is giving visibility and appreciation to the European Union. The application of Resolution 1701 does not appear to be in danger, although the balance is fragile and we should protect it for the sake of peace in the area as a whole, just as we must support the Lebanese Government so that it can introduce suitable reforms of the economy, society and the political system.</p>
      <p sl="el">Apart from the defence of citizens' rights, I should like also to highlight the need for us to protect cultural treasures …</p>
      <a text="(The President cut off the speaker)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-065" speaker_id="28400" name="Francisco José Millán Mon" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, via the Presidency of this House I would like to send a message of condolence and solidarity to various municipalities in Galicia, particularly in the province of Pontevedra, in view of the grave situation they are suffering as a result of serious floods since the weekend.</p>
      <p sl="es">The storm has caused serious damage. There has been great damage to homes, companies, transport routes, agriculture and cattle. Unfortunately, there have also been injuries and deaths.</p>
      <p sl="es">As we all know, last August the Autonomous Community of Galicia suffered an enormous disaster as a result of a great wave of fires, which this Parliament debated in September. On that occasion we backed the mobilisation of the European Solidarity Fund.</p>
      <p sl="es">The serious effects of the heavy rains over recent days are linked to the August fires, as today’s Galician press points out. The loss of wooded areas and the tonnes of ash swept away have increased the ferocity of the floods. This is a further demonstration of the scale of the disaster that struck Galicia in the summer.</p>
      <p sl="es">Several Galicia municipalities are unfortunately once again in mourning.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-066" speaker_id="28115" name="Mairead McGuinness" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, we had a very useful dialogue last week with a group called EAGLES, which is made up of scientists from around the globe who are interested in helping the developing world, and I think it is a dialogue we need to extend throughout this Parliament. We are witnessing scientific apartheid on a vast scale: the developed world has too many scientists and engineers and the developing world has none, which is widening the gap between rich and poor.</p>
      <p sl="en">I have a very simple message which will not take a minute: there is an onus and a duty on the European Union and the Commission to work with the scientific community to persuade it to devote part of its efforts to projects that will help the developing world, whether it is for animal health, human health or agricultural production. This is a problem which is being neglected at the moment and the poor are suffering. It is something that this House should take on board by looking at the important role of science in the developing world.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-067" speaker_id="23864" name="Toomas Savi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="et">A couple of weeks ago the entire world was shocked by the murder of Anna Politkovskaya. The trampling of human rights and freedom of expression in Chechnya that Anna Politkovskaya sought to make public was stifled using the methods of gangster politics.</p>
      <p sl="et">A week ago we had to talk about the Georgian crisis, which Russia began with a political show of force, imposing economic sanctions and a transport and postal blockade against Georgia, prohibiting imports of Georgian goods, closing Russia’s border with Georgia and beginning to deport Georgians from Russia.</p>
      <p sl="et">Today we must be prepared to prevent the possible use of all kinds of military force in connection with the secession attempts of Abkhazia and South Ossetia.</p>
      <p sl="et">The European Union and Parliament cannot simply stand by and watch the situation in Georgia unfold. We must use every available option – the whole gamut of measures provided for in the European Neighbourhood Policy, the organisation of border guard missions, the facilitation of free trade and the simplification of the visa system – with the objective of preserving peace in the South Caucasus.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-068" speaker_id="28215" name="Jacky Henin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, Airbus’s strategic and industrial decisions decide not only the fate of tens of thousands of employees but also the future of a large part of the European aeronautical industry. It is vital that respect be shown for the knowledge, work, and investment of Airbus’s employees and subcontractors via efforts to prevent a situation in which they are reduced to nothing. Airbus’s employees should under no circumstances be made to pay for the mistakes and the errors made by the managers and shareholders. Through the knowledge that they bring, these employees represent the true jewel in Airbus’s crown. Airbus is failing because of the liberal policies that have been implemented, and, if it is to get back on track, a return to public ownership and funding of EADS at European level is required.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I am also pleased to note that, in both Germany and Spain, many people are speaking out in an effort to see the employees granted genuine powers to intervene in the management of Airbus.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Let Mr Mandelson do his job so that the Americans no longer challenge the system of repayable advances and so that the European Central Bank and the Commission intervene at last to counter the weak dollar.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-069" speaker_id="28251" name="Jörg Leichtfried" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, my intervention relates to the problem of stray dogs on Corfu. The Austrian animal welfare association has for some years been supporting many projects on Corfu, although the local authorities constantly prevent it from doing its work in an effective and efficient manner. Foreign veterinarians are disbarred from treating animals, homes for animals that have already been built are prevented from being taken into service, and, even though the travel agency TUI funded the project, stray dogs are not allowed to be sent to families in Germany and Austria, but instead meet a cruel death in Corfu.</p>
      <p sl="de">I appeal to the Council, and to the Members of this House, to do something about this state of affairs, demanding in particular that aid from overseas be permitted and recognised in order to resolve the problem with the minimum possible delay and for the animals’ benefit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-070" speaker_id="28421" name="Marianne Mikko" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="et">Ladies and gentlemen, 50 years ago this evening the students and intellectuals of Budapest presented 16 demands to the Hungarian puppet government. The demands were rejected, the authorities opened fire on the crowd and the uprising began.</p>
      <p sl="et">The Hungarians were encouraged by their faith in assistance from the West. European unity appeared natural to them. The expected assistance did not come, however, not even in the form of official declarations. The Suez Crisis that was unfolding at the same time somewhat limited the West’s ability to act, but the real reason for this reserve was the division of Europe into spheres of influence at Yalta.</p>
      <p sl="et">13 000 people were repressed by the Soviets, 350 of whom were executed. Hungary became a cautionary case for other nations that thirsted for freedom.</p>
      <p sl="et">The Soviet Union no longer exists, but the spirit of Yalta lives on in our fear of standing up in defence of Moldova, Georgia and other countries that Russia considers to be part of its sphere of influence. In memory of the victims of the Hungarian uprising, I propose that we overcome our fear and take a united stand in defence of democracy and freedom.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-071" speaker_id="28382" name="Andrzej Jan Szejna" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, creating a common market for energy that is as efficient, secure and competitive as possible is a priority for the European Union. It is important to remember, however, that the impact of the Union’s energy policy extends beyond the energy sector, and that the three political objectives of energy policy are to ensure the security of energy supplies, to ensure competitiveness and to protect the environment, notably by countering climate change. As we are aware, the creation of the internal energy market is brought about indirectly through harmonisation of the legislation of the Member States, and directly through liberalisation of national energy markets. Nonetheless, Europe needs a single common strategy and broadly based cooperation both as regards the common internal market and as regards foreign partners. That is why I am delighted that at the recent Lahti Summit, where, for the first time in many years, the European Union countries endeavoured to speak about energy cooperation with Russia in one single voice, and individual Member States did not allow themselves to be led astray by the prospect of the potential benefits of a special relationship with Russia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-072" speaker_id="23787" name="Czesław Adam Siekierski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, I have attended two important events this month. One was the conference on the simplification of the common agricultural policy organised by the European Commission, and the other was the Conference of European Farmers, held under the auspices of COPA/COGECA. It was repeatedly stated that what Europe needs is a clearly defined strategy for agriculture and the future of its farmers. What is it actually getting? Wave after wave of reforms churned out every few years. Farmers need stability to be able to plan production and investment. We would do well to remember that if it is denied aid of any kind, European agriculture will have great difficulty in competing with products imported from other countries. Europe is already at a disadvantage, because the requirements imposed on our farmers are much stricter, and their production conditions are often more difficult. It is therefore incumbent on us to enlighten the citizens and also certain Members of this House as to why we have a common agricultural policy, what its benefits are and why consumers have to pay its costs.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-073" speaker_id="23881" name="Marios Matsakis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Mr Behiç Aşçi is a Turkish lawyer who has been on hunger strike for 202 days and is now very close to death. Although not a prisoner himself, he is protesting against the inhuman action of Turkish authorities in subjecting mainly political prisoners to isolation in so-called F-type prisons. One hundred and twenty-two hunger strikers in such prisons have died so far, and yet the Turkish Government stubbornly refuses even to discuss the matter.</p>
      <p sl="en">Isolation, sometimes for years, is one of the worst forms of psychological torture and Turkish civil society, including the lawyers’ and doctors’ associations, have called for its abolition.</p>
      <p sl="en">I call upon you, Mr President, in the name of respect for human rights and in order to save Mr Aşçi’s life, to contact the Turkish Prime Minister urgently and stress to him that isolation in F-type prisons is incompatible with Turkey’s European aspirations and must cease forthwith.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-074" speaker_id="28197" name="Árpád Duka-Zólyomi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="hu">Today we remember events that occurred 50 years ago, those of the Hungarian Revolution of 1956, the people’s revolution, which shook the communist system that had been thought to be rock solid. What were the Hungarian people fighting for? For freedom and independence. We Hungarians living beyond the borders of Hungary were also following the heroic struggle against the overwhelming Soviet power with concern and keen attention. The defeat of the Revolution was followed by dark, cruel years and harsh reprisals. Particularly in Transylvania, but in Slovakia as well, those who openly sympathised with the Revolution were subjected to severe retribution. It is with deep reverence that we recall the victims, the heroic freedom fighters, whose struggle was not in vain. 34 years later, the inhuman system fell, and today we belong to a European Community which is based on democracy, the rule of law and human and civil rights. It was for these values that the participants fought and the heroic dead gave their lives during the 1956 Revolution.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-075" speaker_id="28276" name="Laima Liucija Andrikienė" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, last week the informal EU summit in Lahti, under the Finnish Presidency, marked a very important step in EU-Russia relations. After a long time the EU was able to speak with one voice and what is especially important is that the EU was united in speaking about EU energy policy.</p>
      <p sl="en">As the need for an increased energy supply and increased energy security are of common interest to the Union, I would like to stress that some projects in the Baltic Sea region ignore the interests of a number of Member States in terms of security of energy supply, particularly the North European Gas Pipeline project, which in 2000 was granted Trans-European Energy Network status.</p>
      <p sl="en">I suggest that we call on the countries already involved in the project, namely Germany and Russia, to invite the neighbouring countries, EU Member States, to join the network and provide them with an opportunity of real partnership.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-076" speaker_id="21918" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">This item is closed.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem16" title="16. Establishment, operation and use of SIS II (regulation) – Establishment, operation and use of SIS II (decision) – Access to SIS II by the services responsible for issuing vehicle registration certificates (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-079" speaker_id="1264" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the joint debate on</p>
      <p sl="unknown">the report (A6-0355/2006) by Mr Coelho on behalf of the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs on the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council on the establishment, operation and use of the second generation Schengen Information System (SIS II) (COM(2005)0236 – C6-0174/2005 – 2005/0106(COD)),</p>
      <p sl="unknown">the report (A6-0353/2006) by Mr Coelho on behalf of the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs on the proposal for a Council decision on the establishment, operation and use of the second generation Schengen Information System (SIS II) (COM(2005)0230 – C6-0301/2005 – 2005/0103(CNS)) and</p>
      <p sl="unknown">the report (A6-0354/2006) by Mr Coelho on behalf of the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs on the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council regarding access to the Second Generation Schengen Information System (SIS II) by the services in the Member States responsible for issuing registration certificates for vehicles (COM(2005)0237 – C6-0175/2005 – 2005/0104(COD)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-080" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Franco Frattini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I wish to begin by congratulating Mr Coelho, the rapporteur, for his excellent work on the legal package for the second generation Schengen Information System. I also take the opportunity to mention the important work that has been carried out by the Finnish Presidency to finalise the discussions on this legislative package.</p>
      <p sl="en">Parliament, the Council and the Commission have all taken a very proactive attitude in finding compromises on this very sensitive and complex dossier. The Justice and Home Affairs Council confirmed earlier this month that this SIS tool remains an absolute priority and the Commission continues to give the highest importance to this dossier.</p>
      <p sl="en">SIS II will be an important tool to ensure the efficient exchange of information between the relevant authorities. SIS II will contribute to a higher level of security as it will have greater functionalities than the current SIS that will be better suited to the operational needs of police and other authorities.</p>
      <p sl="en">Moving forward with SIS II will be a decisive step in underpinning free movement, effective border controls and the ongoing fight against serious crime and terrorism. At the same time, better safeguards have been included: for example precise data protection rules have been introduced that should also provide for more transparency and accountability.</p>
      <p sl="en">I strongly hope that the Council and Parliament will agree on a first reading compromise because the legislative framework is a key element – indeed a precondition – that will allow the Commission to complete the development of SIS II and allow it to start its operational phase. Any further delays on the legal basis will inevitably have a negative impact on the revised timetable of SIS II, and thus on lifting the internal borders of the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">Therefore I can agree to the rapporteur’s proposal and I will continue to hope for a first reading compromise in order to speed up the process of implementation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-081" speaker_id="1892" name="Carlos Coelho" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="pt">Mr President, Mr Frattini, ladies and gentlemen, what we have on the table are three documents: two regulations and one decision. I should like to draw the Chamber’s attention to five issues, the first of which is institutional, namely the absurdity of the legislative process.</p>
      <p sl="pt">We have three different legal documents subject to two different procedures: the regulations are subject to codecision and the decision to the consultation process. The three documents refer to the same situation; we do not have three Schengen Information Systems, we have one, on which we are making laws using different legal systems. This is an absurd situation that must not be allowed to continue. If the European Constitution had been adopted we would not be finding ourselves in this ridiculous situation.</p>
      <p sl="pt">This was a complex legal procedure which required everyone to work in a great spirit of cooperation. I should like to thank publicly the shadow rapporteurs and all the members of the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs. I wish to thank in particular Mr Lax, Mrs Mastenbroek and Mrs Kaufmann for their invaluable help and for working under great pressure to secure an agreement at first reading.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The second point I wish to make is that, to my mind, this is a good outcome for Europe. This is because we have more security, better data protection and the system has been tightened up. Biometric data make it easier to identify people, so that a more reliable connection can be made between the person and the identity document, which serves to strengthen security standards. Furthermore, alerts can be tackled more intelligently, which we call the interlinking of alerts. This enables a policeman to distinguish between a less serious crime and an act that may be linked to a criminal network or to a series of crimes that require a more sophisticated security response. Not only are we managing information more intelligently, we are also helping the law enforcement bodies to guarantee security more effectively. With the three documents on which we are about to vote, we are helping to make our external border controls more effective and movement within the Community more secure.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Thirdly, I believe that this is a good outcome for the new Member States, which justifiably want to give their citizens the feeling that they are fully-fledged citizens with the same right to free movement as those in the rest of the Community. This is why we must not hold back the legislative process. There needs to be an agreement at first reading and once this is in place we will be in a position to adopt a legal basis by the end of 2006 as we have undertaken to do.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Fourthly, Mr President, I feel that this is a good outcome for Parliament, because we have managed to achieve most of what we had been fighting for, of which I should like to highlight the following: Community management of the central system, under the democratic control of the European Parliament and the legal control of the Court of Justice (the creation of a Community agency within five years, established in codecision with Parliament, is provided for); the fact that there is greater harmonisation of alerts in the Schengen Information System (SIS), whereby entry into the Schengen area can be refused (the Commission is invited to submit initiatives, within three years, aimed at achieving higher levels of harmonisation); the fact that European Arrest Warrants are stored in the SIS central system; the fact that we are using biometric data as a research field only after the drafting of a report to be submitted to Parliament on which Parliament will have its say; the fact that we have clearly strengthened the rules on data protection and the rights of individuals in relation to the system, the fact that the supervision system has been strengthened at both European and national level; and the obligation to draw up reports in order to increase transparency regarding the overall functioning of the system.</p>
      <p sl="pt">My fifth and final point, Mr President, is a remark to the Council and a vote of thanks to the Commission. I wish to thank the Commission, and in particular Mr Frattini, who worked closely with Parliament throughout the process and – let me stress this point – helped the Commission and Parliament to find a great deal of common ground. I should also like to thank the two Presidencies – of Austria and Finland – for the huge amount of work that they put into this process. I should particularly like to thank Mr Rajamäki, Finnish home affairs minister and current chairman of the Justice and Home Affairs Council, and all his team, and a special word of thanks for the chairman of the Schengen working group. People worked very hard and, to my mind, achieved success, both in terms of the legal solutions that we found and the institutional undertakings that we have made; for example, the Presidency has undertaken to channel all its efforts into adopting the framework decision on data protection in the third pillar by the end of the year.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Mr President, I should like to say, however, that the Council did not always do the right thing. It failed to honour the promises it made at the high-level informal trialogue in May held in Strasbourg, and this led to a major defeat for the Austrian Presidency. I hope that the Council does not do likewise with the compromise reached in the Brussels trialogue of 26 September. I say this because although we managed to reach an excellent agreement at the 26 September trialogue, 48 hours, just two days, before the vote on the compromise text at the Committee on Civil Liberties, the Council sought to open up the SIS to the secret services of the Member States on the basis of an initiative by one Member State. It must be said that, in terms of its actual content, this proposal makes no sense. We cannot, on the one hand, increase personal data protection requirements, which we did in the compromise text, and, on the other, open up access to the structures of the Member States, which by definition are not answerable, either partly or totally, to the authorities responsible for data protection. This paradox makes no sense. It is also ridiculous for procedural reasons, insofar as two days before Parliament voted on the text that had been agreed upon in the trialogue with the Presidency and Mr Frattini, attempts were being made to amend the text. One does not make changes to a negotiation and a compromise in 48 hours.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Relations between the European institutions should be characterised by loyalty and good faith. The President of Parliament is good to his word. We are ready to vote on a text that we managed to reach over many months and lengthy negotiations. I trust that the Council will also honour its commitment and that the new second generation SIS will be up and running, at the earliest opportunity, operating effectively and efficiently, and delivering security.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-082" speaker_id="23713" name="Mihael Brejc" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group">
      <p sl="sl">Negotiations concerning all three documents have been long drawn-out and very arduous, but we have finally reached a compromise, both within the European Parliament and, some time later, in our negotiations with the Commission and the Council. We are aware of the responsibility we owe to a project as demanding as the enlargement of the Schengen area, which is why we on the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs adopted the legal bases virtually unanimously – that is, with a large majority. I believe that the same thing will also happen when we vote at the plenary session. Any further procrastination in adopting the legal bases will affect the launch of SIS II. For this reason, the European Parliament should adopt the bases as a matter of urgency, as they clearly provide a cornerstone for the technical set-up of SIS II. However, how the Council will act and how the next stage of harmonisation will proceed is another question.</p>
      <p sl="sl">It has now become clear that the enlargement of the Schengen area will be delayed for technical reasons. These difficulties are probably considerable. The new Member States, among them Slovenia, which have invested a lot of effort in meeting the Schengen criteria, have confirmed that they have fulfilled all these criteria. Consequently, the delay is not due to any lack of preparation on our part. Linked to this is the extremely serious issue of the costs we will incur as a result of the delay in acceding to the Schengen area.</p>
      <p sl="sl">I therefore support the alternative solutions which will grant accession to SIS I only to those Member States which have finalised their preparations, that is to say, to those which have fulfilled all the criteria for inclusion in the Schengen Information System within the time limit originally envisaged. I hope that Parliament will adopt the afore-mentioned legal bases and I would like to thank Mr Coelho and Commissioner Frattini for their outstanding cooperation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-083" speaker_id="4313" name="Martine Roure" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PSE Group">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, I should like to begin, of course, by thanking Mr Coelho and the groups’ shadow rapporteurs for their intensive work.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The implementation of the second generation Schengen Information System (SIS II) should enable us to help remove the internal borders with the ten new Member States. Enlarging the Schengen area is a priority for our Parliament. We understand the difficulties faced by our Eastern European colleagues in terms of explaining to their fellow citizens why they cannot move freely within Europe. That is why we wanted to reach an agreement at first reading so as not to hinder the free movement of all European citizens.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The Schengen Information System must provide us with a high level of security with which to remove the borders, but any centralised database must comply with the principles of proportionality and purpose so as to ensure that everyone’s private life is protected. That is why we are pleased to see a direct, specific reference in this text to the future framework decision on the protection of data under the third pillar, something for which I am especially grateful to Mr Coelho. I hope that the Council will be able to send us its first reading of this text very soon, just as it promised to do during our last plenary session.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The SIS is a monitoring tool that has been implemented at the external borders and that has replaced the old fixed installations, which were abolished as part of the efforts to promote the free movement of persons. We wanted strictly to define those authorities that would have direct access to the data. The list of authorities granted access will thus be published in the Official Journal, and this will help to prevent any misuse of the data by making it possible to identify by whom, when and why the data from the system were exploited. Furthermore, our priority is to grant people access to information about themselves, by giving them the opportunity to appeal and to correct any errors.</p>
      <p sl="fr">We have worked together, in a spirit of compromise, in order to arrive as quickly as possible at a joint text. I understand the concerns of the new Member States following the Commission's announcement that there has been a delay in implementing the system. These are, however, technical problems in the system for which the European Parliament cannot be held responsible. Finally, I should like to call on the Member States not to impose any last-minute requests that might jeopardise the compromise accepted by all of the institutions, and not to further delay the adoption of this text, which is necessary from the point of view of free movement.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-084" speaker_id="28262" name="Henrik Lax" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="sv">In a short time, we shadow rapporteurs have joined the rapporteur in approving all the legislative proposals necessary in order to extend the Schengen area also to include the new Member States. I wish to extend a special thank you to the rapporteur, Mr Coelho, and to the shadow rapporteurs for the splendid consensus we have achieved and for the constructive outcome of our work.</p>
      <p sl="sv">The fly in the ointment is the timetable. Despite having done our utmost in order as quickly as possible to phase out internal borders, the Schengen enlargement will be delayed. By how long is not yet clear. We in the Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe do not think that we have had enough by way of answers from the Council and the Commission as to why there has been a delay which, moreover, threatens to go on for some time. Every citizen who is waiting no longer to have to pass through internal border controls is entitled to be told where the problem lies. We therefore propose that the Commission immediately set up an independent inquiry into the causes of the delay.</p>
      <p sl="sv">The Schengen area is one of the EU’s most successful projects. Abolishing internal borders is one very practical way of creating a common European identity. It might be said to be one of the EU’s most fundamental tasks.</p>
      <p sl="sv">During the preparations for SIS II, the introduction of biometrics – that is to say, the inclusion of fingerprints in databases – was perhaps the most controversial issue. The solution whereby biometrics are to be introduced in two stages is a good one. In the first stage, it would only be permitted to confirm a person’s identity with the help of fingerprints. In the second stage, it would also be possible to make searches using biometric criteria.</p>
      <p sl="sv">I am convinced that it should only be possible to use biometrics with very great care and discernment. In the SIS II system, their use is, however, relatively uncontroversial because the database concerned contains, for the most part, information about people sought by the authorities.</p>
      <p sl="sv">What is, however, much more controversial is the use of fingerprints in the future common Schengen visas, which will be issued by the new Member States too. Here, we are concerned in most cases with tourists, relatives and business people who have never had any problems with the authorities.</p>
      <p sl="sv">The use of biometric criteria is a much bigger issue, both technically and administratively, in the case of the visa system than it is in the case of SIS II. For the visas, the fingerprints of 20 million people per year are to be taken. Therefore, it is probably important for governments not to delay in considering the possibility of excluding fingerprints from the system, in any case at the beginning. Otherwise, there is a great risk of the Schengen enlargement being delayed in this important area too, and that is something that we really do not wish to see happen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-085" speaker_id="28139" name="Carl Schlyter" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="sv">Mr President, thank you, Mr Coelho for your work on improving this proposal. It is important for us to enhance data protection, something that the European Parliament is trying to do. It is important for people to be allowed to know what information is being recorded about them, for sound reasons.</p>
      <p sl="sv">I think that Schengen, including the Schengen Information System, has been beset by problems from the very beginning. In practice, we have replaced simple border controls by an ability on the part of the authorities constantly to keep a check on people when they are actually in their own countries. What is being proposed here is an increase in the number of authorities that have access to data. The proposal thus entails increased use of this data, so we have to be still more careful about the information we submit. For that reason, I think it inappropriate to submit biometric data.</p>
      <p sl="sv">When the United States debated going down this road, it allowed its Supreme Court to examine the options. The implication for ourselves of their decision is that there would be a great risk either that many people who are entitled to enter the EU would not be able to do so, or – in the event of the safety margins being reduced – that undesirables would get in. There are many people – for example, hard-working people with poor fingerprints – who it would not be possible to identify with certainty using fingerprints. There is a danger that innocent people would be turned away and that guilty people would slip though.</p>
      <p sl="sv">Biometric data is also extremely expensive. Increased use of such data is unacceptable when it is now to be possible to search for such data. Nor is it acceptable for a decision on the matter to be made through a committee procedure. Biometric data entails an invasion of privacy, especially as it might very well affect innocent people. It is not a route we should go down.</p>
      <p sl="sv">A number of governments now wish, at the last minute, to introduce a provision whereby the security police are to have access to the data concerned. That would put an end to the whole principle of data protection, to the whole principle of the right to know what has been recorded about oneself and to the whole principle of legal certainty and the rule of law. It would be as well, I think, if the Council were to withdraw this debate from the agenda. The security police must not have access to such information.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-086" speaker_id="1849" name="Sylvia-Yvonne Kaufmann" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, Mr Vice-President of the Commission, even though the primary reason why SIS II is needed is that it enables the citizens of the new Member States to avail themselves of their right to unrestricted freedom of movement within the EU, my group will nevertheless be voting against the draft legislation, and there are two reasons why we have decided to do that.</p>
      <p sl="de">The first has to do with data protection. The fact is that SIS II is not just about the free movement of persons, but also – and above all – about cooperation between police and justice authorities and a system of investigation. It is common knowledge, however, that the current arrangements for data protection within the third pillar are unsatisfactory. If citizens’ rights and the requirements of security are to be kept in balance, what is needed is the framework decision on the protection of personal data.</p>
      <p sl="de">This is something that this House recently voted unanimously to endorse, but what is the Council doing? The framework decision has not been forthcoming. As we have heard, there are those in the Council who still have reservations about it, and what that means in plain language is that we know, at present, neither when this framework decision is to enter into force, nor what substantial changes the Council has made to it, even though considerations of human rights make it imperative that proper data protection be guaranteed, and, moreover, even before this sort of comprehensive database is created.</p>
      <p sl="de">Secondly, the inclusion of biometric data is problematic, and for a variety of reasons. For a start, the impact of the use of biometric data in such a large system has not been assessed, and nor have the conditions for the inclusion of such data been adequately laid down. Another consideration is that it is not – in my group’s view – acceptable that the question of when biometric data should be allowed to be used as a primary search criterion should be decided without reference to Parliament.</p>
      <p sl="de">In conclusion, I would like to thank the rapporteur Mr Coelho for the good cooperation, but, while I am on that subject, I would like to emphasise that I take an unsympathetic view of the way in which the Council – largely in response to pressure from my own country – has dealt with this House over recent days. It is not acceptable that new demands should be made after the conclusion of the trilogue, thereby putting a pistol to Parliament’s head.</p>
      <p sl="de">It is made even less acceptable if one is aware of precisely why Berlin chose to try to blackmail the Council. By all means let the police have access to SIS II, but I have to tell the House that I do not believe that the secret services should be allowed to get their hands on it, for, as we have discovered all too often, they are accountable to themselves alone, and for that reason we should not make SIS II more accessible than it already is.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-087" speaker_id="28615" name="Roberts Zīle" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the UEN Group">
      <p sl="lv">Mr President, I wish I could be delighted about the fact that the European Parliament will consider this packet of three documents in the October part-session and that we shall probably take a reasonably rapid decision, which will also mean that it will be a codecision. While I have a high opinion of the rapporteur’s main position, which is based on the European Parliament’s traditional stance, and while really important issues have been debated, together with issues which, in my view, are not important at all, such as the location of the Community’s agency, we have in reality forgotten about communicating with the public and we have lost track of the time that has been spent. For the public in the new Member States it is difficult to understand why the technical, financial and human resources for the internal borders of the new Member States will be applied two years later than planned and why Schengen agreement rights will not be extended to citizens of the new Member States until at least 2009. In reality, in the eyes of citizens of the new Member States, the Schengen area is a much greater symbol of the European Union’s unity than the European Union constitution.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-088" speaker_id="1969" name="Johannes Blokland" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the IND/DEM Group">
      <p sl="nl">Mr President, the European Union is currently working hard at reinforcing external border control, which is important, but there are also the internal borders to consider, and incidents involving suspects crossing borders throw up questions about internal border control. I see Schengen as a romantic concept. In the European Union, it is not only innocent citizens who benefit from the free movement of persons; so did Hussein Osman, a 27-year-old who was one of those suspected in connection with the attacks in London, who was able to travel to Rome without any problems, and that cannot be what Schengen is about.</p>
      <p sl="nl">More frequent and more targeted controls will therefore need to be put in place, not only at national borders, but also on ferries, at airports and at railway interchanges. This is where an effective information system such as SIS II can be useful. Going back to the pre-Schengen era is not an option; after all, the free movement of persons and the effective functioning of the European Union go hand in hand, and the latter is dependent on the former.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-089" speaker_id="28371" name="Marek Aleksander Czarnecki" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, the Schengen Information System is a highly complex information transfer system linked to a computerised database. In its present form, this system is only capable of serving a maximum of 18 participating countries. No provision was made for extending it to include the new Member States of the Union after the enlargement. This was one of the reasons why it was necessary to start work on a new, second-generation information system, namely SIS II. The new Member States would like to join this system at the earliest opportunity. Initially, this was planned for October 2007 but, three weeks ago, the European Commission agreed that there would be a one-year delay. Commissioner Frattini stated that, at best, the new SIS II information system would be ready in June 2008. This is not the whole truth, because the date given only applies to the old Member States. The new entrants, like Poland, will be connected later, with our experts reckoning that it might not happen until the middle of 2009. We cannot agree to such a lengthy delay. We appreciate that the system needs more work, but the middle of 2009 is an unacceptable date. We want our nationals to feel they are fully-fledged European citizens when they travel.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-090" speaker_id="28284" name="Barbara Kudrycka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, I would like to begin by thanking Mr Coelho and all the political groups for their serious and well thought-out work on the SIS II package. I agree with the rapporteur, however, that it is not acceptable for the Council to introduce amendments to the compromise already reached in the three-party talks. That is why, at this juncture, we should give priority to approval of the legislative package at first reading. The SIS II package provides increased security, better protection of personal data, and tighter border controls. It also increases both the freedom and the security of all citizens who live in the European Union and travel within it, not just the citizens of the new Member States. Of course, putting the new legislation into practice is just as important as approving it, and we therefore look forward to the debate on SIS II implementation when Commissioner Frattini is present. I would point out that, to date, no information has been made available to this House concerning the extent of the delay in constructing the central unit for the SIS II and the reasons for it. We are therefore eagerly awaiting the conclusions of the audit report on the European Commission’s work on the construction of SIS II promised by Mr Kallas. This audit report and the forthcoming European Council summit, which will decide on the timetable for removing border controls with the new Member States, will both be good opportunities to debate an issue that is of such importance to ordinary people. SIS II is being created to fulfil commitments entered into at the highest political level in the Treaty of Amsterdam, the Accession Treaty and the Hague Programme. Meeting these commitments on time is vital for the European Union’s credibility. It will be judged on whether it can meet the obligations and deliver the specific benefits and advantages it has promised its citizens.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091" speaker_id="28169" name="Edith Mastenbroek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, let me take this opportunity to thank Mr Coelho for his outstanding performance on this file. It is, after all, thanks to him and his negotiating skills that the decision-making procedure on this important and complex package of legislation has been finished in time. Mr Coelho was confronted with some tough choices during this process. Producing law at record speed is efficient, but it cannot be denied that this efficiency comes at the expense of transparency.</p>
      <p sl="en">My group is worried about the lack of data protection concerning the second generation of the Schengen Information System. The Council finally agreed to refer to the framework decision on data protection in the third pillar. A referral like that is the least we can do to protect our citizens’ rights and we are not there yet – far from it. The Council initially refused the referral because the decision had not yet been taken. That is true, but why? Is it not the Council that is putting the brakes on this issue? And is it not the Council that is aiming to water down the decision, almost to the point that there is hardly anything left to protect?</p>
      <p sl="en">I cannot help but mention here the German Government’s offer to make data protection in the third pillar a priority during its Presidency, provided we agree to make some fundamental changes at the last minute in situ . Well, that leaves a bitter taste indeed, after the British Government promised to deliver if Parliament agreed with data retention and did not; after both the Austrian and Finnish Presidencies did not seem too keen on pushing the issue forward, but are nevertheless watering down the proposal. Yes, German Government, you will have to make this one of your priorities, but not in exchange for a favour. You will have to do it because citizens deserve it and they deserve it now. The lack of data protection makes it all the more worrisome that the Parliament is asked to give up its decision-making rights concerning biometrics. Again, this is all in the spirit of efficiency, but at the expense of transparency, and therefore democracy.</p>
      <p sl="en">So why am I proposing to vote in favour, in spite of all this criticism? For many reasons. I will mention just a few. The citizens of Europe do not appear to be particularly worried about co- or framework decisions; they are, however, worried about the increasing number of stolen cars finding their way to eastern European Member States and would like us to take the necessary steps to fight that growing area of crime. In an area without internal borders, we also need to have a joint approach to illegal immigration. No matter how difficult this issue is for many of us, we need a common tool to deal with the presence of illegal immigrants. Also, the Schengen Information System will add more meaning and substance to the European arrest warrant and strengthen the role of Europol and Eurojust with the increasing cooperation of our police and security forces.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-092" speaker_id="4740" name="Marco Cappato" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I should like to congratulate the rapporteur.</p>
      <p sl="it">I believe that the great mystery is this huge technical delay in preparing the SIS. One might well suppose that there is a political reason for the fact that the SIS, as an instrument designed to guarantee freedom of movement, is in danger of becoming more and more secondary to the requirements of security, which are, of course, legitimate requirements. I believe, however, that we are overstepping the mark if we want – as the German Government seems to do – to make these databases accessible to the secret services, too.</p>
      <p sl="it">This, together with the increasingly frequent use of biometrics are likely to be the – let us say – technically necessary result of inward-looking policies on freedom of movement and immigration. I therefore believe that the reason for these technical delays can only be an eminently political one.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-093" speaker_id="28979" name="Giusto Catania" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I believe that a worthy end – that of the free movement of EU citizens and the abolition of internal borders – is concealing an unacceptable means. The second generation Schengen Information System introduces new forms of social control, and the unlimited use of biometric data will in reality undermine personal data protection.</p>
      <p sl="it">We are concerned because, recently, these data have been misused, with a genuine form of control being exercised. As we have said time and again, we believe that it is unacceptable for these data to end up in the hands of the secret services. We are concerned because an administrative function is being turned into an instrument of police control.</p>
      <p sl="it">While we welcome the commendable work done by Mr Coelho, our group will therefore vote against, since we believe that, instead of debating the free movement of EU citizens, we are debating ways in which they will be completely controlled.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-094" speaker_id="28389" name="Zbigniew Krzysztof Kuźmiuk" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, the delay in extending the Schengen area will have both political and financial implications for the new Member States. The political implications will involve a deepening of the divide between those who are equal and those who are more equal within the Union, just when that gap should be disappearing. The financial implications will be considerable, because the bulk of the costs of the delay will have to be met by the new Member Sates. I very much hope, therefore, that most of these costs will be met from the European Union’s budget, as proposed by the eight countries in the Salzburg Forum. I also hope that henceforth the Commission will play fair with the new Member States. The Commission was aware of the scale of the delays a long time ago, but chose not to make them public. What is even worse is that it is planned for the old Member States to join SIS II in June 2008, but the new Member States will only be able to join in the distant future. They may not be able to do so until the end of 2009. Discriminating against the new Member States in this way is simply unacceptable.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-095" speaker_id="28587" name="Georgios Karatzaferis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, Commissioner, the question is how effective the Schengen Agreement has been to date. Did it stop the Islamic fundamentalists in Madrid? Has it stopped Islamic fanatics throughout Europe? Did it stop them in London? So why should we apply it when we cannot defend Europe?</p>
      <p sl="el">Tell me; is there a coastguard in the Aegean? Here you have not defined where the borders of Europe are. Two thousand people a day attempt to enter Greece and another two thousand attempt to enter Spain. Consequently, we are helping them. Once they have entered Greece, they can enter Italy, Austria, Germany or France. We are helping them by abolishing internal borders. What do we gain? And now we want a second generation. What are we offering our citizens? Agents tapping their telephones, cameras watching them, the Schengen system recording their personal data. We are therefore creating a democratic deficit without any corresponding benefit.</p>
      <p sl="el">Of course I shall be voting against this dumbing down of democracy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-096" speaker_id="24029" name="Koenraad Dillen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="nl">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, this debate revolves around the question as to how the future, modified Schengen Information System can be utilised in a common European strategy, bearing in mind the two main challenges Europe is facing today, namely the tide of illegal immigration – the consequences of which we see from day to day – and the risk of Islam terrorism. That is the central question in this whole debate.</p>
      <p sl="nl">An information system in which all countries participate and that possesses more functions than its predecessor could prove useful in the tracing and expulsion of illegal immigrants and also in the fight against terrorism. Such an information system was dealt a heavy blow as long ago as last year, though, when the European Court of Justice stipulated that a country cannot deny anyone access on the basis of their being flagged in the system as a danger to law and order. After all, the Court specified that a country must be able to decide for itself whether the person involved forms a threat.</p>
      <p sl="nl">A deeper and more fundamental question is whether the individual Member States themselves have taken on board the Schengen logic and the spirit of the Schengen system. Accordingly, the legalisation of illegals, people who have entered the Schengen area illegally, is a manifest violation of the Schengen agreement. To put it in a nutshell, the information system must be placed in a broader framework. It is only useful if the Member States monitor the external borders effectively, adopt an active and consistent policy of tracing and expulsion and come down hard on human traffickers who make a fortune at external borders that are scantly monitored.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-097" speaker_id="28150" name="Kinga Gál" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="hu">The integration of the European Union has reached an important milestone with the vote in the European Parliament on the regulations creating the legislative basis for the second-generation Schengen Information System. Parliament has indicated that it will do everything in its power to ensure that the promises made in the course of enlargement are fulfilled, and that the new Member States can join the Schengen system as soon as possible. Thanks are due to the rapporteur, who has done everything possible for this to be achieved.</p>
      <p sl="hu">It is precisely in order to avoid further delay that it is important for Parliament and the Council to reach an agreement on first reading. Thus, it is strange that, while here in Parliament we are striving to establish the legal background as quickly as possible and are prepared to accept compromises, the government representatives on the Council are voting on passages that will necessarily delay the solution. The key question regarding the path towards lifting the internal borders under Schengen is to know when the new Member States will be able to join the Schengen Information System; according to the Commission this is causing considerable delay. The objection given is that SIS II has taken longer to complete than planned, but one cannot help but presume that there are political reasons for the delay, although the Commission invokes technical reasons. But I would like to ask, can this justify maintaining this clearly discriminatory situation? Is it not irresponsible to burden the new Member States with so great a security deficit?</p>
      <p sl="hu">For Hungary, as for the other new Member States, one of the main challenges since accession has been to attain full Schengen membership. In popular opinion, this is one of the signs of the credibility of enlargement, and therefore we have to be open to any solution that can make it possible for entry into this system to take place by the planned deadline. The Commission, the Council, and Parliament have a great responsibility in this regard.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-098" speaker_id="23807" name="Magda Kósáné Kovács" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="hu">We have reached an extremely important stage of a long process. We would like to thank everyone who took part in this process, and in particular the rapporteur.</p>
      <p sl="hu">Nevertheless, the current situation is not an entirely happy one for us, since it seems that a multilevel membership is emerging within the Union, which we consider unacceptable. It is not certain that the new Member States will be able to join the Schengen system in October 2007, although the lifting of internal borders is one of the most important achievements of the European Union, especially for the citizens of those Member States who during the days of dictatorship were either unable to travel to the 'old' Member States, or could do so only under excessively severe restrictions. The opening of the borders under Schengen on the one hand strengthens a sense of belonging to a single community on the part of new EU citizens, and on the other hand can increase the confidence of the old Member States in the new ones. For this reason, the question of what we can join and when is far from insignificant.</p>
      <p sl="hu">The delay officially recognised by the Commission comes as a shock to us. We know that adequate guarantees for the security of the new system are necessary, yet the opening of the borders is also a moral question for the new Member States. There are others who share our view, as we can see in the Portuguese proposal. As an MEP from a new Member State, I have mixed feelings. I am glad that there is solidarity among Member States, but I regret that for the moment our joining SIS I is not yet certain. What is certain is that everything that lies ahead will involve budget overruns.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-099" speaker_id="28514" name="Kyriacos Triantaphyllides" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, the second generation Schengen Information System is an enhanced version of the database used to record the data of the citizens of the European Union and of third countries on the pretext of safeguarding public order within the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="el">When we talk about the second generation Schengen Information System, we need to be clear. We are not simply talking about a technical aid which will help the Union to function better; we are talking about an institution of strategic importance, through which the forces of repression will acquire a politically enhanced role in order to combat terrorism and manage immigration, without any importance attached to data protection and without ensuring that data will not be passed to third countries.</p>
      <p sl="el">In fact, exactly the opposite is happening, given that the Union has endorsed the facility to transfer our personal data to the secret services of third countries, such as the USA, via Europol and Eurojust. We are therefore all potential terrorists, or perhaps the new order is, at the same time, imposing a new legal order, in which our freedoms must first be sifted by the secret services and then granted to us? And this is supposed not to worry us.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-100" speaker_id="28276" name="Laima Liucija Andrikienė" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="lt">I would first like to thank Mr Coelho, who mentioned at our session today that the SIS II system is very useful for the new EU Member States that planned to join the Schengen area in autumn 2007.</p>
      <p sl="lt">I would like to note that my country, Lithuania, was very earnest in its preparations for Schengen membership, as was confirmed by a recent inspection of readiness to join Schengen area by European Commission experts. After all, the free movement of persons, which would be ensured by the enlargement of Schengen, is one of the key freedoms on which the European Union is based.</p>
      <p sl="lt">Unfortunately, we have recently been informed that Schengen enlargement will be delayed for technical reasons because the preparatory work for the second generation of the Schengen Information System SIS II will not be completed on time.</p>
      <p sl="lt">I fully agree with the ideas voiced by the rapporteur and would like to note that we should urge the Commission to present exhaustive and transparent information and findings of investigations to Parliament, specifying how the main SIS II project is being implemented, including the reasons for the delay.</p>
      <p sl="lt">We should also urge the Commission and the Council to take steps to enable compliance with the original date for new EU Member States to join Schengen.</p>
      <p sl="lt">If this is not possible, we must encourage the Commission to present a comprehensive assessment of the impact of the delay, specifying the resources necessary to cover the financial and organisational costs deriving from the development and implementation of SIS II and the liability for such costs.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-101" speaker_id="28576" name="Stavros Lambrinidis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, with Schengen ΙΙ we are not, for better or for worse, reinventing the wheel. We already have the Schengen area in Europe for freedom of movement and security. We owed solidarity to the new Member States and we owed solidarity, which we are granting in this way, given that the Commission has announced that the system will not be ready for several years.</p>
      <p sl="el">However, with Schengen ΙΙ we also need to ensure that fundamental rights will be better protected than under Schengen Ι. Thanks to the amendments by the European Parliament, Schengen ΙΙ contains more detailed rules on data protection, makes provision for Community control of and responsibility for the functioning of the system, controls by the European Parliament and the jurisdiction of the European Court of Justice, bans access to third countries and makes provision for active control by the European Data Protection Supervisor and greater transparency.</p>
      <p sl="el">At the same time, however, the ministers are unfortunately persistent in their refusal to harmonise the alerts system. What does 'clear indications that someone has committed a serious criminal offence' mean? We are talking here of the possibility of arbitrary action by over-zealous police officers. Fortunately, the Commission will try to harmonise it in three years, but you will need to work on this, Commissioner Frattini.</p>
      <p sl="el">Finally, there is no data protection under the third pillar. The Council promised Parliament that it would do this, but it did not. Are we deluding ourselves? We are passing a measure here which, for the police and other authorities, concerns exchanges of private data, and yet the Council refuses to bring in this data protection measure, putting pressure on us instead to adopt this proposal.</p>
      <p sl="el">I thank you, Mr President, but you can be sure that, if we do not have this framework decision immediately, Parliament's voice will be heard loud and clear.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-102" speaker_id="28173" name="Zita Pleštinská" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="sk">Over the past few days, doubts concerning the original deadline for accession to the Schengen area in October 2007 have become a focus of mass media attention in the new Member States.</p>
      <p sl="sk">Compliance with the deadline is conditional on the deployment of the new generation Schengen Information System, SIS II. In this regard I consider Mr Coelho’s three reports to be very important. I would like to praise his work, including the amendments designed to make the Commission’s proposal more transparent and to ensure that the Council adopts the consensus in the first reading.</p>
      <p sl="sk">Even though these three reports to a large extent focus on technical matters rather than on the frequently discussed Schengen area enlargement date, their smooth passage and implementation will determine the conditions under which the 2007 deadline might be still feasible.</p>
      <p sl="sk">A delay in deploying the Schengen system would certainly increase the final cost of completing it. In the case of Slovakia alone it has so far entailed about EUR 6 million. For this reason we find any delay unacceptable.</p>
      <p sl="sk">In the Hague Programme of 5 November 2004 the European Council called on the Council, European Commission and Member States to take all possible steps to lift border checks on the European Union’s internal borders as soon as possible. Almost two years have elapsed since then, and the citizens of the Member States cannot understand the European Commission is only now tackling the technical and legal problems associated with implementing SIS II.</p>
      <p sl="sk">In conclusion I would like to call for consensus and for this legislation to be adopted in Parliament at first reading in order to ensure that the European Union does not lose credibility in the eyes of its citizens because of ineffective bureaucracy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-103" speaker_id="28129" name="Inger Segelström" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="sv">Mr President, Commissioner, fellow Members, ladies and gentlemen, I wish to thank Mr Coelho and others for their constructive work.</p>
      <p sl="sv">Those of us from the countries that have been able to participate in SIS have seen the ‘wanted’ register produce immediate results in our efforts to combat crime that knows no frontiers and that moves from one EU country to another. We are looking forward to a more developed SIS II system in which all 25, and soon all 27, countries can participate.</p>
      <p sl="sv">In the reports made accessible to citizens, this cooperation has given us both an instrument for preventing people with previous convictions from returning and a tool in the fight against drugs. We have also obtained a tool in the fight against people-traffickers, who not only smuggle in children and consign them to prostitution but also consign them to exploitation as a labour force. Once SIS II has been extended and brought into operation, we shall be able to supply Europeans with effective proof of our cooperation. This also means, however, that we must do more work both on combating crime and on protecting personal privacy.</p>
      <p sl="sv">Dialogue is required if we are to be able to meet the expectations that people have of us in the general debate on peace, security and justice as the basis for all the work we do. Is it not possible for such dialogue to take place more quickly, however?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-104" speaker_id="23717" name="Genowefa Grabowska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, the citizens of the old European Union have enjoyed freedom of movement within the Schengen system since 1985. Following enlargement, however, the system has been unable to cope with the citizens of the new Member States. So, if these people wish to cross a border they are still subjected to checks, and required to spend long hours queuing patiently at crossing points. The time has surely come to put an end to this divide between the old and the new EU, whereby the citizens of the old and 'better' European Union can enjoy the freedom of movement laid down in the Treaties, whilst for the citizens of the new and 'worse' countries time has stood still since 1985. It seems paradoxical that although FRONTEX, the agency charged with protecting the EU’s external borders, is located in Warsaw in a new Member State, Poles and citizens of other nations remain deprived of full freedom of movement within the European Union. I therefore call on this House to adopt the three reports debated today at first reading. We have to eliminate this tangible border which is perceived as a great wall that continues to divide the old from the new European Union. It is our duty to get rid of it. In conclusion, I would like to thank all the Members who have expressed solidarity with the new Member States today.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-105" speaker_id="37200" name="Katrin Saks" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="et">As the representative of a new Member State, I am very glad that the second generation of the Schengen Information System is nearing completion. The problem, however, is that the completion of the information system has been delayed. Whereas in June the Council confirmed that everything was under control and that the deadline would not change, two months later the situation was different.</p>
      <p sl="et">Today it is apparently clear to everyone that the expansion of Schengen will be delayed, but it is not clear exactly how long this delay will be. I believe it would be better for all parties if an honest answer were given to all those concerned as to when accession will take place.</p>
      <p sl="et">The new Member States have made a strong effort, and this must continue. We have problems in Estonia too. Our homework would, however, be much more effective if there were certainty concerning the future. Freedom of movement is not the only issue; there is also the fact that the uncertain situation creates mutual distrust. How does the Commission plan to act in this situation, and what would the deadlines be? This is a very important question today.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-106" speaker_id="28169" name="Edith Mastenbroek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, after months of heavy negotiating, two and a half minutes is simply not enough time in which to enlighten this Parliament with my vision. I am going to finish my speech if that is OK with you.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is now up to the European Commission and the relevant organisations within the Member States to make this new system perform in the best interest of our citizens. I want to call on the European Parliament here, however, to do some serious soul-searching about why we so often insist on having codecision, only to give it up again as soon as we can actually use it, and about our flip-flopping attitude concerning data protection. We will not prove the added value of the European Parliament to citizens by fighting for rights alone. We will prove that only by using them to society’s benefit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-107" speaker_id="28358" name="Konrad Szymański" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, Schengen is one of those EU projects that enables the citizens of the Member States to appreciate the benefits of belonging to the European Union. It makes travelling easier, helps with border control and also means crime can be dealt with more effectively. Parliament is keeping to its word and timetable, but the Commission is sadly lacking in this regard. It is still not clear when the new Member States will be able to join the enlarged system. The SIS I Plus proposal actually amounts to a step backwards, as it involves applying a different timeframe to the countries of the old and new European Union.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Along with other Central European countries, Poland implemented costly and politically difficult requirements in respect of its Eastern neighbours back in 2003. I shall be interested to know how Commissioner Frattini intends to explain to Polish, Czech, and Hungarian public opinion that the entry of our countries into the Schengen area has been delayed, possibly until 2009.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I shall also be interested to know whether the specific reasons for this delay will ever be divulged to us. It may well be that too many central EU institutions are located in Strasbourg and that it therefore cannot cope. But it may be that this situation is the result not of technical problems with the introduction of SIS II, but of the political reluctance of certain Member States to implement the Treaty in their domestic policy. I shall be unable to rid myself of such nagging suspicions until I receive a response to these questions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-109" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Franco Frattini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, I believe that the majority of the speakers have mentioned the major problems faced by the second generation Schengen Information System (SIS II), and that a minority of them mentioned the legal basis. I am therefore going to speak about the legal basis and about the major problems that the functionality of the system has brought up, but before doing so, I should like once again to thank the rapporteur, Mr Coelho, for having worked closely not only with the Council, but also with the European Commission, with the aim of reaching a satisfactory compromise on the legal basis about which I shall say a few words in a moment's time.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Several of you spoke about the delay in implementing the second generation system. I will, as ever, be frank with you: I believe that the game that consists in constantly looking for someone on whom to pin the blame, instead of resolving the problem, is not helpful. Why? Because the Member States, and especially those represented by the speakers who have taken the floor in this House, know only too well what has caused this delay. The Member States have already examined on several occasions the revised time-limits for implementation, which will be submitted for approval at the December Council. One of you spoke about 2009. I cannot guarantee that final approval will be given by the December Council, but the Commission proposal’s target date for the entry into operation of a second generation system is not 2009, but indeed June 2008. As for the delays - I repeat - they are linked to the purely technical problems relating to the functioning of the sites. Thus the central site, installed in Strasbourg, where we are, has experienced some delays. However, these delays are also linked to contractual procedures in several Member States, especially in the new Member States.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Furthermore, virtually all, or, at any rate, a great majority, of the Member States have requested more time in order to test the technical connections linking their national systems to the central site. It is the Member States that have requested an additional three-month extension, not the Council or the European Commission. The Council and the Commission have committed themselves to limiting the delay, and even to making up for the time lost. I can tell you that a working group, working alongside the Commission and the Member States, has been set up in order to oversee the implementation of the revised plan that I proposed and that the Member States have examined and are going to approve in December.</p>
      <p sl="fr">We are in the process of evaluating some temporary solutions. Thus, Portugal’s proposal, which has been called SIS Plus, is only a temporary solution in terms of reducing the time limit and can under no circumstances constitute an alternative to the SIS II system. I could also take account – and I am saying so here in this Parliament – of the financial impact of the delay on the new Member States. I am saying this and I am confirming it, but on one condition: that the Member States making the requests are not themselves lagging behind in terms, for example, of contractual procedures. Furthermore, I can tell you, in all honesty, that, to date, Slovenia is the only country technically able to meet the initial deadline of October 2007.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I should like to say a few words now about the legal basis. With regard to the proposal submitted to Parliament, I can say, just as Mr Coelho himself quite rightly said, that this is a good result for the European Union. The controls carried out by the police authorities will be made more effective, with the result that the external borders will be more secure and an appropriate level of protection of personal data will also be maintained. Frankly, I hope, like several of you do, that the Council will finally act on the political commitment made by the Austrian and Finnish Presidencies, and by that I mean the agreement on the proposal for a framework directive aimed at integrating data protection into the third pillar so as to create a comprehensive system incorporating security and the protection of fundamental rights.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Parliament, the Council and the Commission have shown that they are capable of working together to reach a balanced compromise. The new Member States are rightly calling for the controls at their external borders to be lifted. The fact that we are acting fairly swiftly in guaranteeing all EU citizens a real area of free movement is one of the most visible results of EU enlargement. Finally, any delay due to the legal basis is going to affect this major political result for Europe, which was a priority objective in the accession treaty.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-110" speaker_id="1405" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The joint debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place on Wednesday at 12.30.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem17" title="17. Women's immigration (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-112" speaker_id="1405" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report by Rodi Kratsa-Tsagaropoulou, on behalf of the Committee on Women’s Rights and Gender Equality, on women’s immigration: the role and place of immigrant women in the European Union (2006/2010(INI)) (A6-0307/2006).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-113" speaker_id="4482" name="Rodi Kratsa-Tsagaropoulou" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, the report which I had the honour of drafting on behalf of the Committee on Women's Rights and Gender Equality is designed to help broaden the debate and our political action on the question of immigration by introducing the parameter of women's immigration.</p>
      <p sl="el">This parameter is becoming more and more important given that, in the enlarged European Union, there is a constant increase in women from various areas of the world who are immigrating either in isolation, as independent economic migrants, or within the framework of the migration of their families or for other reasons, accounting for approximately 54% of all immigrants, although this is not an exact figure.</p>
      <p sl="el">We all realise today that our objectives for development and social cohesion are directly linked to the management of migration flows, by ensuring that immigrants are valued and integrated into our communities. As such, the 'femalisation' – if you will permit the phrase – of immigration is a new challenge which must be studied and taken into account in all our policies. Female immigrants, either at a personal level or as members of their families, can constitute added value both for our communities and for their communities of origin.</p>
      <p sl="el">In our report, reference is made to the problems faced by female immigrants. These problems have to do with the discrimination which they suffer on the labour market and in education and, more specifically, with the recognition of their qualifications and vocational skills and they are problems which result in unemployment and poverty. Reference is also made to cases of violation of human rights, such as violence and sexual exploitation, which are matters which we have repeatedly debated and condemned in the European Parliament.</p>
      <p sl="el">We also wish to shed light on the problems faced by women in certain immigrant communities, in which they are the victims of cultural and religious stereotypes, resulting in their marginalisation. Even worse are the cases of forced marriages and crimes of honour.</p>
      <p sl="el">The basic thrust of our report and the resolution which we propose is, on the one hand, the protection of the rights of immigrants and, on the other hand, their improved integration into the labour market and social life. This means, first of all, the application of the acquis communautaire in order to remove discrimination, prevent trafficking and make provision for family reunification and the rights of women as accompanying family members.</p>
      <p sl="el">The report recognises the right of the Member States to decide on the numbers and rules under which they accept immigrants into their country. Within this framework of national legislation, therefore, we support respect for the rights of women, their family rights and, more importantly, the rights of children, in accordance with international conventions and protocols.</p>
      <p sl="el">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, we recognise that integration is a complex and two-way process. Therefore, alongside this framework of reception and respect for the rights of immigrants, which we must apply with proper coordination and use of all our policies, we must cooperate seriously with the countries of origin and the immigrant communities in our countries so that we can prepare the proper integration of immigrants and, more importantly, of female immigrants, because they are the ones who know least of all about their rights and about the benefits and obligations which derive from those rights. These have to do with language, with the authorities, with our values, with the potential for vocational careers and with the potential to participate in the educational system of their children. Thus our objectives for development and prosperity and our fight for solidarity, justice throughout the world and the protection of human rights will be better achieved.</p>
      <p sl="el">My warmest thanks to all the political groups whose participation enriched my work and helped us to prepare a text which is cohesive, respects subsidiarity and the Community and international legal acquis and includes a courageous and in-depth approach to the real problems and the real challenges.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-114" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Franco Frattini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, I must truly congratulate the rapporteur on this report.</p>
      <p sl="it">I broadly agree with her remarks, firstly as regards access to the labour market. I believe that the role of women can represent one of the factors contributing to the creation, in Europe, of a genuinely balanced and comprehensive development and employment policy. As you will know, this is one of the objectives of the Lisbon Strategy and it is primarily a means of guaranteeing women a full role within society and a genuine life of independence, and I therefore fully support the emphasis laid on the theme of employment.</p>
      <p sl="it">I also support the emphasis laid on the theme of the integration of immigrant women, firstly as regards language learning. Learning the language of one’s country of residence must be a fundamental part of everyone’s integration, be they men, women, children or babies. In particular, as regards women immigrants, we note that there has been a delay in guaranteeing them genuine access to the languages spoken in their host countries, and that is a factor that slows down and hinders integration.</p>
      <p sl="it">As the rapporteur rightly points out, the theme of integration is connected to the crucial dialogue between cultures and religions. I believe that the European Union is based on absolute values in terms of respect for the dignity of every woman and every man, and that it is therefore impossible to accept, under any circumstances, acts that demean human dignity, in this case women's dignity, as they are the polar opposite of symbols of integration.</p>
      <p sl="it">I am concerned about cases in which, for example, women are made, against their own will, to wear submissive symbols of their female status, such as veils that completely cover their faces and do not allow them to be seen. Unfortunately, these are symbols that sit uncomfortably with integration and suggest the subjection of women.</p>
      <p sl="it">I also think it absurd that, in some European countries, so-called honour crimes, or, as I would instead call them, ‘dishonour crimes’ take place, and I will, of course, be doing even more to promote initiatives aimed at abolishing these crimes. In my view, they must be treated harshly, not lightly, because, with motives like these, they attack absolute values such as human life, physical integrity and dignity.</p>
      <p sl="it">When applying the European directive on family reunification, we intend to pay special attention to the prevention of forced marriages. This is another theme on which I shall be working. As you know, this is a binding directive for the Member States. When applying the directive at national level, I shall pay special attention to forms of violence within the family, such as forced and polygamous marriages – which are not permitted by the laws of the European Union and of the Member States – and to the guarantees made to women in the event of separation or divorce, so that they cannot be singled out as second-class citizens when their marriages break down.</p>
      <p sl="it">With regard to the directives on asylum seekers and refugees, I believe that one aspect needs to be highlighted. For the first time, discrimination against women must be made to count as sufficient grounds for obtaining refugee status. I believe that being subjected to violence within the family and to female genital mutilation, or being at risk of being subjected to a forced marriage, is enough of a reason for women who demonstrate that they are exposed to such risks to be granted 'refugee' status.</p>
      <p sl="it">Finally, in all sincerity, once again, I should like to point out to the rapporteur an aspect on which I harbour some doubts, namely granting illegal woman immigrants exactly the same status as legal women immigrants. I believe that there is an area in which absolute rights must be guaranteed to everyone, without any difference in status. It is clear that people cannot be denied rights to health care, emergency medical treatment and a minimum level of subsistence just because, for a given period of time – perhaps while they are waiting to be repatriated – they reside in a country illegally.</p>
      <p sl="it">There is certainly a basis of rights that they have in common, but I believe that we should not go beyond that and mix up the two levels. There is illegal immigrant status, which is regulated and dealt with in one way. Legal immigrant status is different. To put them both on exactly the same footing sends out a dangerous message, and it is obviously on this point that we are working, in order to achieve a balanced European policy both on illegal immigration and on legal immigration.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-115" speaker_id="4423" name="Amalia Sartori" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I gladly take the floor to endorse Mrs Kratsa-Tsagaropoulou’s report, even though I do so with a touch of sadness, since, last weekend, we received a further tragic piece of news in relation to women, namely the stoning to death of a woman in Baghdad, on Saturday 21 October.</p>
      <p sl="it">I believe that everyone is aware of the fact that it is only by women having equal dignity throughout the world that a change can occur, too, in the major problems facing the world today. It was in this frame of mind and with this firm belief, that is to say with a firm belief in the value and the role that women can have now and in the future in enabling this world to move towards a solution of peaceful coexistence, that I welcomed the work done by Mrs Kratsa-Tsagaropoulou, in which consideration is given above all to the fact that women migrants are a somewhat special case.</p>
      <p sl="it">We would prefer it if this were not the case, but it is. In a world in which the division is still so clear-cut – and for a large part of the world there is still a division in terms of rights and duties – I believe that treating women and men migrants in the same way would probably be a mistake, just as it is always a mistake to treat different circumstances identically.</p>
      <p sl="it">The Union therefore needs to pay special attention to women’s immigration, also taking account of implications that do not, in contrast, characterise men’s immigration. I believe that we can find this focus in Mrs Kratsa-Tsagaropoulou’s report, which I accordingly intend to support.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-116" speaker_id="28168" name="Marie-Line Reynaud" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PSE Group">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, I should like sincerely to thank Mrs Kratsa for her commitment and her sense of cooperation. This own-initiative report is, in my view, one of the most important reports dealing with women’s rights that we have had to express an opinion on since the start of the Parliamentary term.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The situation of women migrants has been overlooked for too long by our governments, despite the fact that they are growing in number and that they now account for the majority of the people arriving on EU soil. They are the ones who forge the first links between their families and nationals in terms of society and integration. Indeed, this report offers many guidelines aimed at putting a stop to the two forms of discrimination - racial and sexual discrimination - that these women often suffer.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I am particularly delighted that a number of provisions have been included in this report that concern illegal women immigrants, because they represent a sub-category that is deprived of its rights and thus made all the more vulnerable. It is therefore vital that these women can benefit, in whichever Member State they are resident, from basic rights such as access to emergency health care, legal aid and schools for their children, as is the case in my country.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Finally, I am delighted that this report features another point to which I am particularly attached, namely the status of women who arrive on EU territory within the context of the family reunification process. These women often only exist in law through their husbands and are therefore placed in a situation of complete dependence. This report calls for them to be granted an independent and autonomous status as quickly as possible and, above all, for this status to be automatically preserved in the event of the couple separating.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I therefore hope that this report will be adopted by a large majority within our Parliament and that the ambitious proposals that it contains will not go unheeded.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-117" speaker_id="1059" name="Hiltrud Breyer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, this report by Mrs Kratsa-Tsagaropoulou – for which I am grateful – puts plenty wind in the sails of women’s rights, particularly the rights of women immigrants, and that was long overdue.</p>
      <p sl="de">We have for too long taken an attitude of cultural relativism towards women immigrants for granted. I am glad to see that the report incorporates many of the things we have been pressing for, such as the requirement that instances of genital mutilation be reported and that there be penalties, if necessary under criminal law for forced marriages, which have been long overdue. I hope we will also be able to get language courses for migrant women made compulsory, for language is an important component in integration and, without them, they will be unable to avail themselves of their rights.</p>
      <p sl="de">We must put a stop to the situation in which girls from families that have migrated to Europe are exempted sex education classes and sports, which are mandatory for others, and in which some of them are even taken out of school or forbidden to go there. We need to be very determined about this and speak out about it loud and clear.</p>
      <p sl="de">We also see it as very important that women should acquire a legal status independent of that of their husbands, and it is on this point that I would like to address Commissioner Frattini personally, for I recently, in a written question, asked to be informed as to whether he shared my concern about the series of court rulings in various Member States that, in the way in which they accord state benefits, effectively endorse polygamy.</p>
      <p sl="de">I was quite horrified to be told, by a Commissioner with responsibility for justice matters, that the object of polygamy was the protection of women. Bigamy is prohibited in Europe, and I would welcome an answer from the Commissioner, for I cannot imagine that he would knowingly allow it to be stated that polygamy was intended to protect women, whilst certain forms of same-sex partnership are outlawed.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-118" speaker_id="4302" name="Feleknas Uca" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I really am very grateful to Mrs Kratsa-Tsagaropoulou for her wide-ranging report, which we in the Confederal Group of the European United Left/Nordic Green Left fully endorse, and adds a great deal to the information available on the rights of women migrants in the EU.</p>
      <p sl="de">Knowing as we do that women now constitute 54% of all immigrants, it is quite utterly incomprehensible and shocking that the attitude of European governments towards them should betray such ignorance and that they should be doing so little to meet the specific needs that women immigrants have.</p>
      <p sl="de">My particular concern is that we should take this opportunity to note the flagrant deficiencies in the Member States’ integration policies, with women immigrants being expected to adapt to the system in silence and without difficulty, not making any demands and allowing the national labour market to make the maximum possible profit out of them. When countries spend decades averting their eyes from the challenges that immigrants present and then make them carry the can for their inadequate integration, I see that as no more than further evidence of ignorance and political blindness.</p>
      <p sl="de">I want to see gender-specific migration management that will be consistent in taking seriously immigrant women’s rights to education, health, safety and independence and in ensuring that those things are available to more and more of them. If that is not done, we risk a further increase in the trafficking of women, in the exploitation of female domestic staff, in the social isolation of women and in domestic violence.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-119" speaker_id="1941" name="Roberta Angelilli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the UEN Group">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I should like to begin by congratulating the rapporteur on the excellent work she has done, and in particular on the fact that she has highlighted some important priorities enabling us to ensure that immigration is primarily understood as two-way integration – therefore involving social, linguistic and cultural aspects – that is to say integration based on mutual respect for rights and duties.</p>
      <p sl="it">Among the main rights that must be guaranteed to women migrants is that of preventing and combating honour crimes, forced marriages, genital mutilation or any other form of violent constraint and exploitation. In this regard, I, on behalf of my group, have tabled an amendment highlighting the need to carry out extensive information campaigns aimed precisely at women migrants, so that they can be informed of their rights and of the bodies that they can turn in times of need.</p>
      <p sl="it">Finally, the European Union needs at last to adopt specific provisions to encourage the Member States, too, to draft laws explicitly prohibiting some of the crimes and issues about which we have already spoken. To conclude, I should like to thank Mr Frattini for the commitment that he has emphasised this evening, too, a commitment that the Commission intends to put to use in addressing these problems.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-120" speaker_id="28334" name="Urszula Krupa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the IND/DEM Group">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, the very serious problem of emigration, particularly by women, due to increasing globalisation and the complexities of contemporary life should also be considered from the point of view of the irreparable damage to their countries of origin. In addition I must mention the problem of increasing poverty in countries exploited by rich and highly developed ones. There are certainly ways in which the opportunity to leave one’s homeland can prove positive. Nonetheless, emigrants are cut off from a community bound together by its history, traditions and culture. An individual who could have contributed to increasing the common good leaves. When that person starts life all over again in a foreign culture and language, he or she is working for the benefit of another society. Such people are often exploited because of their circumstances. That is why it is vital to have the relevant legislation in place, particularly regarding social protection and the individual’s right to work. The document under debate goes some way towards emphasising this. An appropriate scale of values is also important, where moral values are also given a place alongside purely material gain, and human labour is considered in the broader sense of the word, although the latter should not mean interference in the personal lives of women who want to have children and bring up families.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-121" speaker_id="22418" name="Esther Herranz García" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, emigration is necessary and it also enriches our society in cultural, economic and social terms, and we are not going to deny that today. It is the case, however, that it can cause us problems if we do not manage it properly.</p>
      <p sl="es">It should never be a problem, because we must ensure that it is not one when we draw up these laws in all of the parliaments of the European Union. If the parliaments are not careful, however, they may cause problems that turn into xenophobia and racism in our societies, and that is precisely what we must prevent.</p>
      <p sl="es">A mistake has been made in drawing up this report, since it has not just dealt with legal emigration, but has treated legal and illegal emigration on the same footing. This is a dangerous message, because some of the things that this report says may have certain mafia gangs rubbing their hands with glee.</p>
      <p sl="es">Democracy, which is the system that fortunately governs all of us, is based on the freedom of the individual, and that is guaranteed through respect for the law, both the laws of the Member States – because this problem is subject to subsidiarity – and the Regulations and Directives that we have now and in the future.</p>
      <p sl="es">The important thing is respect for the law. I fear that some of the amendments presented by the radical left do not respect the law of the Member States and run counter to equality, democracy and the freedom of the individual.</p>
      <p sl="es">I would therefore ask the House to think hard about these amendments, which are designed to attract mafias, to confuse emigrants and to attract more illegal immigration. They are going to be of little use to emigrants and European citizens as a whole, given the draw effects, given the comings and goings and dealings of mafias and given the fact that the criteria for granting residents’ permits are not clear.</p>
      <p sl="es">I would like to make an appeal to this House and the Commission with regard to cases of mutilation or forced marriage. When it comes to talking to third countries and giving them money for cooperation, we must – if we genuinely want to protect women and women’s equality – demand of those countries, before giving them that money, that they respect minimum fundamental rights.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-122" speaker_id="28310" name="Edite Estrela" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pt">I should like to begin by congratulating Mrs Kratsa-Tsagaropoulou. We agree that European immigration policy must encompass the gender dimension and the situation of women in the Member States, because they suffer from twofold discrimination: sexual and ethnic, as has been mentioned by previous speakers. What is more, they suffer from discrimination both in the host society and within their own community.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The involvement of immigrant women in all areas of the host country’s social life is a vital factor in making them less isolated and in enabling them to help the younger generations to integrate. For this to happen, a number of barriers need to come down, beginning with the linguistic barrier. In some immigrant communities, not only are women marginalised, they are also forced into marriages and subjected to humiliating and cruel practices, such as genital mutilation. They also fall victim to honour crimes, as Mr Frattini mentioned. The Member States have a duty to do all they can to put an end to these criminal practices, victims of which have justifiable grounds for being granted asylum.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-123" speaker_id="4453" name="Luisa Morgantini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I am grateful to Mrs Kratsa-Tsagaropoulou for her characteristic sensitivity and for the positive proposals on the role and status of both legal and illegal immigrant women in the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="it">We are concerned here with women migrants who are discriminated against in the workplace, physically and mentally violated, used as commodities for sex trafficking, deprived of their freedom and passports, held to ransom by patriarchal customs and killed in honour crimes. I should, however, like to point out to us all that, in reality, these women are used and exploited by European families and European businessmen. They are very often alone, with the pain of having left behind their children in their countries of origin. They work as carers, alleviating the suffering and the loneliness of the elderly and the sick, and they do not have any security. I believe that we need to do a great deal in relation to this issue.</p>
      <p sl="it">These women represent a high percentage of the immigrant base and a major resource for the countries of Europe. They are not just victims; these women are all different and, in recent years, they have organised themselves into associations, sought to establish relations and put themselves in touch with women from their host countries. These women are requesting access to information, health care and housing. They want to have control over their lives, and we must help them. That is why we must mainstream the fight against discrimination and apply in every Member State the directives that the European Union has provided itself with – and about which Mr Frattini was also speaking – from the reception of migrants up to and including active citizenship. The experiences of women migrants and their criticism of inequality are helping to pave the way for establishing democracy in relation to the few differences that exist.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-124" speaker_id="28343" name="Bogusław Rogalski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, we are currently witnessing mass migration which has a variety of causes. There is economic migration, where the aim is to earn more and improve one’s standard of living. That is the most common type of migration. Then there is migration to reunify a family or to escape from persecution in the country of origin.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Technological development has meant that it is becoming ever easier and cheaper to travel in today’s world, so the problem of immigration can only increase. It is therefore incumbent on us to take appropriate measures to deal with the growing number of new arrivals, particularly in Europe. The sensible long-term solution would be to avoid discriminating against foreigners, especially against women who are in the majority. Too many immigrants are being consigned to the margins of society at present. The Member States should create better conditions for immigrants to integrate into our societies, whilst still retaining a pride in their origins. This would allow us to pre-empt the problem of alienating immigrants, which leads to frustration and sometimes to violent disturbances, and very often results in a life of poverty.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-125" speaker_id="23866" name="Edit Bauer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="sk">The Commission’s communication about the demographic future of Europe notes that over the next five decades the working-age population of the Member States will decline dramatically, by an estimated 48 million people.</p>
      <p sl="sk">Even an optimistic scenario involving a resumption of demographic growth and the discovery of new sources of productivity would still leave Europe needing a major inflow of new migrants, estimated at 40 million people. This may be the most serious challenge facing the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="sk">The report we have before us, for which I would like to thank Mrs Kratsa-Tsagaropoulou, indicates that the position of migrant women plays a crucial role in the process. This group of women deserves special attention, not only because they are frequent targets of discrimination but also because they have a key mission in facilitating the integration of the first and second generations of migrants; therefore, the access of such women to education is of fundamental importance. Against the backdrop of these challenges, the need to develop common procedures for integrating migrants, and to devise common procedures over immigration policy appears both urgent and unavoidable. The diverging approaches adopted by the individual states give rise to unnecessary confusion.</p>
      <p sl="sk">Developments in the area of human trafficking and human smuggling also point to a pressing need for clear immigration policies, for transparency, for unequivocal rules and for access to the common labour market. A lack of legitimate opportunities clearly encourages illegal activities, with illegal migrants being greatly exposed to all sorts of human rights violations and left without the assistance to which they would otherwise be entitled as victims.</p>
      <p sl="sk">In our future deliberations, however, it is essential to make a clear distinction between asylum policy, legitimate migration and illegal migration. Confusing these notions would generate new and unnecessary misunderstandings.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-126" speaker_id="28153" name="Britta Thomsen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="da">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I would like to thank the rapporteur for this very important and highly relevant report. The nature of immigration into Europe has undergone a change. Today, more women than men come to Europe, as there is a great demand for workers in the operational service and healthcare sector. However, the labour market in question is also characterised by a large grey economy in which the normal rules for pay, working hours and the working environment do not apply. Women therefore find themselves in a very vulnerable situation without social and economic protection, and many of them perform jobs that do not provide the opportunity of becoming legal.</p>
      <p sl="da">Their vulnerability puts these illegal women immigrants at greater risk of being abused, both physically and mentally, while their illegal status in itself makes them easy prey for those who wish to abuse them and sexually exploit them in the workplace. They are also particularly at risk of being denied their fundamental rights, and they become victims of violence and discrimination in their everyday lives. Many do not dare report assaults for fear of deportation.</p>
      <p sl="da">It is absolutely imperative to place the conditions in which immigrant women find themselves more firmly in the spotlight. We need to ensure that the Member States take account, through their legislation, of the problems facing immigrant women. Those women who are victims of people-trafficking or who are exposed to violence should be given the opportunity of being granted temporary residence permits and have the right to legal aid and access to healthcare and social services, irrespective of whether or not they have a legal right to stay in the country in question.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-127" speaker_id="28976" name="Pia Elda Locatelli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I concur with Mrs Kratsa-Tsagaropoulou’s report, and in this regard I would like to point out, in agreement with her, that the implementation in the Union of the directive on family reunification is unsatisfactory and that there is a need to amend the directive with the aim of reducing the time it takes to obtain autonomous status for spouses, almost always wives, and of guaranteeing that spouses' status will be maintained in the event of separation, divorce or widowhood.</p>
      <p sl="it">In addition, I would like to emphasise the importance of several instruments of Community intervention, in particular the Daphne programme, since these instruments fill in the gaps in national policies, which are all too often lacking with regard to the gender dimension in both policy content and data collection. Finally, the report calls for the risk of female genital mutilation to be included as grounds for requesting asylum.</p>
      <p sl="it">I agree with this, but I believe that now is the time to include as grounds for requesting asylum other factors involving the repression of female sexuality, such as homosexuality and so-called adulterous behaviour, for countries in which these acts carry violent punishments. I am thinking, in this regard, of stoning to death in Iran.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-128" speaker_id="28171" name="Emine Bozkurt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="nl">Mr President, migrant women as a group, vulnerable though it is, are not so much a problem as an opportunity. They are vulnerable because they may be exposed to discrimination, not only for being women, but also on the basis of their being Muslim, Somali or Moroccan. They are also vulnerable to domestic violence, or because they do not speak the local language, or are financially dependent on their spouses or fathers. We must therefore support them by not letting domestic violence and honour crimes go unpunished, but that cannot be done by imposing stricter rules alone. Rights on paper are not sufficient for women; they must also be able to assert them in practice, because a woman who is dependent on the perpetrator of domestic violence will, in practice, not benefit a great deal from her rights on paper.</p>
      <p sl="nl">That is why we must promote the financial independence of migrant women by, for example, counteracting discrimination within the labour market. The economy benefits when more migrant women participate in the labour market. Another opportunity we cannot afford to miss is the positive impact migrant women can have on the integration of their children in the new society. That is why, as a host community, we must be open to support of, and contact with, migrant women, for they, too, belong here. I am pleased that Mrs Kratsa-Tsagaropoulou deals with these aspects at great length in her excellent report, and I should therefore like to thank her for it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-129" speaker_id="28349" name="Teresa Riera Madurell" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, I would like to congratulate the rapporteur and emphasise one consideration. Any immigration policy must surely take account of specific gender issues, but also the differences between immigrant communities, since the causes of the double discrimination suffered by immigrant women and the problems resulting from it differ according to their reasons for emigrating.</p>
      <p sl="es">If women emigrating alone for economic reasons find work, it is usually low-level work, sometimes in undeclared jobs, which gives them neither the independence nor the security they were seeking, though it allows them to relate to people and to integrate further. Nevertheless, women emigrating for the purposes of family reunification usually stay at home, with no opportunity to familiarise themselves with the host society or to learn the language, and that hinders their integration and increases their isolation.</p>
      <p sl="es">The designation of 2007 as ‘European year of equal opportunities for all’ and of 2008 as ‘European year of intercultural dialogue’ must help to increase citizens’ awareness of the situation of immigrant women, one that is always tough but which varies in nature, and to implement policies to promote equality and integration in accordance with each different situation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-130" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Franco Frattini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I would like to make just a brief observation after having listened to many speeches which I endorse. First, Mrs Breyer, I would like to tell you that I have always considered and will always consider polygamous marriage to be against the law and a serious violation of the right of women to choose freely. I can therefore confirm to you that I will continue to move in this direction.</p>
      <p sl="it">Some of the Members who have spoken – Mrs Angelilli and Mrs Morgantini – have raised the issue of communication. I believe – if I may say so – that giving a voice to immigrant women in a more direct and stronger way can be of great help, even in drawing up stronger European defence policies. ‘Giving a voice’ means allowing these people to have effective means at their disposal to be able to speak and to be listened to. Otherwise, there is a risk – if I may say so – that the voices of these women may also be subject to a filter operated by the communities in which they reside.</p>
      <p sl="it">In many European countries cases of personal segregation and submission of immigrant women have been observed. This is the group, among the many with which I work, from which I receive the lowest number of individual complaints. When compared with other sectors connected with the protection of people’s fundamental rights, individual violence against women in immigrant communities is the area in which the fewest complaints about specific cases are received. Why? Because there is a fear of reporting such cases, because they are never communicated, because the women themselves are subjected to violence so that they do not disclose the abuses that they are suffering within the free and democratic territory of the Member States. Communication is therefore an absolutely central issue.</p>
      <p sl="it">Finally, precisely to help this integration effort, I would like to point out that in Spring 2007 I will be publishing a European manual on integration, which will be issued in all the languages spoken in the countries of the European Union, containing descriptions of cases of successful integration in the cities, provinces and regions where they have been found. By distributing millions of copies of this practical manual, we will publicise positive examples so that they can be imitated. These are examples coming from the world of local bodies. I can inform you that up to now the sector for which I have the least information is precisely that of the integration of immigrant women.</p>
      <p sl="it">I am therefore appealing to you, so that in the coming months I may receive specific examples, both positive and negative, on which I can take action. Otherwise, we will carry on making important statements of principle without being able to translate them into practical action, something that I, however, intend to do.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-131" speaker_id="1405" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place tomorrow at 12.00.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statement (Rule 142)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-213" speaker_id="23805" name="Zita Gurmai" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Large number of immigrants, with special emphasis on women, face multiple discrimination and vulnerability to social exclusion. This is the highest challenge for us how to integrate them into the society, to help them getting access to proper education which helps them to wider employment facilities and to contribution to the development of the European Project.</p>
      <p sl="en">Proper legal framework is just one side of the coin. Implementation of legal commitments by the relevant national authorities, willingness of immigrants to respect fundamental European norms, values and to become the integral part of the society is the other.</p>
      <p sl="en">Huge potential lies in successful integration policies since wider employment of immigrants could help with getting forward with Lisbon employment targets.</p>
      <p sl="en">No actions can gain success without proper and regular dialogue with immigrant communities. The dialogues are perfect tools for monitoring integration processes, learning about mutual interests, intentions, request as well as obligations, determining and if necessary, altering methods and of inclusion programs.</p>
      <p sl="en">The forthcoming European year of equal opportunities 2007 and the year of intercultural dialogue 2008 will be a useful and potential framework opportunity to provide immigrant societies with a wide range of information on their rights, opportunities as well as informing them what Europe is expecting from them.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem18" title="18. Recovery of Community funds (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-133" speaker_id="1405" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report by Paulo Casaca, on behalf of the Committee on Budgetary Control, on the recovery of Community funds (2005/2163(INI)) (A6-0303/2006).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-134" speaker_id="4447" name="Paulo Casaca" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="pt">Mr President, Commissioner, if we are to recover the amounts missing from the Community budget, what is needed is suitable determination, paperwork, transparency, stringency, proportionality and harmonisation of the rules and procedures. Sadly, we are a long way off achieving that.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The European institutions must not shut themselves away in a world of rules and regulations, far removed from reality. For this reason, this report on the recovery of Community funds takes as its starting point a specific example: never before have we had a bigger sum to recover – it is put at almost EUR 100 million – and the circumstances surrounding the missing money are worse still.</p>
      <p sl="pt">This concerns a crime perpetrated by a criminal organisation that has enjoyed the collusion of any number of European companies, and, following the investigation and cooperation on the part of the Italian authorities, the European bodies were notified of the details of the case. The Guardia de finanzia held an investigation into the illegal import of butter by firms controlled by the Naples Camorra, the adulteration of that butter with unrendered beef fat, vegetable oils and a chemical known as lipostrol, the sale of tens of thousands of tonnes of the finished product to various European companies and lastly the use of this product for the fraudulent use of export refunds and disposal subsidies for pastry goods. The findings of this investigation were then passed on to the relevant Community and national authorities.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Seven years after the Italian investigation, and what has happened? In one of the Member States concerned, the authorities only decided to launch an inquiry four years after the original Italian report came out, and none of the estimated missing EUR 40 million has been recovered. In another Member State, the inquiry has not even got off the ground, so none of the EUR 50 million-plus has been recovered. In a third Member State, the problem was deemed merely administrative and the original fines have been cut and the amounts involved almost nominal.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Outside Italy, where, on the basis of a national initiative, dozens of people were arrested for murder, illegal possession of weapons and association to commit offences, and where complex legal processes are ongoing, there is no realistic expectation of securing any convictions in the countries concerned or of the Community money being recovered. Everything indicates that the whole process will lapse.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Owing to legal confidentiality, most of the national authorities responsible for food safety have not, as yet, been notified of this fraud. While the Community and national authorities act with such a lack of determination and coordination in addressing a crime of this magnitude, countless cases have come to light, in which, under discretionary powers granted in the cause of recovering Community funds, the authorities have hounded honest farmers to return money, without any substantive justification and for procedural reasons that are not always genuine, and this has often left the farmers in a state of poverty. For these farmers the principles of the presumption of innocence, the right to be informed of the nature of an accusation, proportionality and the guarantee of adequate resources to mount a defence are not worth the paper they are written on. The crux of the matter is that Article 280 of the Treaty is being ignored. The notion of cooperation between the Commission and the Member States for protecting the Community’s financial interests is pie in the sky. The effective and equivalent protection of these interests for the citizens is not being delivered.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Against this backdrop, root and branch changes must be carried out, be it by redefining the functions of Eurojust, by establishing a European Public Prosecutor or by some other means. We need a European initiative that ensures that cooperation on justice, with a view to protecting the Community's financial interests, is backed up by action, and is not mere rhetoric, as has happened in this case, the biggest of its kind in the area of Community finance.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-136" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Dalia Grybauskaitė" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to thank Mr Casaca for a very good, interesting and useful report. It takes account of direct management, which is mainly the responsibility of the Commission, and shared management, which the Commission shares with the Member States.</p>
      <p sl="en">Regarding recoveries in direct management, the Commission thanks the rapporteur for his support in the current revision of financial regulation which we have already placed on the table, in particular the proposals aiming to establish a uniform time limit of five years, and of course the level of privilege for Community entitlement to fiscal claims in national law which, to our regret, the Council was reluctant to support.</p>
      <p sl="en">Regarding recoveries in shared management, the Commission agrees with the emphasis placed on the responsibility of the Member States, since this accounts for the biggest part of Community expenditure. The Commission shares the rapporteur’s analysis concerning the low level of recoveries by some Member States. In one particular case, the sum involved is EUR 95 million.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, I would like to mention that this Commission has laid special emphasis on recovery. Between 2003 and 2006, the Commission was able to reduce recovery amounts from EUR 553 million to only EUR 160 million by September this year. The specific case of the 95 million is the subject of a criminal investigation in the court of one Member State and another is involved in the problem. So in fact less than EUR 100 million have to be recovered in the near future, and EUR 95 million after the investigation has been completed.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are very satisfied with the report as a whole. We are working with Parliament, especially the rapporteur on the Financial Regulation. We are cooperating closely with the Committee on Budgets on that. We shall give a proper response to your report and your recommendations in writing.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-137" speaker_id="28220" name="Ingeborg Gräßle" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, let me start by extending my group's thanks to the rapporteur for a really very interesting and also important report, for there is still a lot wrong with the way in which the funds to which the Community is entitled are recovered, particularly in the way in which the Member States go about it, and it is certainly very regrettable that the Council is conspicuous by its absence today.</p>
      <p sl="de">We can see that more progress has been made since you, Commissioner, took the matter in hand, but I do believe that we will still have to get seriously stuck in to improvements in specific areas over the coming months, particularly in agricultural policy, which is at the heart of the whole recovery issue, and where much is still not as it should be, with 70% of old claims dating back to the period from 1971 to 2002. We are talking here about EUR 3.1 billion, 70% of which has still not yet been recovered. The present situation is pretty shameful. The total recovered amounts to less than one fifth of the EUR 6 billion outstanding in 2002.</p>
      <p sl="de">The President of the Court of Auditors said recently – and may I say, Mr President, that I object to the timing of this debate, since a very important report is being presented to the Committee on Budgetary Control at this very moment – that recovery was proceeding at an increasing sluggish pace and that the penalties are wholly unsuitable. The problem lies with the Member States; I believe that all of us here in this House are on the same side and will, come what may, raise the parity of tax demands and claims for the repayment of funds as an issue in the deliberations on the Financial Regulation, for we regard this as vitally important.</p>
      <p sl="de">It is also important that there should be more support for the auditors who work where these things happen, particularly those who work for national authorities, for they face the possibility of being punished for their own department’s failings, and so they need our special protection.</p>
      <p sl="de">There is another problem within the Commission itself. Until recently, it was impossible to ascertain just how much was currently outstanding, and I hope that the improved accounting procedures will improve matters. I will close by saying that we will ensure that this issue stays on the agenda.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-138" speaker_id="4515" name="Jeffrey Titford" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the IND/DEM Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, I believe this report is a long and drawn-out justification for the creation of a European public prosecutor. Indeed, judging by Mr Casaca’s tone, he is positively affronted to find that the law of a Member State should ever prevail over the Commission: heaven forbid! According to this document, to get round the problem we should create a law officer with authority to overrule the laws of Member States. This is to be done ‘in the interests of a more joined-up procedure’, and the other vital reason quoted is to help reduce complexity.</p>
      <p sl="de">As a staunch defender of the national state, I strongly oppose the creation of a European public prosecutor and anyone in this Chamber who sincerely believes in democracy rather than just paying it lip service should oppose it too. I particularly call upon MEPs from my country to stand with me in defence of British law.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-139" speaker_id="28255" name="Andreas Mölzer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, it is evident that many regard the squandering of EU funds as a minor offence, for there seems to be no other explanation for the fact that, over the past thirty years or so, irregular payments were made amounting to EUR 3.1 billion, only 17% of which has been recovered. Inadequate monitoring procedures and non-compliance with EU rules and regulations appear to be the order of the day.</p>
      <p sl="de">It is bad enough that billions of euros in EU funds should disappear into fictitious accounts, but when, even in the rare cases where irregular payments are brought to light, the recovery of them is bungled or proceeded with so slowly that the culprits go to ground and the money disappears, it becomes clear that the European Union is suffering from something very like organised negligence.</p>
      <p sl="de">It is intolerable that there should be repeated instances of the negligent use of EU funds – and, moreover, in the same Member States – without someone having to take the consequences. Where Member States fail to do everything possible to recover missing funds within a maximum of two years, I believe that those Member States should themselves make good the loss.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-140" speaker_id="28120" name="Simon Busuttil" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, EU money that is lost or unaccounted for often hits the headlines. It is a pity that the work done to prevent money being lost in the first place – and to recover funds that are lost – is all too often too technical, too tedious to be reported at all, let alone hit the headlines. However, efforts to recover funds are being made and should be supported, although, as the rapporteur clearly points out, more needs to be done.</p>
      <p sl="en">In particular, more needs to be done on the recovery of funds where there is shared management. We need to rely on the full cooperation of the national authorities to help us succeed. Sometimes I get the feeling that, as long as we are talking about Community funds, national authorities are not quite so keen to do their part. In effect they are saying: ‘Our responsibility is the national budget, and that is it’. However, that is not it. When EU money is spent at national level, it is clear that national authorities are actively involved. National authorities also bear a strong responsibility for ensuring that Community funds are not spent erroneously, irregularly, or even fraudulently. If they are, then action is taken to recover them.</p>
      <p sl="en">The report rightly calls for Member States to stand up and be counted, to do their part, to better organise themselves and to cooperate more with the Commission so that the recovery of funds is effective and becomes a deterrent in itself.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-141" speaker_id="28224" name="Markus Pieper" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I very much welcome Mr Casaca’s report, and, as a member of the Committee on Regional Development, I have to say how very embarrassing I find the dramatic increase in frauds and irregularities.</p>
      <p sl="de">The financial impact on structural policy measures went up from EUR 480 million in 2003 to EUR 694 million in 2004, the last reported year, in which a good 70% of the misspent funds were attributable to structural policy. To that we must also add a grey area. If we are less than fully able to get back the money wrongly paid out – as this own-initiative report says we are – then that shows the EU in a bad light. It is no small thing to have outstanding debts totalling EUR 3 billion.</p>
      <p sl="de">This is not, however, just about the financial loss to the EU. If the recovery of these funds is less than efficient, others will be encouraged to misuse money granted in aid. Whether money has been obtained by deliberate fraud or paid out in error, the recovery of it must run smoothly and efficiently, and even if the procedure may appear disproportionate in individual cases, the Member States must apply it, so I call on them to proceed with greater rigour and coordinate their public prosecutors’ offices accordingly, while also asking them to make room for the European anti-fraud authority OLAF to become more involved in the proceedings. As for the Commission, I call on it to do more to make the misuse of subsidies a cause of public disgrace.</p>
      <p sl="de">Europe needs transparency, and so does its system of grants and subsidies. Where funds are used for purposes other than those for which they were originally intended, we have to put a stop to it, and for that we need more openness. I thank the rapporteur for helping to bring that about.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-142" speaker_id="28115" name="Mairead McGuinness" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I should like to thank the rapporteur for the almost forensic work he has put into this report. Apart from the obvious loss of money, which is very serious from an EU point of view, the public perception of fraud is quite large and to some extent it is unfair and detracts from the very good work that the European Union budget does throughout Member States. We should remember that by concentrating on the problem that is there. Unfortunately, the public blames this anonymous European Union, when the problem is much closer to home in their individual Member States. That message needs to go out very clearly too.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is unacceptable that there is so much money outstanding – some EUR 3.5 billion is owed as of June 2002. A great deal of money in the agriculture sector has just not been recovered because of the difficulties with Member States not cooperating.</p>
      <p sl="en">The reform of the common agricultural policy in 2003 should see an improvement in the position in relation to agriculture: the introduction of the single farm payment, its close links to cross-compliance measures, will ensure that money is only paid out when it should be. I have a niggling worry that because of past failures in agriculture, we are coming down very heavily in policing cross-compliance. I have farmers come to me saying that they get no notice of inspections and are faced with significant penalties for very minor mistakes. That is going too far, and we need to be careful not to push too far in that direction, because while it is very easy to tackle and trace EUR 5, EUR 5 billion seems to slip through the net. I am pleased that Commissioner Fischer Boel has said she will look at less draconian implementation, while at the same time ensuring we meet the rules.</p>
      <p sl="en">We do need to get the money back. But I would like to end by making the point that the talk, and hopefully the work towards better regulation, should improve this position. The past is not a pretty picture. Let us hope the future is a nicer one.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-143" speaker_id="28387" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place on Tuesday at 12 noon.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written Statement (Ru1e 142)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-144" speaker_id="4412" name="Véronique Mathieu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="fr">It has to be said that the recovery of Community funds, following irregularities or fraud, remains insufficient. The financial regulation needs to be applied more rigidly, and revised.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Thus, Parliament believes that the simplification of the recovery procedures and better coordination between the Commission services and those competent at national level constitute a crucial line of work. The main problem is that no national authority is totally responsible for the quality and supervision of the national controls even though 80% of the responsibility for executing the Community budget falls to the Member States, because they jointly manage it. The complex nature of the mechanisms thus prompts the media to hold the Commission responsible for the problems associated with illegal operations and, hence, even for the recovery of funds, even though these problems lie above all at Member State level.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Enhanced cooperation between OLAF, Eurojust and Europol, a broader application of the recovery procedure through the use of legal channels and a request by Parliament for the Commission to lay down a regulatory framework for the financial handling of irregularities and for it to regularly present a report, via the Directorate-General, on the state of the recovery procedure, are all so many important measures that will make the procedures more transparent and effective.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem19" title="19. Implementing measures (level 2) of the &quot;Transparency&quot; and &quot;Prospectus&quot; directives (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-146" speaker_id="28387" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the Commission statement on the Implementing measures (level 2) for the ‘Transparency’ and ‘Prospectus’ directives.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-147" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Charlie McCreevy" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, allow me to address two measures proposed by the Commission on which Parliament will vote tomorrow. They concern the postponement of the decision on the equivalence of third country accounting standards – we aim to reach that decision by July 2008 – and the general implementation measures for the Transparency Directive.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would first like to thank the rapporteurs for their efficient and helpful work on these important and sensitive matters. Along with the Committee on Economic and Monetary Affairs, they have worked very constructively with the Commission and all parties concerned. The careful work of Parliament has demonstrably improved the legal texts. I would also like to thank the Committee of European Securities Regulators for its excellent work. The draft measures now represent a balanced and efficient solution.</p>
      <p sl="en">Firstly, on equivalence: postponing our decision on equivalence will not only ensure that EU markets remain open while work on convergence is ongoing, but will also allow us to work actively with United States and other third country authorities towards the elimination of reconciliation requirements for EU issuers abroad. This is and will remain our number one objective.</p>
      <p sl="en">The additional two years will enable us to align the equivalence decision with the Securities and Exchange Commission's timeline in its roadmap towards eliminating the need for reconciliation between IFRS and US GAAP. The United States authorities are committed to working towards the recognition of equivalence of IFRS and US GAAP. With the new timing of the equivalence decisions, we will be able to work in parallel towards common agreed objectives.</p>
      <p sl="en">In this context, it is important to emphasise that nothing is predetermined. We will decide on equivalence by mid-2008, in the light of progress in convergence, and it is certainly not a foregone conclusion that any specific GAAP will 'pass the test'. It has always been our priority to keep our options open. I know that Parliament shares that objective. Before 1 January 2008, we will have decided on both a definition of equivalence and the equivalence mechanism. This will be done by way of comitology, with the full involvement of Parliament.</p>
      <p sl="en">Exemption for issuers of professional securities from the need to provide narrative description of differences between third country GAAPs and IFRS remains an issue of concern. We know that Parliament has doubts about this amendment. Its aim is strictly to remove the ambiguity in the existing Prospectus Regulation. We regret that we were alerted about this ambiguity only a few weeks ago, but we are convinced that this amendment is necessary to ensure legal certainty.</p>
      <p sl="en">Secondly, on the transparency measures: the Transparency Directive is a major step towards integrated European financial markets that investors and the public can trust. To achieve this, it is important to complete the transparency obligations by adopting the Commission implementing measures today under your consideration.</p>
      <p sl="en">Parliament has made several proposals to the Commission for improving this text, which I appreciate. The Commission is ready to accept the substance of most of them, unless this is not possible for technical reasons. In particular, Parliament raised questions on the notification to be made by market makers indicating their intention to make use of one of the exceptions to the Directive. The Commission prefers a solution that limits the administrative burden, and therefore the cost, for market makers. This is why the Commission is in favour of market makers filing this notification with their own competent authority only, instead of with potentially 25 authorities. I believe this solution fits perfectly with the simplification agenda that the Commission supports.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-148" speaker_id="729" name="John Purvis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, in this era of globalisation we often bemoan Europe’s laggardness in setting global standards. However, International Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS) are essentially a European project incorporating a principles-based system of accounting. Much of the world will adopt that European accountancy standard. It is appropriate that we allow third countries the time to adapt, but 1 January 2009 is surely long enough a delay for that purpose.</p>
      <p sl="de">Until now our European companies have had to adapt to US general accounting principles while we accepted US Generally Accepted Accounting Principles (GAAP) in Europe. With IFRS there is no reason for that discrimination to continue. I am glad that the American authorities are intent on meeting the deadline for agreeing equivalence. They even seem increasingly persuaded of the advantages of principles-based accounting.</p>
      <p sl="de">Nevertheless, finding commonality between a strict rules-based system and a more flexible principles-based system is not simple. Both sides of the Atlantic agree that equivalence, rather than strict convergence, will be a suitable outcome. That is why we call upon the Commission to stick to the January 2008 deadline to define what equivalence will be, so as to make the ultimate time limit of 1 January 2009 a strict time limit.</p>
      <p sl="de">Any third-country companies reporting in the European Union from that date on will have to report either in IFRS or an accounting system that is agreed to be equivalent, and that agreement will be reciprocal.</p>
      <p sl="de">European accounts, in accordance with IFRS, will be accepted without adjustment in the US and other consenting third countries. That will help European companies to cut costs and compete for capital in a globalised marketplace.</p>
      <p sl="de">My group looks to the Commission to pay due attention to the proposals in our joint resolution and to achieve a successful outcome of these important negotiations before 2009.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-149" speaker_id="2081" name="Peter Skinner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PSE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I welcome the Commissioner and thank him for his words about the report. I believe it is the close working relationship that has developed between Parliament, its various groups and the Commission that has helped to steady the rudder on this one. Quite clearly we are entering a very dangerous time: we have two years in which to get this right, to measure the value of equivalence and reach convergence with countries around the world. So the Commissioner is absolutely right to point this out not only to the USA but also to other third countries. However, the USA is certainly the big project that we all know about. That is going to be the tough one, and we are quite clearly afraid that the billions of dollars and euros between our two capital markets at the transatlantic level will be put in jeopardy if we do not get this right.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am very positive that we are on the right route and I believe that what Parliament has put forward has helped to strengthen the methodology, also scrutinising the approach which will be involved in this particular battle.</p>
      <p sl="en">Looking at the bulk of this directive and the amendments from the supervisors and others in this House – and I am very grateful to colleagues who have assisted on this issue – I believe that we have not overburdened the business community. That is and has always been vital. You cannot use the term ‘light touch’ all the time and then overburden business. This is an important cross-border capital market issue and we need greater coherence and communication between the various operators within that market.</p>
      <p sl="en">We also need to ensure that investors are protected and that the right information is communicated to them in a relevant and timely manner. These are issues which, of course, are now left to the Member State. I think the Commissioner might agree with me that we should be using the most modern methods to communicate to investors.</p>
      <p sl="en">I do not have much time, so I shall not pursue all the issues of this particular directive. However, I should like to turn to one recital in the original directive and bend the Commissioner’s ear. That recital concerns the voluntary initiatives to help companies report what they pay governments around the world in the extractive industries. As the Commissioner might remember – and I am sure his departments will – this was an initiative which was to help end corrupt practices. It was aimed not only at places as far-flung as Africa, but also within our own borders. Companies were meant to volunteer information about what they pay governments so that we in turn would know, and investors would know, just what money changed hands between governments and companies. It was aimed at the extractive industries because it was clear that this was an area in which an awful lot of money was going abroad, away from the countries where it should have been used.</p>
      <p sl="en">My final question to the Commissioner is to ask what he and his services might do to support that initiative. I think this House would enjoy hearing again what your predecessor gave as a promise some years ago.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-150" speaker_id="28244" name="Wolf Klinz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I would like to say something about the implementing provisions of the transparency directive, which Parliament, since they are what are termed Level 2 measures, is capable of influencing only to a limited extent. That makes it all the more important that the Committee on Economic and Monetary Affairs adopted, unanimously, a draft report on the basis of which the plenary will now adopt a resolution of its own.</p>
      <p sl="de">By presenting a united front, the committee has succeeded, even before tomorrow’s vote, in getting the Commission to accept some of its core demands. The first is that market makers cannot be compelled to invest the financial instruments that they keep for market-making activities in a separate account, although the supervisory authority can require a separate account if the market maker is unable to identify, at any given time, the relevant financial instruments when asked to do so.</p>
      <p sl="de">Secondly, fair competition requires that the same conditions should apply to parent companies of management companies and investment firms from third countries as do to those from the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="de">Finally, a distinction is to be drawn between transactions on stock exchanges and outside them, for, while, in the former, ownership is transferred when the contract is concluded and immediate notification is thus made not only possible but also necessary, the conclusion of the contract and the transfer of ownership may be separate when transactions are concluded off-market, and it would be wrong to require notification as soon as a contract was concluded, since a report at this juncture could, unlike in the former instance, have the effect of distorting the market.</p>
      <p sl="de">Despite Parliament’s success on this negotiating front, there are still areas – and Commissioner McCreevy has indeed referred to them – where the Commission has not yet done as Parliament would wish, including, for example, such questions as, firstly, to which authority a market maker must apply for an exemption from the notification requirement when he reaches a specific threshold value; secondly, what is the minimum content required of non-consolidated half-year accounts not drawn up in accordance with international financial reporting standards, and, thirdly, how it can be guaranteed that accountants will proceed in the same way when auditing half-yearly reports.</p>
      <p sl="de">I appeal to the Members of this House to vote ‘yes’ tomorrow, in order that we may seize our opportunity to get the Commission and the Member States to carefully examine Parliament’s demands on these outstanding items and, in due course, accede to them.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-151" speaker_id="1922" name="Thomas Mann" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, as I did in the Committee on Economic and Monetary Affairs, I am today standing in for my colleague Professor Lauk, the shadow rapporteur of the Group of the European People’s Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats, to whom we all wish a good recovery following the operation on his shoulder.</p>
      <p sl="de">It is on his behalf that I would like to thank not only the rapporteur, Mr Skinner of the Socialist Group in the European Parliament, but also the shadow rapporteur of the Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe, Mr Klinz – who, like me, hails from Hessen – for their constructive cooperation. It was the compromise reached by these three that made it possible for us, in the committee, to adopt the draft resolution unanimously.</p>
      <p sl="de">Even the Commission has been efficient. Commissioner McCreevy has incorporated the essential points in his draft of the implementing Directive and, following consultations, made further modifications. This solution makes for more transparent information on securities authorised on the regulated market.</p>
      <p sl="de">There are three points that the PPE-DE Group saw as particularly important. The first had to do with the need for the requirements applicable to half-yearly audits not to be excessively bureaucratic, the consequence of which was that the figures for comparison purposes do not need to be submitted immediately upon the entry into force of the directive; a more reasonable transitional period was decided upon. Secondly, where voting rights were concerned, our intention was that subsidiaries would be listed both as part of their parent companies and as independent entities, and we managed that too. Thirdly, where publication, of necessity, has to be accomplished rapidly, it should be laid down in detail which media are to be used. That was agreed to as well.</p>
      <p sl="de">These productive changes have prompted my group to endorse Mr Skinner’s report. Both Mr Lauk and I look forward to it receiving broad support in this House tomorrow.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-152" speaker_id="2286" name="Harald Ettl" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, Commissioner, the number of globally-active enterprises is on the increase; their need for comparable and globally recognised group accounts in order to gain access to international capital markets has been an agent of change in accountancy at the international level, and the headlong progress of globalisation is making the harmonisation of accounting procedures across borders a matter of positive necessity. The adoption of the International Accounting Standards Regulation was an important milestone in the creation of an integrated single financial market and in the harmonisation of accountancy in Europe.</p>
      <p sl="de">A developed capital market puts national economies in a better competitive position, and studies have demonstrated that Member States with a high degree of share capitalisation and high stock exchange turnovers relative to their gross domestic product also achieve more growth and create more jobs. That being so, it is certainly desirable that the IFRS and American GAAP accounting regulations, together with the accounting principles generally accepted in third countries, should be made more closely approximate as an essential contribution to the development of standardised and internationally recognised accounting standards and hence to the integration of capital markets.</p>
      <p sl="de">Rather than aiming simply to do away with the existing difference in the accounting systems of the United States, Canada or Japan, the primary object of convergence must be the creation of high-quality accounting standards, which alone will be of lasting value and meet with unconditional acceptance. It is of vital importance to European businesses that the SEC, the USA’s stock exchange supervisory body, should recognise year-end accounts prepared in accordance with IFRS.</p>
      <p sl="de">The one-sidedness in the recognition of accounting standards should become a thing of the past by January 2009 at the latest; that is the only way in which European businesses will become more competitive.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-153" speaker_id="28285" name="Margarita Starkevičiūtė" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="lt">The document being discussed is technically concise and clear – we are speaking here about accounting standards. Yet, as we emphasised in our draft resolution, in economic and political terms this issue is very significant and complex, since in essence it concerns the role of the European Union in the global financial market.</p>
      <p sl="lt">International financial accounting standards based on principles form a constituent part of our European financial model, which will be adopted by developing countries as well. Therefore, the European Commission must take action in support of the application of such standards in developing countries, promote their quality and European nature and in this way develop an image of the European financial market and offer various solutions (not only in a technical sense).</p>
      <p sl="lt">We should not forget that the United States also has a perfectly functional system of accounting standards. Therefore, whether we like it or not, international and American accounting standards are presently competing in the market of the European Union; that is, we, the legislators, are competing.</p>
      <p sl="lt">I believe that the European Parliament is ready for this competition, but for businesses it is too costly to adhere to more than one standard, and the developing markets feel confused. They do not know which standards are to be implemented. Consequently, the European Commission should look for ways to harmonise the standards or encourage harmonisation of the standards at the level of appropriate bodies.</p>
      <p sl="lt">We should not forget that it is not only a technical issue that we are discussing, but rather the development of the global financial market, and for harmonisation of the standards we need two things: clear guidelines for implementation of harmonisation and a clear definition of what harmonisation really means.</p>
      <p sl="lt">Some of us think that informal negotiations are more effective, since no one needs to voice their positions in advance. Different methods and tactics in negotiations are possible, but I do not think the European Parliament would agree that decisions to be made in harmonising accounting standards should infringe on key IFRS principles, their high quality and reputation. It is out of the question for the European Parliament to make decisions without consulting Parliament and the players in financial markets.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-154" speaker_id="4292" name="Alexander Radwan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, I would like to use this opportunity to highlight two crucial points in both these reports. The first is that, formally speaking, and as far as I am aware, the new comitology procedure is not yet applicable in this area, but I take it as read that the Commission will take due account of how this House votes, since it will be applicable to new amendments in the future.</p>
      <p sl="de">The second has to do with the question as to how we should apply the IFRS standards in future, an aspect that will become more and more important. What I can say on behalf of our own group is that we, in principle, welcome IFRS standards as an international rule for European businesses, but it has to be said that there are conditions attached to that. Convergence must be achieved, but that must also involve the European outlook and European priorities prevailing in future discussions on this subject. It is for that reason that I am annoyed when I hear, emanating from the Board of Trustees, signals to the effect that a thoroughly critical view is being taken of the discussion as to whether, and if so when, convergence is achievable.</p>
      <p sl="de">The main question, though, has to do with how, in future, we are to devise further standards. It is no secret that we have now had a debate on what are termed ‘IFRS for SMEs’. The wheels are very definitely turning, and discussions are in progress in the relevant bodies; all of this has become quite separate from any political process, and so I would like not only to encourage the Commission but also to urge them to monitor this process very rigorously in the interests of its being subject to political and democratic constraints, and ensure that this House is involved.</p>
      <p sl="de">I am this House’s rapporteur on this subject area, and I also have experience of Basel. You can take it as read that this process will not work on the basis of an agreement being reached at international level and Parliament being left with no option but to adopt it; that is why there needs to be close dialogue between Commission and Parliament. The Commission is not merely encouraged, but also urged, to take active account of European interests and not to allow the Board to present it with faits accomplis in the way it has done before on other issues.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-155" speaker_id="1985" name="Pervenche Berès" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, on the occasion of this debate on the adaptation of the Prospectus and Transparency directives regarding the road map negotiated by Mr McCreevy with the US authorities, we are in a position to review the way in which the IFRS have been implemented. The greatest caution must be exercised in relation to this matter. One of the great contributions, I believe, of this Parliament is the way in which it ensured, during the equivalence negotiations, that there was genuine equivalence and not just a deadline that would elapse before it was finally pointed out that, where there were once differences, there would now be equivalence.</p>
      <p sl="fr">As you know only too well, Commissioner, this issue is all about negotiation. You have succeeded in getting the Americans to commit themselves to reconciliation at the end of the time period and, when that time period expires, you will remain empty-handed if, in the meantime, this Parliament has not helped to consolidate the matter so that, in the end, we secure an acceptable recognition of equivalence.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I very much regret the fact that we were unable, before this plenary session, to organise with our colleagues from the US Congress the videoconference that I proposed, that my fellow coordinators accepted and that would have enabled us, together with the US political authorities, to hold the necessary debate on the latter’s ability to comply with this road map that you have made your own, Commissioner.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-156" speaker_id="4258" name="Piia-Noora Kauppi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I wish to begin by thanking my colleagues who have worked on these very difficult dossiers. I welcome the spirit in which the implementing measures for the ‘Transparency’ and ‘Prospectus’ directives were formulated, after the very tough MiFID procedure for which I was the rapporteur before the spring break.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is extremely important for the European Parliament to be able to have confidence in comitology, especially now, after the July decision. We are delegating a large part of our decision-making powers to the Commission and we want to ensure that the legislation enacted in the Lamfalussy process gives the best possible technical quality, as well as democratic legitimacy.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, for Parliament to get rid of, for example, the sunset clauses – which is the wish of the Commission –we still need more guarantees on the improved procedure of the comitology decision and on Parliament having full influence on the second-level measures.</p>
      <p sl="en">For the record, MiFID is a very important process and will certainly do far more than many people think for the financial services sector. It is also a good example of the influence Parliament can have. Industry and the market participants want us to use our powers more and people really respected the changes Parliament was making with that report. I think the same thing will happen with the ‘Transparency’ and ‘Prospectus’ directives.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is very important that the European Parliament strengthens its powers in those areas. Through this we will be able to give more support to the Community. Sometimes there is unnecessary gold-plating by the Council. It has put forward proposals which are placing the single market at risk and I think that the Community’s soldiers – the Commission and the European Parliament – should march together on these issues, as it would benefit the single market.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-157" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Charlie McCreevy" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I shall briefly touch on the two topics.</p>
      <p sl="en">As regards the equivalence decision, it is right to postpone it. It is the most efficient way to promote the use of IFRS. It gives us leverage in our efforts to obtain the removal of reconciliation requirements for EU issuers abroad, as it ensures that EU markets remain attractive to foreign issuers. It will benefit EU investors and issuers alike.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am aware of the concerns of Members of the European Parliament and others regarding many of these issues, but a clear roadmap has been set out. If there is goodwill on all sides we will reach a satisfactory end, but in any event if we do not reach a satisfactory outcome then, as we say in my country, nothing is lost. So I think that the prolongation of the time period is the correct decision for many reasons. First, so that we give ourselves here in Europe an opportunity to see how IFRS has been implemented in the various Member States – and we will be learning in that process as well. We have a clear commitment from our colleagues in the United States as to the roadmap and the time lines there and, all things being equal, we should reach a satisfactory conclusion. But if we do not and if we are not satisfied, then, as I say, nothing is lost. Worldwide more people are moving to the IFRS accounting standards which Europe adopted as from last year, so therefore it will be to our benefit.</p>
      <p sl="en">Concerning the great question posed by Mr Radwan and others about this question of convergence and equivalence, let us see where we are in the few short years hence.</p>
      <p sl="en">On the transparency directive, I shall deal with the point raised by Mr Skinner. His point relates to a provision in the recital of the level 1 directive, and this recital stipulates that payments by the extractive industries should be reported. This as such is not the subject of today’s debate, but I can confirm that the Commission will monitor this issue.</p>
      <p sl="en">Concerning the implementing measures to the transparency directive, I should also add that I understand some of the concerns expressed in relation to future developments. In this regard, the Commission commits itself to making a declaration that will be added to the minutes of the European Securities Committee on the date of the vote on the draft implementing measures. It should state that the Commission undertakes to re-examine the issue of the auditors’ review of half-yearly financial statements once the work in relation to the international standards on auditing, currently under development, is sufficiently advanced.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission will also re-examine, within two years of the final deadline for transposition, the question of the minimum content of the condensed set of half-yearly financial statements that are not prepared in accordance with international accounting standards.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission also undertakes to conduct a review of how the regulated information is disseminated in practice pursuant to the obligations of the transparency directive and the future implementing directive. This could be undertaken two years after the end of the transposition period for the implementing directive. In this way we will ensure that the transparency directive tools are adapted to improvements in the market.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-158" speaker_id="28387" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Pursuant to Rule 103(2) of the Rules of Procedure, I have received two motions for resolution .</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place on Tuesday at 12 noon.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem20" title="20. LIFE+ – Financing of the Natura 2000 network">
    <intervention id="1-160" speaker_id="28387" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is</p>
      <p sl="unknown">the recommendation for second reading (06284/1/2006 C6-0226/2006 2004/0218(COD)) on the Council common position for adopting a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council concerning the Financial Instrument for the Environment (LIFE+)) (Rapporteur: Mrs Isler Béguin) (A6-0288/2006)</p>
      <p sl="unknown">the debate on the oral question to the Commission on financing of the NATURA 2000 framework by Mr Florenz, on behalf of the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety (O-0113/2006 B6-0441/2006).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-161" speaker_id="1833" name="Marie Anne Isler Béguin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I must begin by thanking the members of the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety and, in particular, my fellow shadow rapporteurs for the work that we have done together, because I believe that it can be said - even though, as is customary at this hour, the Chamber is not very full - that we have genuinely carried out a joint piece of work and that this report, which bears my name, could just as well bear the name of my fellow Members, Mrs Gutiérrez-Cortines, Mrs Ries or even Mrs Lienemann, who apologises for not being able to take part in this evening’s debate.</p>
      <p sl="fr">We have also produced a joint piece of work with the Commission. Unfortunately, it is regrettable that the Council is not present, because, ultimately, our results will depend greatly on it. I am entirely convinced that the cooperation that we have been able to put in place during this first reading and that follows on from the common position will enable us to reach a consensus with the Council and with yourself, and I am counting on you, Commissioner, to pass the results of this debate on to the Council.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Indeed, ladies and gentlemen, LIFE+ is no longer the programme that we once knew, but will indeed constitute the Union’s ‘environment’ budget heading. Thus, it is LIFE+ that will govern Europe’s innovative policies, that will rise to the challenges, such as the fight against climate change and the efforts to rid the air and soil of pollution, that will prevent biodiversity damage and that will provide the Environment DG and the NGOs, our bio-indicators par excellence , with the means to endow the Member States’ environmental policies with European added value.</p>
      <p sl="fr">In fact, as you will know, ladies and gentlemen, we are talking here about an ‘impossible budget heading’, given the derisory sum that the Council and the Commission have granted it. We made an attempt, at first reading, to increase this LIFE heading, which, I must point out, does not even represent 1% of the overall budget, with the aim of bringing it into line with the policies much-publicised by the Union itself. The debate focused back then on support for the Natura 2000 network, our flagship environmental policy. By adding EUR 21 billion, which even the Commission felt was necessary if Natura 2000 was to be managed properly, the European Parliament sent out a strong signal to the Commission and to the Council. We were right to do so.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Today, with the reduction in the Structural Funds budgets, a form of unbridled competition has begun in the regions, and all of our colleagues are having a change of heart. As Natura 2000 does not specifically feature in the financial regulations, well, it will undoubtedly be environmental volunteers who produce the results. We should not get our hopes up too much, however, regarding the share that will be reserved for the protection of nature and biodiversity, despite the fact that, at the European Parliament’s first reading, we were virtually unanimous in our support of an ambitious European policy.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The common position proposed to us has spectacularly ignored our warning. Worse still, it is deviating from it in an alarming way, going so far as to grant 80% of the delegated management responsibility to the Member States, even though you did not mention this percentage in your initial proposal. What minister would refuse such a gift? Admittedly, we also realise that, with too few staff members, the Commission is afraid of managing multiple projects. This is made all the more difficult by the fact that, with a reduction in the number of European officials having been announced, there remains little hope of the Environment DG strengthening its staff.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Let us make it very clear to you: this approach is not the right one because the European level remains the most relevant and most secure one for dealing with environmental issues. We even feel that this handover of power from the Commission to the Member States is dangerous. In our view, this initial strategy to renationalise the environmental policies is the sign of a slow disintegration of the European idea. Each Member State demanding its initial bet would thus be free to dip into the Lisbon Strategy, and thus to become an unrivalled competitor – and we know full well that competition generally goes hand in hand with environmental damage – or to claim that sustainable development, which requires a global approach, is the opposite of such competition. We also know the extent to which the label ‘environment' serves to justify problems that destroy the environment.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, this is the trap that we refuse to fall into because to do so would be to negate all of the successes that Europe has had in relation to the environment. If there is one policy that can be seen, identified, recognised and appreciated by Europeans, it is indeed the one that we have succeeded in implementing on environmental protection.</p>
      <p sl="fr">We all know that LIFE must enable us to deal with emergencies and to implement policies aimed at restoring our environment. The EUR 100 million that were extracted at the time of the financial perspective and that we are demanding, Commissioner, be allocated entirely to the environment will not be enough to achieve these aims. Commissioner, unless you are a magician, it will be impossible for you to keep your promises with such derisory sums. Entrusting them to the Member States therefore means running the risk of failure.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Our ambition is for the Union to remain the flagship, the global leader that takes the initiative for establishing laws to protect the planet. That requires the Commission to be able to produce ambitious policies, to assume responsibility and control of the quality of the projects launched at Member State level and to reject any that are unsuitable. European policy must under no circumstances compensate for the Member States’ failings in relation to the environment, and, as you will understand, we are refusing to give them a blank cheque.</p>
      <p sl="fr">On the other hand, we are perfectly aware that the delay that this procedure could cause is also liable to cause delays in terms of funding. That is why, together, we have tabled the same amendment, so as to ensure that the work done by your Environment DG continues to be funded, pending an agreement, of course. Above all, we also want it to be possible for this work to continue and even for you to launch new projects and oversee the funding of the work done by NGOs. We should like to make it clear in this House that, legally and financially, that is possible.</p>
      <p sl="fr">To conclude, Mr President, I would say that the ball is now in the court of the Council and of the Commission and that we are convinced that we are going to reach an agreement amongst ourselves precisely so as to ensure that this ambitious environmental policy is taken forward. That is what our fellow citizens expect, and they encourage you in that regard.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-162" speaker_id="4326" name="Cristina Gutiérrez-Cortines" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, there are two parts to my speech. In the first part, I shall put the oral question on Natura 2000 by Mr Florenz, who is not present and who has asked me to speak on his behalf.</p>
      <p sl="es">The question is as follows: since the Commission estimates that EUR 6.1 billion per year is needed to maintain and conserve the Natura 2000 protected areas, and since the funding is expected to come from the rural development funds, the Structural Funds, LIFE+ and the fisheries funds, how does the Commission intend to coordinate this policy? How does the Commission intend to send clear messages about its coordinated policy to users, to proprietors and to those who are in charge of Natura 2000 land. Where are the funds? What actions must be taken? How accessible is European Union protection and aid?</p>
      <p sl="es">This is something that is still not clear. Matters need to be drawn up in a very clear way so that there can be full genuine communication between the proprietors and the Commission.</p>
      <p sl="es">With regard to LIFE+, I agree with everything Mrs Isler Béguin has said. The results of the vote reflect a genuine agreement within the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety, though there may be discrepancies and differing positions due to the diverging views of the different States. Why? Because the new LIFE+ now being presented represents a decentralised policy and is very different to the policy in place until now.</p>
      <p sl="es">We believe that LIFE has traditionally been a leader programme for funding innovation projects and innovative management models, particularly in the field of the environment. It is a prestige programme, which NGOs have looked upon as a guide and a model. For local and regional authorities, it has become a path that must be followed, a permanent reference. We want that reference to remain.</p>
      <p sl="es">This has, however, been the case because emphasis has been placed on the universal nature of environmental policy, a factor that has been one of the reasons for the success of European policy in this field.</p>
      <p sl="es">Europe knows that environmental policy cannot just be applied to a single region. It requires a global approach. The European Union has always made this clear, and the 6th Environmental Action Programme has taken that into account at all times.</p>
      <p sl="es">Policy in the fields of climate change, desertification, water, waste, safeguarding quality of life, well-being and pollution are all of a universal nature, and that is why we want it to be applied beyond Europe and for Europe to become a model for the whole world.</p>
      <p sl="es">We should remember, however, that LIFE was created in order to bring this about, and that is stated in the text of the financial statement, which I am going to read and which states that LIFE+ credit ‘is intended to fund economic contributions for actions intended to apply, update and implement Community legislation and policy in the field of the environment, including the integration of the environment into other policies’. How can we do this if the policy is only national? How can we do this if Europe loses its leadership, if it leaves these actions in the hands of the Member States?</p>
      <p sl="es">We therefore advocate in the clearest and strongest terms a more centralised model in which Europe once again provides guidance and initiative. We understand that the Commission has a lack of resources. We are going to support it in the future, where possible, because this policy of reducing the number of officials cannot carry on.</p>
      <p sl="es">Unless Europe has a management structure and management capacities, as well as qualified personnel, it will not be able to carry out this task. With a view to its being able to do so, we undoubtedly believe that part of the management should be returned to the European Commission and that international European projects should be created, so that Europe can improve its capacities in the future, by means of ‘capacity building’, in order to ensure that projects are better monitored, to find ways to coordinate policies and to continue taking action that cuts across policy areas.</p>
      <p sl="es">That is our proposal, and we shall cooperate fully in the conciliation process so that we can reach a quick agreement, so that funding can be guaranteed and, of course, so that the Commission can do its job. That is precisely why we are here: in order to cooperate with the Commission and tell the Member States that the policy of sustainability is a process and that Europe is more than just a market.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-163" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Stavros Dimas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Μember of the Commission. Mr President, I should like to start by thanking the rapporteur, Mrs Isler Béguin, for her exceptional work and for her report on this proposal. I should also like to thank Mrs Gutiérrez for her very positive approach and to assure both ladies and all the Members of Parliament that the Commission will work to facilitate this approach and to achieve fast agreement with the Council.</p>
      <p sl="el">I must stress that, since September 2004 – when the College of Commissioners adopted the Commission proposal – about one year after first reading, we have made a great deal of progress with LIFE+ and the position of the European Commission has changed significantly on several counts in comparison with its initial proposal.</p>
      <p sl="el">I believe that the Council's common position, with which the Commission agrees to a large extent, satisfies many of Parliament's basic demands. The draft regulation now includes a section relating to nature and biodiversity. LIFE+ will be able to fund measures and activities for exchanges of opinions and best practices or demonstration projects, including those relating to the management and designation of Natura 2000 sites and guidelines for habitats and birds.</p>
      <p sl="el">The percentage of LIFE+ relating to the management of nature is large. At least 40% of the resources will be made available for expenditure in this sector. I should like to stress that this percentage is a minimum limit and that the Member States may spend a greater percentage if they so wish.</p>
      <p sl="el">As far as the question of funding for Natura 2000 is concerned, the Commission has secured funding opportunities through the Structural Funds, the Fisheries Fund and the Agricultural Fund for Rural Development. The Commission may, of course, encourage spending on Natura 2000; however, in accordance with the principle of subsidiarity, the Member States have the jurisdiction and discretion to decide on the extent to which they wish to make use of these funding opportunities.</p>
      <p sl="el">The Commission, for its part, will do what it can to ensure the Member States make use of the funding opportunities whenever possible. The opinion of the Directorate General of the Environment is always sought before strategic reference frameworks and operational programmes for the Structural Funds and rural development programmes submitted by the Member States are approved.</p>
      <p sl="el">I repeat that one of our top priorities is to safeguard suitable funding for Natura 2000 and that is why I particularly value Parliament's support on this issue.</p>
      <p sl="el">However, the most important subject of debate this evening is the method of implementation of the programme. According to the common position, 80% of funding for LIFE+ is to be made available to the Member States. I consider that Parliament's preference for maintaining central management of the programme to be an indication of its confidence in the Commission. However, this choice, as I emphasised earlier, requires more human resources.</p>
      <p sl="el">That is why the method proposed in the common position is preferable. First, it is in keeping with the principle of subsidiarity, granting the greatest possible flexibility in order to cover the various requirements of the Member States. Secondly, it ensures that all the countries receive a minimum percentage of the funding. Within the framework of the current LIFE III system, they often do not receive any money. Thirdly, it is transparent and controlled and safeguards the maintenance of added value for the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="el">As you know, delegated management is at the epicentre of the Commission proposal. The Member States are relying on it and are already preparing their draft programmes. That is why the Commission cannot accept the various amendments deleting all references to delegated management.</p>
      <p sl="el">Unfortunately, the outcome of the informal meetings between Parliament, the Council and the Commission following the vote in the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety on 14 September did not enable us to make significant steps towards achieving agreement as regards delegated management. Nonetheless, despite the differences, we are all in favour of the LIFE+ programme and of its being applied as soon as possible, so that funds can be disbursed and there is no delay in the execution of the programmes.</p>
      <p sl="el">The Member States have over two billion euros for the LIFE+ programme. A way needs to be found so that this money is disbursed as quickly as possible, even if this means compromise on all sides. We must therefore continue to work together to find practical solutions, especially as regards the method of implementing LIFE+. Within this framework, we shall make every possible effort to bring about a compromise between the Council and Parliament and we shall intermediate in order to facilitate an agreement.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-164" speaker_id="28636" name="Péter Olajos" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group">
      <p sl="hu">Within the framework of the LIFE III programme, running since 2000, we have spent more than EUR 950 million on various environmental protection programmes for the successful completion of countless local, regional and cross-border projects. Even more importantly, it is precisely these projects which have brought the Union into close proximity to ordinary people, and which contribute most directly to improving the living conditions of EU citizens. These are important considerations at a time when the popularity of the European Union is at an all-time low.</p>
      <p sl="hu">The status of LIFE+, and within it of the Natura 2000 programme, gives cause for concern and raises at least two significant questions. The first is the fact that it is already clear that no timely decision will be taken regarding the new programme, and, as a result, we will not be able to launch the environmental protection programmes next January, as planned. In my view, this is a serious problem. Therefore, I propose that we follow the solution adopted in 2004, when a regulation of the European Parliament and the Council extended the LIFE III programme, which was then expiring, for two more years with an additional budget of EUR 317 million.</p>
      <p sl="hu">I propose that we now take a decision that will keep the LIFE programme, which is due to expire in 2006, in force until the new regulation has been accepted. The second problematic area is the Council’s proposal to delegate 80% of the funds to be managed by the Member States. In my view, this is contrary to the logic and the practice followed hitherto, according to which environmental protection, by virtue of its cross-border nature, calls for a supranational approach.</p>
      <p sl="hu">For this reason, I personally can only support proposals that leave a greater proportion of the power to decide on the funds available within the competence of the Commission and of Parliament than does the present proposal.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-165" speaker_id="5735" name="Anne Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PSE Group">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, firstly, please accept Mrs Lienemann’s sincere apologies for being unable to attend this evening, as you are all aware of her commitment to this matter. It is, however, with the same pleasure and the same convictions that I take her place.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I would like to remind you of all the support that our group offers to Mrs Isler Béguin's report and to pay tribute to the agreement reached by our political groups on an ambitious strategy to consolidate the only direct financial instrument intended for European environment policies. It should also be emphasised that it is our Parliament that obtained additional budgetary credits for LIFE, although well below our initial aims. Today, it is once again MEPs who are calling for strengthened resources to support the implementation of the Natura Directive. An effort has been made, undoubtedly insufficient, but obtained in a tight budgetary situation within which we must work.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Our disagreements, as matters stand with this issue, concern the method chosen for financing activities. LIFE is an exemplary European instrument. It has proved itself, and we cannot accept that this policy should be renationalised, as planned, with the management of 80% of its budget delegated to the Member States. The European Union must not content itself with handing out money, it must hold the reins of this environmental policy. At a time when the European idea needs to be safeguarded, and given that this is a policy largely supported by EU citizens, it is unacceptable to undermine the European dynamic in this way. Our credibility in the eyes of Europeans is at stake following the statements in the future sustainable development strategy.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Moreover, LIFE must retain its exemplary status, which is founded on the choice of innovative and reproducible projects. It is clear that we must guarantee Member States the level of funding that they expect, while requiring that the selection of projects is informed by a double rationale: one involving the European dimension and meaningful environmental practice.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Our group supports Mrs Haug's amendment calling on the Commission to guarantee continued funding for programmes now under way. Indeed, we cannot accept that NGOs and other parties involved in LIFE should be penalised.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-166" speaker_id="4253" name="Frédérique Ries" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, twelve months ago, together with our rapporteur Mrs Isler Béguin, we deplored this veritable gift made by the Commission. I am referring to a subject on which a great deal has been said already: the delegation of environmental policies to the Member States, which are to manage up to 80% of the LIFE+ budget. In this regard, I share our rapporteur's regret that, during our informal discussions with the Finnish Presidency, the latter did not take a firm step in the direction of meeting public concern for a better environment and quality of life.</p>
      <p sl="fr">It is clear that a solution must be found to this institutional disagreement and, in the meantime, the principle of providing continued funding for Community environment policy must, of course, stand. This is the aim of our Amendment 32. Like my fellow Members, I therefore question this ‘blank cheque’ offered to the Member States on a plate. Why renationalise what Europe as such does so well, even with so very few resources, as has already been said: namely, protecting biodiversity and rare species?</p>
      <p sl="fr">I would point out some of the successes achieved in the areas of nature, the environment and third countries since LIFE was first set up, in 1992. In my own country, Belgium, no fewer than 120 biodiversity protection projects have been cofinanced by the European Union. It is thanks to LIFE and the proper overall functioning of Natura 2000 that 20% of Belgium territory is now classified as a special nature protection area.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Furthermore, last Thursday, the Commission unveiled 75 environmental projects that will benefit from the Union's support - support totalling EUR 136 million thanks to the LIFE programme. To return to Belgium, I am delighted that the restoration of the Hautes Fagnes plateau covering more than 4 500 hectares in the beautiful Ardennes region is one of the projects accepted.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Should we see this as a good omen? I hope so because, in championing Europe in terms of its environment, we are also providing for the health and well-being of future generations. I am sure, moreover, that, as I have emphasised, Europe has everything to gain by committing itself wholeheartedly, as Europe, to this fight to preserve the natural world and biodiversity.</p>
      <p sl="fr">To conclude, Mr President, this is a fight that, as has been said and as it is important to emphasise, has transcended political divides throughout the debate. The fact that we have all rallied strongly around our rapporteur – whom I would like to thank and congratulate once again – is the best proof of this today.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-167" speaker_id="28161" name="Margrete Auken" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="da">Mr President, I would like to thank Mr Florenz for his question. Last year, I was the rapporteur for Parliament’s report on the financing of Natura 2000. In that report, we expressed concern about the willingness of the Member States and of the Commission to take this issue seriously. There will be plenty of voices speaking out for the natural world when it is time for headline speeches. Just think how solemn the Heads of State or Government were in Gothenburg in 2001 in their assurances that Natura 2000 would be implemented. Yet, for all that, everything was forgotten when it came to the budget being adopted, when the separate budget heading for Natura 2000 was rejected point blank. Now it will be interesting to see whether those promises are recalled when the agricultural lobbyists again try to ensure that all the subsidies, including the rural development funds, go to large-scale agriculture and to industry. The Commission will have to be stricter in this area. The slackness and lack of supervision that have been the case up to now are on the point of having disastrous consequences, first and foremost for the natural world, but also for the reputation of the EU, as many of my fellow MEPs have mentioned today. For many people, the protection of nature and the environment is one of the pivotal benefits of the EU. We politicians, when we have had to defend and expound upon the necessity of European cooperation, have continually made reference to what the EU can do in this area. At present, however, many experience an indifference on the part of the EU in respect of those values that cannot quickly be converted into money.</p>
      <p sl="da">Rapid action needs to be taken if our good name is to be rescued. The Commission should make it a condition for the payment of, in particular, rural development funds that the Member States put forward plans and also appropriate sufficient resources to Natura 2000. It should remember also to remind agriculturalists that the rural development funds do not constitute agriculturalists’ own private money. Natura 2000 must receive its share, and without agriculture receiving compensation for this. Agriculture should bear its share of responsibility for the health and diversity of nature. This would be good news for everyone in rural areas. There are splendid opportunities for money-making in the development of Natura 2000. We know, for example, that approximately a quarter of a million people are engaged in the protection of nature, while the potential in the tourism sector is greater still.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-168" speaker_id="28586" name="Dimitrios Papadimoulis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, I should like to thank the rapporteur for her exceptional report and her strong position as regards the demands of the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety in connection with LIFE+.</p>
      <p sl="el">A key point is to secure adequate resources for the Natura 2000 programme. That is why I heartily support the call for another EUR 50 billion to be added to the LIFE+ budget. If we leave the 50 million in the margin, with just one political commitment, as called for by the Council, we shall have no clear guarantee.</p>
      <p sl="el">I also support the call by the Committee on the Environment for 55% of LIFE+ to be allocated to nature and biodiversity, which are issues of critical importance in the effort to achieve the corresponding objective of the European Union. In all events, the additional EUR 100 million agreed within the framework of the financial perspective should be committed to above the 40% proposed by the Council. If the percentage remains 40%, this essentially will mean a proportional reduction in the corresponding funding for biodiversity in comparison with the previous financial perspective and that is unacceptable.</p>
      <p sl="el">Finally, I agree with the rapporteur, who has reacted to the Commission's proposal to grant 80% of resources to the Member States, thereby giving them a blank cheque. The resources for LIFE+ are not there for the Member States to plug financial gaps, but to promote joint European programmes.</p>
      <p sl="el">Commissioner, you know full well that, in the country we both come from, money often goes to cover wages rather than to protect the Natura 2000 network. We want a strong European policy; all of us in the European Parliament want more Europe for environmental protection. If the Commission wants the same, then why does it not stand up for it against the Council?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-169" speaker_id="28119" name="Kathy Sinnott" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the IND/DEM Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, I would tend to support the 80% management of LIFE by Member States. This would ensure a much better and fairer spread of funds across the EU and across the many different types of environment within the EU. It would bring more local knowledge to the project selection process and make public awareness easier to achieve.</p>
      <p sl="de">I have only one hesitation as an Irish MEP: I believe that the second half of the second pillar of LIFE – implementation of existing environmental policy – is critical. This is a priority, because there is no point in funding new policies and projects when we have not learned to implement the standards we have already imposed on ourselves. Frankly, this is a problem in my home country, when it comes to industry. My Member State’s Environmental Protection Agency seems to be very reluctant to force the same compliance on industry as it does on the public.</p>
      <p sl="de">In my willingness to support management of LIFE+ at Member-State level, I would still like to see a reasonable level of scrutiny to ensure that the projects selected prioritise efforts to improve compliance by industry with EU environmental law.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-170" speaker_id="28372" name="Ryszard Czarnecki" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, a number of amendments were proposed during the first reading of the LIFE+ Regulation. It was unanimously agreed that this financial instrument fails to meet expectations in the area of environmental protection. The main difficulty concerned the restriction of financial resources for implementation of all the policies in this area. The financial understandings with the Council and the Commission were not transferred to the environmental protection budget for the next seven years.</p>
      <p sl="pl">In my view, the difference of approach between Mrs Sinnott and most of the other Members is rather abstract in nature. My conscience would be much easier if I voted in favour of this report in the certainty that the resources allocated to the various countries will be devoted to environmental projects. The problem is that the funds are being spent on staff and not on environmental projects. I believe this is the reason why we really are compelled to intervene in some way.</p>
      <p sl="pl">To conclude, I should like to say as an aside that at a time of crisis concerning our vision of the Europe of the future, and of scepticism about European institutions, the environment could serve as a true common point of reference for many citizens of European Union Member States.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-171" speaker_id="2025" name="Françoise Grossetête" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="fr">Commissioner, during the first reading, our message concerned the limited funds allocated to LIFE+. Today, the European Parliament is interested in sending a clear message to the Council and the Commission. Under no circumstances can we accept that 80% of the credits for LIFE+ should be delegated to the Member States for management by national agencies. Why is this unacceptable? It is because environmental policy is one of the European policies most highly regarded by Europeans and seen by them as being one of the most transparent. One wonders for what possible reason the Commission should want to abandon this opportunity to show people the direct impact of a Community policy on their everyday lives. There is no sense in this, particularly at a time when we are being criticised for a lack of communication with citizens.</p>
      <p sl="fr">LIFE+ is an indispensable financial instrument for all our environmental policies. Yet there is such inconsistency. In session after session we are voting for strong environmental commitments in the framework of sustainable development, while LIFE+ is being whittled away. In this too, moreover, we are not in agreement with the Council. Handing over responsibility for 80% of the funding to the Member States means taking the risk of causing all our commitments to fail and seeing this funding diverted from its initial objective.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Yes, Commissioner, we are all in favour of LIFE+, but not in the guise that you are proposing. We must retain a centralised model managed by the Commission, with projects selected on the basis of their merits and the added value they will bring. As you are well aware, we shall otherwise face the watering down of our environmental policy. Renationalisation is not the right solution. We must use these resources not to pay civil servants but to launch and fund projects.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-172" speaker_id="28581" name="Evangelia Tzampazi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, Commissioner, the nationalisation of LIFE from the outset contradicts the application of this environmental tool to date</p>
      <p sl="el">The proposal to delegate the management of 80% of the admittedly inadequate budget for LIFE+ to the Member States would mean that all the European added value would be lost and, most importantly, that the Member States would be given carte blanche to – possibly – follow national objectives. We are therefore calling for efficient and transparent management under the control of the European Commission of important programmes with added European value.</p>
      <p sl="el">Finally, if no agreement is reached, I consider it especially important that we support the common proposal, on the basis of which it will be possible to fund activities which will have to be brought under the programme in question from 2007 onwards.</p>
      <p sl="el">I should like to congratulate Mrs Béguin on her exceptionally positive report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-173" speaker_id="28305" name="Mojca Drčar Murko" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I agree with the rapporteur, Mrs Isler Béguin, that during the first reading Parliament significantly improved the Commission's proposal on LIFE+, particularly with respect to the amount to be included for the funding of Natura 2000. I therefore welcome Amendment 18, which restates the sum of EUR 100 million agreed during negotiations on the financial perspective.</p>
      <p sl="en">There are, however, some reasons why I am not enthusiastic about Amendment 10, which, for the new Member States, deletes the very important second paragraph of Article 6 of the Council’s common position. I am afraid that centralised allocation of funding entirely through the projects favours old Member States that are more familiar with the procedures. It is common knowledge that institutions of the new Member States are not yet sufficiently prepared to compete with their projects on an equal footing. The Commission’s proposal that 80% of funding should be allocated to the Member States rectifies this objective initial disadvantage, and detailed eligibility criteria should ensure European added value of funding. Seen from this angle, I do not consider it renationalisation. With regard to the implementation, I would not object to the Council’s solution to the problem.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-174" speaker_id="28252" name="Richard Seeber" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, Commissioner, you have now often enough heard it said that all of us are opposed to this European programme being handed back to the Member States. It should remain European.</p>
      <p sl="de">Here in this House, we talk about environmental programmes and how to fund them, but we should consider well the way in which we do this. It is not acceptable that the habitat programme or the Birds Directive should be used in the Member States to do things that actually go against this House’s normal understanding of things. Environmental policy should indeed be treated as having the value it does, but frogs are not meant to enjoy more protection than do human beings, and one function of the Commission and of its offices is to maintain the proper sense of proportion in this respect.</p>
      <p sl="de">What matters is that we, here in this House, should join with you in the Commission in putting into effect programmes that add European value. This must not be about a mere transfer of funds, that is to say giving Member States back their money and leaving it to them what becomes of it. Nor is it acceptable that these funds should be used to finance NGOs with whose background and connections we are not familiar. We must, then, take care that European taxpayers’ money is used properly.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-175" speaker_id="4242" name="Karin Scheele" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, the second reading of the financial instrument for the environment shows us once more that the Financial Perspective for the period from 2007 to 2013 does not adequately enable the EU to perform its functions as regards the environment, and, indeed, much else besides.</p>
      <p sl="de">The fact that we are in such a problematic financial position makes it important that we should, tomorrow, give our rapporteur support in the shape of a massive majority. The Commission may well be indicating its willingness to compromise, but we know that the negotiations will be extremely tough, for the amendments that the Commission has this evening declared itself unable to accept are at the very heart of this House’s position.</p>
      <p sl="de">As has already been said, handing this programme back to the Member States would imperil European environmental policy and the value that Europe adds to it, and it is for that reason that I support all the rapporteur’s amendments to delete, for they take us several steps in the right direction.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-176" speaker_id="28363" name="Alfonso Andria" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, the determined work by the rapporteur has already produced substantial results at first reading. Nevertheless, the resources allocated for LIFE+ for the 2007-2013 period are not sufficient to meet the environmental challenges of the coming years and we therefore risk jeopardising the positive work that has been achieved thus far. For this reason, it is particularly important to support the rapporteur’s Amendment 3, in order to be able to guarantee more adequate funding, at least after the 2008-2009 review of the Financial Framework, with a view to adapting LIFE to the necessary changes and ensuring a high level of Community cofinancing.</p>
      <p sl="it">Furthermore, I would like to underline the significance of the destination of European environment funds, in that they should not be used to make up the financial deficits of the Member States – it has in fact been pointed out many times that they are often used to pay civil servants – but to implement European projects that put the Gothenburg Sustainable Development Strategy into practice.</p>
      <p sl="it">Finally, I am glad of the fact that the new LIFE+ programme pays greater attention to the issue of energy efficiency, lending financial support to new technologies, and I agree with the rapporteur on the need to involve civil society to a greater extent in the development phase of both multiannual programmes and annual national programmes.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-177" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Stavros Dimas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I should like to thank the Members for their very positive contributions and for the acknowledgement that the initial proposal – adopted by the Commission in September 2004, with the help of Parliament – has been improved considerably. What we have to strive for is a balanced solution. In this respect, I will try to facilitate an agreement between the Council and Parliament.</p>
      <p sl="en">With regard to the amendments, I am aware of 31 amendments tabled by the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety and a further amendment introduced since last week. The late amendment, similar to what happened in the budget debate, encourages me to believe that Parliament wishes to help find a solution to the funding gap that the late adoption of LIFE+ will create. While the budget question will ultimately be solved by the budgetary authority, the Commission will do all it can to facilitate an agreement that, with your support, will provide funds to DG Environment throughout 2007.</p>
      <p sl="en">Turning now to the 31 amendments on LIFE+, I will divide them into four distinct blocks. Firstly, on the delivery method, the Commission cannot accept the group of amendments opposing delegated programme management.</p>
      <p sl="en">Secondly, on allocation of funds, the budget, ring-fencing etc., Parliament has tabled an amendment aiming at adding the whole EUR 100 million extra to the LIFE+ instrument. If Parliament and the Council were in agreement to allocate that amount to the LIFE+ programme, I would welcome the opportunity to see the programme expanded. Parliament also calls for at least 55% of LIFE+ funds to be allocated to the nature and biodiversity component. The Commission cannot accept this amendment, since it would reduce the flexibility needed by several Member States to tackle other pressing environmental concerns. The 40% in the common position is a minimum and nothing prevents Member States spending double that figure on nature and biodiversity if they so wish and can justify it.</p>
      <p sl="en">Thirdly, with regard to comitology issues, the amendments seeking greater involvement by Parliament during the various phases of programming and introducing the regulatory procedure with scrutiny would be acceptable in principle.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lastly, with regard to a series of amendments seeking clarification, greater transparency, etc., on questions such as the application of the Aarhus Convention, cross-border projects, specific reference to the impact of climate change on biodiversity, the role of the Commission in supporting integration, etc., my view is that these amendments could be acceptable to the Commission in principle, subject to some drafting changes.</p>
      <p sl="en">I should like to repeat what I said earlier, namely that we should continue working together to find practical solutions, especially on the implementation method for LIFE+. In addition, together we need to solve the 2007 funding gap. I am heartened by Parliament’s good wishes in that respect.</p>
      <p sl="en">We need a funding instrument for the environment in order to spend our EUR 2 billion budget. I am therefore willing to help find a practical compromise between the Council and Parliament on these issues and I am willing to help facilitate such an agreement.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-179" speaker_id="4393" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place on Tuesday at 12 noon.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem21" title="21. Community civil protection mechanism (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-181" speaker_id="4393" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report (A6-0286/2006) by Mr Papadimoulis, on behalf of the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety, on the proposal for a Council decision establishing a Community civil protection mechanism (recast) (COM(2006)0029 C6-0076/2006 2006/0009(CNS)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-182" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Stavros Dimas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Μember of the Commission. Mr President, first I wish to thank the European Parliament and, in particular, the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety and the rapporteur, Mr Papadimoulis, on drafting an exceptional report.</p>
      <p sl="el">The Commission proposal to recast the 2001 Council decision establishing a Community civil protection mechanism takes account of the demand by both the European Parliament and the Council for resources and facilities to be strengthened in the field of civil protection in Europe. Its objective is to strengthen the mechanism with the experience acquired from previous emergency situations. It provides a basis for the further development of cooperation in the field of civil protection by improving and strengthening the existing project in this sector and by launching new activities.</p>
      <p sl="el">We must highlight two innovations which we are proposing: funding for the cost of hiring equipment and of hiring transport means. We often face situations in which aid is available but there are no suitable means for taking it to the scene of the disaster. As a result, this aid either arrives late or does not arrive at all. In the case of emergencies which affect several European countries at once, such as, for example, forest fires in summer, floods in spring and possible simultaneous terrorist threats throughout Europe, the Member States may find it hard to provide help to other Member States, due to their own needs. That is why the Commission proposed that a safety net be created at Community level, so that we have the facility to hire the necessary transport means and equipment. The Commission, of course, knows that the European Parliament understands the importance of the benefit which will accrue from the reforms in question and expresses its thanks for the support which it has already given to the proposed new funding mechanism.</p>
      <p sl="el">As emphasised in the Barnier report, the result of the enhanced cooperation in the field of civil protection will be better protection, both for the citizens of the European Union and for the inhabitants of third countries. It will ensure that the Community as a whole can offer more coordinated and more effective and more prompt aid to any country affected by a major disaster.</p>
      <p sl="el">I should remind you here that the proposal to hire transport means and equipment was part of the proposal for the new funding mechanism on which Parliament formulated its opinion earlier this year. The negotiations which followed in the Council proved to be very difficult. That is why we are calling on all the members of the European Parliament who wish to advance this proposal to do what they can at national level to support it; otherwise we shall not be able to achieve the enhanced cooperation in the field of civil protection called for by Parliament.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-183" speaker_id="28586" name="Dimitrios Papadimoulis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, over recent years we have experienced a tsunami, hurricane Katrina and earthquakes in Pakistan and Indonesia with high death tolls, while in the European Union the Member States have frequently faced major floods and storms, forest fires, disasters at sea and industrial accidents. The repercussions of these tragic events are huge not only in terms of human lives, but also to the economy. That is why the citizens of the European Union are rightly calling for a more effective approach.</p>
      <p sl="el">Improving the European Union's ability to respond to emergency situations is a priority for the European Parliament. That is why we are today debating ways of improving the Community civil protection mechanism.</p>
      <p sl="el">During the preparation of the committee proposal we are debating, various alternative proposals were examined. One of them was recast, which the Commission chose and which is the least ambitious choice, because it introduces a limited number of improvements to the Council decision governing the civil protection mechanism. Could the Commission therefore tell me how it arrived at this choice, the least ambitious choice, despite the repeated announcements by the European Council and the resolutions by the European Parliament on greater and stronger development of the Community civil protection mechanism?</p>
      <p sl="el">The main weaknesses identified in the recast proposal tabled by the Commission relate, firstly, to the transportation of rescue teams and equipment. Today every Member State bears responsibility for organising the transportation of its own civil protection aid. However, this shortcoming undermines the effectiveness of European aid. In 2005 alone, in five emergencies, Member States were unable to send experts and equipment, because they did not have the means to transport aid where it was needed. I think that the Commission needs to do more to address this problem.</p>
      <p sl="el">The second weakness relates to the development of a European rapid response capability. Today, Community civil protection aid is provided by the Member States on a voluntary basis. This does not add up to the European rapid response capability demanded by the European Parliament. In its communication on 25 April, the Commission proposed the creation of special standby modules which would be mobilised on request by the competent European authority. I ask you, why did the Commission not include its own proposal in the recast?</p>
      <p sl="el">The third problem relates to early warning. The ability of the European Commission to respond to natural disasters also depends upon the existence of early warning systems. The recast states that the Monitoring and Information Centre in Brussels should be linked to the systems of the Member States and international organisations. That is good, but it is not enough because, immediately after the earthquake caused by the tsunami, the governments learned, but the citizens never learned. That is why a suitable legal basis must be set up within the framework of the Council decision, so that early warning systems can be developed within the framework of the mechanism.</p>
      <p sl="el">The fourth weakness concerns the coordination of interventions in third countries. In this sector also more work needs to be done, because there is a blatant lack of coordination. Some Member States work constantly through the Community mechanism, some Member States prefer to work with the United Nations, some Member States work with both and some Member States with neither. This fragmentation and lack of coordination completely contradict the ambitious announcements by the European Council.</p>
      <p sl="el">As rapporteur, together with the shadow rapporteurs from all the political groups, we tabled amendments which were approved almost unanimously by the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety. In brief, they relate to information for citizens, to the integration of civil protection measures in education programmes and advertising campaigns, to land management and use, in order to strengthen prevention, to the definitions of terms based on the agreed international terminology, to the inclusion of public health and to the use of military means on an auxiliary and voluntary basis.</p>
      <p sl="el">Finally, I should like to mention the Barnier report on the creation of Europe Aid. In January 2006, the President of the European Commission and the President of the European Council asked Michel Barnier to examine the role of the European Union in dealing with crises. It turned out to be a very detailed report with interesting proposals. Unfortunately, however, both the Commission and the Council simply welcomed the report as an important contribution and did nothing about it. I should like the Commissioner to tell me how the Commission intends to make use of the Barnier report.</p>
      <p sl="el">The price of the lack of a unified and effective Europe when it comes to crisis management is very high, which is why we need to proceed more effectively and with greater coordination.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-184" speaker_id="2182" name="Antonios Trakatellis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, the Council decision being approved, with our adopted amendments, is the product of an exhaustive preparatory procedure and of the experience acquired over recent years from dealing with natural and man-made disasters, disasters which, apart from their huge impact on every aspect of citizens' every day lives, revealed objective shortcomings in the capacity for national intervention and, hence, enhanced expectations for Community assistance.</p>
      <p sl="el">We are therefore being called upon today to strengthen and arm the Union so that it can respond to this demand by the citizens for effective intervention in the fields of the prevention of and rapid response to natural and man-made disasters. This is therefore an expression of the real solidarity sought between the Member States, which will further strengthen the feeling of participation in a community and will thus further strengthen the European conscience. As far as the amendments to the initial proposal are concerned, I consider it necessary to draw your attention to the following points:</p>
      <p sl="el">An effective early warning and response system is founded on the following four components: identifying and assessing risks, constantly monitoring them, a warning and communication mechanism and, lastly, preparedness – the capacity to react and assist.</p>
      <p sl="el">I too, like the rapporteur, should like to emphasise that the amendments which we tabled concern matters such as the early warning system, standby modules from the participating states, response and citizen information guidelines, best practices for dealing with situations and, lastly, mutual consular assistance for determining contact points between Member States.</p>
      <p sl="el">I should also like to say – and I think that this should be accepted – that we must pay special attention to the public health sector, because disasters are usually accompanied by dangers to public health, either as a result of a lack of food or water or from epidemics and, consequently, this component should also be included in the proposal.</p>
      <p sl="el">Finally, I should like to observe, as our rapporteur said, that the Barnier report is an exceptional report, which should be taken into account because, otherwise, what was the point in doing all this exceptional work? I think that, together with your report today, we shall have an effective mechanism.</p>
      <p sl="el">To close, I should like to thank our rapporteur for his excellent work. Congratulations, Mr Papadimoulis.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-185" speaker_id="28310" name="Edite Estrela" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PSE Group">
      <p sl="pt">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I should like to begin by congratulating Mr Papadimoulis on his report and the Commission on its initiative. The EU has at its disposal various legal mechanisms for preventing, and responding to, natural disasters. There are indeed a number of Parliament resolutions to this effect.</p>
      <p sl="pt">I myself drew up a report on the European strategy for responding to natural disasters on behalf of the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety in which I advocated the need for the Union to have quicker and more effective resources for responding to serious emergencies. On the basis of the experience of recent years with the forest fires in southern Europe and the floods in Central Europe, the creation of detection and early warning systems to protect the citizens and their property from natural disasters, including earthquakes and tsunamis, has become a priority.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Although responsibility for managing the response to natural disasters rests primarily with the country affected, with the Union playing a supporting role, the Community civil protection mechanism set up in 2001 lacked resources and powers. In other words, it fell short of what was needed.</p>
      <p sl="pt">This recast, improved proposal is worthy of praise. It will lead to better coordination and quicker assistance for the people affected. More needs to be done, however, and the model needs to be perfected, not only on the basis of the Barnier report, but also the amendments tabled by the Committee on the Environment, of which I should like to highlight the following: cooperation in civil protection should be based on a European strategic coordination centre responsible for gathering and disseminating information on emergencies and for providing additional resources for rapid intervention to fight natural disasters; the involvement of communities in prevention and response, for which they will need training and information; and greater investment in training the assistance intervention teams.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-186" speaker_id="28363" name="Alfonso Andria" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I should like to congratulate Mr Papadimoulis on his excellent work. His report translates in practical terms that which has already been provided for in the report on the Solidarity Fund, which represents the legal and financial basis for intervention in the field of civil protection.</p>
      <p sl="it">The European Union currently has financial means and new knowledge based on the experience of the Community Civil Protection Mechanism, created in 2001, which will enable us to improve the instrument's practicality and effectiveness. It is true that the emergency response to disasters must come first and foremost from the local level, with prevention and reconstruction measures, but it is also true that there is a need for crisis management measures, which can and should be coordinated at European level, if we want to achieve significant economies of scale and, above all, greater efficiency.</p>
      <p sl="it">Furthermore, when the scale of a disaster overwhelms the local or even national capacity to react, it would be desirable to be able to provide rapid additional assistance from other countries, using their available skills and resources. We should in fact bear in mind that in many cases major disasters have effects that transcend borders, having an impact on the territories of neighbouring countries.</p>
      <p sl="it">In addition, I agree with the rapporteur on the importance of proper and appropriate planning of land use and of prevention and management of disasters with a view to reducing risks. There is a need to strengthen the European civil protection system, in order to be able to provide coordinated responses to tackle emergencies and contribute to a European Union capable of giving its own citizens confidence and safety. I believe that we have to learn to live up to these legitimate expectations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-187" speaker_id="28252" name="Richard Seeber" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, Commissioner, we all learn from the past and from our own experiences, and I believe that disaster prevention is one area in which we do this. The documents you have submitted and Mr Papadimoulis’ outstanding report represent an attempt by us at putting these experiences to good use.</p>
      <p sl="de">Three aspects need to be considered: firstly, the preventive measures; secondly, interventions in a crisis situation, and, thirdly, how to deal with the aftermath. While the European Union can afford a great deal in the way of preventive measures, it is an unfortunate fact that disasters strike in a variety of regions and for various reasons, so it is of the utmost importance that we, here in the European Union, should learn from one another. It is in this respect that the European Union has a particular task to perform.</p>
      <p sl="de">During interventions to deal with a crisis situation, the Union must discharge its particular role as a coordinator. The Member States must not be discharged from their responsibilities; the prevention of disasters is and remains a national responsibility, and it is for that reason that I take an extremely critical view of the EU's current acquisition of equipment, which represents what might be termed an attempt at duplication, and certainly is not beneficial. It is important that duplication should be avoided, and we should concentrate on good coordination of the resources present in the Member States in order to do that.</p>
      <p sl="de">The next stage is dealing with the fallout, and a crisis response instrument – in the shape of the Solidarity Fund – has already been put in place by the European Union in order to do this. Here, too, we should consider how more efficient use may be made of it, possibly by changing the basic rates and concentrating on dealing only with crises that affect Europe as a whole.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-188" speaker_id="28581" name="Evangelia Tzampazi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, the protection of European citizens from accidents and natural disasters is directly connected to their economic and social security. Over recent years, there has been a huge increase in the number of natural disasters, resulting in an equally huge increase in requests for assistance from the civil protection mechanism on the part of the governments of the Member States.</p>
      <p sl="el">Civil protection is a complex system which consists of prevention, intervention and, lastly, restoration. The excellent report by Mr Papadimoulis on the proposed recast does, I think, improve the Council proposal in a way which strengthens the supportive and supplementary actions by the Union when they are needed.</p>
      <p sl="el">However, I stand by the ongoing need for instruction of the parties involved and I consider that greater information for the public is needed, especially in areas with a high degree of risk, in order to help improve prevention and preparedness in the areas in question.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-189" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Stavros Dimas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Μember of the Commission. Mr President, I should like to thank all the speakers for their excellent comments. Before I touch on the matter of the amendments, I should like to reply on the question of the Barnier report and to say that the Commission has already started work on many of the issues connected with this report, the most important, of course, being the development of civil protection modules. Meetings have been held with specialists from the Member States in order to ascertain what types of modules should be available in each case and the specific terms and conditions for each type of module.</p>
      <p sl="el">A second field of work relates to exercises and, despite the fact that no provision is made for the creation of a European institute in accordance with the Barnier report, we do nonetheless propose that a network of centres should be developed which will extend the existing exercise programme.</p>
      <p sl="el">We also agree that the Monitoring and Information Centre should be reinforced. We have already requested an increase in the number of employees, of officers, to be employed at the centre. We have also asked the Member States to give us the opportunity next year to use certain specialists at the MIC.</p>
      <p sl="el">Finally, the Commission has two legislative proposals, one for the means of financing and one for the recast of the 2001 decision, which will give us the possibility of working in another sector, the transport sector, about which I spoke earlier.</p>
      <p sl="el">Now, as far as the amendments are concerned, the European Parliament has presented a series of important amendments with a view to strengthening civil protection capabilities at European level. The amendments relate to the need to safeguard prompt transportation of civil protection aid, the importance of early warning and alert systems, the interoperability of civil protection modules and the role which the mechanism can play in helping the citizens of the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="el">The Commission can accept most of the proposed amendments. However, there are some which cause problems and cannot be adopted as they stand. I refer to those relating to the provision of measures relating to prevention, public health and deliberate maritime pollution.</p>
      <p sl="el">As regards the measures relating to prevention, the Commission wishes to emphasise that the proposal for the means of financing civil protection will cover actions in this sector. The Community civil protection mechanism is designed to cover actions in the sectors of preparedness and intervention only. Nonetheless, the Commission agrees with the European Parliament about the importance of actions in the field of prevention and has promised to promote them within an appropriate framework.</p>
      <p sl="el">As regards the inclusion of public health, the Commission recognises that civil protection actions very often aim to protect public health. However, the civil protection mechanism set up at European Union level does not form part of public health policy, which is covered by other existing Community mechanisms, such as the Community action programme in the health sector.</p>
      <p sl="el">As far as deliberate or intentional maritime pollution is concerned, the Commission fully supports the proposal whereby it must be possible for the civil protection mechanism to intervene in cases of extensive maritime pollution caused either accidentally or deliberately. The proposal by the European Commission to extend the scope so that it also covers man-made disasters covers this possibility. However, the term 'intentional, deliberate' maritime pollution usually refers to the jettisoning of small quantities of oil from ships and the Commission wishes to avoid the interpretation that the scope of the regulation covers jettisoning to such a minor degree. It would be practically impossible for the Commission to mobilise the mechanism – nor, as I said earlier, does it have the staff – and this sort of minor jettisoning should be dealt with by the means available to each country. That is why the corresponding amendments were not accepted.</p>
      <p sl="el">Finally, the Commission would point out that a series of amendments relates to aspects of existing legislation. The Commission supports some of these amendments in essence. However, the interinstitutional agreement on the use of the recast technique does not allow the Commission to accept them, unless they are of vital importance to the application of the new provisions contained in the proposal or derive directly from the new provisions. However, the Commission will bear the issues in question in mind within the framework of the development of our policy in this sector.</p>
      <p sl="el">These are the main issues on which the Commission's position differs from that taken in the European Parliament report. However, I wish to stress that these differences of opinion do not overshadow our common objectives. We agree fully with the ambition of the European Parliament to develop a very strong European intervention capability in the field of civil protection, both inside and outside the European Union, and we thank you for your support. I shall send the European Parliament secretariat a full list of the Commission's positions on the amendments. I should like once again to congratulate the rapporteur, Mr Papadimoulis, on his excellent work.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-190" speaker_id="4393" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place on Tuesday at 12 noon.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statement (Rule 142)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-191" speaker_id="28146" name="Hélène Goudin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="sv">The European Parliament is now dealing with a proposal for revising the Civil Protection Mechanism set up in 2001. There is no doubt that disasters put great strains on the parties affected. Coordinated European civil protection is not, however, the solution to the problem, especially in the form in which it appears in this proposal.</p>
      <p sl="sv">Civil protection in each Member State is funded through taxes. It is up to each State to choose how tax revenue collected from its citizens is to be distributed. This proposal may entail a risk of certain Member States choosing to invest a minimum of resources in national civil protection, relying on other EU countries contributing when a disaster occurs. This problem of free-riding is very serious and is unfair towards people in those countries that choose to have strong civil protection. Where international efforts are concerned, these should be coordinated through OCHA and funded by the Member States and not by the EU.</p>
      <p sl="sv">The Commission's document also talks about rapid reaction forces and about the Member States having to give notice of available resources, including military resources and military capacity, in cases where an affected country requests that type of aid. The June List resolutely objects to these proposals. A country’s military resources are a matter for that particular nation, and it is up to each Member State to decide whether or not such resources should be mobilised.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem22" title="22. European order for payment procedure (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-193" speaker_id="4393" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the recommendation for second reading (A6-0316/2006), on behalf of the Committee on Legal Affairs, on the Council common position (07535/3/2006 C6-0227/2006 2004/0055(COD)) for adopting a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council creating a European order for payment procedure (Rapporteur: Arlene McCarthy).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-194" speaker_id="2173" name="Arlene McCarthy" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Commissioner, almost 12 months ago we first gave our approval to the European payment order, a new law to assist in simplified debt recovery for businesses and citizens owed money in another EU Member State. Today, a year later, the committee’s view has not changed. We believe that we need this pragmatic and practical EU law, in particular to ensure that businesses and citizens have an affordable system to recover those debts owed to them. Why? Because until this law comes into force, recovery of debts from another EU State is a costly legal process. In some cases, money spent on lawyers and administrative costs exceeds the amount owed to the individual. More significantly, studies and experience show that companies which do not get their debts paid are at risk of collapsing, with knock-on effects not just in terms of job losses, but also for other SMEs in the supply chain.</p>
      <p sl="en">Out of between 30 and 40 billion invoices in Europe each year, as many as 1 billion default and turn into debt cases. Interim Justicia carried out a survey on payment practices in 16 European countries some 10 years ago. The average delay then was just 14 days. By the end of 2003, however, this had not declined, but risen to 16 days. According to a World Bank study, ‘Doing Business in 2004: Understanding Regulation’, the Nordic countries have the most efficient and effective legal systems of the countries surveyed. They take the least time to reach a solution while keeping costs low. Italy is one of the countries with the longest delays worldwide. The explanation it is said lies in the lax appeal process, which allows proceedings to be disrupted at any point during a trial. Spain, by contrast, has one of the most complex legal systems, which generates higher costs and leads to longer court proceedings. My own Member State, the UK, has some three systems operating for payments, again creating confusion for businesses or the public.</p>
      <p sl="en">Extensive differences in legal regulation of overdue payment recovery therefore lead to uncertainties, especially in EU trade, and the additional costs prevent the EU’s aim of equal opportunities for market access for both local and EU operating companies. It is clear that a lack of enforcement systems for payments undermines the internal market and business confidence and that, as a result, SMEs have continued to experience cash flow problems caused by late payments.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European payment order will also apply to individual citizens who work or live in another Member State and who can also take advantage of this new law. Of course, the high and expanding volume of trade within the EU and the increased movement of people raise the likelihood that more and more businesses may become involved in cross-border litigation. There is a risk that citizens may not be inclined to assert their rights because of the obstacles they face, particularly in dealing with the legal system in another Member State and with unfamiliar procedures and unknown costs. It is essential, therefore, that the EU provide for a judicial area where private individuals and businesses can have access to justice and redress in the case of an uncontested claim.</p>
      <p sl="en">This procedural law will help facilitate that access. The payment order introduces a practical EU-level instrument for obtaining an enforceable decision and I believe in this way we can demonstrate to citizens that the EU is delivering a practical tool to assist them with redress and remedies.</p>
      <p sl="en">I want to put on record my thanks to members of the committee, in particular the shadows, Mr Wieland, who is here this evening, and Mrs Wallis, who cannot be here. They have not only supported my approach but have made useful and constructive proposals for amendments at every stage of the procedure. The committee consulted with key protagonists and we believe we focused on the core issues. Both my shadows were concerned to ensure that the forms and the annex, the bones of the proposal, were simple enough for businesses to be able to fill them out with minimum bureaucracy. Only time and experience will tell if this has been achieved. That is why, under the new comitology procedures, Parliament needs to be consulted and informed of any changes the Commission would like to make to the system.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would also like to thank the British Presidency, in particular the Minister Baroness Ashton, who was instrumental in helping us to make progress on the clear drafting of this law.</p>
      <p sl="en">So now, Commissioner, at second reading we are down to the last few details. Mrs Wallis is concerned that the Commission should seriously address the potential discrimination affecting citizens and businesses where EEA members can participate in the single market, but cannot be a party to the EPO. I hope the Commission will address this issue.</p>
      <p sl="en">The forms should be user-friendly and simple and we would therefore like the Commission to take on board our amendment in this area.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, since we started this process a year ago and since the Commission’s original proposal, we now have a new institutional agreement, with effect from July 2006. The committee and Parliament insist that the new regulatory scrutiny procedure and rule should be respected in this legislation and on the payment order.</p>
      <p sl="en">Commissioner, let me say how much we have appreciated the cooperation of your departments in this area. I hope that, together with the Finnish Presidency, we can sign off the European payment order and begin the process of putting it into law across all the Member States of the EU, so that businesses and citizens can be confident of operating in the internal market in the knowledge that the failure to pay a debt does not end up in endless court proceedings with no outcome. Thanks to the European Union, there is now a simple and user-friendly system for speedy payment of debts which, I believe, will drive forward the internal market for SMEs and boost the EU economy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-195" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Franco Frattini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, first of all, I would like to thank the rapporteur, Mrs McCarthy, warmly for her work and her efforts to bring this project, which is very important for our citizens, to a satisfactory conclusion.</p>
      <p sl="en">Like the rapporteur, I would also like to thank the former United Kingdom Presidency, particularly Baroness Ashton, for the work done in moving ahead with this important project.</p>
      <p sl="en">As you know, this regulation on the European order for payment procedure aims at facilitating the mass recovery of uncontested claims in Europe. It is thus very important, as it will allow all creditors in Europe to recover their claims in a uniform way and more rapidly and cheaply than in ordinary court proceedings. It will also alleviate the burden on the courts by removing from ordinary proceedings those claims where the debtor does not contest the debt.</p>
      <p sl="en">The proposal potentially concerns all citizens and economic operators in Europe. A European order for payment can circulate freely in Europe and will be enforced automatically. There will be therefore no need to request a declaration of enforcement – the ‘exequatur’ – in the Member State of enforcement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Concerning the amendments, I can accept the third amendment as proposed. On the second amendment, I can accept the compromise amendment on the comitology procedure, which is in line with the Council decision taken in July 2006. On the first amendment, while I understand the reason and the concern expressed by the committee, I think that we should not at this stage reopen the question of the definition of a cross-border case, adopted at first reading by the Council and the European Parliament. At the same time, I can confirm that the Commission is available and willing to look more closely into the effects of the regulation for parties domiciled in third countries and, in particular, states of the European Economic Area. I am ready to give very careful consideration to any proposals.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-196" speaker_id="2323" name="Rainer Wieland" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, the rapporteur, Mrs McCarthy, has set out the essentials of why this matters in economic terms.</p>
      <p sl="de">This European order for payment procedure represents a major step forward in the application of laws across borders, and, in particular, a step forward for business, which has a particular interest in the legal soundness of claims being established without delay, in the prompt assignment of title, and in this claim being capable of being enforced, without further cost-intensive procedures, in the country of the debtor. It has to be said, though – and it is to this that I want to give particular attention – that legal relationships across borders will become increasingly important to private citizens, who find it particularly difficult to enforce claims across borders, whether such claims are contentious or not.</p>
      <p sl="de">Today, it is undisputed claims that we are discussing, and that is why this first step is so important. Private individuals find the business of getting what they are entitled to complicated enough as it is, and they have serious problems with getting claims enforced in a country other than their own; this instrument will make things easier for them. A form that even an ordinary member of the public can complete will make it possible for claims to be enforced relatively simply and without great expense.</p>
      <p sl="de">Another consideration is that constant reference has been made to businesses and to creditors, but not enough has been said about the debtors. Systems have been introduced in the Member States of the European Union – not least in the one from which I come – to make the establishment of such claims a positively economical business, not least for those who owe the money. The debtor who is willing – but perhaps not able – to pay up, can agree reasonable repayments with the creditor, who has an interest in establishing title and thereby preventing the debt from lapsing, and, in the absence of a contested case, fewer costs are incurred.</p>
      <p sl="de">It is therefore in the interests of all parties that we should make cross-border legal proceedings speedy, efficient and affordable.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-197" speaker_id="28382" name="Andrzej Jan Szejna" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PSE Group">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, late payments are the main cause of insolvency, which threatens the survival of businesses, especially small and medium-sized ones. They jeopardise the operations and solvency of these businesses, often resulting in the loss of many jobs. Swift and efficient debt recovery when no legal dispute is involved is therefore vitally important for business entities in the European Union. It helps to preserve jobs.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The Member States have attempted to solve the problem of large-scale debt recovery in the case of undisputed claims, generally by simplifying proceedings regarding payment orders. There are, however, significant differences between national provisions and the way individual procedures operate. As a result, the latter may be inadmissible or impossible to apply in cross-border situations. It is therefore appropriate to respond positively to the proposed regulation setting up a European procedure for payment orders.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-198" speaker_id="4393" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place on Wednesday at 12.30 p.m.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem23" title="23. Agenda for next sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem24" title="24. Closure of sitting"/>
</text>
