<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20070315.EN" lang="en" date="2007-03-15" place="Strasbourg" edition="OJ edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Opening of the sitting">
    <intervention id="4-006" speaker_id="28139" name="Carl Schlyter" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="sv">Mr President, it is an issue of protocol that I am addressing. Yesterday, when I was to talk about the report on trade defence instruments, I wanted to quote the Muscardini report from October, whereupon I discovered that an important bit of it was missing. As a result, I do not know how we are to proceed now. The report is from October 2006, but there is a serious error in the Swedish version, as the whole of the following text is missing from paragraph 11, and I wonder how we can remedy this. The following text is missing from the Swedish version: ‘with a view to including non-compliance with global social and environmental agreements or international covenants as forms of dumping or subsidy’. If the whole aspect of the environment and social dumping is missing from the Swedish version, the Swedish people will get a false picture of what it is that Parliament wants.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-007" speaker_id="1983" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Mr Schlyter, this comment is very important and it will be taken into account. It will be checked and the necessary action will be taken.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Regional policy (islands and natural and economic constraints) (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-009" speaker_id="1983" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report (A6-0044/2007) by Mr Musotto, on behalf of the Committee on Regional Development, on the islands and natural and economic constraints in the context of the regional policy (2006/2106(INI)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-010" speaker_id="4471" name="Francesco Musotto" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I would like to express my sincere thanks to all my fellow Members who have contributed to the drafting of this report. We believe that this is the first time that a complete study has been dedicated to the islands, taking account of their specific characteristics with regard to all areas of Community competence: although the 2007-2013 cohesion policy pays particular attention to structurally disadvantaged regions, no specific measures are provided for island regions.</p>
      <p sl="it">Parliament has highlighted this gap several times and, although the situation in European islands is varied – there are 121 islands in all, with a population of roughly 15 million inhabitants – they share a series of difficulties that constitute a competitive disadvantage: higher prices due to additional transport costs and little competition; difficulty in accessing the single market, the need to import raw materials, higher energy costs, lack of infrastructure, immigration, limited diversification of economic activities and vulnerability to environmental risks. It is no accident that the average per capita GDP on the islands is 72% of the European Union average. It is therefore necessary to recognise their specific island characteristics when implementing Community policy, beginning with State aids. We believe that greater flexibility is needed in order to offset the additional costs and, as regards energy, to compensate for fluctuations in the cost of fuel.</p>
      <p sl="it">In the context of the Structural Funds operating programmes, particular emphasis must be given to carrying out infrastructure projects, especially within the framework of European maritime policy, in order to integrate the islands fully into the internal market and the Lisbon Strategy. On the other hand, islands enjoy an advantage as regards the generation of energy using wind, sun and sea. These represent unequalled potential value, which is why the Commission must support projects for renewable energy sources and energy security.</p>
      <p sl="it">Tourism is another resource to be exploited. We need a Community policy for promoting island tourism, a quality and origin label and an in-depth study on sustainable tourism. Among other things, we propose 2010 as the European year for the islands.</p>
      <p sl="it">The report also tackles the issue of illegal immigration, which we view as both a human tragedy and an unsustainable burden for the Mediterranean islands, for which the European Union must take responsibility. We welcome the creation of Rapid Border Intervention Teams and call for the establishment of a European coastguard body. As a matter of urgency, the European Union must allocate the necessary resources to guarantee rapid and timely intervention in this field.</p>
      <p sl="it">There are other proposals which warrant further development, such as the financial instruments JASPERS (Joint Assistance in Supporting Projects in European Regions) and JEREMIE (Joint European Resources for Micro to Medium Enterprises) to facilitate access to credit for small and medium-sized enterprises and to promote the diversification of island economies, or the distribution of broadband to bridge the technology gap.</p>
      <p sl="it">Finally, it is essential that we revise the legal framework in order to take into full consideration the specific characteristics of islands and update the statistical indicators accordingly: taking account of the islands within the context of the European Spatial Planning Observation Network and setting up an administrative unit for the islands within the Commission Directorate-General for Regional Policy.</p>
      <p sl="it">We hope that this report will represent a real turning point, once and for all, by producing genuine development and providing practical answers for new generations who intend to continue to live and work in the place where they were born, integrated into the European context.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-011" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neelie Kroes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, islands and other territories with natural or specific constraints are very important to the Commission in terms of ensuring territorial cohesion, developing cross-border cooperation – usually with third countries, tourism, culture and other issues.</p>
      <p sl="en">While acknowledging that a cross-sectoral approach may be useful, cohesion policy aims to play a central role in dealing with the specific problems of these territories. In the draft 2007-2013 Cohesion Policy General Regulation, issued in July 2004, the Commission specifically proposed granting a co-financing rate top-up to these regions. Unfortunately, this proposal was not finally adopted by the Council in the final version of the regulation approved in July 2006 and which is now in force, as you are aware. However, the Commission will ensure, during the ongoing negotiations on the Cohesion Policy intervention for 2007-2013, that the specific constraints of these territories are duly taken into account in the corresponding programmes and that suitable measures are programmed to tackle them.</p>
      <p sl="en">In addition, the Commission is now preparing the Fourth Cohesion Report to be published in May, which will contain a comprehensive analysis of the state of play and trends in territorial cohesion in the EU, including islands and regions with natural handicaps. Likewise the Commission intends to continue upgrading work within the ESPON programme in order to obtain more suitable indicators and more updated information on these territories. At the same time, the Commission would point out that statistical data for islands or other territories that are NUTS II or NUTS III regions are already available. Gathering statistical information for smaller territories is certainly more difficult, but in fact 95% of the European island population, outermost regions excluded, live in NUTS II or NUTS III regions.</p>
      <p sl="en">Turning to the practical implementation of the notion of territorial cohesion, despite the lack of an explicit legal base as provided by the Constitutional Treaty, the Council already agreed in 2004 in Rotterdam to introduce the territorial dimension into the Lisbon process. It also started to develop the territorial agenda and this document, which aims at presenting the challenges, objectives and policy recommendations for territorial cohesion, is due to be adopted in May 2007 in Leipzig.</p>
      <p sl="en">Moreover, the Community strategy guidelines on cohesion adopted by the Council last October include a specific chapter on the territorial dimension of cohesion policy. The Commission is now working to ensure their practical implementation in the programming documents that are now being negotiated.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission is very much in favour of promoting Euro-regions or similar structures in order to manage cross-border transnational and interregional cooperation. These bodies could be particularly suited to islands and other regions with natural handicaps and, in addition, the Commission encourages these territories to make use of the brand new European Grouping for Territorial Cooperation in order to facilitate the management of the corresponding programmes.</p>
      <p sl="en">With regard to state aid, it may be that regional investment aid is not the best instrument to tackle local problems in islands. I believe that the islands’ main problems can be tackled more effectively with, for example, horizontal instruments. Our state aid rules already allow for many forms of aid. For example, our rules on services of general economic interest allow compensation for the provision of local public services, including passenger transport services.</p>
      <p sl="en">Secondly, our new guidelines on risk capital and our framework for research development and innovation offer new opportunities to support young, innovative companies, with extra bonuses for small and medium-sized enterprises.</p>
      <p sl="en">In some cases, the support levels needed by small islands will not be counted as aids at all. Under the new de minimis regulation, aid of up to EUR 200 000, granted over any period of 3 years will not be counted as aid. Investment for all kinds of public infrastructure can be financed. They do not have an aid element. Moreover, the specific situation of islands is effectively taken into account in the new regional aid guidelines. Under the new form of aid to help business start-ups, a 5% bonus is given to small islands.</p>
      <p sl="en">I think that these examples really show how, through our state aid reform process, we are making the rules more predictable and reducing the administrative burden of state aid notification, and that was what you were asking for in the interests of island regions and all other stakeholders.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-012" speaker_id="28120" name="Simon Busuttil" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group">
      <p sl="mt">I would like to begin by congratulating my colleague, Mr Musotto on this report. It is an extremely important report, especially for those who, like me, come from islands. It is particularly important because it lends a voice to islands. Islands deserve to be heard, because up until now the European Union has not paid them enough attention. This report is therefore devoting the appropriate consideration to them. I was also pleased to hear Commissioner Kroes state that islands are important for the European Commission. However, Commissioner, we want islands to be considered in all the various policy areas within the European Union and not simply viewed through the lens of regional policy. For example, you are Commissioner for competition and, as you rightly stated, there are rules on state aid that, as yet, are not sufficiently flexible in the case of islands. The rules intended for the whole of the European territory are not necessarily flexible enough to apply to islands, and we would like you to examine these rules seriously, to dedicate more attention to islands and to ensure that the rules can be applied as flexibly as possible.</p>
      <p sl="mt">I would like to highlight paragraph 10 of the report. It talks about the need for the Commission regularly to draw up a report on the requirements of islands and on how these can be addressed. I expect the Commission to draw up such a report, and we will keep insisting that this be done. Once again, I would like to say that this is a good report and, undoubtedly, one that all the islands involved will appreciate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-013" speaker_id="28578" name="Stavros Arnaoutakis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PSE Group">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, once again the European Parliament has brought up the subject of islands. Once again it has clearly stated in this report – and I should like to congratulate Mr Musotto on a job very well done – that island regions need special treatment. They need more aid, in order not only to overcome the development problems they face, but also so that they can make use of the potential of the common market and the globalised economy.</p>
      <p sl="el">For all of us who inhabit island regions, problems to varying degrees, such as geographical isolation, the lack of infrastructures, economic and demographic stagnation and limited resources and options are, I would say, a way of life. At the same time, however, we are all – both permanent residents and the millions of citizens who choose European islands for their holidays – well aware of the advantages of island regions: their cultural wealth, their rich but sensitive ecosystems, their natural environment, their special way of life and their quality products and traditional methods of manufacture. We must support these advantages, we must highlight them and we must promote them through the policies of the European Union, especially through the cohesion policy, if we really want fundamental economic and territorial cohesion between the regions of Europe. It is in this context that I should like to refer to the particular importance of granting state aid to island regions, where the cost of fuel and energy has an adverse impact on their competitiveness and on the flexible application of both existing and future state aid in relation to the cost of transport, the application of an integrated policy on tourism, the application of an effective business policy and the immediate creation of an administrative unit for islands at the Regional Policy DG on the basis of experience acquired by the administrative unit for remote regions, the operation of which will safeguard all the peculiarities and needs of the islands and of their permanent and seasonal inhabitants which are taken into account in the development and application of European policies, especially in the transport, energy and water resource management sectors.</p>
      <p sl="el">At a time when the Fourth Cohesion Report is being prepared and the debate on the future of regional policy is starting in the run-up to the review of the financial perspective for 2008-2009, the European Parliament should remember that the European Union cannot deal differently with similar situations or with different situations in the same way.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-014" speaker_id="4547" name="Elspeth Attwooll" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, Commissioner, the ALDE Group thanks Mr Musotto for his very valuable report on the natural and economic constraints affecting islands.</p>
      <p sl="de">All the topics covered merit full attention, but I should like to concentrate on issues relating to state aid and paragraphs 8, 9 and 19. The reason has to do with the realities of life on islands, particularly those remote from centres of population. The examples are from my own constituency, but resonate across the whole of the EU.</p>
      <p sl="de">To emphasise the problem of distance, it takes a friend from the Shetland Islands a 14-hour journey by car and ferry to reach the nearest cinema. The price of petrol is some 11% higher in the Western Isles than in Scotland’s central belt. This rises to around 16% for the Shetland Islands. A bale of hay costs five times as much in the Western Isles as it does just outside the nearest city of Inverness. Facts like these only begin to illustrate how far matters of location alone can place islands at a competitive disadvantage.</p>
      <p sl="de">I thank the Commissioner for what she said about state aid, but a more flexible regime is still needed simply to level the playing field. I have particular concerns, as she knows, with the market investor test. Again, the realities of life on islands and in other remote regions make this test very difficult to satisfy, as no appropriate comparator may be available and the small size of the market creates problems where the average level of return for a given sector is concerned.</p>
      <p sl="de">All we seek in this context is for our islands to enjoy access to the single market on equal terms with mainland regions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-015" speaker_id="28355" name="Mieczysław Edmund Janowski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the UEN Group">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, I would like to congratulate the rapporteur for the work done. If we are honest with ourselves, we must today admit that not all citizens of EU Member States enjoy the same advantages. In our Community there are areas where particular constraints exist because of distance or poor accessibility. Those areas include islands, and they are often also ultraperipheral and mountain areas.</p>
      <p sl="pl">We talk about solidarity, and internal cohesion. These fundamental principles require us to exercise due care and if necessary, provide adequate support for the people who live in the areas mentioned. Transport difficulties, scarcity of raw materials, increased energy supply costs, difficulties in accessing the Internet, and telecommunications networks, difficult terrain, particularly in the mountains and the furthermost northern areas, depopulation, or illegal immigration – those are the major problems addressed by the report.</p>
      <p sl="pl">In support of the conclusions arrived at by the rapporteur, I wish to call to us all not to abandon these people to their fate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-016" speaker_id="28508" name="Alyn Smith" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to add my own congratulations to the rapporteur and thank him for his very constructive approach to our amendments as we were working on this in the committee. I am very pleased to support his report today.</p>
      <p sl="en">Coming from Scotland I have a particular interest and a particular perspective, as other Scots colleagues do, and I would remind colleagues firstly that peripherality is relative. Brussels is actually pretty peripheral if I am looking for Scottish football scores on a Saturday. Islands have a distinctive culture, a distinctive identity and a distinctive geography, which is something to celebrate, not pity. If the playing field is level, there is nothing wrong with Europe’s islands that will not be put right by what is right with Europe’s islands in their dynamism, their innovation and their potential contribution to the EU’s objectives. If Malta was in central Europe with good transport links and easy links to the rest of Europe, then it would not be Malta any more, it would be Munich. We must celebrate Europe’s islands as well as recognise their distinctiveness.</p>
      <p sl="en">Being an island means that there are specific issues which need to be dealt with and this report makes a number of solid suggestions. I hope that our Commissioner will give us specific assurances today that this report will be acted upon because there are a lot of good ideas in it and I would hope that this would not become another wish list that the Commission pays lip service to but does not necessarily do very much with.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to highlight a few specific points. Islands have specific disbenefits in interaction with the European Union single market and we must have up-to-date, accurate statistics in order to inform policy. Can our Commissioner assure us that we will work with Eurostat in order to make this happen?</p>
      <p sl="en">In paragraphs 12 and 16 of our report, we call for the creation of a specific cross-cutting administrative unit within the Directorate-General for Regional Policy to deal with islands. This already exists in respect of outermost regions. The case for a specific unit dealing with islands is very clear. Can our Commissioner assure us that this will actually happen?</p>
      <p sl="en">On state aid, as other colleagues have mentioned, we must see a more realistic approach from the Commission in assessing state aid criteria for islands. Islands have specific economic factors which are not currently sufficiently taken into account and I would welcome an assurance from our Commissioner that we will review policy on this.</p>
      <p sl="en">Concerning state aid cuts, particularly in the field of transport to, from and within islands, in Scotland our own government has just squandered EUR 25 million on a very wasteful tender in respect of ferry services. This mistake was largely domestic in origin, but the complexity of the interlocking EU rules did not help and we must take a look at this again. We also need to look in particular at public service obligations and aid of a social character in terms of how they are viewed in respect of Article 87(2) of the Treaty. The position of road equivalent tariff must also be clarified.</p>
      <p sl="en">On energy, islands have a clear natural advantage and we would like to see the Commission use all means available to encourage sustainable energy communities, in particular the European grid, and the abolition of domestic constraints. In Scotland with Shetland, Orkney, the Western Isles and Argyle and Bute we have the best wind, wave and tidal resources in the EU and a vast potential contribution to make to the EU’s energy and climate change objectives, but we are not developing these resources because we have seen insufficient investment in the grid. If the EU is serious about meeting the climate change challenges, invest in interconnectors to the Scottish islands and the Scottish islands will make a vast contribution to our objectives.</p>
      <p sl="en">Similarly, the UK Government is holding us back in terms of a discriminatory pricing system in access to the National Grid in the UK. Simply, the further away from the main market, the higher the connection charge is to feed electricity into the UK National Grid. I am firmly of the view that this is discriminatory under Article 7(6) of the 2001 Renewable Energy Directive and I believe that the Commission must open formal proceedings against the UK for holding us back. The islands have a vast contribution to make and they can make it. There is nothing wrong with Europe’s islands that will not be put right by what is right with them, but we must ensure the playing field is level.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-017" speaker_id="1983" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Your speech reminds us of an important fact: we are always on the periphery of someone. The problem of centrality is not easy to define.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-018" speaker_id="28514" name="Kyriacos Triantaphyllides" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, we must, I think, congratulate the Committee on Regional Development for taking the initiative to prepare such a report.</p>
      <p sl="el">The islands of the European Union truly are a crucial element within the framework of the cohesion policy for the period from 2007 to 2013, because most face difficulties which they must overcome in order not to be at a disadvantage in relation to the rest of the European Union. Thus, for an island such as Cyprus, for example, the difficulties faced are as follows: high prices due to the interaction of captive markets and additional transport costs, low wages due to the levels of demand and opportunity, a lack of raw materials, increased energy costs, shortcomings in infrastructures, a limited range of activities and greater vulnerability to environmental risks which can impact on tourism. The report covers the broader framework of these problems in a satisfactory manner. However, there is a problem in the report with which I do not agree, and that is the problem of immigration. In proposing greater policing of external borders, the creation of a border guard and the stamping out of so-called illegal immigration, we are hiding our heads in the sand and we are not proposing viable solutions to a very big social problem, because we cannot advertise the European Union as a global economic power on the one hand and close our borders on the other. As far as this is concerned, the islands have a positive role to play which, unfortunately, is not the role described in the report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-019" speaker_id="28493" name="Derek Roland Clark" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the IND/DEM Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, so, we need another initiative do we? This time for island people. Actually, island people are by nature resourceful. They are all still there, but they need help where the EU has interfered.</p>
      <p sl="de">Last year this Parliament approved the resumption of licences for EU fishing fleets to plunder the waters of Western Sahara. Unable to compete with the modern vessels of the EU, these people sought work elsewhere, and the Canary Islands began to experience the trauma of massive illegal immigration. Graphically displayed on TV, boatloads of West Africans were seen trying to make their way across the Atlantic, their misery compounded as dozens died when their inshore craft could not cope with the open sea. Once this EU-inspired exodus began, people from neighbouring countries followed suit, making it worse.</p>
      <p sl="de">Malta faces the same problem of mass immigration. Of course it does: the EU’s high tariff barriers depress trade, with the poorer countries of northern and eastern Africa being hard hit, so off they go to try their luck in Europe using Malta as a staging post. Pouring aid into Malta is not the answer. It is the tariff barriers: bring those down, trade improves and most people in Africa will be able to make a living without moving home. If you persist with a closed shop of 27 EU countries when there is a whole world out there just waiting to engage in trade with Europe, then the problems of your own making will continue.</p>
      <p sl="de">Do I see in the report that EU islands, especially in the outermost regions, might be used as sources of renewable energy? I suppose that means we intend to plant these ridiculous wind farms on them. Well, that is one way of driving the indigenous population away, and all for useless turbines producing insignificant amounts of power at unpredictable times, located on remote islands so as to ensure that much of their pitiful output is lost in transmission.</p>
      <p sl="de">I notice that islands are said to be vulnerable to rising sea levels: another dimension of the hysterical, doom-laden warnings of the ‘global warmers’. It is not happening on the scale that has been claimed. And it is natural. It has happened before. The world experiences cycles of warming and cooling. In the Medieval warm period it was hotter than now, and for decades. There are enough records of these hotter events, such as certain crops growing where never before, but there are no records of islands disappearing beneath the waves.</p>
      <p sl="de">It is about time we all calmed down and realised that minimal global warming is naturally occurring in a cycle that has no input from man. We should simply adapt as nature intended.</p>
      <p sl="de">In conclusion, let us stop interfering. Leave successful islands alone. Where help is needed, for third world islands or otherwise, let trade be their aid. The EU’s protectionist attitude is no long-term help, it is just sticking plaster and that always peels off after a while.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-020" speaker_id="28457" name="Luca Romagnoli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ITS Group">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, how can we not take into account the structural disadvantages of our islands in Europe? It was vital for this issue to be an objective in the EU regulations on State aid. The own-initiative report on islands in the European Union and their undeniable constraints, presented by my highly esteemed colleague, Mr Musotto, is a milestone in recognising the importance of islands within the context of Europe’s regional development.</p>
      <p sl="it">In this parliamentary term, this is the first time that I have found myself analysing and commenting on a report that is so valuable and worthy of endorsement. It is worthy of endorsement because it considers all the aspects necessary and is very balanced in its approach, as well as being absolutely worthy of support on its merits and with regard to its aims. I will be happy to vote for it and I hope that it receives full endorsement from all my fellow Members.</p>
      <p sl="it">Is it possible for the EU not to take into account a statistically undeniable fact, which is that approximately 15 million citizens live on islands, and that over 90% of these people have incomes lower than the European average? The main causes of this state of affairs are the undeniable structural deficits directly resulting from island status, and for too long the European Union has all but ignored this fact.</p>
      <p sl="it">Now, the valuable Musotto report, as well as setting out in the observations reasons for this underdevelopment, and clearly describing the specific resources of islands, finally focuses on what action the Union can take, and through which specific tools, analyses and statistics, as part of the allocation of the Structural Funds and aid to disadvantaged areas, to accommodate the structural disadvantages of islands. This course is one that we owe to island communities, acknowledging both their role in European civilisation and their current role as an extremely important environmental and economic resource for the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="it">If the islands are sustained within the undeniable constraints on their development that they still face in the shape of obstacles associated with island status, and if due consideration is taken of this in the guidelines on the Structural Funds, the European Union will be making a significant contribution to removing inequalities, or, in fact, discrimination, which is not only unjustifiable in terms of the Community acquis but antithetical to the established objective of fair and consistent development of Europe’s regions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-021" speaker_id="28573" name="Nikolaos Vakalis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, despite the pronounced objective of the European Union to achieve convergence between its regions, the peculiarities of island regions lead to divergence. The resources of the Structural Funds did not have the anticipated results for these regions. As such, new action needs to be planned and special measures need to be taken for the islands. The systematic monitoring and recording of their development in comparison with the other regions of Europe will be a useful tool.</p>
      <p sl="el">I welcome the incorporation of a series of issues in the report we are voting on today, such as a re-examination of the conditions of contracts in order to facilitate transport and public transport on lines of little commercial interest, the safeguarding of energy security with the emphasis and priority on renewable sources of energy, a study and measures to combat the effects of climate change which exacerbate existing problems such as drought, broadband coverage to facilitate the daily life of island dwellers and resolve important problems, proper, controlled development which protects the appearance of the islands and dealing with the problem of illegal immigration and border controls by introducing a European coastguard.</p>
      <p sl="el">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, today's report is a good start. However, if we are to achieve the desired results, I call on the Commission to propose immediate measures and action so that what is set out in the own initiative report is put into practice.</p>
      <p sl="el">To close, I wish to thank and congratulate the rapporteur, Mr Musotto, on his important and consistent work.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-022" speaker_id="4545" name="Catherine Stihler" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, an island holiday may be the stuff of dreams in terms of getting away from it all, but living and working on islands can pose many difficulties, and we should acknowledge this in our policy-making.</p>
      <p sl="en">I congratulate the rapporteur, Mr Musotto, on his report, which outlines the natural and economic constraints faced by islands in the context of regional policy. The report deals with the singular difficulties that many islands face in competing successfully with their counterparts on the mainland.</p>
      <p sl="en">The report usefully identifies categories of islands: some are large – 5 island regions have populations exceeding 500 000 and account for 75% of the European island population – whilst the remainder are much smaller.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am more familiar with the problems faced by smaller islands, such as those off the coast of my native Scotland. For example, only this week it has been reported that twice as many young women than men are leaving the Hebrides. If this continues, the population will not be sustainable from 2019.</p>
      <p sl="en">As Mr Musotto’s report outlines, there are also common difficulties faced by islands, for example higher prices, difficult terrain, remoteness and poor infrastructure. I support the call for these problems to be recognised in regional policy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-023" speaker_id="28363" name="Alfonso Andria" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I should like to begin by warmly congratulating Mr Musotto on his excellent work. I have expressed my awareness of the specific features of islands when participating in the negotiation process on the new regulations on cohesion policy as rapporteur for the regulation on the Cohesion Fund and as shadow rapporteur on the general regulation and the regulation on the European Fund for Regional Development.</p>
      <p sl="it">I am well aware, therefore, that Parliament has recognised the disadvantaged status of islands and has confirmed that they represent a natural and cultural heritage for us all as Europeans. The European Union must be able to sustain and promote these areas, providing the resources they need for harmonious development while complying with the principle of territorial cohesion, allowing a more flexible implementation of policies on State aid and ensuring effective protection of special environmental features.</p>
      <p sl="it">Special attention should also be paid to islands that are a long way from large population centres, which have great difficulties in accessing services, even basic ones, by developing an EU maritime policy that is able to establish stable economic and commercial relations with bordering countries.</p>
      <p sl="it">I am very much in agreement with Mr Musotto on the need to improve transport connections and infrastructure – I refer to ports and airports – as well as the need to offset the greater costs, particularly energy costs, that result from their geographical locations. I find the rapporteur’s proposal to set up a European coastguard body to monitor the external borders of the European Union an interesting one, since one of the problems from which our islands suffer most of all is illegal immigration via the sea.</p>
      <p sl="it">In conclusion, I would like to say that I endorse Mr Musotto’s excellent proposal to designate 2010 as the European Year of Islands.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-024" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro Guerreiro" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pt">In order to give real practical shape to the economic and social cohesion that has been announced, it is necessary not only to promote genuine convergence among the economically less developed Member States – the cohesion countries – but also to help reduce regional disparities, so encouraging the harmonious development of the territory of each Member State.</p>
      <p sl="pt">With this in view, it is now crucial – partly by increasing the financial resources allocated to cohesion policy – to support the disadvantaged regions and those with structural problems, so helping eliminate those obstacles to regional development that exist due to the permanent natural and geographical disadvantages that exist in, for example, the island regions.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Despite recognising the structural disadvantages from which islands suffer, the strategy adopted has been inconsistent, and that is why we approve of certain proposals emphasised in this report, such as an increase in the Community cofinancing rate on the basis of existing eligibility criteria, or flexibility in authorising State aids to the regions concerned, so as to alleviate the costs of fuel, transport and energy in a way that discriminates positively in favour of these regions.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Recognition of the obstacles, which have already been more than adequately highlighted, is not the main issue here. Nor is the disadvantaged regions’ competition over priorities. Rather, it is the inadequacy of the financial resources allocated to cohesion policy, as shown in the current financial framework 2007-2013, within which the Structural Funds were reduced from 0.41% to 0.37% of GNI and priority was given to the liberalising and privatising objectives of the Lisbon Strategy, which undermine the specific competitive advantages of these regions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-025" speaker_id="4340" name="Margie Sudre" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="fr">Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, on the basis of Article 158 of the Treaty and of the Declaration on island regions annexed to it, the European Union takes into account the handicaps and constraints suffered by these regions in adopting specific measures to encourage the integration of European islands within the internal market. However, Mr Musotto, whom I thank for supporting my amendments in the Committee on Regional Development, has good grounds today for questioning the European Commission about the actual implementation of these provisions.</p>
      <p sl="fr">First, I should like to remind you that the concepts of ultraperipherality and of insularity are completely separate, whatever the ties of proximity or of solidarity that unite them, since the main characteristics of the outermost regions are their great distance from the European continent and their belonging to a geographical area that is composed, for the most part, of ACP countries.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Insularity constitutes both a geographical and cultural advantage that represents a potential to be developed within an appropriate development strategy and a permanent handicap that causes extra difficulty for the competitiveness of these regions.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The principle of territorial cohesion, which was strengthened in the Structural Funds Regulations for 2007-2013, must aim at the polycentric integration of European Union territory so as to give all regions and their people equal opportunities. In addition to the measures that you have mentioned, Commissioner, I would ask the Commission to further integrate the possibility afforded by the Treaty in terms of adjusting Community policies that could have negative repercussions for the economic and social development of these regions, in order to solve in practice the problems that specifically affect every island region or group of regions.</p>
      <p sl="fr">In conclusion, I think we should congratulate ourselves for holding this debate at a reasonable time and not at 11 p.m., as is too often the case, Mr President.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-026" speaker_id="1983" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">I am delighted, too, because I have always thought that this matter is important and deserves to be tackled by the European Union, including in the Treaties. In the past, I have attached great importance to it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-027" speaker_id="28377" name="Lidia Joanna Geringer de Oedenberg" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, each enlargement of the EU involves a systematic increase of the role of islands in all Community policies, from territorial cohesion through to tourism and culture. Unfortunately, the Union’s policy so far has not taken into account these specific constraints of islands, and the problems they face when trying to compete with mainland regions.</p>
      <p sl="pl">There is therefore an urgent need to establish statistical indicators to help identify the specificities of all areas with difficult geographical conditions. It is also necessary to take account of the need of islands to enjoy access to the single market on equal terms with mainland regions, with priority given to the improving transport links with islands. Each Commission should examine the possibility of granting aid also to island regions where fuel and energy costs clearly adversely affect their competitiveness.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Another priority is the energy security of islands and the development and implementation of relevant projects using renewable energy sources and new technologies. In addition, the Commission should examine the impact of climate change on island regions.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Recognising the efforts made by the FRONTEX Agency it is nonetheless appropriate to highlight the need to monitor the impact of illegal immigration on island communities on an ongoing basis. Member States must not overlook the need to provide effective measures to preserve the unique characteristics of island regions in terms of protection of the environment and cultural heritage and promotion of the sustainable development of tourism, which also affects the growth of other important sectors such as trade, fishery, and agriculture.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Finally, I would like to congratulate the rapporteur on a very well—prepared document.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-028" speaker_id="28979" name="Giusto Catania" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I believe that it is useful to discuss a specific economic instrument to support islands, their special features and characteristics, and I believe that it is useful for cohesion policy to pay special attention to the outermost regions.</p>
      <p sl="it">I believe that we must act to bring about a real improvement in the transport system and infrastructure, external and internal connections and also connections within the islands, for instance between the coasts and the interior, but that we should avoid wasting European resources on monumental, useless projects, often designed to connect islands with the mainland via enormous bridges, which would certainly mar the very idea of island status.</p>
      <p sl="it">While I welcome the drawing up of Mr Musotto’s report, I think that it places undue emphasis on describing a relationship between islands and illegal immigration. There is no relationship. The vast majority of migrants to the Canaries arrive by plane, not by sea, just as the vast majority of irregular immigrants to Italy do not disembark at Lampedusa but also arrive by plane.</p>
      <p sl="it">In my opinion, therefore, this argument is misplaced, and for that reason I believe that this aspect is probably not integral to Mr Musotto’s report. We must also question whether the mobilisation of rapid intervention brigades on the borders may perhaps be more useful in preventing the deaths of emigrants in the Mediterranean rather than in stopping them from arriving.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-029" speaker_id="1842" name="Rolf Berend" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I would like to take just one important area from my colleague Francesco Musotto’s very good report, an area whose importance not only for the islands concerned but for the EU as a whole should not be underestimated, namely the problem of illegal immigration.</p>
      <p sl="de">This problem of illegal immigration must in my opinion be tackled more effectively, having as it does a highly disproportionate effect on the EU’s islands in the Mediterranean. Even though progress has already been made with the measures the EU has taken – with the development of an integrated border management system and the establishment of a community code on the rules governing the movement of persons across any kind of borders, for example – the immigration figures nevertheless show that those measures are still not enough.</p>
      <p sl="de">Even though the competence for measures clearly lies with the Member States and will have to remain with them in future, the islands cannot be made to carry the excessive burden alone simply because of their geographical position, because what is at first sight a Spanish, Italian or Greek problem subsequently becomes a problem for the whole of Europe and therefore also calls for a response at Community level. Solidarity in action is what is required here and must be made reality.</p>
      <p sl="de">In this connection, the creation of a European coastguard to monitor the EU’s external borders would certainly be no panacea for this island problem, but this proposal of Mr Musotto’s does deserve to be examined to see whether it could be one of many measures to combat illegal immigration and protect the islands and the EU as a whole.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-030" speaker_id="4447" name="Paulo Casaca" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pt">Mr President, Mr Musotto, as the elected Member for the Autonomous Region of the Azores – which, as our fellow Member, Mrs Sudre, capably pointed out, is an outermost region whose status is not to be confused with that of the island regions – I should like warmly to congratulate the rapporteur, Mr Musotto, as well as the whole of the Committee on Regional Policy, Transport and Tourism, on the excellent work they have done. I should like most especially to draw attention to the proposal concerning a European coastguard body – a proposal crucial to defending the marine environment, monitoring fishing, supporting maritime trade and, in particular, monitoring compliance with international labour and safety standards and, of course, dealing with the problems surrounding immigration. Opposition to, or approval of, immigration is not at issue in this case. The fact is, there are people who take to the ocean in unseaworthy vessels, and they need support while they are on the high seas. In this context, I should like to point out that – contrary to what is stated by some of my fellow Members – these plans for a European coastguard body do not conceal an agenda overly preoccupied with security. What we do have is a vision of European maritime policy vital to all island regions and, most especially, to the outermost regions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-031" speaker_id="4452" name="Sérgio Marques" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pt">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I should firstly like to thank Mr Musotto for the high quality of his report which we are now examining on the problems associated with the island regions.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The fact is that, as the report amply demonstrates, island status is an insuperable and permanent reality that seriously affects these regions’ ability to compete. It therefore makes eminent sense for specific EU resources to be demanded within the context of the various common policies, given the fact that island regions are at a competitive disadvantage in relation to continental regions.</p>
      <p sl="pt">This need was recognised by the treaties but, unfortunately, never gave rise to consistent overall arrangements. What is more, the need for a European response designed to mitigate the competitive disadvantage from which the island regions suffer is all the greater inasmuch as increased European competitiveness in an international context is demanded nowadays.</p>
      <p sl="pt">It is therefore important for the European Union to be innovative in responding to the problems specific to the island regions and affecting their competitiveness. What is needed is a response by the European Union that helps island regions derive more benefit from dynamic, highly competitive developments such as Europe’s large internal market, Economic and Monetary Union and the Lisbon Strategy.</p>
      <p sl="pt">I should therefore like to support, in particular, the report’s recommendation that an administrative unit, charged with defining and promoting a European strategy for the island regions, be set up within the Directorate-General for Regional Policy on the model of what already exists for the outermost regions. Only in that way will due account be taken of the very specific circumstances of the island regions in the context of policies relating, for example, to transport, energy, the environment, tourism, taxation and State aids.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-033" speaker_id="28382" name="Andrzej Jan Szejna" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, I first want to thank the rapporteur and congratulate him on his thorough presentation of the natural and economic constraints of island regions with regard to regional policy. The specific characteristics of these regions are generally recognised by the majority of Member States.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Despite the efforts made through regional policy, however, the relative position of island regions in rankings based on regional GDP has remained practically unchanged over the past 20 years. I am glad the Commission has recognised that per capita GDP and unemployment rate are considered insufficient indicators with which to assess the socio-economic situation of regions beset with natural handicaps.</p>
      <p sl="pl">In these areas the ability to react positively to economic change is limited and island economies tend to be hardest hit by economic crises. The economies of island regions are often dependent on a limited number of economic sectors. The islands are heavily dependent on the public sector too.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Another important issue addressed by other speakers is illegal immigration. I agree with the rapporteur that the Commission should undertake a special needs assessment study of island regions, propose solutions, and that this issue should be duly addressed in the Fourth Cohesion Report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-034" speaker_id="4552" name="Den Dover" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I come from the United Kingdom and of course we have several large islands there. But we also have the western islands of Scotland and these were briefly mentioned by my colleagues from the Scottish part of the United Kingdom.</p>
      <p sl="en">You will know, Mr President, when you were President of the Malta delegation, as does Mr Busuttil, that Malta is suffering a lot of illegal immigration at the moment. This is a matter that needs urgent attention, as Mr Berend pointed out. I go each year to the Canary Islands. They too have suffered enormous immigration. Illegal immigration from Africa has already been mentioned this morning.</p>
      <p sl="en">But I want to emphasise in my speech today two paragraphs. One has the full support of the British Conservatives, that is paragraph 26, which talks about the need to really home in on this very important matter of illegal immigration. But there is another, paragraph 25, which Mr Berend mentioned, where I dispute and disagree with some of the findings or recommendations put forward by the rapporteur in what is otherwise a very excellent report.</p>
      <p sl="en">First of all, the report mentions rapid border intervention teams with the purpose of providing swift operational technical assistance to any Member State requesting it. I agree that is very important, but when it goes on to say that it urges the Commission to examine the need for the creation of a European coastguard body to assist in parallel these regions and the Member States in monitoring the EU’s external borders, I think that is far too wide a remit. If the isolated islands want a concentrated coastguard specialist brigade helping them, fine, but not for the United Kingdom, not for the bigger islands. We do not want too large an agency.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-035" speaker_id="28318" name="Emanuel Jardim Fernandes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pt">Mr President, Commissioner, I want to begin by congratulating the rapporteur on his excellent report. Coming from an island region that is also an outermost region and, for that reason, recognised and dealt with specifically in the Treaty on European Union, I can state that, by means of this initiative, Parliament is offering not only a useful perspective on the permanent structural difficulties peculiar to all the island regions and affecting the lives of their citizens but also a helpful view of what the islands, and by extension the EU too, have by way of potential.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Without its islands and, in particular, its outermost regions, which rightly benefit from special treatment, the EU would have a lower profile in the world. Nor would it have its current maritime area, associated of course with the advantages of the new European maritime policy, currently subject to public consultation. Cohesion – which is one of the basic objectives of the European Union – will only be achieved if the regions concerned are able to count on across-the-board support in helping reduce and eliminate the obstacles to their development.</p>
      <p sl="pt">It is therefore necessary to help bring about an adjustment to EU policies, particularly when it comes to transport, energy, public service contracts and State aids, and this with a view to guaranteeing, for example, full employment, economic growth, integration into the internal market, the European model and the objectives of the renewed Lisbon Strategy. Hence, I would ask the Commissioner and also the Commission to consider how best to transpose the policies to be adopted in future in the areas of development and regional policy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-036" speaker_id="28399" name="Antonio López-Istúriz White" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, I must express my satisfaction with this initiative report by Mr Musotto, since it represents a step forward in terms of viewing the islands, within the framework of the European Union’s regional policy, as disadvantaged as a result of the geographical, natural, structural and permanent limitations that slow down their socio-economic development.</p>
      <p sl="es">I share the rapporteur’s view that the Euro-regions play an important role, both in local projects for exchange of good practices, and also in the field of cross-border cooperation.</p>
      <p sl="es">For this purpose, the Balearic Islands form part of the Pyrenees-Mediterranean Euro-region. Furthermore, I applaud the rapporteur’s special mention of the issue of illegal immigration. I would like to take this opportunity to call upon him, when drawing up his compromise proposals, to take account of the amendments that Mr Fernando Fernández and myself presented to the paragraph in question of the report that we are discussing today.</p>
      <p sl="es">We are insisting on those amendments and I must point once again to the islands’ great vulnerability in the face of illegal immigration, in view of their particular geographical situation. It is therefore necessary to integrate emigration and development issues within the framework of the Union's aid policies, and also in its programming, both through the funds making up the new framework programme on solidarity and management of migratory flows and through the regional policy instruments, in particular the European Social Fund and the European Regional Development Fund.</p>
      <p sl="es">Annex 30 to the Treaty of Amsterdam recognised the special characteristics of the islands, but unfortunately this recognition in the Treaty has not been implemented by means of effective actions and specific measures necessary to alleviate and correct the inevitable extra costs resulting from the characteristics of islands.</p>
      <p sl="es">I come from the Balearic Islands, the rapporteur is from Sicily, and many of our Members come from islands, and we are therefore well aware of our regions' struggle to overcome the difficulties resulting from their island characteristics.</p>
      <p sl="es">We therefore call upon the Commission, the Member States and the Council, in addition to specific measures to alleviate these disadvantages, to provide help and offer understanding in relation to this special situation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-037" speaker_id="28459" name="Giuseppe Castiglione" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, firstly I would like to thank Mr Musotto for his excellent work in having highlighted the problems of island regions. I have experienced these problems myself and know how complex they are.</p>
      <p sl="it">The economic and social cohesion policy is essential in reducing the divide between differing levels of development in different regions, and on this point I would argue that special attention should be paid to the situation of islands, and I would like to thank the Commissioner for having mentioned this point.</p>
      <p sl="it">Better development of our islands means strengthening infrastructure, improving connections, integrated transport and tackling problems and weak points in water and energy supply. We need to make our island industries, such as agriculture, fisheries, craft and tourism, more competitive and more attractive. It is necessary to focus on creating conditions to promote full employment, attracting private investment and, at the same time, securing a sustainable standard of living and a significantly higher level of development, including through the promotion and development of alternative energies and new technologies.</p>
      <p sl="it">Finally, we must not underestimate the ever-increasing impact of illegal immigration on island communities, particularly in the Mediterranean. This is a disproportionate burden that the islands cannot and should not bear by themselves. It should be our priority to find a general, responsible solution, which includes ways of tackling the emergencies connected with mass arrivals of immigrants – who unfortunately do not arrive only by plane – across marine borders, while respecting fundamental rights.</p>
      <p sl="it">As a matter of urgency, therefore, we need to reduce the development lag of the islands through a policy of real solidarity, which will encourage island peoples to support the new European Union. I would like to congratulate Mr Musotto once again on his excellent work and on having placed the focus on the many issues that are important for our islands.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-038" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neelie Kroes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, it has been a most interesting debate.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me start by congratulating the rapporteur, Mr Musotto, on his report – which I did not do in my opening remarks –and for bringing this issue before us today in the first ever report dedicated to islands. He has made history!</p>
      <p sl="en">Much has been said this morning about state aids, and I should like to respond to that first. Again, operating aid – aid aimed at reducing a firms current expenses – is normally prohibited. It is prohibited in the Treaty and it is prohibited by the regional aid guidelines, because of its highly distortive effect. That being said, it can be granted exceptionally in the poorest regions that are lagging behind in terms of regional development.</p>
      <p sl="en">The regions that can benefit from operating aid are, as you are aware, the 87(3)(a) regions, which are the outermost and sparsely populated regions, provided that a number of conditions are fulfilled. In the poorest regions and, again, the 87(3)(a) regions, operating aid can be authorised only on a case-by-case basis, provided it is limited in time, degressive, proportionate, and designed to tackle specific structural handicaps.</p>
      <p sl="en">In reply to Mrs Sudre, as you are aware, the Commission accords a particular status to the outermost regions, given their remoteness and specific constraints on integrating into the internal market.</p>
      <p sl="en">For islands other than outermost regions, a generalised approach based on the characteristics of these regions seems rather difficult. Enormous differences exist between island regions in Europe, and you are an example of that. They are characterised by a large diversity, and in terms of regional development and their GDP per capita, a significant number of large islands are rather wealthy, as some of you rightly pointed out. Granting operating aid to an island that has a GDP per capita among the highest in the EU would completely distort competition in the relevant markets without any justification in terms of regional development. Thus, the Commission cannot accord the status of assisted area to all European islands, given their extreme diversity.</p>
      <p sl="en">In response to Mr Arnaoutakis, I note that subsidising fuel and energy costs constitutes operating aid. Such aid can only be authorised if the general conditions – which I have just touched upon – are fulfilled. It must not prop up structurally loss-making activities, particularly those that are very damaging, for example, to our environmental or climate change objectives. Furthermore, regional operating aid is certainly not the best instrument to tackle the local problems of islands.</p>
      <p sl="en">As I mentioned in my opening remarks, the islands’ main problems can be tackled more effectively with horizontal instruments. For example, local services that are not economically viable can be supported through services of general economic interest. Work and investment for all kinds of infrastructure can be financed. They do not have an aid element and, in the case of very small islands in particular, the de minimis aid and the EUR 200 000 threshold can be sufficient, as I mentioned.</p>
      <p sl="en">As regards Mrs Attwooll’s comment about the market investor principle, I believe that we can apply a more refined economic approach to assess situations of market failure in islands and proposed investments. However, as I have mentioned already, making the rules more predictable and more transparent and reducing the administrative burden of state aid notification are objectives of the state aid reform. I understand the specific concerns of smaller businesses, who have to try to pick their way through the state aid maze, and we agree upon this.</p>
      <p sl="en">That is why I have followed up on the suggestion made by some of you that the Commission should provide user-friendly guidance explaining our rules clearly and simply. My services have now almost completed a full update of a vade mecum offering a concise overview of the basic EU rules on state aid. The vade mecum does not aim to provide an exhaustive description of the rules. Instead, it focuses on the issues that are most relevant for people involved in regional development. I hope to have this vade mecum on line on the DG Competition Europe website very shortly, in a couple of weeks time, and I would be happy to provide copies to interested Members.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would now like to turn to four wider issues raised by some Members. Mr Smith mentioned the need for statistics. The Commission is working well with Eurostat on a regular basis. This May we will publish the Fourth Cohesion Report, which will include more statistics. Mr Smith also mentioned access to the transmission network for renewable energy. It is indeed vital and that is why the Commission takes the view that full structural unbundling of energy markets is the best solution to the problems of concentration and foreclosure of new entrants we have experienced in these markets.</p>
      <p sl="en">Several Members suggested the need for a specific unit on islands in DG Regional Policy. I will certainly take good note of this, but, as you are aware, it is my colleague, Mrs Hübner, who is taking the decisions here and not me. I am sure she will examine your idea carefully.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, we will look carefully at your proposal for designating 2010 as the Year of Islands, but I assure you that the Commission will continue to pursue the best interests of islands in 2007, 2008 and 2009, so do not think that we are neglecting this important issue. On the contrary.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-039" speaker_id="4470" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place at 12 noon.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 142)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-040" speaker_id="23938" name="John Attard-Montalto" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">One of the contexts where Malta is concerned relates to illegal immigration: ‘islands are in the front line of defence against this problem; all are suffering under the weight of illegal immigration’. In fact, the Commission’s decision to set up four funds is giving visibility to the concept of ‘solidarity in action’.</p>
      <p sl="en">In the case of Gozo, Malta’s sister island, we have a scenario of double insularity. The Commission has highlighted the special situation of islands in the guidelines on (i) National regional aid for 2007-2013 and on (ii) state aid and risk capital for small and medium-sized undertakings. But that does not address the issue where fuel and energy costs adversely affect the competitiveness of the communities living in such islands.</p>
      <p sl="en">The economic activities prevalent in islands, notably tourism, agriculture, fisheries and crafts, need special attention. Tourism represents one of the primary sources of wealth creation in islands with spin offs on other sectors – fisheries, agriculture, crafts. But what importance do we give tourism in the European Parliament? Perhaps the prevalent thought is that it is a natural issue, as one very senior Commissioner put it. On the contrary, it is about time that the European Parliament set up a separate committee on tourism, as at present it is part of the Transport Committee and hardly appears on any agenda.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-041" speaker_id="28123" name="Louis Grech" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">The report has quite a number of recommendations that go a long way to addressing a host of disadvantages which are very specific to small islands. We expect the Commission to take on board and implement the recommendation outlined in Mr Musotto’s report. Islands – whether in the outermost regions or not – suffer from natural geographical limitations that severely affect the inhabitants’ lives on a daily basis, both economically and socially.</p>
      <p sl="en">Small islands like the island of Gozo in Malta are the first to feel the effects of high transport costs, lack of investment, problems of communication, high rates of unemployment, social separation, and a more restrictive choice in the opportunities available. In theory it is well recognised and accepted in the EU that islands, especially small ones, have to be assisted to overcome these natural disadvantages. It is time to translate the well meaning objectives into concrete action.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Local authorities and development cooperation (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-043" speaker_id="4470" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report (A6-0039/2007) by Pierre Schapira, on behalf of the Committee on Development, on local authorities and development cooperation (2006/2235(INI)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-044" speaker_id="28172" name="Pierre Schapira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, I took the initiative for this report because I am convinced that, at a time when European aid is being reformed, it is essential to give local authorities a central political role in development cooperation.</p>
      <p sl="fr">This is an important year: in 2007, 50% of the world’s population live in towns, and that figure is obviously going to increase very quickly. Local authorities are experts in all fields of local development, and the United Nations has already recognised their central role in the realisation of the Millennium Development Goals. In Europe, however, our consultation stops at civil society organisations. I think that that is unsatisfactory. While the involvement of civil society is necessary, especially that of NGOs who work most closely with local communities on the ground, local authorities have a specific added value.</p>
      <p sl="fr">First of all, they are in most cases legitimately elected over the whole territory. This democratic legitimacy is an advantage in enabling us to improve local democracy and good governance on the ground. Secondly, they have expertise in the management of public services, such as water, health care, education, town planning, waste management, the environment, etc. Finally, they have a territorial approach. They know the local development problems specific to each region and each community.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Their active involvement in European development policy would allow aid to be better distributed over the whole of the territory and better targeted according to the specific needs of each area, whether it be rural, urban, maritime, mountain, desert or any other kind of area.</p>
      <p sl="fr">In view of these observations, my report sets two major challenges for the future of European cooperation. I have not worked out my strategy on my own. For more than four months I consulted the largest international and European local authority organisations in order to obtain their analysis. My report is, in fact, the result of these analyses.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The first challenge: we believe that local authorities must become full political partners of the European Union alongside central governments and civil society organisations. By partnership, I mean the development of a structured political dialogue between the European Commission and local authority organisations.</p>
      <p sl="fr">This dialogue must be active, as much here, in Brussels, as on the ground in developing countries. In Brussels, we want the Commission to put in place a platform for dialogue modelled on CONCORD, the European NGO Confederation for Coordination of Relief and Development. In developing countries, in accordance with the new development instrument and the revised Cotonou Agreement, it is a matter of involving local governments at each stage of the development strategy right from the stage at which strategy documents are drafted for each country.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The second challenge: this report makes several financial proposals to the European Commission. Firstly, we believe that decentralisation must be a priority for the European Union and, consequently, that it has to become a focus for European Union financial aid. In many countries decentralisation is constantly increasing. Local authorities have more and more powers, without having the financial capacity to carry out this new role.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Secondly, we propose that part of the aid budget should go directly to these local authorities. Indeed, our recent debate showed the extent to which aid can pose a problem in these countries, where there is a higher risk of corruption. Decentralising budgetary aid would make it possible, on the one hand, to distribute it more effectively over the whole territory and, on the other hand, not to concentrate it all in the same hands, thereby ensuring better management of European funds.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Lastly, we believe that the involvement of these local authorities and of non-State actors is necessary in order to ensure that European aid fulfils the real needs of disadvantaged populations. We therefore ask for an increase in the budget for the thematic programme, non-State actors and local authorities.</p>
      <p sl="fr">In conclusion, Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I should like to emphasise what is, in my opinion, the main issue in this debate. Our cooperation policy does not take sufficient account of the territorial dimension of development, and, as Kofi Annan said at the Millennium summit, while the Millennium Development Goals are global, it is at a local level that we can provide solutions. The answers are local and specific, according to the territory. If we do not take that into consideration, our aid is liable to remain concentrated in the hands of a central government and not to be distributed in the country as a whole.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The former President of Benin, Mr Soglo, recently said to me that, at the time of his Presidency, he thought that aid was distributed fairly in the country, but that, now that he is mayor elect of Cotonou, he realised that this was not the case.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I am pleased that the new development instrument recognises the need to involve local governments in the political dialogue. It remains now for this commitment to be reflected on the ground and for local governments to be given the means to fulfil their new responsibilities.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-045" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neelie Kroes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members, I would like to thank the rapporteur, Mr Schapira, for this report that brought due attention to the role of local authorities in development cooperation.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission shares most of the rapporteur’s observations and agrees on the high importance of local authorities, both for better governance and for improving the wellbeing of populations, for example through better service delivery in the basic social sectors. The Commission pays great attention to this aspect, on the one hand by supporting decentralisation processes and local governance through geographic and thematic instruments and, on the other, by involving local authorities in the programming process itself.</p>
      <p sl="en">While decentralisation is considered one of the important areas of cooperation under geographic programmes, the Commission does not impose focal sectors on the partner countries. Instead, focal sectors in each country are decided following the principle of ownership and in close consultation with all stakeholders. The Commission’s delegations have been provided with guidelines on how to facilitate the inclusion of local authorities’ representatives in the whole consultative process. In cases when the government did not select specific support to local authorities as an area of cooperation, the latter were often supported through sector programmes – in health and education – or through other types of interventions, in particular defining decentralisation policy, elaborating a legal framework and/or supporting planning and financial management capacities at local level.</p>
      <p sl="en">Another instrument at our disposal is the thematic programme, non-state actors and local authorities in development. It is designed to be subsidiary and complementary to intervention programmes in the country strategy papers. For the period 2007-2010 an amount of EUR 903 million has been earmarked for this programme, of which up to 15% can be allocated to local authorities. As you know, Mr President, it is an actor-oriented programme aimed at capacity-building through support to own initiatives from local authorities and non-state actors originating from the EU and partner countries. Its main objectives concern the facilitation of local authorities’ and non-state actors’ participation in poverty reduction and sustainable development strategies as well as strengthening their networking activities.</p>
      <p sl="en">Regarding the involvement of local authorities in creating development policies, efforts are being made both at global and country level. At global level, the Commission has established continuous dialogue with the existing European and international platforms such as the United Cities and Local Governments, the Council of European Municipalities and Regions and the Committee of the Regions. At country level, the participation of local authorities in the programming process was introduced under the ninth European Development Fund. It then became an essential principle of the ongoing tenth EDF programming process and, as I have already mentioned, the Commission’s delegations are actively promoting this process.</p>
      <p sl="en">Following the adoption of the final country strategy papers, the Commission will draft a report to assess the progress made in promoting participatory approaches under the tenth EDF. The analysis will examine a number of issues relating to the consultation process, including questions such as the one mentioned by the rapporteur, whether the consultations held with stakeholders were based on draft CSPs. We are all convinced that close cooperation with the local authorities can bring important benefits to our efforts to combat poverty in the world and I am confident that this process can be further improved through our joint efforts. The report we are discussing now is an important contribution to these efforts.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-046" speaker_id="28574" name="Manolis Mavrommatis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I should like to start by congratulating the rapporteur, Mr Schapira, on his exceptional work and to thank him for his constructive cooperation.</p>
      <p sl="el">Local authorities have specialised in all aspects of town planning in the developing world for many decades. Their budgets are getting bigger and bigger and they are constantly expanding their activities. They are therefore an immense solidarity network which extends to all five continents. However, the real value of local authorities lies in the fact that they provide aid which best responds to the expectations of the populace, in that they are closer to the citizens than central government or international donors. Another contribution by local authorities would therefore be to achieve objective 2 on education.</p>
      <p sl="el">With effective cooperation, local authorities can help to build and maintain enough schools with trained teaching staff and free transport and meals for pupils, so that every child is able to study at school. In addition, they could also help in the fight against child labour, given that it is easier and more effective in principle to control industry and agriculture, where exploitation of children is most frequent, at local level, although it is equally serious at global level and this is something we need to combat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-047" speaker_id="34229" name="Атанас Папаризов" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">от името на групата PSE . – Докладът на г-н Schapira, който заслужава нашите адмирации за обективността и задълбочеността, засяга изключително важен аспект на превръщането на политиката за развитие на Европейския съюз във фактор на растежа и социалния прогрес в развиващите се страни. С основание може да се очаква, че Европейският съюз като най-голям глобален донор, ще определя и стандартите за оказване на международна помощ, в това число и чрез пряко финансиране на бюджета на развиващите се страни.</p>
      <p sl="en">Двустранните споразумения за партньорство с подпомаганите страни, където подкрепата е вплетена в система от социално-икономически и политически мерки, съдейства за устойчивото демократично развитие на тези страни и води до намаляване на бедността и спазване на човешките права и правата на малцинствата. Предимствата на тази помощ са свързани с прилагането на принципа на субсидиарността, т.е. решенията се вземат колкото се може по-близко до бенефициентите.</p>
      <p sl="en">Но разбира се, бюджетната помощ крие и някои рискове, които са свързани с корупцията и липсата на капацитет за финансово усвояване на средствата. Тези рискове в голяма степен се преодоляват, когато се разчита на по-голяма връзка с местните власти, когато се отчита децентрализацията в управлението на съответната развиваща се страна.</p>
      <p sl="en">България съвсем отскоро е член на Европейския съюз и не би могла да дава съвети как да се организира европейската помощ за развитие, но направеното в нашата страна може да се има предвид при търсенето на аналогии при използване най-ефективно на средствата на Общността. По мое мнение, особено би бил полезен нашият опит при създаването на регионални асоциации на общините, които подпомагат регионалните власти при разработването и прилагането на регионални програми за развитие. Това особено може да се използва при прилагането на общата бюджетна подкрепа.</p>
      <p sl="en">Що се отнася до секторната бюджетна подкрепа, ние също имаме определен опит, предимно при използването на средствата по програма САПАРД, където се разчита на подкрепата на браншови асоциации и неправителствени организации. Важно е при секторната подкрепа да се отчитат и мненията на потребителите и техните обединения.</p>
      <p sl="en">Още веднъж, докладът заслужава нашата адмирация и предполагам, че Комисията, на основа на препоръките в т. 18, ще направи необходимото, за да подкрепи асоциации на местните власти при използването на бюджетна помощ.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-048" speaker_id="28205" name="Jean Marie Beaupuy" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, first of all I should like to thank Mr Schapira for drawing up this report, which should prepare the ground for a very positive advance in our development policies. To put it another way, with this text we shall be able, I am convinced, to actually become more effective. After all, what is the point of generous – often general – objectives and what is the point of having significant financial resources if one does not achieve effective and efficient results?</p>
      <p sl="fr">Local authorities – and this is very well explained in Mr Schapira’s report – are the operational link which, on the ground, can provide real solutions to the problems of the citizens of these countries: problems with drinking water, health, education, public transport and social problems. Among these unfortunately numerous problems, it is above all health problems that should receive our closest attention. On the ground, it is local authorities that are best placed to find solutions. Do they have the means to provide the right solutions to these various problems? Rarely, because they do not have the financial resources, or the experience, or the means for putting these solutions into effect.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Thanks to this text, we shall, I am sure, be able to provide the required financial resources and the appropriate intellectual engineering. In this respect, too, I hope that the good practice processes that we have put in place, at European level, with URBAN (Intergroup on Urban Issues and Housing), will genuinely be made available to all these local actors.</p>
      <p sl="fr">In the face of this major issue, I also believe that the growing experience that we have acquired with regard to the structural funds, and especially in cities, will be a great advantage. Furthermore, may I say, as coordinator of my group in the Committee on Regional Development, and as chairman of the Intergroup on Urban Issues and Housing, that, while 80% of the EU population lives in cities, urban demographic growth is phenomenal in all these developing countries, and only local actors will really be able to provide the right solutions that are required at local level.</p>
      <p sl="fr">These right solutions will be the result of a new form of governance: the mayors of these local authorities, in particular, will have to be both operational in terms of power – the application of their legal powers – and also operational in terms of acting as motivators for all those issues concerning waste-disposal, water, health, and so on. It is in this regard that the support that we shall be able to give them will enable them both to be operational by virtue of their legal powers and to fully assume their role as motivators.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Commissioner, along with our fellow Members and the members of the European Commission, I would like the various DGs concerned to be fully involved in making a success of this operation. Our countries expect us to act on this issue. We have the means to grant their wishes. Tangible results must be equal to their expectations.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-049" speaker_id="28374" name="Wiesław Stefan Kuc" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the UEN Group">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, the role of local authorities in solving the problems of urban and rural communities cannot be overestimated. We should therefore welcome the fact that in all documents reviewed by the rapporteur, these authorities are perceived as full stakeholders in development, their capacities are recognised, and their importance and key role in meeting various goals is highlighted. It is a pity that this positive picture has only been declarative.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Hardly any of the actors involved, including both states and organisations, have drawn on the experience of local authorities to provide genuine solutions to local problems. Their experience has not been used in connection with planning or social economy. It is well known that local authorities are spread over the whole territory and that this enables them to conduct a proximity policy and to communicate the expectations of their populations on a day-to-day basis. It is also known that they have the capacity to address local problems, and that their involvement may contribute to strengthening local democracy. Despite all this we continually rely on government administrations.</p>
      <p sl="pl">We need to draw on our experience and convictions at the earliest opportunity by supporting the activities of local authorities, and making it possible for them to play their rightful role. I believe that Mr Schapiro’s excellent report will make a substantial contribution thereto.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-050" speaker_id="4453" name="Luisa Morgantini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I fully support the Schapira report – as the entire Committee on Development does – and I do so because it recognises the fundamental role of local authorities in development policies that are effective, efficient, inclusive and actually work to combat poverty and to fight for the right of all men and women to human development – examples of this are already legion.</p>
      <p sl="it">In recent years the European Union has recognised in its strategies the vital contribution that local authorities and civil authorities throughout the world have been able to make, with dedication and creativity, to help democracy become what it ought to be: a practice in which the citizens are protagonists both within their regions and outside them.</p>
      <p sl="it">Now we need to make those involved in decentralised cooperation, which in the main means the local authorities, not only managers of funds and projects, which are, in any case, going to increase in financial terms, but also operators capable of exerting a political influence on the definition and application of the EU’s development policy and development cooperation. We should do this by providing them, as well as the NGOs and other non-state bodies, with permanent representation on and consultation with the EU’s development policy bodies, with a view to structured dialogue in Europe and its partner countries. This report shows Parliament acting fully in line with its functions and the EU’s basic values.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-051" speaker_id="28427" name="Alessandro Battilocchio" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I have been a trade union representative for over six years now for a town north of Rome and I am well aware of how every particular locality has specific problems that can rarely be dealt with successfully by programmes at the national or regional level. Promoting twinning with non-EU countries might be an effective way, for example, to spread good practice at the local level too.</p>
      <p sl="it">As rapporteur for the Committee on Development on the financing instrument for human rights I strongly highlighted the added value that local communities represent for the development of non-EU countries. Only those directly involved, the citizens most in contact with the needs and requirements of each individual community, can be fully aware of their own problems and above all, if necessary, together with European and international experts, take action with specific measures.</p>
      <p sl="it">Particularly in countries in the hands of corrupt or unstable governments, an approach that places the local authorities at the centre of development actions funded by the international community would, in my view, make it possible to implement swifter and more concrete measures, with less waste of economic resources and skills.</p>
      <p sl="it">It is important for the Commission, as in fact happens with the new instrument for development and, in general, the international donors, to recognise civil society and the local authorities as political partners in the challenges to combat poverty and achieve economic and social development. This theoretical recognition, however, must be matched by deeds, through direct funding lines of increasing amounts.</p>
      <p sl="it">In recent days I have backed a campaign for co-responsibility in the granting of loans to governments, so that the flow of funding, which is allocated for development purposes to the beneficiary governments, is managed with the full approval of the representatives elected by the citizens involved. If thirty years of development cooperation have not yet produced the hoped-for results, perhaps it is necessary at this point to recognise the errors made and change course while there is still time.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-052" speaker_id="4470" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">I would like to wish you every success in your trade union activities.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-053" speaker_id="28112" name="Gay Mitchell" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to commend Mr Schapira for his work on this report as well as Mr Mavrommatis for his work as shadow rapporteur. I believe this is an important part of the work of the Committee on Development.</p>
      <p sl="en">I had the privilege to be rapporteur on the Development Cooperation Instrument: quite a controversial instrument which took us two years to agree on. As part of that, we insisted that the role of local authorities be acknowledged – and indeed it was acknowledged – and through the new implementation procedure which we have now agreed through the Development Committee’s four working parties, we must now ensure that local authorities are fully involved in the consultation process and in the implementation of development aid, and that the wishes of Parliament are not simply taken as wishes but that the DCI is taken as the legislative will of this House.</p>
      <p sl="en">Secondly, we should not confine the involvement of local authorities to local authorities in developing countries. As a former Lord Mayor of Dublin, let me give you my own experience as chairman of the biggest local authority in Ireland. Within Dublin City Council, for example, we have a huge resource: engineers who know how to provide clean water, how to deal with sewage, how to construct roads and piers and all sorts of things, and I believe that that resource could be put to use in the developing world, not just from Dublin but from all the counties in Ireland and from all the counties and local authorities within the European Union. We should be thinking of twinning our local authorities with the local authorities in the developing world. I know that a lot of people who work for local authorities within the European Union who have skills would love to bring those skills to bear in delivering clean water and other things in the developing world. I ask the Commission to pursue this idea, not just to involve local authorities within developing countries, but to involve our local authorities who have skills and will bring them to assist the developing world. I commend that idea to the Commission and I hope it will be borne in mind.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-054" speaker_id="28392" name="Józef Pinior" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, local government institutions are key players in the field of development, helping to stimulate and coordinate economic and social operators at local level.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The involvement of local government institutions in development policy is necessary to achieve the Millennium Development Goals, and to ensure good governance. Local authorities have been experts in all areas of development for more than 30 years. We should recall that local government budgets have been increasing steadily. Local authorities constitute a global solidarity network extending around the whole world. They are closer to the local area than central government or international donor entities, and this enables them to keep track of the local impact of national and international development strategies.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I would like to express my appreciation to the rapporteur, Mr Schapira, for his report which takes account of many aspects of the relationship between local authorities, and cooperation to promote development. The European Parliament report combines the 60-year experience of European cooperation between towns with development policy in today’s global civilisation.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I would like to highlight that in our report we call on the Commission to set up a worldwide monitoring centre for local democracy and decentralisation, in partnership with local government organisations. This makes it possible to draw up a world map of local governance, listing projects, stakeholders, and budgets available to local authorities around the world. It would facilitate coordination, coherence and synergy between the various local government partners.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-055" speaker_id="4338" name="Thierry Cornillet" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, I would like to join others in congratulating Mr Schapira on his excellent report. In this report, above all, he puts his finger on the essential role that local authorities must play in development on account of their proximity and of their capacity for dialogue with local populations, and also on account of their knowledge of the territory.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Everywhere in the world, one fact is clear: the region, whatever name it is given – province, governorate, département, to put it plainly, the lowest infra-state level – is becoming recognised as a significant entity in relation to spatial planning and development. In many countries, moreover, urban units are themselves organised into regions.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Regions, therefore, are already essential partners. It must be pointed out, for example, that EUR 35 million are given each year by French regions to Francophone regions in the world.</p>
      <p sl="fr">That is why last week in Marseilles – this is information that I wanted to make public and to pass on to you – an international organisation of regions was set up. In other words, 12 international networks grouping together regions in five continents irrespective of their characteristics – Francophone, peripheral, maritime or otherwise – are in the process of organising themselves into a network, the world regions Forum. They are waiting for the European Union, Commissioner, so that they can have access to direct international funding, so that they can play a part in setting up national integrated programmes and in the European Development Fund, and so that they have the right to those programmes that will be theirs.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-056" speaker_id="28389" name="Zbigniew Krzysztof Kuźmiuk" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, I should like to begin by saying that I support the key message presented in Mr Schapira’s report, namely that the European Union should cooperate with local authorities as it seeks to support the development of African, Caribbean and Pacific countries.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Accordingly, it is first necessary to strengthen the potential of local authorities in ACP countries, because only strong local authorities are capable of taking responsibility for providing essential public services. Secondly, it is vital for local authorities to be able to provide the most important services for human development, such as education, medical care, or culture, as well as essential daily needs, including the supply of water, waste disposal, and collective transport.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Thirdly, it is necessary for a significant proportion of EU budgetary aid to developing countries to be allocated directly to local authorities, in consultation with central governments, because this is the only way to improve the effectiveness of aid, and also to reduce the possible corruption, and bureaucracy involved.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Fourthly, it is also necessary to support the restructuring of local authorities’ financial systems to enable their budgets to generate their own financial resources for development, and to promote their financial independence.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-057" speaker_id="28325" name="Sylwester Chruszcz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">We are focusing today on local authorities and development cooperation at different levels of authority.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Undoubtedly, the local authority level is precisely the level at which issues important to citizens and local communities are dealt with on a daily basis, both in Europe and world wide. I refer to many different issues, often related to by specific circumstances. Local authority institutions are key players in the field of development, helping to motivate and coordinate economic and social operators at local level.</p>
      <p sl="pl">My country – Poland – is an example of increasingly dynamic development of local communities. I have had evidence of this having recently visited the municipalities of Choszczno, and Łobez in the West Pomerania Voivodship. It is to be hoped that both in Europe and in developing countries, the European Union, its aid programmes and legislation would stimulate the economic growth of local communities, rather than hinder it through excessive bureaucracy, and inappropriate legislation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-058" speaker_id="33964" name="Roberta Alma Anastase" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">În intervenţia mea doresc să subliniez, încă o dată, importanţa Parlamentului European în ceea ce priveşte sprijinirea comunităţilor locale şi asigurarea afirmării rolului acestora în contextul realizării Obiectivelor de Dezvoltare ale Mileniului. Parlamentul European, care îşi găseşte legitimitatea în votul direct, secret şi liber exprimat al cetăţenilor europeni, trebuie să fie forul care exprimă cel mai fidel mod aşteptările şi necesităţile acestora. Este, într-adevăr, rolul Comisiei de a gestiona problemele referitoare la dezvoltarea la nivel macro-european. Această dezvoltare, însă, nu poate fi realizată ignorându-se problematicile, experienţele şi tradiţiile existente la nivel micro, la nivel de comunitate locală. Este rolul nostru de Parlament să punem în vedere Comisiei să-şi ajusteze politicile şi programele în funcţie de cele de mai sus.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dezvoltarea Europei este alcătuită dintr-un puzzle de dezvoltări specifice fiecărei colectivităţi locale. A ignora aceste colectivităţi înseamnă a iniţia un proces de dezvoltare artificială care nu va corespunde niciodată realităţilor locale. În plus, ignorarea unor aspecte sensibile ce ţin de o anumită moştenire culturală, de un filon tradiţional specific, va conduce la respingerea de către comunităţile locale a soluţiilor de dezvoltare propuse la nivel european. Tot comunităţile locale sunt cele îndrituite să analizeze existenţa resurselor umane şi materiale pentru punerea în aplicare a Obiectivelor de Dezvoltare ale Mileniului.</p>
      <p sl="en">În concluzie, permiteţi-mi să afirm că este rolul şi obligaţia Parlamentului European de a veghea la crearea şi desăvârşirea unei construcţii europene care să utilizeze experienţa şi acquis-ul local.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-059" speaker_id="28268" name="Danutė Budreikaitė" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="lt">In the implementation of the Millennium Development Goals, there are usually two parties participating: the assistance-giving party and the assistance-receiving party. The EU applies certain requirements when giving assistance, foremost among them being good management.</p>
      <p sl="lt">The European Commission has always maintained a cautious attitude toward the role of local government institutions in the field of development policy, seeking to maintain good diplomatic relations with third countries and to pay the countries the money allocated to them as soon as possible, since negotiating with local governments requires a lot of time, and in my opinion, is difficult to carry out.</p>
      <p sl="lt">The decentralised collaboration that has begun to be applied in developing countries, as defined in the Lomé Convention, provides an opportunity to specify the application of development assistance with collaboration, not only between countries, but also with the involvement of local government institutions. This gives the assistance-receiving countries a chance to use the assistance for the solution of the particular problems of the local population.</p>
      <p sl="lt">I think, however, that local governments should themselves participate more actively in the management of their country, collaborating actively and regularly with the central government. Realistically, it is hard to imagine any economic and social development of a country without bilateral links between local governments and the central government.</p>
      <p sl="lt">The Cotonou Agreement envisaged that local institutions would be invited to participate in the formulation of development policy, so demands need to be made on the central government to adhere to the Agreement, and if the rules are not obeyed, the provision of support may need to be reconsidered.</p>
      <p sl="lt">In my opinion, the European Commission should not have to solve specific local management problems of the third countries. It is not equipped to do that. Its task is to control the use that the support provided is put to.</p>
      <p sl="lt">I have my doubts about the effectiveness of establishing a centre for monitoring world democracy and decentralisation at the local level. There are too many different countries, management structures, cultures and customs. Each country must choose its own methods of collaboration between different levels of government.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-060" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neelie Kroes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members, the Commission welcomes this report and shares its analysis of the important role local authorities can play in development cooperation. Their contribution is crucial for the achievement of the Millennium Development Goals for good governance and for better ownership of development cooperation strategies.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is for these same reasons that the Commission is supporting local governance through geographic and thematic instruments and also involves local authorities in the programming process itself. The Commission is trying to further improve their level of participation and we are grateful for Parliament’s support in these efforts.</p>
      <p sl="en">You have also raised some interesting ideas, such as twinning, which I shall certainly bring to the attention of my colleague, Mr Michel, and he will study that further.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-061" speaker_id="4470" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place at 12 noon.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 142)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-062" speaker_id="28199" name="Gábor Harangozó" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">First of all, I would like to warmly welcome the content of the own-initiative report of our colleague Pierre Schapira on the importance of the role of local authorities in achieving the goals of development cooperation. Due to the wide range of objectives set within the framework of the Millennium Development Goals and given the delays in the implementation of these goals, this report is of high importance in order to foster the involvement of local authorities as essential partners in all phases of the cooperation process, with a view to achieving these goals. In line with the subsidiarity principle, local actors are the best partners in order to ensure that the development aid is appropriately geared to the real need of the local communities. Their role has been up to now far too limited despite the long political recognition of the added value they can bring to development policies. In this respect, I also warmly welcome the proposal to set up an international monitoring centre for local democracy and decentralisation to monitor the progress of the involvement of local authorities in both the implementation of projects and in the elaboration of development policies.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-063" speaker_id="28280" name="Filip Kaczmarek" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pl">I wish to thank the rapporteur, Mr Schapira, for a very important project. There is no doubt that local authorities play a very important role in development cooperation. This is true both for countries providing aid, and for those receiving it.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The reason is that local authorities are closer to people. They are better aware of the needs of local communities, and of social, economic, and infrastructure-related problems. Development aid administered by local authorities can therefore be more effective. We should take advantage of these aspects of local authorities more often and appreciate their competences. In addition, strengthening local authorities in developing countries may itself help to reduce poverty and inequality. It is therefore worth supporting and even investing in the development of local authorities.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I agree with the view that local authorities should receive the financial resources needed to enable them to play an appropriate role in the achievement of the Millennium Development Goals. Many local authorities, in particular those of new Member States, are not capable of financing such tasks from their own budgets. Also, local authorities can enlist the support of the other local stakeholders such as universities, NGOs and enterprises. This serves to stimulate citizens' participation in public life in general, and in particular, their involvement in development cooperation. Thank you very much.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. Voting time">
    <intervention id="4-066" speaker_id="1253" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the vote.</p>
      <a text="(For the results and other details on the vote: see Minutes)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem6" title="5.1. Nominations to interparliamentary delegations (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem7" title="5.2. Community action on the provision of cross-border health care (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem8" title="5.3. Illegal bird hunting in Malta (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-071" speaker_id="28123" name="Louis Grech" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, for purposes of clarification, I wish to add the words ‘at the time’ after the word ‘Commission’, so now Amendment 7 would read, ‘notes that prior to the accession to the European Union, the Maltese Government stated that it had negotiated a derogation on spring hunting with the Commission; regrets that the despite the fact that other political forces and segments of civil society in Malta had challenged the Maltese Government’s statements, the Commission at the time opted to remain silent on the subject, thus bringing about a potentially ambivalent situation’.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-073" speaker_id="28120" name="Simon Busuttil" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, our group wanted to request a roll-call vote on amendment 12, but unfortunately we failed to do so in time. I therefore ask the House to allow a roll-call vote on amendment 12, even though we did not request it in time. I am sure that my colleague Monica Frassoni will not object.</p>
      <a text="(Laughter)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem9" title="5.4. Euro-mediterranean relations (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-077" speaker_id="1065" name="Pasqualina Napoletano" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, I believe that Mr Tannock has withdrawn his amendment in favour of an oral amendment which – I refer to paragraph 21 of the French text – would read as follows: after the phrase ‘aucun cas refouler une personne’ , add ‘demandeur d'asile vers un état où elle risque …’ .</p>
      <p sl="it">Mr President, I would like to take the opportunity to call on my group to vote in favour of the final text because there was an error on the voting list.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-078" speaker_id="4521" name="Charles Tannock" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I have not withdrawn the amendment that I submitted, but I would be prepared to do so in exchange for a change to that oral amendment adding words along the lines of ‘for the duration within which the asylum seekers are having their cases considered by the authorities’, because otherwise they could stay in our countries indefinitely.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem10" title="5.5. Euro-Mediterranean Free Trade Area (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-082" speaker_id="36396" name="Gianluca Susta" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, I would like to request that in the text that was tabled the words ‘by extending’ be replaced with the words ‘by considering’.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem11" title="5.6. Bosnia-Herzegovina (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem12" title="5.7. Compliance with the Charter of Fundamental Rights (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-087" speaker_id="2053" name="Johannes Voggenhuber" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, shortly before the vote, my attention was drawn to a problem that is very easily solved. Paragraph 15 reads: ‘intends to this end to amend Rule 34 of its Rules of Procedure’. As we need a different majority for Rules of Procedure than for this vote, many Members find the word ‘intends’ too strong.</p>
      <p sl="de">I would therefore suggest amending paragraph 15 as follows: ‘is to this end considering an amendment to the Rules of Procedure’. I hope the PPE-DE Group will also be able to agree to amending the Rule in this way.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem13" title="5.8. Negotiation of an EU-Central America Association Agreement (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem14" title="5.9. Negotiation of an EU-Andean Community Association Agreement (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-095" speaker_id="28278" name="Luis Yañez-Barnuevo García" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, in agreement with several groups, I wish to present an oral amendment intended to replace, in the first line of paragraph 1(b), ‘the aim’, with the phrase: ‘some of the aims’, and to replace ‘is gradually to liberalise trade’ with the phrase, ‘should be the establishment in time of an advanced free trade area’.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-097" speaker_id="28278" name="Luis Yañez-Barnuevo García" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, I would like to table an oral amendment intended to introduce, in the second line of paragraph 1(s), following ‘trade liberalisation under’, replacing ‘competitive conditions’, the phrase, ‘conditions of justice and mutual benefit based on complementarity and solidarity’.</p>
      <p sl="es">It is also proposed that the same paragraph should end with ‘the parties’ economic and trade relations’.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-099" speaker_id="28278" name="Luis Yañez-Barnuevo García" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="es">This oral amendment is intended to replace ‘FTA’ in paragraph 1(u) with the expression: ‘Euro-Latin American Area of Global Interregional Partnership’.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-101" speaker_id="28278" name="Luis Yañez-Barnuevo García" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="es">This oral amendment is intended to replace ‘FTA’ in paragraph 1(v) with the expression: ‘Euro-Latin American Area of Global Interregional Partnership’.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-103" speaker_id="28278" name="Luis Yañez-Barnuevo García" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, this is the last of the oral amendments and it is intended to replace ‘FTA’ in paragraph 1(x) with the expression: ‘Euro-Latin American Area of Global Interregional Partnership’.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem15" title="5.10. Missing persons in Cyprus (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-106" speaker_id="1253" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">May I draw your attention to the fact that Mrs Resetarits and Mr Triantaphyllides have also signed this motion for a resolution? Mrs Resetarits on behalf of the Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe and Mr Triantaphyllides on behalf of the Confederal Group of the European United Left/Nordic Green Left.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-107" speaker_id="23730" name="Panayiotis Demetriou" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, allow me to inform you that we have among us today the three members of the Committee on Missing Persons for Cyprus: Mr Christophe Girod, the Chairman of the committee, representing the UN; Mrs Gülden Plümer Küçük, representing the Turkish Cypriots; and Mr Elias Georgiades, representing the Greek Cypriots. All the members of the Committee are here to obtain our support.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem16" title="5.11. Regional policy (islands and natural and economic constraints) (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem17" title="5.12. Local authorities and development cooperation (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-111" speaker_id="1253" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">That concludes the vote.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem18" title="6. Explanations of vote">
    <intervention id="4-114" speaker_id="1403" name="David Martin" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted for this resolution and welcome the Commission initiative to launch a consultation procedure on the best form of Community action with a view to providing a framework for cross-border aspects of health-care.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-116" speaker_id="28120" name="Simon Busuttil" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="mt">I would like to explain my vote on the resolution on spring hunting in Malta. I voted against the resolution because I felt that it was both unnecessary and disproportionate. There was no need for it, given that there are ongoing discussions between the European Commission and the Maltese authorities on the issue. The resolution is pointless, considering that Malta has made great strides in tackling those who defy the hunting rules. In addition, what should be kept in mind is that, during accession negotiations between Malta and the European Union, the European Commission recognised - in writing and not in words - an agreement whereby Malta could use a derogation to allow spring hunting.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-117" speaker_id="4242" name="Karin Scheele" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, unlike the previous speaker, I believe this resolution on bird hunting in Malta is a very important resolution. The European Parliament has already shown on many occasions that animal conservation and compliance with the animal conservation laws we have in the European Union are very important to us. That is why this resolution is very important, even if we have faced quite a strong headwind from the other side of this Chamber.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-118" speaker_id="24087" name="Marcin Libicki" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, I would like to say that I voted for the resolution concerning Malta because there has hardly been any progress on the part the Maltese Government. We are still witnessing the killing of huge quantities of birds in Malta. Many millions of birds are dying there, contrary to all the fundamental provisions adopted by the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I would also like to state that in the first roll-call vote, I voted for paragraph 2 of the Voggenhuber report by mistake, but I wanted to vote against, so please record this fact.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-119" speaker_id="4537" name="Robert Atkins" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">British Conservatives have voted against this resolution on purely procedural grounds. We feel that this resolution represents an abuse of procedure. Our vote should not be taken as an indication of British Conservative MEP views on the merits or otherwise of the particular case under consideration.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-120" speaker_id="1403" name="David Martin" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted for this resolution and wish to see an immediate ban on all illegal bird-hunting in Malta</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-121" speaker_id="4751" name="Bart Staes" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="nl">The tabling of this resolution to the plenary meeting of this House could have easily been avoided had Malta simply cancelled the spring hunt and, in doing so, conformed to the provisions of the Birds Directive, but it persists in ignoring the countless parliamentary initiatives and the legal steps taken by the Commission, and looks set once again to permit its hunters to shoot a huge number of protected migratory birds. Shooting them serves no higher purpose than as a hobby for the local hunters, and it has got out of hand, now threatening the diversity and preservation of the bird species in the whole of the European Union. Representatives of the hunters have no qualms about calling those opposed to the spring hunt fascists. They threaten their own government, their elected representatives and their police apparatus in an aggressive manner, and that is something that we in this Union of ours, cannot condone. The Maltese Government may feel hurt by this resolution, but it could also feel invigorated by the support of the whole of Europe when taking measures to abolish the spring hunt, and it is for this latter reason that I am completely behind this resolution.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-123" speaker_id="1413" name="Glyn Ford" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I will be supporting this report, despite the failure to include paragraph 21 in its original form: 'Points out that, under European Court Human Rights case law, the European States can in no circumstances send a person back to a state where he or she is likely to be subject to torture or cruel, degrading or inhuman treatment, including the death penalty.'</p>
      <p sl="en">I am disappointed that there was a small majority in this House in favour of excluding this important human rights principle.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-124" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro Guerreiro" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">There is a lot I might have said about this resolution. However, I am allowed only 200 words, which I shall use to condemn the resolution’s silence concerning the unacceptable boycott of the Palestinian Authority (PA) proclaimed by the Israeli Government and the United States Administration following the Palestinian elections in January 2006. The EU joined in the boycott and also suspended its financial aid, so exacerbating the already serious humanitarian situation with which the Palestinian people is confronted as a result of Israeli occupation and aggression.</p>
      <p sl="pt">It was silent on the unacceptable, wait-and-see and follow-my-leader attitude of the EU, which still continues to make the re-establishment of relations with the Palestinian authorities, including the recommencement of financial support, dependent on their meeting certain conditions such as the ‘commitment to non-violence’, when it is Israel that is occupying Palestinian territories militarily; or the ‘recognition of Israel’, when it is Israel that does not recognise the right of the Palestinian people to its sovereign and independent state; and ‘respect for previous agreements and obligations, including the Road Map’, when it is Israel that does not comply with the United Nations resolutions, the Oslo Accords and the Road Map itself and is continuing with its construction of the illegal wall and the policy of settlements.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-125" speaker_id="1403" name="David Martin" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted for this resolution. In particular, I am in favour of the Amendments in line with the European Court rulings which stated that no individuals should be sent where they are at risk of maltreatment, torture or capital punishment.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-126" speaker_id="4461" name="Luís Queiró" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">One of the major successes of the European Union is the effect of successive enlargements – an effect due partly to the fact that the prospect of accession has been one of the main factors in the democratisation and modernisation of our countries and societies.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Since unlimited enlargement of the EU is impossible and not something that I would champion, I am in favour of an arrangement that would help bring about similar results in the Mediterranean basin. I am thinking of a new European project, devised in partnership with our Mediterranean neighbours and designed to create, in the medium term, an area of free movement in the Mediterranean region and one whose rationale would be as close as possible to that of the EU model. Accession to this area would be open to surrounding countries that fulfil the basic Copenhagen criteria of being democratic, having market economies and respecting human rights. It would be an enhanced partnership in return for reforms. It would also have the incidental and subsidiary virtue of being a solution that, being perhaps of interest to Morocco, Israel or Tunisia, might also be of possible interest to Turkey if that country were to come to the conclusion that the accession process had reached a dead end.</p>
      <p sl="pt">To have prosperous and democratic neighbours, tied in by the potential benefits and with populations that would not need to emigrate at all costs, would be a constructive European project. Moreover, it would not even be a completely new one.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-128" speaker_id="1164" name="Bruno Gollnisch" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">It is clear that a genuine policy of cooperation with the Southern and Eastern Mediterranean countries is necessary in order to stem the migratory flows that Europe no longer has the means to accommodate, means that it has not had for a long time now. It is also clear that a reasonable trade policy can be mutually beneficial to both shores of the Mediterranean.</p>
      <p sl="fr">This is not, however, what Mr Arif’s report is proposing, which is to do nothing more and nothing less than extend, to North Africa and to part of the Middle East, the European Union, its functions and its policies: integrated agricultural policy, free movement of people and goods and freedom of services, to name but a few areas.</p>
      <p sl="fr">For what purpose? We do not really know, since a study quoted by Mr Arif himself envisages negative social and environmental repercussions in the short and medium term.</p>
      <p sl="fr">It is therefore purely due to its free-trade ideology, and not in the interest of European Union countries, nor even in that of Mediterranean countries, that Parliament is supporting this project.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-129" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro Guerreiro" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">Despite containing a degree of reformist rhetoric, the objective of this report is essentially to promote the creation of a free-trade area (FTA) between the EU and the Mediterranean region and to do so, moreover, in the context of EU efforts to bring about the effective liberalisation of world trade through the signing of bilateral/regional agreements in an attempt to rise above the difficulties involved in negotiations within the World Trade Organisation.</p>
      <p sl="pt">For example, the report provides for the, albeit regulated, ‘opening up of agricultural markets’, with particular reference to the wine and the fruit and vegetable sectors; the liberalisation of services, albeit excluding (only …) those public services considered to be basic (health, education, drinking water provision, the arts and audiovisual services); the liberalisation of energy supplies through the creation of a Euro-Mediterranean market; and the liberalisation of the industrial sector, specifically through the ‘establishment of a Euro-Mediterranean production area’ for textiles and clothing, in that way basically encouraging a large proportion of production capacity to be relocated.</p>
      <p sl="pt">In other words, the intention is to promote the liberalisation of trade, to the delight of the multinationals and major European importers, which long to dominate new markets and natural resources and to create new opportunities for exploiting cheap labour.</p>
      <p sl="pt">What, basically, is being put in danger are the nations’ own development models based on specific national needs and circumstances, together with a project of cooperation between these different countries that is genuinely based on mutual support.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-130" speaker_id="28585" name="Diamanto Manolakou" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="el">In the 12 years since the Barcelona Declaration, the peoples of the Mediterranean have become poorer and more desperate, while some areas have been at war. At the same time, capital – both local and foreign – is getting richer.</p>
      <p sl="el">The report on the construction of the Euro-Mediterranean free-trade zone expresses the EU's concern about the lack of progress in the Barcelona process. It calls for action to be stepped up, in other words for blatant intervention by the imperialist European Union in the internal affairs of the countries of the south and southeast Mediterranean, to be targeted at all aspects of the social, economic and political life of these countries. The EU spends huge sums in these countries subject to terms and conditions, so that economic development and political structures serve Euro-unifying capital and its profits and circumvent any national sovereignty for the states in the area.</p>
      <p sl="el">The concern expressed about political instability in the south and southeast Mediterranean, about the material damage caused by war, is hypocritical. The imperialist EU is equally guilty and equally responsible, as the thousands of soldiers in the area bear witness.</p>
      <p sl="el">Prosperity for the peoples can only be possible if they have full national sovereignty and the freedom to develop their structures and production as they so choose. That is why they need to be freed from any form of foreign intervention and their anti-imperialist fight needs to be stepped up, so that the real rulers are the people.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-131" speaker_id="1403" name="David Martin" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted for this report which puts forward several suggestions concerning the creation of a mutually beneficial Euro-Mediterranean FTA. I believe that the implementation of economic and political reforms can be an opportunity for growth. In particular I am pleased that the report stated that the FTA must look at countries’ specific economic and social characteristics to entitle them to protect their most vulnerable economic sectors, such as agriculture and public services.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-132" speaker_id="1944" name="Sebastiano (Nello) Musumeci" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="it">The three main objectives set by the Barcelona Conference of 1995 – namely the creation of a free trade area by 2010 between the European Union and its African and Asian partners; an area of peace and stability and the development of free, democratic societies – have not yet been achieved.</p>
      <p sl="it">The conflict between Palestine and Israel is, unfortunately, light years away from a peaceful resolution. Furthermore, since Israel’s withdrawal from the Gaza Strip a dramatic civil war has broken out between Hamas and Fatah supporters.</p>
      <p sl="it">In some non-European countries in the partnership, although some of the fundamental human rights have been recognised they are often not fully applied.</p>
      <p sl="it">The economic and social partnership too, fed by funds from the Meda Programme, has not produced the hoped-for results, and there is still a dreadful development lag, both because Europe has not taken enough care over the full implementation of the first and second Meda programmes, and also because the beneficiary countries have not always been able to create the economic and social infrastructure necessary to make themselves competitive.</p>
      <p sl="it">Finally, in many Euro-Mediterranean regions, there is no effective transport system, Information Technology is still insufficiently developed and the telecommunications modernisation is still some way off. For these reasons, I think it necessary to postpone the creation of a Euro-Mediterranean free trade area.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-133" speaker_id="4461" name="Luís Queiró" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">My comments with regard to Euro-Mediterranean relations apply fully to this debate, mutatis mutandis .</p>
      <p sl="pt">As I have said on previous occasions, I support the objective of creating an in-depth partnership between ‘Europe’ and its Mediterranean neighbours. Anything less than that – and a free trade area is less than that – is insufficient, in my view. It is also clear, however, that anything that moves in that direction is positive and deserves my support. That is essentially the case with what we are debating today.</p>
      <p sl="pt">I therefore voted in favour, but I would like our debate on these issues to move towards a broader view of the form our relations with our southern neighbours should take. For the good of both sides of the Mediterranean.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-134" speaker_id="28457" name="Luca Romagnoli" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="it">On behalf of the Integrity, Tradition and Sovereignty Group and the Tricolour Flame Party that I represent, I say ‘No’ to this unacceptable resolution. This is not with regard to the creation of a free trade area, but because of the confusing contents of the proposal and the outlook for the future.</p>
      <p sl="it">In the current context of political instability and institutional confusion, it is not possible for the free trade area to mean simply an opportunity for the countries of the south-east Mediterranean. The delays that these countries have encountered in implementing the reforms necessary to create a Euro-Mediterranean market must not automatically allow them to be given the right to protect the most vulnerable sectors of their economies, to the detriment of the countries of the EU, whose only role, according to this report, is to provide assistance, and whose citizens have to pay the costs.</p>
      <p sl="it">The only account taken of the need to adjust the speed and intensity with which the markets are opened up is through the timely supply of support for the integration of the south-eastern Mediterranean countries. The plans made for the creation of a kind of integrated agricultural policy for the Mediterranean and corresponding financial support for the countries of the south-eastern Mediterranean are on such a scale as to prefigure the transformation of FEMIP into an outright development bank. To complete this farce, the report sets out to facilitate the free movement of workers, through legal and administrative procedures to facilitate the granting of entry visas. There is no benefit in this, but just more burdens for European taxpayers.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-136" speaker_id="1403" name="David Martin" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted for this report and am pleased that there is an emphasis in the report on police reform and education.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-137" speaker_id="1318" name="James Nicholson" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I support this report on the basis that it makes proper recommendations in order to pursue justice and uphold peace in the region. I particularly commend the rapporteur for encouraging the authorities in BiH to pursue wanted war crimes perpetrators and bring them to justice. I also welcome the recently submitted draft plan for the police structure reform as it lays down a balanced allocation of responsibilities at all levels, while ensuring transparency in selection of police chiefs and officers and for monitoring their work. Here I also want to commend the work of the dedicated men and women of the Royal Ulster Constabulary who helped train the local police force.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-139" speaker_id="24029" name="Koenraad Dillen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="nl">Mr President, I have voted against the Voggenhuber report, because this House is once again wiping the floor with the Dutch and French referendums about the European Constitution. How else could this be described? Despite the fact that the Charter of Fundamental Rights has never been a legally binding document, and, following the rejection of the Constitution in those two countries, never will be, this politically correct catalogue is being smuggled back in via all kinds of backdoors. This is both legally and politically unacceptable.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Official Europe’s obvious unanimous contempt for national democracies is the reason why the Dutch people were recently, and in their own country, instructed by Commission President Barroso to at last accept this Constitution. The citizens are welcome to carry on voting, but it is ultimately the European mandarins who take the decisions. Whoever thinks that this sort of arrogance is going to make the public less Eurosceptic can think again.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-140" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Gerard Batten, Nigel Farage, Michael Henry Nattrass and Thomas Wise" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">UKIP have supported this amendment because it states very clearly the factual position that the Constitutional Treaty has been rejected and therefore should be abandoned. However, in no way does voting in this manner imply any support whatsoever for the political Group that have tabled the amendment.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-141" speaker_id="4540" name="Philip Bradbourn" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">Conservatives support the principle of having a Charter of Fundamental Rights in place as an advisory declaration to Member States. However, Conservatives voted against this report as the issue was to make the Charter legally binding (Justiciable) across the whole Union, which we are wholly opposed to.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-142" speaker_id="28493" name="Derek Roland Clark" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I have supported this amendment because it states very clearly the factual position that the Constitutional Treaty has been rejected and therefore should be abandoned. However, in no way does voting in this manner imply any support whatsoever for the political group that tabled the amendment.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-143" speaker_id="1892" name="Carlos Coelho" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">The Charter of Fundamental Rights is a summary of the common European values with which all of the citizens can identify, providing them with an instrument with which to defend themselves, through awareness and understanding of their rights, and to better control the activities of national and European authorities when they adopt and apply the Union’s legislation.</p>
      <p sl="pt">I regret the fact that it has not yet been made legally binding, although it has become a reference text for the activities of the European institutions and for the European judiciary, as in the case of the Court of Justice.</p>
      <p sl="pt">It is crucial that we do everything we can to develop a genuine ‘fundamental rights culture’ in the European Union, by creating a general system for monitoring fundamental rights and by actively promoting those rights, and by intervening in the event that Member States violate them or fail to uphold them properly.</p>
      <p sl="pt">There must therefore be rigorous and systematic monitoring with a view to finding the best solutions to ensure a fair balance between security objectives and restrictions of fundamental rights.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Furthermore, respect for the Charter of Fundamental Rights must be extended to the entire legislative process and to comitology.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-144" speaker_id="1164" name="Bruno Gollnisch" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">Mr Voggenhuber’s report claims that all European legislation should be subject to the Charter of Fundamental Rights, that veritable ideological rag-bag, and therefore that this Charter should be made binding. In other words, it is in favour of disregarding the people’s rejection of the European Constitution, of which the Charter formed Part II, and imposing a legal constraint that has not been adopted by either the people or their parliaments!</p>
      <p sl="fr">What is more, that would have three effects. It would legitimise the intervention of the Luxembourg Court in areas from which it is excluded by the Treaties themselves, such as police and judicial cooperation, which is quite a paradox. It would impose illegitimate constraints on Member States: Brussels could, for example, impose ‘lock out’, a right recognised in the Charter, but a practice that is banned in many States. It would impose constraints on the direction in which the European Parliament votes: how could we amend, other than just at the margins, any legislation implementing a ‘fundamental right’?</p>
      <p sl="fr">This text is very worrying: in the name of human rights, it pulls off the amazing feat of violating democracy, the Treaties and the rights of the European Parliament itself!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-145" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Hélène Goudin and Nils Lundgren" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="sv">The report points in the right direction but contains a couple of unhelpful proposals, for example in paragraph 2, all of which conflicts with the mandate we have from our electorate. It is important for all the EU’s decisions to be taken with respect for fundamental human rights. The report criticises the previous agreements on the transfer of passenger data entered into by the Commission with American authorities. The rapporteur points out why the secret transportation of prisoners engaged in by the CIA on EU territory was illegal and emphasises how important it is that such human rights violations should not be repeated.</p>
      <p sl="sv">The report clearly shows that a European Constitution is unnecessary for the protection of human rights in the Member States.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-146" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro Guerreiro" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">There have been repeated manoeuvres to try to restore the so-called ‘constitutional process’, flagrantly disregarding the sovereign decisions of the French and Dutch people in their 2005 referendums.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The use of the ‘Charter of Fundamental Rights’, an integral part of that ‘European constitution’, has long been a ploy in this unacceptable game.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The rapporteur's intention is to see the content of the constitution introduced via the back door, that is to say, to make this text binding when in reality it is not, and hence 'preserve’ the (in)famous ‘central achievements of the Constitution’</p>
      <p sl="pt">If the objective is to defend rights, then we should observe those that are laid down in the Constitution of the Portuguese Republic, in the European Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and in the European Social Charter, internationally valid texts, which are more complete and whose legitimacy is recognised, compared to the ‘Charter of Fundamental Rights’, the content of which is thin with regard to economic, social and cultural rights, for example.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Once again, the intention is essentially to make use of human rights (now known as ‘fundamental’ rights) in order to (re)impose the so-called ‘constitutional process’, by hiding its unacceptable neo-liberal, federalist and militarist agenda behind statements manipulating the legitimate expectations and reasonable concerns of the different peoples of the EU.</p>
      <p sl="pt">We therefore voted against.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-147" speaker_id="2057" name="Carl Lang" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">The European Parliament has a very particular and partisan conception of the definition of fundamental rights.</p>
      <p sl="fr">These rights serve as a support in fighting against individuals whom Parliament sees as undesirable, against political opponents, or else in attacking embarrassing governments that are not politically correct. Curiously, they are never invoked in the defence, for example, of the rights of political minorities within its Chamber. Minorities, whose error is not to belong to the great right-thinking mass of Eurofederalists. In this area, the great principles of freedom of expression and equality are utterly despised. The European Parliament puts that famous expression ‘do as I say, not as I do’ into practice.</p>
      <p sl="fr">This breed of European politicians is prepared to do anything to impose its vision of Europe and to do so against the wishes of the people, if necessary. Therefore, even though the European Constitution was rejected by referendum in France and the Netherlands, this breed of politician is still doing its utmost to try to get it through bit by bit. Likewise, although the Charter of Fundamental Rights has no binding legal status, the text proposed to us here seeks to make it indispensable – worse, an essential reference text – for European courts.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Far from being innocent, this report is dangerous for the freedoms and rights of the people.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-148" speaker_id="1403" name="David Martin" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted in favour of this report which looks at ways of improving the mechanisms for checking all EU legislation conforms with international human rights standards and fundamental rights are considered via impact assessment procedures as early as the draft Commission proposal stage. In particular I am pleased that the report looks at ways of increasing the role of the Parliament in the defence of fundamental rights and in ensuring EU legislation conforms with international human right standards.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-149" speaker_id="4313" name="Martine Roure" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">The European Union is currently going through an institutional crisis. By means of their vote, the people of France expressed their wish for a European Union, but a Europe that is not limited to the single market. The citizens want a Europe that also confers social rights.</p>
      <p sl="fr">This proposal for a methodology for the effective implementation of the Charter of Fundamental Rights in the Commission’s legislative proposals and, in particular, systematic and rigorous monitoring to ensure that all of the fundamental rights concerned are complied with at the time of the drafting of all legislative proposals, must lead to Europe's wishes being fulfilled. It therefore seems essential to me to find a way of not undermining the legally binding character of the European Charter of Fundamental Rights, so that it can have all the weight that European citizens want it to have.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-150" speaker_id="28139" name="Carl Schlyter" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="sv">The report contains a lot of drivel about the EU constantly having to be developed more and more, and a number of helpful wordings about the Constitution and about more power for the new agency. None of this is to the benefit of democracy and development. Rather, these are standard wordings that constantly crop up again and again in the reports by the Committee on Constitutional Affairs. What is exciting in this case is the demand for the Subcommittee on Human Rights to be able to prevent EU legislation that threatens such rights. That is extremely important when a constant stream of new anti-terrorist laws evermore threatens the society such laws are intended to protect. I am therefore voting in favour of the report, despite its shortcomings.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-151" speaker_id="28382" name="Andrzej Jan Szejna" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pl">I voted in favour of the report on compliance with the Charter of Fundamental Rights in the Commission's legislative proposals methodology for systematic and rigorous monitoring.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Mr Voggenhuber prepared a very good report concerning the vital issue of fundamental rights. It highlights the need to respect and comply with these rights, and also the need to create instruments for freedom. It is essential for the Charter of Fundamental Rights to become legally binding.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Systematic control and scrutiny by the Commission in order to examine all Commission legislative proposals for compliance with fundamental rights would seem to be appropriate. As the main legislative body, the Commission should be charged with checking compliance of legislative proposals with other international instruments regarding the rights and freedoms guaranteed to citizens. I support the Commission position. It intends to apply the Charter of Fundamental Rights in its legislative proposals until such time as this Charter enters in force.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The protection of fundamental rights and ensuring compliance with them should be one of the Union’s priorities. It seems that early control of Commission acts to ensure their compliance with fundamental rights is a good sign, and indicates the direction of Union bodies’ activities. Hopefully these will lead to the Charter of Fundamental Rights becoming legally binding.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-152" speaker_id="23894" name="Anna Záborská" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">Making the European Charter of Fundamental Rights legally binding is politically dishonest and irresponsible in practice. This Charter has always been conceived as a document that is symbolic of political compromise influenced by powerful representatives of individual interests that do not promote the common good.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The Charter creates 18 new ‘fundamental rights’ that are unwarranted but obligatory for national constitutions, without any government or nationally elected representative being able to oppose them. This Charter is useless and pointless so long as we have not formally determined the legal instrument to be applied at the European Court of Justice in Luxembourg and at the European Court of Human Rights in Strasbourg. Faced with doubts about double standards, I will not support the Charter, and I declare myself in favour of the Convention.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The only institution entitled to deal with the protection of human rights on the continent is the Council of Europe. The only legal instrument in relation to human rights in Europe is the European Convention on Human Rights. Our European super-agency on human rights is the European Court of Human Rights.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-155" speaker_id="28310" name="Edite Estrela" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">I voted in favour of the report by Mr Meyer Pleite (A6-0026/2007) on the negotiation of an EU-Central America Association Agreement because I believe that the European Union must continue to play a fundamental role in protecting the environment and human rights worldwide.</p>
      <p sl="pt">This agreement must seek a balance among the three pillars – political dialogue, cooperation and trade – that makes it possible to consolidate the democratic processes in Central America, improve the efficiency of democratic institutions and administrations, combat violence, corruption and impunity, as well as human rights violations, and, finally, improve social cohesion and the living conditions of all of the region’s inhabitants.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-156" speaker_id="1403" name="David Martin" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted for this report as I support a balanced association agreement in which progressive trade liberalisation should be a tool (and not a goal) put at the service of the main objectives of the promotion of socioeconomic development, sustainable development and social cohesion. The political, economic and social deficit suffered by the Central American countries deserves an agreement taking into account the asymmetries between both regions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-157" speaker_id="966" name="Jean-Claude Martinez" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">Against the backdrop of the globalisation of finance, agriculture, migration and the market, the nations of Europe must form an alliance of civilisation with the countries of Central America. Our farmers, for example, are basically confronted with problems similar to those of the campesinos in Mexico or of Latin American SMIs, faced, as they are, with the confiscation of their intellectual property, their expertise and, above all, faced with their gradual wiping out by a global trade system that pits our banana producers in the French West Indies and the Canaries against producers from Honduras or Nicaragua, solely to benefit multinationals like Chiquita.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The need for this alliance of civilisation between Europe and Latin America becomes all the more clear in the light of global migrations. Therefore, if, in the 1970s, French manufacturers in the car, steel and building industries had turned to the Latin American workforce instead of to that of Aures, Anatolia and Kabylia, French society would have avoided today’s tensions and public budgets would have avoided heavy expenses.</p>
      <p sl="fr">By entering into an alliance with Europe, Latin America would find the allies it needs, within international and trade forums, to defend a concept of the management of human societies and economies that are different from the Anglo-Saxon ideology of the market’s being everything.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-158" speaker_id="28407" name="Willy Meyer Pleite" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="es">On being appointed rapporteur for this report, I drew up a text, in collaboration with Central American civil society and political organisations, that recommended an Association Agreement based on three fundamental pillars: political agreement and good governance, development cooperation, and trade between two regions under conditions of fairness and mutual benefit based on complementarity and solidarity. Following the debate in the Committee on Foreign Affairs, a series of amendments were incorporated based on the opinion of the Committee on International Trade which entirely distorted the approach of my report, by indicating that the establishment of a free trade area was a priority strategic objective. My view, which is shared by a majority in Central America, is that an Association Agreement dominated by neo-liberal formulae would be a mistake and would only lead to inequalities and poverty in Central America, benefiting the multinationals. Within this context, the different political groups have reached a series of compromises that water down the neo-liberal nature of the report, but not sufficiently so in my view. This report is still very different from the one I initially intended and I have therefore abstained.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-160" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro Guerreiro" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">There is no question that the current situation in many Latin American countries make a clear explanation of the true intentions of the Association Agreements promoted by the EU rather contentious. This is why, at the last minute, in certain points of the resolution, the European Parliament has replaced a clear indication of its aim, the creation of a ‘free trade area’, with the phrase ‘Euro-Latin American area of interregional partnership’, while maintaining the content of the former as the objectives of the latter.</p>
      <p sl="pt">This piece of trickery does not disguise the fact that the aim is the ‘establishment in time of a free trade area’, providing in its ‘negotiating guidelines for gradual reciprocal trade liberalisation’ (which has been softened at the last minute by adding, ‘in conditions of justice and mutual benefit based on complementarity and solidarity’), aiming to ‘negotiate a single and indivisible trade agreement which goes beyond the negotiating parties’ present and future WTO obligations, and establish over a transition period compatible with WTO requirements a Euro-Latin America Global Interregional Association Area … without excluding any sector …’, developing a ‘customs union’ and a ‘common internal market’, guaranteeing ‘market access in agriculture’ and in services (except health and education).</p>
      <p sl="pt">What more needs to be said?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-161" speaker_id="28251" name="Jörg Leichtfried" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="de">I will vote for the report on a negotiating mandate for an association agreement between the EU and the Andean Community if the asymmetries between the various member countries of the Andean Pact are taken into account when negotiating a free trade area (attention must be paid to the different economic levels, demographic characteristics, different political courses, the great lack of modern communications and transport infrastructures between the individual Member States). Another important point is the introduction of core labour standards and the fight against drugs and arms trafficking.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-162" speaker_id="1403" name="David Martin" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted for this report because it supports a balanced association agreement in which progressive trade liberalisation should be a tool (and not a goal) put at the service of the main objectives of the promotion of socioeconomic development, sustainable development and social cohesion.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-154" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel Hannan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I want to focus on just one aspect of the Meyer Pleite and Yañez-Barnuevo García reports, namely their support for regional integration in Latin America. In last night’s debate, Commissioner Mandelson told this House that such integration is the key to growth and stability. He is entitled to his view, but no one in Latin America has elected Mr Mandelson to anything – nor, come to that, has anyone in Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">As colleagues know, some states in Central America in particular are complaining that Brussels is making its trade and aid agreements conditional on their participation in regional structures. I do not question the sincerity of those in Europe who insist that supranationalism is in everyone’s interests, but is it our place to tell other countries to mimic what the EU is doing? Why is it that whenever we debate in this House say Iraq or Iran, Members are quick to denounce Washington for seeking to impose its values on the world, but when it comes to hectoring other states about the need to cede their sovereignty, Brussels is suddenly keen to impose its values on the world? We cannot have it both ways.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-164" speaker_id="28146" name="Hélène Goudin" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="sv">The June List believes that when trade is freer, world prosperity is furthered. The concept of free trade is based on the idea that the more parties there are involved with it, the better the results they will see.</p>
      <p sl="sv">This own-initiative report contains much that is worthwhile and that could give rise to increased prosperity. Unfortunately, as is so often the case with reports from this Parliament, there are also extraneous and unhelpful wordings.</p>
      <p sl="sv">The report talks, for example, of the strategic external policy aspects of an agreement and of giving Parliament more power in relation to issues of both trade and external policy.</p>
      <p sl="sv">It is unfortunate that the aspects I have just mentioned overshadow the desirable things that could be achieved. I have therefore voted against the report in today’s vote.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-165" speaker_id="28142" name="Nils Lundgren" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="sv">Free trade is the most important agent of prosperity in the world, and the more countries that participate in it, the more the prosperity of those countries will grow. The incorporation of large parts of South and Central America into a free trade area with the EU would therefore represent a big step towards prosperity and the eradication of poverty.</p>
      <p sl="sv">This own-initiative report therefore contains many worthwhile proposals that could lead to increased prosperity if they were implemented. As is so often the case with reports in this Parliament, however, it unfortunately also contains a number of points whose aim is to promote the development of the EU into a federal superpower and to increase Parliament’s power at the expense of the Member States.</p>
      <p sl="sv">The report talks, for example, of the strategic external policy aspects of an agreement and of giving the European Parliament more power over both trade policy and external policy.</p>
      <p sl="sv">Despite these strong objections of mine, it is my judgment that it is better for these Interregional Association Agreements to be entered into than for them to be prevented.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-167" speaker_id="28310" name="Edite Estrela" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">I voted in favour of this motion for a resolution because I believe that the disappearance of people, which has a dramatic impact on everybody, on the people and on their families and friends, is unacceptable under any circumstances, and particularly in European territory.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The EU cannot shirk its responsibilities and must play a key role in resolving these problems. Effective measures must be taken, backed up by effective cooperation amongst the parties involved, with a view to putting an end to the atrocities that have been going on for decades and which violate human dignity and the Declaration of Human Rights.</p>
      <p sl="pt">I am also delighted with the removal, on 9 March, of the wall which for decades separated ‘the last divided capital in Europe’.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-168" speaker_id="4461" name="Luís Queiró" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">Beyond the intrinsic merits of the proposals we are voting on, regardless of any particular view of the Cyprus issue, this resolution is important because it reminds us that in our ‘Europe’ there is still a wall as shameful as the one we have called the ‘wall of shame’, even though in Nicosia the wall has been replaced with boarding.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The problem, however, lies in the line that separates an island, divides Europe and causes suffering on both sides. We must always remember that, and this declaration is a reminder of it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-170" speaker_id="4552" name="Den Dover" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">British Conservatives can welcome certain elements of this report such as the need to monitor the impact of illegal immigration on island communities.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, we cannot support the creation of Rapid Border Intervention Teams. Nor can we support any moves towards the creation of a 'European coastguard body'.</p>
      <p sl="en">For these reasons, we have decided to abstain on the final vote.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-171" speaker_id="1164" name="Bruno Gollnisch" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">The existence of this report on the integration, in regional policies, of the characteristics and handicaps of island regions in the European Union, in itself demonstrates that these special characteristics, while not having been completely hidden over the years, are not being properly addressed. This is, no doubt, because of the very nature of the European Union, which is given to standardising and levelling.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I also regret that stress was not put on the unbearable restrictions that the application, or the threat of application, of ordinary European law represents for these areas, particularly in matters of tax and competition. In France, dock dues, VAT rates or reduced excise duties, applicable to Corsica and to the French Overseas Departments, are periodically called into question and must also be periodically renegotiated in Brussels by the government.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Finally, I deplore the fact that the swamping of certain European islands by the influx of illegal immigrants is seen, almost clinically, in this report as a purely local matter, when it is an extremely serious problem. The removal of internal borders and the immigrationist proselytising of the EU are, it must be stressed, one of the major causes of this problem.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-172" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro Guerreiro" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">I have just two points to add with regard to the resolution in question:</p>
      <p sl="pt">I would like to stress that we agree that the issue of being an island should not be confused with the issue of being an outermost region, and that we must therefore bear in mind that the outermost regions are doubly disadvantaged. This is due, firstly, to their distance from the European continent, and, secondly, to the fact that they suffer structural disadvantages due to their island characteristics, in particular, and to other natural and geographical obstacles;</p>
      <p sl="pt">I would like to emphasise our complete disagreement with the points of the resolution backing the current immigration policy, in particular with regard to immigration from North Africa, in that it supports the creation of ‘Rapid Border Intervention Teams’ and of a ‘European coastguard body’ within the framework of the European Agency for the Management of Operational Cooperation at the External Borders (FRONTEX), with the aim of alleviating ‘the immediate pressure to deal with this problem’. We believe that this is a repressive policy, which criminalises immigrants, who are merely seeking better living conditions for themselves and their families, in the same way as thousands of Portuguese people who emigrate each year. It is a policy that sidesteps and fails to tackle the underlying causes of immigration, which have been identified for a long time, particularly by the United Nations.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Hence our decision to abstain.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-173" speaker_id="1403" name="David Martin" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted for this report. The importance of islands in major Community policies is increasing with the expansion of the Union. I am pleased that this issue remains on the agenda as it is still a challenge for the EU. This report has identified the main problems of islands, such as higher prices, lower salaries and difficulty of access to the single market.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-174" speaker_id="28111" name="Mary Lou McDonald" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">While fully supporting the calls for greater consideration to be given to the plight of islands in the context of regional development I felt I had no choice but to vote against today's report by Mr.Musotto because of its endorsement of a "Fortress-Europe" approach.</p>
      <p sl="en">The economic and social development of islands is very important and requires special measures such as the flexibility requested in terms of competition regulations. The islands off the coast of Ireland have played and continue to play an important role in preserving the Irish culture and economy. Sinn Féin will support any measures which contribute to the support of such islands.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-175" speaker_id="1944" name="Sebastiano (Nello) Musumeci" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="it">The islands of the European Union, whether they are extremely remote or not, almost all have to deal with the same difficulties. These include a lack of infrastructure, higher prices caused by additional transport costs, higher energy costs, emigration and immigration.</p>
      <p sl="it">For these reasons I have on several occasions called on the European Commission to give an opinion on some issues that are vital for the development of islands, and specifically Sicily, my region of origin.</p>
      <p sl="it">I believe, first and foremost, that it is vital to grant all islands special lower rates of taxation, as has been done for other European Union regions. This would make it possible to attract more capital, generating development and employment.</p>
      <p sl="it">With regard to incentives for investment, I have asked the Commission to look at the development of a policy that will encourage, in particular, foreign investment, particularly from outside the European Union, at a zero tax-rate.</p>
      <p sl="it">Finally, with regard to the lack of infrastructure, which constitutes one of the greatest obstacles to socio-economic growth in the islands, I am in full agreement with the call upon the Commission to review its policy regarding failure to grant State aid for infrastructure projects that improve transport connections. On this point, I would like to emphasise the need to build a bridge over the Straits of Messina.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-176" speaker_id="4461" name="Luís Queiró" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">The island regions face great difficulties as a result of natural and economic constraints. Higher transport and energy costs, lack of natural resources, depopulation, poor infrastructures and illegal immigration make it necessary to adopt specific Community measures to respond effectively to the characteristic problems of these regions.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The Structural Funds are therefore the principal instrument for Community action in this field. They can respond to the Union’s political will not to abandon its islands.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Specifically, we must ascertain precisely what their characteristics and needs are. The Commission must then ensure that the specific problems faced by the European islands are always taken into account, and accordingly it must take border control measures to tackle the illegal immigration that threatens them. It must also draw up an integrated development policy, which is able to ensure the sustainability of economic activities, such as tourism, on the islands.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Finally, this whole package of measures is essential in order finally to create the conditions to allow these regions to enjoy the same access to the single market as the continental regions. I therefore voted in favour of this report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-179" speaker_id="23787" name="Czesław Adam Siekierski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, I welcome the fact that the European Union is acting along the right lines by increasing the role of local authorities in our cooperation with individual countries, in particular with third countries. I am glad it is focusing on decentralisation of both cooperation and aid.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Local authorities play an important part in local and regional development, because they understand the needs of local communities, are locally based, and have usually been democratically elected. They play a particular role in combating poverty and inequality. Their role as institutions mainly involves issues related to education, health, the environment and entrepreneurship. It should be highlighted that they do not usually have enough financial resources at their disposal. This is true in particular for poverty-stricken regions with high unemployment rates.</p>
      <p sl="pl">These local authorities do not receive appropriate support from Member State’s budgets. Empowering local authorities to act in their own right in the framework of our development policy therefore deserves our full support both now and in the future. This is confirmed by our experience of cooperation with local authorities in Union countries, including my country – Poland.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-178" speaker_id="1403" name="David Martin" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted for this report as I believe it is crucial that communities have their aid delivered by the structures closest to them in order to achieve their Millennium Development Goals. In particular, I am pleased that the report contains concrete suggestions for actions to be taken by the Commission, most notably by increasing dialogue with local authorities on development aid, improving decentralisation of aid delivery and supporting structured dialogue between local authorities in the developing world and the EU.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-180" speaker_id="1253" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">That concludes the explanations of vote.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem19" title="7. Corrections to votes and voting intentions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem20" title="8. Approval of Minutes of previous sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem21" title="9. Banning seal products in the EU (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-186" speaker_id="23788" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the statement by the Commission on banning seal products in the EU.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-187" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Stavros Dimas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Μember of the Commission . Mr President, honourable Members of the European Parliament, thank you for giving me this opportunity to formulate the Commission's position on the ban on seal products in the European Union and to comment on the action already taken or planned.</p>
      <p sl="el">Seal hunting has been the subject of dispute and intense debate for many years now. I absolutely agree that there are reasonable questions in connection with seal hunting, irrespective of where it takes place. Nonetheless, it is encouraging that most seal populations appear to have stabilised and their survival is not endangered in their natural habitat. This opinion is based on the scientific statistics available on the development of populations of grey harp seals and blue hooded seals. There are no scientific indications of serious adverse repercussions from the hunt on the survival of these species of wild fauna.</p>
      <p sl="el">The seal population in the northeast Atlantic has increased significantly since the beginning of the 1970s from just 2 million to about 5.8 million grey harp seals, which are the main target during the annual hunting season. In other words, the seal populations in question are endangered at present and, consequently, they do not come under the CITES Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora. In order for these species of seal to be included in the CΙΤΕS Convention, international trade would have to threaten their survival in their natural habitat.</p>
      <p sl="el">This should not of course dissuade us from addressing the other important issue which arises in connection with seal hunting in numerous countries, including certain Member States of the European Union, by which I mean the issue of whether the importation and exportation and the marketing of seal products should be banned where the seals are not hunted in a way which complies with the specifications we have laid down on the proper treatment of animals. This is the reason why I agree that, even if we have not yet taken legislative measures at European Union level, the concerns formulated by the European Parliament on the proper treatment of animals and, in particular, on seal hunting, need to be examined in detail. In order to do this, we need to have the relevant information and statistics needed and that is why we have asked for an independent study to be carried out. On the basis of the results of this study, which has been prepared mainly by the European Food Safety Authority, we shall decide to propose to the Council and Parliament that measures be taken. According to the principles of good governance and lawmaking and the clear rules of procedure for the Commission, we must work on the basis of solid scientific data and the relevant impact study must be carried out before examining whether any measures should be taken.</p>
      <p sl="el">I have also issued instructions to my services to examine the possibility of the Commission's sending a mission to inspect and observe seal hunting during the 2007 hunting season. The Members of the European Parliament may examine the possibility of taking part in this mission.</p>
      <p sl="el">A full and objective evaluation of all aspects of this issue will enable us to take the right decisions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-188" speaker_id="4527" name="John Bowis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, our Commissioner is a reasonable and a humane man. He asks for time for research. We grant him that, but in return he should impose a moratorium on any imports of such seal products during that time.</p>
      <p sl="de">He says that the seal cull in Canada is sustainable. It may be, but in 2006, 330 000 harp seals were killed and 95% of those were under three months old. A large number of those were then skinned alive, because 79% of sealers do not check adequately as to whether the pup is still conscious.</p>
      <p sl="de">The cull is cruel and it is not worthy of a civilised country. It is certainly not sustainable in a country like Namibia. In Namibia, which has the second largest seal hunt in the world, the quotas increase each year. In 2007 the quota was 91 000 and a combination of high quota and natural mortality of seals means that the entire pup population could be annihilated this year.</p>
      <p sl="de">Seals are not killed for food; they are not really killed to protect fish stocks. They are killed for fashion, and Europe is the market for that fashion. It is the key market for seal skin imports from Canada. Belgium has banned it. Italy and Luxembourg have temporarily banned it. The United Kingdom and Germany have called for an EU-wide ban. The European Parliament in its written declaration has called for a permanent ban and the majority of Members of this Parliament have signed it. So please, Commissioner, ‘yes’ to research, but ‘yes’ also to a moratorium now.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-189" speaker_id="4447" name="Paulo Casaca" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PSE Group">
      <p sl="pt">I would like to express my agreement with what Mr Bowis has just said.</p>
      <p sl="pt">In reality, there is no reason why the moratorium should not go ahead immediately and the studies that the Commission sees fit be carried out subsequently. There is already plenty of striking information about this issue. Furthermore, a clear example has already been set by other countries, such as the United States and Mexico – the United States banned any use of seals more than three decades ago – and I do not understand why the Commission believes that we do not yet have sufficient information to act immediately.</p>
      <p sl="pt">As our fellow Member has already explained very well, this is not just a question of sustainability. It is essentially a question of ethics. The question is whether it makes sense, simply in order to satisfy certain fashion tastes, to kill in an entirely barbaric fashion – as reported last year by a delegation from the Intergroup on the Welfare and Conservation of Animals, including our fellow Member Carl Schlyter, and as we have been shown in many different ways.</p>
      <p sl="pt">If the Commission wants to see what is happening on the ground, a mission from this Parliament is going to Canada next week. We shall go directly to the places where this hunting is taking place. The Commission is welcome to come. It can certainly take part in that mission and it will be able to clear up any doubts that it may still have with regard to this problem.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-190" speaker_id="23881" name="Marios Matsakis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, sometimes I wonder how it is possible not to see the blindingly obvious, and then I think of the Canadian Government’s persistence in allowing an annual festival of blood-spilling carnage to be carried out on hundreds of thousands of defenceless baby seals.</p>
      <p sl="de">Other times I wonder how it is possible not to have any feelings in the face of extreme cruelty, and then I think of the thousands of fashion-mad individuals who pay through the nose to wear seal fur, taken in many cases by skinning still-conscious animals.</p>
      <p sl="de">However, at no time do I wonder how it is possible not to hear what is deafeningly loud, neither do I ever wonder how it is possible not to understand what is comprehensively simple, because, with respect, Commissioner, I have seen this happening only too often when it comes to the way in which the Commission sometimes deals with the European Parliament, and the subject matter under discussion here today is a good example.</p>
      <p sl="de">In September 2006, Parliament called on the Commission very clearly and very loudly to introduce an EU-wide ban on the trade of all seal products. Six months later the Commission is before us today telling us that, with seal killing being notoriously at the forefront of senseless cruelty to animals for so many years, it still needs more time to consider the matter further.</p>
      <p sl="de">Being a close friend and ally of the Commission and stretching our patience generously, I think we should give the Commission more time, if that is what it wants, but, as other speakers have said, on the condition that, in the meantime, an immediate moratorium banning all seal products in the EU is put into effect. This is dictated by our firm conviction on the matter, the need to act quickly and the fact that some EU Member States have already proceeded with national bans.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-191" speaker_id="28139" name="Carl Schlyter" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="sv">Mr President, Commissioner, last year I went and saw the seal hunting in Canada on behalf of the Animal Welfare Intergroup. The seal hunters used violence to try to prevent me from seeing what was going on. They forced our car off the road, they climbed onto our helicopters so that we could not fly in them and they threatened to kill us if we left our hotel in order to try to document the seal hunting. In spite of these methods, we succeeded in obtaining photographs and we saw how incredibly cruel seal hunting is. The hunters knew that they had something to hide. The seals are skinned alive, clubbed and left to choke on their own blood. They are wounded and either drown or have to suffer still more, as a second shot, designed mercifully to finish them off, would cause a two-dollar fall in the value of the skin.</p>
      <p sl="sv">It is not for conservation reasons that we should ban such hunting. It is for ethical reasons. I would nonetheless point out that the population declined the last time there was a huge hunt. We are now also faced with climate change, and the Greenland seal needs the ice sheet in order to be able to suckle her young. Many young seals are at present aborted in the water. Through being the world’s largest market, the EU supports such hunting, and Parliament has clearly said that we do not want our market to be a party to it. As Mr Bowis said, many countries have introduced national bans. When it was cat and dog fur that was at issue, the Commission said that the internal market was not working and that it would introduce an EU ban. The same logic applies in this case.</p>
      <p sl="sv">Does the Commission want studies to be carried out? There are many studies indicating the problems mentioned here in this House, especially the Bird and Veterinary Report , but these should not mean a delay in taking necessary measures. If you want more time, we can give you that time, but in that case we want a temporary ban in place until you are ready, and you must determine the legal basis for such a ban. Thank you for choosing the European Food Safety Authority’s animal protection committee to carry out the study. That decision has led to it being accepted and to it being independent and representative of the will of the countries concerned.</p>
      <p sl="sv">I want to point out that seal hunting is not of vital interest to the economies of any of the countries that hunt seals – Canada, Norway, Russia and Namibia. We see in the case of whale hunting that when this was abolished and replaced by whale watching, the latter was more profitable, so we can also help the seal hunters themselves improve their financial position if they manage to give up their cruel practice.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-192" speaker_id="4508" name="Erik Meijer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group">
      <p sl="nl">Mr President, seals have been a threatened animal species for years. Their numbers have not only diminished as a result of illness or pollution of the sea water along densely-populated coasts, but also by the increasing hunt for them. For a while, it looked like seals were set to die out completely in some coastal areas. Even now when seal quotas seem to be restored to some extent in some areas, there is a continued need for sustained protection.</p>
      <p sl="nl">There is evidence of the opposite of protection where people’s possessiveness is given free rein. Seal skin is a sought-after material for the decoration of clothing and toys, and the craving for this is satisfied by the disgraceful means of clubbing young seals to death and skinning them alive – an abhorrent activity on which some coastal residents have become economically dependent, and a system perpetuated by the possibility of exporting seal skins and finding buyers for them far from the scene of the crime. This is why it has been vital for many years to ensure that products of this kind are no longer for sale, particularly in the richest parts of the world, such as Europe.</p>
      <p sl="nl">The first part of Commissioner Dimas's statement shows that he shares this House’s, and the public’s, disquiet at this. The subsequent outcome, however, is disappointing. There would be no objection whatsoever to an impact study, and increased inspection in Canada and Namibia would be welcomed. This cannot be a justification, though, for continuing with a policy of ‘wait-and-see’.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Some EU Member States have already followed the USA in taking action against imports, but why are some European countries lagging behind in this? There is every reason for an immediate moratorium. Even if we introduced one tomorrow, it would come years too late given the seriousness of the situation. I would therefore urge you not to use the study as an excuse for further procrastination.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-193" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Stavros Dimas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to thank all the speakers for their very constructive contributions to this afternoon’s discussion.</p>
      <p sl="en">First of all, I would like to repeat that from the conservation point of view there is no basis to take any action, because in 1970s we had 2 million seals of the most hunted species, and now we have 5.8 million of these seals. We are looking only at the second issue – it is very important.</p>
      <p sl="en">As regards the study, firstly I have to repeat that the Commission fully recognises the high level of public concern regarding the application of humane killing methods, and in line with its commitment to high animal welfare standards, we will examine all available information. There are reports – which are partly contradictory – that seals are being hunted and killed in some regions in an inhumane way. The assessment that I referred to – and which one of the speakers found to be necessary – will present balanced, objective and operational conclusions and recommendations. The overall outcome should enable the Commission to draw some conclusions and to come back with possible legislative proposals if this is warranted by the situation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Regarding the moratorium, in legal terms the Commission does not have available an immediate remedy to impose a moratorium on the import, export and trade in seal products. It would not be possible to refer to the safeguard measures provided for under the public health and animal policy that would allow for a temporary ban when public or animal health is threatened. For example, the decision to temporarily suspend imports of wild birds was adopted in order to protect animal and public health because of the risk of a worldwide spread of avian influenza.</p>
      <p sl="en">Furthermore, under the trade policy there is no immediate remedy possible. Any measure the European Union decided to adopt would need to be necessary and proportional and would need to be notified to the World Trade Organization. At this stage it is therefore not appropriate, nor is it feasible, to impose an immediate trade ban.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission first needs to carry out an objective assessment of all available information. The outcome of this assessment should enable the Commission to draw sound conclusions and to come back with possible legislative proposals if this is warranted by the situation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Reference was made to the United States, and its Marine Mammal Protection Act was enacted in 1972, which was before the International Convention on Trade in Endangered Species entered into force in 1975. Furthermore, Member States have the opportunity to impose measures according to the case law of the European Court of Justice, but the Community has no such legal basis.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would ask you to urge your governments in your Member States to impose bans – they have the legal means. We need to have the appropriate legal basis before we can impose bans at European Union level and that is what we are trying to do by having an impact assessment and by gathering information. However, if you show your concern in your countries and urge your governments to impose bans, this will facilitate internal market reasons for the European Union to take steps.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, I wish to reiterate that the Commission is strongly committed to high animal welfare standards, both within the European Union and at international level. A full objective assessment of the animal welfare aspects of seal hunting will allow us to see the whole picture and have a solid basis before drawing any conclusions. We shall examine all available information and take the necessary steps. If it is established that seals are being hunted and killed in an inhumane way, a ban on the import and export, as well as the placing of products derived from the seal hunt on the market, will also be considered.</p>
      <p sl="en">We will report back to the European Parliament within the shortest possible time. I repeat that we have already asked the European Food Safety Authority to conduct the scientific part of the study, and I have written to the Canadian Government to ask that we be allowed to participate in a mission, and the European Parliament is also invited to participate in order to see how the hunt is being organised. What you said previously about your experiences is very interesting.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-194" speaker_id="23788" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The floor is yours Mr Beazley. I understand that this will be a formal motion.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-195" speaker_id="1429" name="Christopher Beazley" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, before the Commissioner speaks, I just wonder if it is in order to put a supplementary question to him on the timing of his statement. It is over 25 years since the European Parliament first raised this issue. When the Commissioner very helpfully said that he would report back in the shortest possible time, could he be more specific as to exactly how long he anticipates that time might be?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-196" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Stavros Dimas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">I saw in your letter that you fear the study will take years. That is not so. It is a matter of months.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-197" speaker_id="23788" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem22" title="10. The attack on Galina Kozlova, member of the board of the Mari national organisation Mari Ušem and editor of the literary magazine Ontšõko (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-199" speaker_id="23788" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the statement by the Commission on the attack on Galina Kozlova, member of the board of the Mari national organisation Mari Ušem and editor of the literary magazine Ontšõko .</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-200" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neelie Kroes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members, the Commission regrets the violent attack on Galina Kozlova which took place on 25 January in the capital of the Mari Republic, and I express my sympathy to her and her family and my best wishes for her speedy recovery from her injuries. The Commission expects that the incident will be thoroughly and speedily investigated and the perpetrators brought to justice. In this context I note that an investigation has been opened and that the President of the Mari Republic has reportedly demanded that it be given special priority.</p>
      <p sl="en">More generally, the Commission is aware of the situation of Finno-Ugric indigenous peoples, such as the Mari-El people in Russia. We are also aware of the concerns raised by a number of Members of the European Parliament concerning the treatment of the Mari-El, notably with regard to the Mari language in school teaching and the harassment of journalists and the presidential elections in December 2004. The Commission took good note of Parliament’s resolution of May 2005.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission sees common values, including the respect for human rights, as a cornerstone of its relations with Russia. The Commission participates actively in the EU-Russia human rights consultations, where we aim to discuss the most important issues with Russia in an open and constructive manner. It would be useful if we could, on issues such as these, move away from mutual recriminations and focus on exchanges of experience and best practice on how to deal with these problems, which can arise in many modern societies. It is for that reason that the Commission has suggested that the participation in the human rights consultations should be widened to include not only diplomats but also experts from line ministries and agencies responsible for tackling these issues on the ground.</p>
      <p sl="en">The next round of consultations with Russia on human rights – including the rights of people belonging to minorities – and fundamental freedoms will take place on 3 May.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission has raised the issue of the rights of the Mari population bilaterally with the Russian authorities. In response, they have given information on the activities which have been undertaken, financed by the government of the Mari Republic, to promote the development of art and culture in the Mari Republic, to encourage multilingualism as well as to foster traditional arts and crafts. Support is given to publishing books by authors in the Mari language, as well as their translation into Russian, for newspapers in the Mari language and for study at the University of Mari El and other institutions of higher education.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, I should add that, in the roadmap for the common space on research and education, including cultural aspects, the EU and Russia have agreed to work together in order ‘to strengthen and enhance the European identity on the basis of common values, including freedom of expression, democratic functioning of the media and respect of human rights, including the rights of persons belonging to minorities and promotion of cultural and linguistic diversity as a basis of civil society in Europe without dividing lines’. We are now working together with Russia on an action plan for cultural cooperation which will aim to translate these principles into concrete action. Exchanges in this field should help to build a better climate in which the cultures and traditions of minority populations are respected.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-201" speaker_id="28424" name="Tunne Kelam" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, I would like to thank the Commissioner for her understanding and quick reaction. Parliament has already voiced its concern about the situation in the Mari El Republic: that was two years ago back in May 2005 after Mari national leader Vladimir Kozlov was brutally beaten up.</p>
      <p sl="de">Alarmingly, no improvement has been noted since then. Clamping down on attempts to revive Mari national culture and language has continued. Therefore, we cannot be satisfied with the fact that an investigation into the beating of Mr Kozlov has produced no results in two years and now there is a new incident.</p>
      <p sl="de">I think that the most alarming fact in today’s Russia is that politically motivated killings, deaths and physical attacks continue unabated and that not a single perpetrator has been caught or tried.</p>
      <p sl="de">The latest case is that of Ivan Safronov, who happened to fall from the window just before he was to publish an article about illegal Russian arms sales to Syria and Iran.</p>
      <p sl="de">Sadly, the robust revival of widespread xenophobia, militant movements of neo-fascists and Stalinists have become part of Russia’s reality.</p>
      <p sl="de">If a government has for several years been unable or unwilling to guarantee the basic right to life and security for all its citizens and to bring contract killers to justice, then such a government necessarily undermines its own position as a credible international partner.</p>
      <p sl="de">Our message today should be the following: there can be no further progress in EU-Russia relations until the Kremlin decides to intervene and stop this vicious cycle of killings and human rights violations. Clearly, if Russian citizens cannot have confidence in the justice of their own state, how can Russia’s partners abroad have trust in future gas deliveries and Russia’s compliance with the international code of conduct?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-202" speaker_id="23808" name="Csaba Sándor Tabajdi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PSE Group">
      <p sl="hu">On behalf of the European socialists, I am very grateful to the European Commission for its rapid reaction, for we face a very serious situation that gives much cause for concern. As my fellow Member Tunne Kelam has already implied, the 2005 decision had its result, and the situation in the Mari Republic improved temporarily. Now, two years later, once again we see a peaceful female activist, Galina Kozlova, brutally attacked, in an incident that rightfully attracts the attention of the European Commission and the European Parliament. We know that the perpetrators of the attack on Mr Kozlov in 2005 have still not been found, and in fact this is also grounds for the current decision. As President of the Minority Languages Intergroup within the European Parliament, and of the Finno-Ugric forum – which is a cross-party initiative – I was able in September 2006 to invite Mr Kozlov here to Strasbourg. I was able to determine first-hand this is no radical, unmanageable individual, but rather a remarkably moderate man. The purpose of today’s resolution is to take note of and draw attention to the fact that the European Commission and the European Parliament are paying attention to what is happening there. We ask the Russian federal authorities to exert pressure on the local authorities of the Mari Republic, because this examination is far from reassuring. The case is being treated as one of light bodily injury, whereas in fact Galina Kozlova suffered a fracture of the skull base, which is a serious bodily injury! Today’s resolution is important for this reason as well, and it is similarly important that at the next EU-Russian summit, the situation be raised along with the situation of other Finno-Ugric peoples, and that it be discussed within the context of the EU-Russian dialogue as well. I wish to thank Mrs Neelie Kroes and the Commission for their cooperation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-203" speaker_id="23830" name="István Szent-Iványi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="hu">On 25 January of this year, Galina Kozlova was seriously injured by an unknown attacker in Yoshkar-Ola. Mrs Kozlova suffered skull, brain and eye injuries. She was treated in hospital for several weeks, and is still recovering at home. The perpetrator or perpetrators have not yet been caught. This is not so surprising, of course, in light of the fact that, as we know, serious incidents against activists struggling on behalf of the rights of the Mari minority occurred regularly between 2001 and 2005, and not a single perpetrator has been brought to justice since that time. This situation does raise the fear that these serious incidents occur at the behest of the local authorities, or at least with their tacit support.</p>
      <p sl="hu">Our parliamentary resolution of 2005 had tangible results, as my fellow Member Mr Tabajdi has suggested, since for a year and a half no such incidents occurred. It is true that the situation of the Mari minority did not improve significantly, but small steps forward are being taken, and therefore I am glad that the Commission is now also addressing these questions and putting them on the agenda. But I also request both the Commission and Parliament to devote much more attention to resolving the problems of the Finno-Ugric minorities and of minorities in general within Russia.</p>
      <p sl="hu">We encourage the Union to speak up within the context of the European Union-Russian human rights dialogue on this matter. This is not simply a matter of an isolated event, but at the rights of the Mari minority and indeed of the Finno-Ugric minorities in general. At the same time I also urge that within the context of the cultural cooperation between the European Union and Russia, subsidised programmes at last be launched in support of the education, language training and maintenance of cultural institutions of minorities, and especially of the Finno-Ugric minorities.</p>
      <p sl="hu">If we are not successful in moving forward, then this matter will have to be put on the agenda of the European Union-Russian summit, for it is intolerable that despite the will of the European Parliament, the Commission and the Council, there should be constant violations of civil rights in Russia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-204" speaker_id="28376" name="Leopold Józef Rutowicz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the UEN Group">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, from this Chamber we protest against those who breach human rights and violate the rules of law. We should, however, ask ourselves what effect our activities driven by solidarity with people of good will are having. I do not believe it is the effect we would wish. Nonetheless, this is one of the ways to hinder social processes that adversely affect us all such as disrespect for human beings, violence and the struggle to be able to present one’s views, something every citizen of a democratic state should be able to do.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Galina Kozlova, who is a member of the board of the Mari Ušem organisation and editor of the literary magazine Ontšõko is an example. She is married to Vladimir Kozlov, President of the Mari-El Republic’s Council. She has given distinguished service to the republic, but unlike many journalists, she does not share her opponents’ political views.</p>
      <p sl="pl">As Europeans it is our duty to monitor, raise, and condemn the discrimination of Mari citizens, and attacks on their representatives and journalists. We support Galina Kozlova in her struggle for the interests of Mari citizens and democracy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-205" speaker_id="4508" name="Erik Meijer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group">
      <p sl="nl">Mr President, in the 1920s, the Soviet Union tried to find a fair solution to the problem of nationalities. The large Russian empire, with its many minorities, made way for regional self-government for the other peoples, with education and administration in the people’s language. It is to this decision that 11 countries, including Ukraine, Georgia and Uzbekistan, now owe their independence.</p>
      <p sl="nl">The many smaller peoples, such as the Chechens, Tatars, Ossetians, Karelians or Mari, on the other hand, were given only autonomous areas within Russia or one of the other federal states. These peoples have been in a bad way ever since the collapse of the Soviet Union. Nobody has recognised their right to independence and they all hope that they, despite everything, can retain the rights that were granted to them 85 years ago.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Unfortunately, the continuation of these rights is threatened by resurgent nationalism in both Georgia and Russia. The bad political climate in Russia is the price for holding onto Chechnya, against the wishes of the Chechens, by extremely violent means. Intimidation and murder are, in fact, promoted within the army in which young soldiers are systematically abused by older soldiers, and obliged to keep quiet about it.</p>
      <p sl="nl">In Putin’s Russia, there is less and less room for protest, critical investigation and change of power. The stability of the regime in power and the ever-increasing concentration of authority over the different regions in Moscow are given absolute priority. Opponents are put behind bars, beaten up or excluded from elections. Even more drastic is the sudden death of critics, in particular people who are suspected of disclosing important information. Europe must help Russia not to slide down further towards a situation that is becoming intolerable for more and more people. It is in this light that the protection of the people who stand up for the right of the Mari Republic should be seen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-206" speaker_id="28276" name="Laima Liucija Andrikienė" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="lt">First I would like to thank my colleagues Tunne Kelam, Vytautas Landsbergis and Charles Tannock for their initiative in arranging for us to hear the Commission's report on Galina Kozlova today and adopt a resolution.</p>
      <p sl="lt">This resolution is yet another European Parliament document, concerning human rights abuses in Russia, which is linked to the EU through a Partnership and Cooperation Agreement – currently in force – and through a strategic partnership that it now appears is based not on shared values but on pragmatism, seeking economic and other benefits.</p>
      <p sl="lt">To me, as a member of the European Parliament's Human Rights Subcommittee, one avenue of EU-Russia cooperation is particularly important – the ongoing EU-Russia consultations on issues of human rights, minority rights and basic rights. In this context the brutal attack on Galina Kozlova, editor of the literary journal Ontšõko and wife of Mari Council chairman Vladimir Kozlov, an attack with precedents in the Mari Republic, not only deserves our attention and consideration, but it forces us to return yet again to the general human rights situation in Russia.</p>
      <p sl="lt">Considering the latest data, Russia is now the second most dangerous place in the world for journalists (after Iraq). Therefore, I fully support the spirit of our resolution, in which the European Parliament urges the Russian Federation and local governmental institutions to honour their commitments under international law, not just to guarantee freedom of the press but to implement legislative provisions relating to the protection and support of minority languages and cultures.</p>
      <p sl="lt">I think the problems of Finno-Ugric minorities in Russia could be raised by the Commission during the ongoing EU-Russia dialogue on human rights issues, and during the EU-Russia leaders' summit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-207" speaker_id="28392" name="Józef Pinior" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, the European Parliament expresses its concern about the attack on Galina Kozlova, member of the board of the Mari Ušem national organisation and editor of the literary magazine Ontšõko in the Mari-El Republic in the Russian Federation. Galina Kozlova is married to Vladimir Kozlov, President of the Mari-El Republic’s Council, who was also nominated for the 2006 Sakharov Prize. We should recall that this prize was presented by the current President of Estonia, Toomas Ilves, who was formerly a Member of the European Parliament.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The question arises as to what Russia is aiming at. There is a growing number of attacks on independent activists and journalists. More and more incidents remain unexplained. Issues such as repression, violation of human rights, and of the rights of minority national groups in the Russian Federation are being raised ever more frequently. Perhaps what is happening is that President Putin’s regime is becoming increasingly authoritarian? This case should be food for thought for us, and we must demand a thorough investigation by the Russian authorities to identify the perpetrators of the attack.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-208" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neelie Kroes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, this has been an impressive debate and I have taken good note of all the points raised. It is good to focus our attention, from time to time, on issues which do not necessarily make the headlines in the EU. The attack on Mrs Galina Kozlova was one such event, and I hope very much that she will make a full and speedy recovery and continue with her responsibilities.</p>
      <p sl="en">As I have said, the Commission would like to have a constructive dialogue with Russia on such matters. We are aware both of the criticism of the present situation regarding the Mari people and of the efforts which have been made at official level in Russia to safeguard their rights and their culture. Modern societies need to find ways of addressing the situation of minorities to encourage peaceful and harmonious social economic development. We all need to continue making efforts in this respect. We shall aim, therefore, to use our contacts with Russia, and in particular the human rights consultations, to identify ways in which we can work together to improve the situation. I have already mentioned that 3 May is one of those meeting days.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission will continue to raise concerns about human rights at all levels, from the summit down. For a more detailed discussion, the best forum for an exchange of views with Russia is the human rights consultations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-209" speaker_id="23788" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Pursuant to Article 103(2) of the Rules of Procedure, I have received three motions for resolutions.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place today at 5 p.m.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem23" title="11. Debates on cases of breaches of human rights, democracy and the rule of law(debate)"/>
  <section id="creitem24" title="11.1. Guatemala">
    <intervention id="4-212" speaker_id="23788" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the debate on six motions for resolutions on Guatemala .</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-213" speaker_id="28392" name="Józef Pinior" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, in recent months in Guatemala there have been a number of unexplained murders, unexplained threats, cases of intimidation of trade union activists, politicians, and of society as a whole. Human Rights Watch published its recent report on human rights in January 2007. This report states that during the 36-month dirty war in Guatemala, which ended in 1996, some 200 000 people were killed. I repeat, 200 000 people were killed during the 36-month dirty war in Guatemala.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Over the last 20 years we have witnessed the process of democratisation in Guatemala, including many achievements concerning the rule of law, and the development of democratic institutions. However, Guatemala still remains a country where the rule of law is compromised, and where democracy has not yet taken root. We are faced with a whole series of unexplained murders and disappearances in the past, together with current incidents involving powerful gangs, and international crime.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Let me remind the House that in 2005 between 70 and 80 million documents linked to the dissolved national police were found. These documents contain information regarding the so-called ‘disappeared’ during the dirty war . An appropriate storage place for these documents has so far not been found. It is high time for Guatemala to resolve these issues in a democratic manner.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, today in this House we have voted through recommendations for the Commission regarding the Association Agreement with Central American countries. My political group has stressed that we believe trade liberalisation should be seen in a political perspective. Trade liberalisation in Latin America cannot be separated from democratisation. The European Union must make every effort to help the people of Guatemala to reinforce democracy, investigate all murders that happened during the dirty war , and strengthen the peaceful transition so as to establish genuine, truly democratic structures in that country.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-214" speaker_id="2229" name="Bernd Posselt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, I would like to thank Mr Pinior for pointing out that in Guatemala terror is a tradition extending back decades, on both sides. When we were dealing with Guatemala in the urgent debate in the last session a few months ago, I reminded the House that in the early 1970s, that is more than 30 years ago, a German diplomat, Karl Graf von Spreti, was abducted and murdered by terrorists in Guatemala; he was a prominent Bavarian politician who always spoke out for freedom and we shall shortly be marking the anniversary of his death again in Bavaria. Even then, terror was used both by the regime and by those opposing it.</p>
      <p sl="de">Since then, the country has still not found rest, despite a degree of democratisation in the last 20 years. There is violence on the extreme right, there is violence on the extreme left and, as Mr Pinior has rightly pointed out, there is unfortunately also the violence of organised crime, which is in many ways mixed up with the political extremists. That is why we really must pursue an intensive and offensive policy on Latin America.</p>
      <p sl="de">I am very grateful to Mr Salafranca Sánchez-Neyra for taking this initiative on behalf of our group, and also to Mr Dess, who is particularly concerned with relations with Latin America – in his case mainly Brazil. We want to make clear, however, that Latin America is of concern not only to our Spanish and Portuguese colleagues but to all of us, and that the continent is an important partner. Only when democracy and the rule of law are at last firmly rooted in Central and South America and all forms of extremism are brought under control will that continent be able to play the role which its economic and cultural weight actually demands.</p>
      <p sl="de">That is why — and I agree with Mr Pinior here — we must use all the commercial policy instruments at our disposal to work for democracy and the rule of law. Democracy and the rule of law are not a luxury, neither are they a flourish that might perhaps be applied to what are really economic relations. In the long term, there can be no successful economic relations with regimes and forces that flout basic human rights. That is why this human rights debate is indispensable and we must apply pressure accordingly.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-215" speaker_id="28372" name="Ryszard Czarnecki" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, in distant Guatemala, three members of the national Parliament were killed. Then, just like in a crime movie, four policemen involved in the case and placed under arrest, including the chief of the anti-Mafia department in Guatemala, were murdered in prison.</p>
      <p sl="pl">This really sounds like a thriller screenplay, but it is not just a movie, it is life, and part of the pattern of everyday life in Guatemala. It is right for the European Parliament to react. We are reacting to the situation in a state whose President has publicly acknowledged that his country’s police force is riddled with corruption.</p>
      <p sl="pl">We are referring to a country in which several thousand murders take place every year, and which, like Colombia, is involved in the drugs trade. Now, as the House will be aware, the authorities of the Central American Parliament are discussing with Daniel Ortega, the re-elected President of Nicaragua, the possibility of moving the seat of the Central American Parliament to Nicaragua from Guatemala where the danger is so high. What can things have come to, if Ortega is now offering a safe haven.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I believe that in such a situation Mr Posselt and Mr Pinior are right, we must adopt an explicit and firm position.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-216" speaker_id="28249" name="Tobias Pflüger" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, the human rights situation in Guatemala is frightening. Mr Czarnecki has referred to the specific case on the basis of which we are dealing with the subject today.</p>
      <p sl="de">The situation in Guatemala is of course marked by the strong influence of social groups outside the political parties, especially the military and business. In some parts of the country, the Indian population in particular has little confidence in the state legal system. Human rights experts in Guatemala say that several thousand people are murdered every year, but only around 2% of cases are actually solved or lead to arrests.</p>
      <p sl="de">Yesterday, a German citizen was shot dead in Guatemala. Trade unionists, like Pedro Zamora in Puerto Quetzal, or farmers’ leaders and their families were killed at the start of this year. Witnesses of murders or their legal representatives are threatened and attacked and their homes broken into.</p>
      <p sl="de">If the security situation is to improve, there needs to be a political solution, not further arming of the security forces. That is why it is essential to note that these very ‘security forces’ are part of the problem in Guatemala. Now the European Union has announced that it intends to support these selfsame security forces and unfortunately also to continue backing an intensification of free trade. The response from thousands of people from Guatemala is relatively clear; we saw that when US President George W. Bush visited Guatemala. There were large demonstrations against his visit.</p>
      <p sl="de">There is a free trade agreement between the USA and the countries of Central America, the CAFTA, and Bush told Guatemalan President Oscar Berger yesterday that it was advantageous for all sides. Bush also promised Guatemala further support in fighting organised crime, especially drug gangs. As in Brazil, Uruguay and Columbia, however, the first stops on Bush’s journey, the president’s visit was repeatedly accompanied by protests. It is good that it was. If the European Union follows the US policy example, that could therefore become highly problematical.</p>
      <p sl="de">What is needed is not free trade and arms for the security forces but real steps to prevent poverty and an improvement in the legal situation of the majority of the population.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-217" speaker_id="23881" name="Marios Matsakis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Madam Commissioner, the European Parliament has passed a number of resolutions on Guatemala in the past. They have had some effect, but it seems that we are still a long way from achieving our aim of helping to bring true democratic reform to this country.</p>
      <p sl="en">The callous murder in mid-February 2007 of three members of the Central American Parliament and the alleged involvement in this and many other crimes of police officials is a reminder that impunity and police corruption in Guatemala are still very much in existence. Such gross deficiencies in democracy, along with attempts to curtail freedom of the press, are cancerous inflictions in the body of any society and drastic action must be taken urgently in order to remedy the situation.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Guatemalan authorities have a lot to answer for and a huge responsibility to act decisively in order to protect their citizens’ rights and freedoms. We shall await and watch closely with a critical eye to see and be convinced that they have the will and the stamina to stamp out the criminals from the police force and from other state institutions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-219" speaker_id="28409" name="Raül Romeva i Rueda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, we debated Guatemala in one of these urgency debates not so long ago, when we discussed the extradition of Ríos Montt and others. Today we are debating it again, this time in relation to the murder of three El Salvadorian members of the Central American Parliament, as well as the people suspected of the crime, in their case in prison.</p>
      <p sl="es">Nevertheless, this worrying episode is not an isolated one within a context that is becoming increasingly tense and dangerous. Lack of security is a serious and growing problem in Guatemala, but so is the impunity following certain acts, some of which are carried out directly by public institutions or at least with their consent.</p>
      <p sl="es">The Guatemalan Government itself, in the person of its Vice-President Stein, has acknowledged that organised crime is becoming increasingly ingrained in the public institutions, including the police.</p>
      <p sl="es">As previous speakers have said, the statistics are striking. Thousands of people are murdered each year in Guatemala, but arrests have been made in just 2% of cases. One of the most recent cases has been the murder of the campesino leader, Pedro Zamora, in Puerto Queztal, which we reported to the Commission and the Council.</p>
      <p sl="es">Nevertheless, in view of the new episode that we are discussing today, we must reiterate some of the demands that this Parliament has made previously.</p>
      <p sl="es">Firstly, we must repeat Parliament’s appeal to the Guatemalan Parliament that it ratify the Statute of Rome regarding the International Criminal Court, and also that it ratify the agreement signed on 12 December 2006 between the Guatemalan Government and the United Nations establishing an International Commission against Impunity in Guatemala (CICIG).</p>
      <p sl="es">Secondly, we must call upon the Guatemalan authorities to adopt measures to protect witnesses and victims of human rights abuses in judicial processes.</p>
      <p sl="es">Thirdly, we must call upon the Commission, in the strategy for cooperation with Guatemala for 2007-2013, to enhance the promotion of the rule of law, the fight against impunity, full respect for human rights and support for the government in increasing the security forces’ capacities to safeguard human security.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-220" speaker_id="28299" name="Bogusław Sonik" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, Guatemala is one of Latin America’s poorest countries. Out of Guatemala’s population of 11 million, more than half live on the verge of poverty. The civil war certainly contributed to the present situation. We should remember that the war spanned 36 years and is estimated to have cost the lives of more than 200 000 civilians.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The people of Guatemala are still suffering particular and permanent violence, intimidation, corruption, and breaches of their civil rights. As long as politicians and government officials responsible for maintaining public order are brutally murdered, there will be no democracy. A society continually affected by violence cannot develop and function normally.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Police corruption makes it impossible to attempt to settle accounts with the bloody past. It is commonly known that the army is largely responsible for crimes and serious violation of human rights. Corruption of the state, politicians, administrative authorities, and public services stimulates the development of inappropriate behaviour and poverty. Society is intimidated and is effectively being held hostage by criminals.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Many international organisations report that Guatemala is a paradise for organised crime. This Latin American country is listed as a part of the world where human trafficking, involving children in particular, is conducted on a large scale.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Every effort must be made to support and protect all those who dare to say ‘no’ to illegal structures, and to the links between state structures and organised crime. Putting an end to impunity by prosecuting those responsible for outbreaks of political violence is an indispensable step in this process. The Union should therefore ban politicians who go along with the corruption of public institutions for the sake of political correctness from entering EU territory, as it has already done in the case of other countries where flagrant violation of human rights takes place.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-221" speaker_id="28376" name="Leopold Józef Rutowicz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the UEN Group">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, our resolution on the murder of three El Salvador members of the Central American Parliament and their driver near Guatemala City, the capital of Guatemala and seat of the administration of the Central American Parliament, is a protest against banditry affecting innocent people.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Guatemala is a country that became a fully independent state in 1839. It is inhabited by Indians with links to the Mayan culture, 80% of which are Catholics. Sadly, the population has not been fortunate in its governments. Undemocratic governments, military coups, civil war, drugs, corruption, poverty, have all created favourable conditions for those who spread the culture of violence and ride roughshod over human rights.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Guatemala is a presidential republic, in which legislative power is vested in the Congress. The institutions of centralised power should make a determined effort to wipe out inappropriate behaviour that destroys democracy and violates human rights. I believe this resolution will contribute to speeding up action in support of values that are fundamental to all of us.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-222" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neelie Kroes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Sadly, Mr President, Guatemala is once again on our agenda following the horrendous murder of three El Salvador members of the Central American Parliament and their driver. The assassination in prison of the four police officers suspected of the crime provided an extraordinary example of the country’s institutional weakness. Despite genuine efforts in the last three years to reinforce the rule of law, the Government has had to recognise that insecurity and impunity were deeply rooted in Guatemala.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission, together with the Member States, has called for a rapid and independent investigation into this very serious affair. We have pressed for decisive action to strengthen the judiciary and security-related institutions. Furthermore, the Commission has reiterated the importance of establishing an International Commission against Impunity in Guatemala. This project has been in discussion for too many years. The Government’s efforts in this respect are to be commended. However, the project is still to be validated by the Constitutional Court before it can be endorsed by Congress.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission therefore welcomes the fact that this debate is on the agenda today. The European Parliament is very well placed to press its peers in Guatemala to support the much needed reforms.</p>
      <p sl="en">The visit by my colleague Commissioner Ferrero-Waldner to Guatemala in April will be an additional opportunity for such messages to be shared with the Government.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Commission will continue to stand by the people of Guatemala as it has done since the signing of a Peace Accord 10 years ago. However, for our partnership to be fully effective, the country must take decisive steps for an all-inclusive long-term security policy, addressing all the aspects involved. It should be supported by adequate national resources for the funding of the government institutions and programmes. It is now more important than ever that a consensual political commitment is made to a courageous fiscal pact, including tax increases.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is hoped that the recent events will mark a turning point in the security debate in Guatemala. As part of its new strategic framework for 2007-2013, the Commission will be ready to offer support for security-related issues as part of a ‘social cohesion and human security’ focal sector.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, the Commission will continue, together with EU Member States, to engage in EU demarches with the local authorities. The recent ratification by the Guatemala Congress of the 2003 EU-Central America Political Dialogue and Cooperation Agreement, as well as the perspective of an Association Agreement between our two regions, will allow intensified dialogue which will undoubtedly include security-related issues.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-223" speaker_id="1838" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place at the end of the debates.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem25" title="11.2. Cambodia">
    <intervention id="4-225" speaker_id="1838" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the debate on six motions for resolutions on Cambodia .</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-226" speaker_id="29579" name="Marc Tarabella" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="fr">Ladies and gentlemen, two years ago, I was already speaking about the human rights situation in Cambodia.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Two points in this joint resolution of six parliamentary groups particularly hold my attention. The first, on which I intend to focus today, is the assassination, on 24 February last, of Hy Vuthy, President of the Free Trade Union of Workers in Cambodia. This assassination is in addition to the murders, in 2004, of Chea Vichea and of Ros Sovannareth, who had been Presidents of the same Union, and in addition to the acts of intimidation and physical attacks of which other trade unionists have been victims in recent years.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The right to form a trade union is recognised in Cambodia, but incidents that have taken place recently lead one to think that this right is being flouted. It is, of course, inconceivable that people should not be able to belong freely to a trade union without having to suffer the consequences. The murder of Chea Vichea remains unexplained to this day. Born Samnang and Sok Sam Oeun have been arrested, found guilty of the murder of the trade unionist and sentenced to 20 years’ imprisonment without any proof of their guilt having been produced. Our wish is for the real perpetrators of these murders to be found and brought to justice and for Born Samnang and Sok Sam Oeun to be given a fair trial.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The second point on which I wanted to focus today is the Khmer Rouge Tribunal. During the mission that I conducted in Cambodia in April 2006, I came to realise the Cambodian citizens’ expectations in relation to this Tribunal. Now, a year after our visit, the Tribunal has still not been set up. It is vital for it to be set up without delay so that all the unpunished crimes of the Khmer Rouge are at last brought to justice.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Finally, we welcome the efforts towards stabilisation and the smooth running of the electoral process. It would seem vital for the Kingdom of Cambodia to continue its efforts and place particular emphasis on the proper functioning of the courts which, at the end of our mission last year, we deemed to be the weak link in the system.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-227" speaker_id="2229" name="Bernd Posselt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, we have been considering the situation in Cambodia regularly for years and repeatedly find severe setbacks followed by small signs of progress. At best, everything has been moving forwards with the speed and method of the Echternach dancing procession. We currently have the major problem that there are two opposite trends. On the one hand, we are grateful to find that ASEAN has at last begun to put human rights questions at least tentatively on the agenda. There is within ASEAN a gentle but nevertheless effective pressure to develop democracy and the rule of law further in Cambodia.</p>
      <p sl="de">On the other hand, however, the necessary process of setting up the Tribunal to try the horrendous crimes of the Khmer Rouge has ground to a halt. That is not necessarily the fault only of the Cambodians. The Cambodians have slowly started to move. Some sections of the international community are no longer so enthusiastic, however. This is because considerable quantities of oil have been found in Cambodia and we are now experiencing something we often have to deal with in human rights debates, namely that the Chinese and Japanese – the Chinese above all – are prepared to invest there and produce oil whatever the political conditions, ignoring questions of human rights, and that western groups – the United States of America in particular in this case – unfortunately then also join this negative race.</p>
      <p sl="de">The USA, which has been a powerful driving force behind the Tribunal up until now, is threatening to lose its zeal in this area. We Europeans certainly have the crucial task of safeguarding the economic and strategic interests of our part of the globe here, but – as we have already said in relation to Guatemala – that will not succeed in the long term if democracy, human rights and the rule of law are neglected.</p>
      <p sl="de">That is why there can only be a stable Cambodia if the country also continues to develop politically. This means putting an end to the currently prevailing state of lawlessness and impunity. The murder of the trade unionists clearly shows that they are not even trying to hide what has happened there and that no serious attempt is being made to actually find and punish the perpetrators, but that there is a prevailing climate of absolute lawlessness. We cannot accept that.</p>
      <p sl="de">There can be no economic stability without political stability and no political stability without the rule of law. This must be our clear and unequivocal message to the Cambodians.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-228" speaker_id="4508" name="Erik Meijer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="nl">Mr President, ever since the Americans invaded it during the Vietnam war, Cambodia has not managed to find its feet. Since then, relations in that country have become unyielding and extremely intolerant. Initially, with American aid, a Right-wing regime was put in power with no goal other than to sabotage China and Vietnam. This was followed by years of domination by the Khmer Rouge, which laboured under the illusion that people would become happier if city residents were forced into the country and intellectuals became farmers. This regime enjoyed Chinese backing and cost a huge number of lives.</p>
      <p sl="nl">All those intolerant regimes have transformed a traditionally relatively peaceful and tolerant society into a land of murder and violence. Even now that Cambodia is a parliamentary democracy, various political parties are carrying on this old tradition. Given the chance, they would ban each other and rule out any possibility of the others gaining power from the outset. People are being attacked while the true perpetrators get off scot-free.</p>
      <p sl="nl">It is still difficult for that country to come to terms with the crimes from the recent past. These crimes are suppressed as much as possible. In this climate, violent forms of intimidation are given free rein, something that could even culminate in the murder of people who stand up for other opinions and other interests. Recent attacks have targeted trade unionists, particularly in the clothing industry, seeming to be directed against the right of workers to organise themselves and to stand up for their interests.</p>
      <p sl="nl">It is important for Europe not to keep quiet about this, but to stand up for human rights in a consistent manner. The Council and Commission should in this respect bring their contacts with Cambodia into play and should not under any circumstances make them secondary to any economic considerations, such as oil off the coast.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-229" speaker_id="28372" name="Ryszard Czarnecki" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, there are a number of countries where trade unions are something more than mere unions. This was once the truth in my country – in Solidarity’s Poland – and is true in present-day Cambodia. A quarter of a century ago in Poland communists murdered trade unionists – just as this Cambodian trade union leader was murdered.</p>
      <p sl="pl">To date, no one has been charged with the crime, even though 10 years ago, in a special agreement signed with the European Communities, Cambodia undertook to respect human rights and democratic principles.</p>
      <p sl="pl">This is of course a part of a larger picture, which was ably described by preceding speakers. I would simply remind the House that for the last three years we, as the Union, have been calling for an anti-corruption law consisting of eight sections to be adopted in Cambodia. We must speak out loud and clear on the situation in Cambodia now, so that we do not have to do so in the future.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-230" speaker_id="4740" name="Marco Cappato" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, it appears that the Cambodian regime has a nasty habit of eliminating trade union leaders: it has already been pointed out that this is not the first time. Today, we learn of the assassination of Hy Vuthy, again in mysterious circumstances.</p>
      <p sl="it">I believe it is necessary for the European Union to make its voice heard in no uncertain terms, particularly in view of the elections due in April. We must avoid arriving at the last minute and being forced to note the irregularities that are bound to be found.</p>
      <p sl="it">Another fundamental issue is that of the tribunal for crimes committed by the Khmer Rouge: for months now, there has been a stalemate, and I believe that the European Parliament as well as the Commission and the Council must now propose a public hearing to the president of the tribunal, in order to gain a proper understanding of what the problems are that are holding up the tribunal’s work and to try to resolve them.</p>
      <p sl="it">We would like to express our solidarity, as the Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe, with our comrades in the same political family in the Sam Rainsy party – many of whose members, including 24 parliamentarians, are also members of the Transnational Non-violent Radical Party – and we also express our solidarity with the Montagnard refugees in Cambodia. I hope that this Parliament will adopt the two amendments that we, the ALDE Group, have tabled.</p>
      <p sl="it">It is true that the United States is adopting, to an increasing extent – for reasons which Mr Posselt pointed out – a policy of appeasement and good relations with the Vietnamese regime, and thus it is not highlighting with the same firmness as before the problems of the human rights of refugees. The European Union has the chance to distinguish itself in a positive way and to raise the human rights clause within the framework of the agreements with the Cambodian regime: this is a good opportunity to do so.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-231" speaker_id="23881" name="Marios Matsakis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, this is another country on which numerous European Parliament resolutions have previously been passed with, unfortunately, only limited success. Cambodia has been plagued by human rights violations of extreme proportions and severity over many decades. The nightmare period of the Khmer Rouge rule and the mass-extermination massacres of civilians are still sickeningly vivid in our minds, but even today in Cambodia respect for human rights and proper application of the rule of law are theoretical aspirations rather than applicable practical realities.</p>
      <p sl="de">The killing, on 24 February of this year, of the President of the Free Trade Union of Workers at the Suntex garment factory and the apparent immunity that seems to be afforded to the psychopathic Khmer Rouge murderers are examples of the lack of will on the part of the Cambodian authorities to take drastic action to correct the abominable situation as regards human rights abuses that still prevails in the country. It is hoped that these authorities will, on this occasion, take what the European Parliament tells them very seriously indeed.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-232" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neelie Kroes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the Commission has been closely following the situation relating to trade unions in Cambodia. The murder of Mr Hy Vuthy, who was shot dead in the early hours of 24 February while going home after a night shift in a textile factory, is the latest in a very disturbing series of attacks on trade unionists in that country. Mr Hy Vuthy is the third official of the Free Trade Union of Workers of the Kingdom of Cambodia to be killed in three years.</p>
      <p sl="en">This campaign of intimidation against trade unionists is aggravated by a weak police force and judiciary, local power struggles, political interference in the judiciary, corruption and impunity. Furthermore, the mix of fierce competition for membership, the low level of professionalism, political influence and a low degree of control over members have made for a tense atmosphere in some of the garment-manufacturing establishments.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission recently raised this issue with the Cambodian authorities to ask for a thorough inquiry into this murder and that appropriate and effective action be taken to follow up the results of the inquiry and bring to justice those responsible. The EU also called on the Cambodian Government, as a party to all major International Labour Organisation conventions, to abide by the commitments it has taken.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission has also raised, and will continue to raise, the issue of the Khmer Rouge Tribunal, and has urged the parties concerned to come to an agreement on its rules of procedure so that the trials can get under way as soon as possible. The Commission is providing EUR 1 million towards the costs of the Tribunal. A successful Khmer Rouge Tribunal will contribute significantly towards eliminating the climate of impunity in Cambodia.</p>
      <p sl="en">As recommended by Parliament in a previous resolution on Cambodia, the Commission has recently established a working party to deal with matters relating to cooperation in the areas of institution-building, administrative reform, legal and judicial reform, governance and human rights in order to engage constructively the Cambodian authorities on these issues.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to assure this House that the Commission, through its Delegation in Phnom Penh and together with the missions of EU Member States in Cambodia, will continue to monitor the situation very closely. The international community – especially the EU – which had such a vital role in the establishment of the new Cambodia, should ensure that human rights are upheld in that country.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-233" speaker_id="1838" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place at the end of the debates.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem26" title="11.3. Nigeria">
    <intervention id="4-235" speaker_id="1838" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the debate on five motions for resolutions on Nigeria .</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-236" speaker_id="2341" name="Michael Gahler" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, quite honestly I think a debate about the developing situation in Zimbabwe would be more urgent than all three topics we are debating this week. The detailed reports I am receiving are deeply distressing. That is not possible today, however, because we have limited ourselves to three topics in the urgent debate. I hope that we in the Working Group on Parliamentary Reform will abolish this self-imposed restriction for the urgent debate.</p>
      <p sl="de">So far as the situation in Nigeria is concerned, we believe it is reasonable to look at the human rights deficits as a whole, especially in the light of the forthcoming elections, and not to confine ourselves to one topic. We also believe, and have said as much, that the present Bill in Nigeria contains violations of fundamental human rights. We are against any form of discrimination on grounds of sexual orientation, and we also believe that a person’s private life is an exclusively private matter, which must not be criminalised by the state.</p>
      <p sl="de">We consider it a violation of the freedom of opinion if a person is sent to prison for advocating more liberal legislation. We believe, however, that a resolution on Nigeria must also take a stance on the other problems affecting people there as a whole, namely the widespread violence, the corruption, the immunity of those who violate human rights, the political intimidation in the run-up to the elections, possibly involving the security forces, the threat to the independence of the national electoral commission, the fact that the death penalty is still in force there, that there are still — especially in the parts of the country where sharia is practised — degrading physical punishments, and also that the problem of child labour is very much alive. Because we want to consider these points as a whole, we prefer to vote for our own resolution and not for the joint text.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-237" speaker_id="4508" name="Erik Meijer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="nl">Mr President, Nigeria is a land of diversity, peopled by many peoples with different languages and cultures. Only colonisation by the British brought them all under one national roof. Separatist movements, such as that in Biafra, were quashed with enormously superior military strength a long time ago, and that has contributed to the country’s militarisation.</p>
      <p sl="nl">A current development is that the Christian south, where European standards have managed to take hold, and which has enjoyed a relatively high degree of individual freedoms, is being subjected to the strict life rules from the traditionally isolated orthodox Islamic north. To an even greater extent than in the United States, where President Bush made unsuccessful attempts to introduce a ban in the Constitution on marriage relations between people of the same sex, attempts are being made in Nigeria to discourage homosexuality. The word ‘discourage’ is, in fact, too weak to describe what is in fact an attempt at the extermination of homosexuals.</p>
      <p sl="nl">As a consequence, not only marriages, or legal positions that are more or less equivalent, between same-sex partners are banned, but all people involved in organised pressure groups of homosexual men and lesbian women are liable to be punished for it. Rights that seem rather self-evident are at risk of being abolished in new legislation. Homosexuality will not be driven away by banning and persecution that will lead only to the justification of violence and oppression against any given section of the population.</p>
      <p sl="nl">This violence is consistent with previous attempts to sentence to death raped women who gave birth to children while unmarried. Injustice in legal form is on the march, and it must be fought against. We must make it clear to those forces in Nigeria who insist on such rules that these lead to unacceptable situations and in this case also to the further spread of venereal diseases, including AIDS. Europe should not brush this under the carpet, not even if we are keen to import Nigerian oil.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-238" speaker_id="28266" name="Sophia in 't Veld" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="nl">Mr President, I share Mr Gahler’s view that there are far more problems in Nigeria and also in other countries, but that problems are sometimes so emotive and so complex that we really need to turn the spotlight on them and that we need to make a special effort to resolve them once and for all.</p>
      <p sl="nl">The situation of homosexuals is problematic all over the world. In Nigeria, since fundamental human rights are being violated, it is really important for the European Parliament and the European Union to take the lead in the fight against the criminalisation of homosexuality. This is why I am delighted that this resolution is before us, and I hope we will draw the necessary consequences, that is to say, if Nigeria does not respond to the call of this House, we really will review our relations with it, for it is unacceptable that we should keep promoting human rights and then turn a blind eye our partners’ failure to observe them. We must be really consistent about this.</p>
      <p sl="nl">I should like to finish off by addressing a few words directly to President Obasanjo, who once received the Liberals’ Freedom Prize for his work in aid of democracy in his country, and to urge him once again to make an effort on behalf of all Nigerians, including those who are homosexual.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-239" speaker_id="28392" name="Józef Pinior" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, there is no doubt that today we should refer also to the situation in Zimbabwe, and to recent acts of repression against the political opposition in that country.</p>
      <p sl="pl">My political group is putting forward a resolution on Nigeria. The situation in Nigeria is currently being carefully monitored by us because of the so-called ‘same sex marriage prohibition act’ , which has been approved by its parliament at first and second reading. Nigeria enjoys enormous prestige and importance in Africa itself, and in the context of the contemporary global order. At the same time we are still aware that violence, infringements of civil rights, or even such violations of human rights as forced child labour and trafficking in children are commonplace in Nigeria.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The law I refer to now is causing particular concern. I would like to point out that the law does not only prohibit same sex marriages. It will also mean that even talking about the rights of different sexual minorities, and organising into clubs, societies, and cultural organisations will be punishable by detention and imprisonment.</p>
      <p sl="pl">There is no doubt that if the Nigerian Parliament passes this bill, very serious violations of human rights and civil rights in Nigeria are likely to ensue. It should be noted that in its statement of 28 January Human Rights Watch stated that this bill was an expression of homophobia.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The European Parliament must ensure that human rights, civil rights, and contemporary culture are to be respected in all countries, especially in countries that enjoy such prestige and respect as Nigeria, and which we deem to be an important point of reference in establishing the international political order.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-240" speaker_id="28139" name="Carl Schlyter" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="sv">Mr President, in spite of many problems, the situation has improved since the fall of the military dictatorship in 1999. It is odd, therefore, that a law impairing human rights is now suddenly being devised. Homosexuality is already banned and can be punished by means of everything from fines to 14-year prison sentences. We also know that, at the level of the constituent states, there is sharia law that condemns unmarried people convicted of homosexuality to 100 lashes and even imposes the death penalty on married people so convicted. Now, there is a desire to introduce a ban not only on homosexual marriages but even on being a witness to, or helping plan, such a marriage, with up to five years’ imprisonment for those convicted.</p>
      <p sl="sv">Can anyone in this House explain to me how it might fatally undermine society to witness a declaration of love between two people? I cannot understand how it could be a punishable offence. Because it is also illegal in any way to help homosexuals organise themselves, lawyers and human rights activists are also in danger of being affected, a state of affairs that makes a debate on homosexual rights impossible.</p>
      <p sl="sv">One thing that does in actual fact exist at present is sufficient tolerance of homosexuality for the largest daily newspaper, This Day , to carry contact ads for lesbians. The law banning homosexuality has nothing to do with combating the spread of AIDS, as some people maintain – the large majority of those infected are heterosexual – and even if there were in fact such a reason for this law, it would be a stupid one because settled relationships reduce the spread of infection. Given the situation, marriages between homosexuals should be encouraged and facilitated. Nigeria needs more love and kinship, and to approve laws of this type would be to begin a retreat to dictatorship and oppression. I would call on the President to abolish the law concerned.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-241" speaker_id="28377" name="Lidia Joanna Geringer de Oedenberg" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="of behalf of the PSE Group">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, I would like to draw the Commission’s attention to the bill on which we are focusing here today, and which is expected to be approved at the third and final reading before the end of the current legislature in Nigeria. The bill obviously infringes fundamental civil rights and freedoms, and it clearly discriminates against a section of the population. It may also result in increased homophobia amongst the general public.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The ban on registration of any association or group bringing together persons of a different sexual orientation, is accompanied by prison sentences for any attempt at public or even private presentation of similar content. Moreover, there is a risk that such policy will result in limiting access by LGTB individuals to medical care, and impact negatively on the effectiveness of measures against AIDS already being implemented.</p>
      <p sl="pl">In view of all this, the Member States and the Commission should take strong measures to prevent the bill in its current form from being passed by the Nigerian authorities. The European Union must also draw conclusions for the future, and place greater emphasis on the importance of the provisions prohibiting any form of discrimination in agreements signed with ACP and third countries.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-242" speaker_id="4740" name="Marco Cappato" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I think that we should answer the question from Mr Gahler, who wonders and asks us if there are more serious and more important issues outside and inside Nigeria.</p>
      <p sl="it">I believe that there are, and in this I share the opinion of my fellow Member Mrs in 't Veld, but I also believe that this resolution should be backed for two important reasons: the first is that we have the opportunity to act before something serious happens. Instead of having to chase after events for the next 15 or 20 years and lament the penalties to which this law would give rise if it were applied to thousands of individuals – as has occurred on numerous occasions in Nigeria itself, for example with death penalties – we have the opportunity, as the European Parliament, to take action in advance. I believe that this is a golden opportunity.</p>
      <p sl="it">The same might be true of the signs that President Obasanjo is yielding to radical Islamic fundamentalist pressure in the northern states. Our friendly relations, as well as harsh criticism, where necessary, could help the president to withstand a catastrophic victory by extremist fundamentalism, which in Nigeria, too, is showing signs of taking root.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-243" speaker_id="24087" name="Marcin Libicki" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the UEN Group">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, I have come across many pieces of legislation I did not approve of in this House. This is normal in political life. However, this is probably the time I have disapproved of one so very strongly. My deep disapproval is due to the incredible insincerity of the document concerned. My judgment is based upon five facts. Firstly, the European Parliament intends to interfere in the affairs of others. It actually intends to interfere in affairs that are not crime-related and not criminal, but simply legislation a sovereign state intends to adopt in order to regulate internal social matters.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Secondly, the joint resolution tabled confuses criticism of the proposed legislation with hypothetical offences that might ensue from such legislation. Thirdly, Nigeria has been conducting a dramatic struggle against AIDS. Its intention is both to limit the ways in which AIDS has been commonly spread, and sexual tourism, European sexual tourism. We want to prevent Nigeria from adopting this law on the pretext of protection against AIDS.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Fourthly, an outrageous proposal is being made. The fourth point refers to sanctions. Sanctions have not been imposed against crimes of genocide in China, Tibet, Sri Lanka and Sudan, yet we seem to be treating Nigeria as we should have treated the states that perpetrated the most serious crimes, though we failed to do so.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Fifthly, I believe it is extremely inappropriate for this matter to have been included under the item on human rights. Sixthly, I am against this joint resolution. I am going to vote in favour of the resolution tabled by the Group of the European People’s Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats. I disagree with it, but I believe that doing so will increase the chances of the original resolution, which is an affront to common sense, being rejected.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-244" speaker_id="28409" name="Raül Romeva i Rueda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="es">I disagree, Mr Libicki. This is a fundamental issue of human and fundamental rights. While in several countries of the world common sense and rationale are prevailing and laws are being adopted not just to eliminate discrimination but also to make it punishable when it is directed towards lesbians, gays, bisexuals and transsexuals, in other countries, such as Nigeria, and the United States, and even within the European Union, legislative initiatives are being promoted that represent a creep backwards. We therefore had to act.</p>
      <p sl="es">In a country in which Chapter 42, section 214 of the Criminal Code stipulates that mere sexual relations between persons, adults, of the same sex are punishable by 14 years in prison, the Nigerian Justice Ministry now intends to go somewhat further and make same-sex marriages, and the performing of such marriages, punishable by 5 years in prison.</p>
      <p sl="es">It would appear that the United Nations’ Human Rights Commission’s repeated calls for States to eliminate any law that discriminates against lesbians, gays, bisexuals and transsexuals, nor the fact that these people are entitled to exactly the same rights as heterosexual people, are not sufficient. I therefore believe that this Parliament needed to respond to this outrageous situation. It has done so, and we are pleased about that.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-245" speaker_id="23881" name="Marios Matsakis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Nigeria is a huge African country which, since the end of military dictatorship in 1999, has been struggling to accomplish modern-day democratic reforms. The forthcoming elections have once again brought issues relating to respect for human rights to the forefront of political debate. In this respect, the Africa Director of Human Rights Watch has very pertinently commented: ‘Nigeria needs leaders who will tackle the country’s appalling human rights problems.’ The issue of freedom of sexual orientation and the decriminalisation of homosexuality, albeit a sensitive one, is regarded by the developed world as important in relation to an individual’s freedom, as long as it does not infringe on other people’s freedoms.</p>
      <p sl="en">We call upon the Nigerian authorities, and in particular the Nigerian parliamentarians and senators, to bear this in mind when considering a relevant bill presently before them. This motion for a resolution should in no way be taken to mean that the homosexuality issue is regarded by the European Parliament as taking precedence over other areas of concern, such as Nigeria’s corruption epidemic or the abominable state of affairs with respect to the abusive behaviour by government security forces. Nigeria needs to remedy these areas quickly too.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-246" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neelie Kroes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the European Commission has been following the evolution of the Same-Sex Marriage (Prohibition) Act submitted early last year to the Nigerian Federal Executive Council. The Commission shares the deep concern already expressed by international organisations, including the UN, through the Secretary-General’s special representative on human rights defenders, concerning the heightened level of discrimination, violation of individual rights and restriction of the right of free association that this bill would introduce, if approved.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission equally shares the analysis by Nigerian and international human rights associations concerning the potential repercussions on persons engaging, or being suspected of engaging, in same-sex relationships. The same is true for human rights defenders advocating against the negative human rights implications of this homophobic bill. The bill would put them at greater risk of arbitrary arrest, detention, torture and ill-treatment. It would also restrict and silence the action of local human rights organisations. The bill reinforces the excessively severe provisions already in place. Nigeria’s criminal code punishes consensual homosexual conduct with up to 14 years’ imprisonment, while the shariah penal code adopted in 11 states in northern Nigeria lays down the death penalty for livat [‘sodomy’].</p>
      <p sl="en">The bill would also infringe a number of international human rights laws and treaties that Nigeria ceded to and ratified, possibly its own Constitution and key articles of the Cotonou Agreement. In view of the above and of the conclusions on EU relations with Nigeria adopted by the General Affairs and External Relations Council in 2003, the Commission would like to confirm its readiness to contribute to the implementation of the resolution this House is about to adopt. The Commission is prepared to actively participate, along with the Member States, in the political dialogue foreseen under Article 8 of the Cotonou Agreement. This political dialogue will fully address the specific issue concerning the Same-Sex Marriage Bill as well as the essential elements regarding human rights, democratic principles, the rule of law and good governance listed in Article 9 of the Cotonou Agreement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, the Commission encourages the European Parliament to follow up last year’s visit by its former President, Mr Josep Borrell Fontelles, to the Nigerian Parliament, with a view to establishing a regular dialogue between the two parliaments.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-247" speaker_id="1838" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place at the end of the debates, that is, in a moment.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem27" title="12. Voting time">
    <intervention id="4-249" speaker_id="1838" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is voting time.</p>
      <a text="(For details of the outcome of the vote: see Minutes)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem28" title="12.1. Guatemala (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-252" speaker_id="23881" name="Marios Matsakis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, a couple of small but important wording errors have managed to creep into the resolution. I propose to correct them as follows: in recital B, to replace the word ‘authors’ with the word ‘perpetrators’, and in recital C, to replace the words ‘intellectual authors’ with the word ‘instigators’.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-253" speaker_id="1838" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Are there any objections to the inclusion of these oral amendments?</p>
      <a text="(The oral amendments were accepted)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem29" title="12.2. Cambodia (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem30" title="12.3. Nigeria (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem31" title="12.4. The attack on Galina Kozlova, member of the board of the Mari national organisation Mari Ušem and editor of the literary magazine Ontšõko (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-257" speaker_id="1838" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">That concludes the vote.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem32" title="13. Explanations of vote">
    <intervention id="4-260" speaker_id="28276" name="Laima Liucija Andrikienė" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, when I spoke during the discussion on the Galina Kozlova case, I expressed my gratitude to our colleagues from the PPE-DE Group Mr Kelam, Mr Landsbergis and Mr Tannock for initiating that resolution. I was informed later that the original initiative came from our Estonian colleague Mr Savi from the ALDE Group. I should therefore like to express my respect and gratitude to him.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-261" speaker_id="24087" name="Marcin Libicki" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">On Nigeria, I voted in favour of the resolution tabled by the Group of the European People’s Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats. I do not consider it a good one, but I believe that adopting the joint resolution tabled by the Left would bring far more discredit on the House. I believe the resolution tabled by the Group of the European People’s Party is a better way forward.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-262" speaker_id="1838" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">I would remind you that there are no explanations of vote concerning emergency matters.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-263" speaker_id="28300" name="Zbigniew Zaleski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, I would just like to add a word to what Mr Libicki said: the Group of the European People’s Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats’s motion was not the result of a compromise.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-264" speaker_id="1838" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">That concludes the explanations of vote.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Before closing the sitting, I have some more announcements to make.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem33" title="14. Decisions concerning certain documents: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem34" title="15. Membership of committees and delegations: see Minutes">
    <intervention id="4-265" speaker_id="23881" name="Marios Matsakis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, as you have to read six pages of names, in order to save time and to save you from the embarrassment of having to pronounce very strange names, can we take those names as having been read, rather than you actually reading them?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-266" speaker_id="1838" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">It is very kind of you, Mr Matsakis, to wish to spare me this tedious work. Unfortunately, our Rules of Procedure are clear: I must read out the entire list of names.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">At the end of the notice on the membership of committees and delegations</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-271" speaker_id="23881" name="Marios Matsakis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to request a roll-call vote.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-272" speaker_id="1838" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">It is your absolute right, but a request should have been tabled within the prescribed time. I cannot, therefore, follow it up.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem35" title="16. Communication of Council common positions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem36" title="17. Written statements for entry in the register (Rule 116): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem37" title="18. Forwarding of texts adopted during the sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem38" title="19. Dates for next sittings: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem39" title="20. Adjournment of the session">
    <intervention id="4-277" speaker_id="1838" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">We have come to the end of our agenda, and I declare the session of the European Parliament adjourned.</p>
      <a text="(The sitting was closed at 5.05 p.m.)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
</text>
