<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20080508.EN" lang="en" date="2008-05-08" place="Brussels" edition="OJ edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Opening of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Framework for the activities of lobbyists in the EU institutions (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-007" speaker_id="1405" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report by Alexander Stubb, replaced by Ingo Friedrich, on behalf of the Committee on Constitutional Affairs, on the framework for the activities of lobbyists in the EU institutions (2007/2115(INI)) (A6-0105/2008).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-008" speaker_id="1264" name="Ingo Friedrich" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, the background is as follows. With the Lisbon Treaty, the European Parliament's powers will substantially increase again, and in view of this increase in powers, it is particularly important for us to carry out a precise analysis of the legislative process once more. As we do so, we see that interest representatives – or lobbyists, as they are often called – also play a very significant role in Brussels. We estimate that there are as many as 15 000 interest representatives working in Brussels, of which 5 000 are already registered with the European Parliament.</p>
      <p sl="de">Our task, then, is to establish a framework in which lobbying activities can be conducted in a fair and acceptable way. Parliament has maintained its own quasi-obligatory register of lobbyists from as long ago as 1996, as well as a very precise code of conduct. The task now is to see whether a similar arrangement can be achieved for all the European institutions. The contents of the report to be voted on today therefore represent an important step towards more transparency: in other words, towards the provision of accurate information about who has participated as a lobbyist – an interest representative – in the development of European legislation, how they have done so, and in which areas.</p>
      <p sl="de">Secondly, we wish to establish ethical and moral standards governing these lobbying activities. Thirdly, there must be proper safeguards in place to ensure the independence of the political decision-making process in Parliament and the Commission. Lobbying activities must be removed from the grey area, as it were, so that we have a clear and factual picture of where influence is genuinely being brought to bear. We have therefore introduced the following elements into the report, which are new features compared with the previous situation: firstly, a relatively wide-ranging definition of what lobbying means, or what it is, namely 'activities carried out with the objective of influencing the policy formulation and decision-making processes of the EU institutions'.</p>
      <p sl="de">The second new feature is the introduction of a 'legislative footprint'. This would mean that when a new directive is deliberated and adopted in a parliamentary committee, the committee secretariat would annex a page to the document listing which associations had participated in the debate and whether they did so in the framework of a public hearing or other type of meeting. This list should also help the interest groups themselves to see who was involved in the process, and who did not wish, or was unable, to participate.</p>
      <p sl="de">Thirdly, our aim is to establish a common register for interest representatives in the EU institutions. It remains to be seen whether this really will happen with the Commission and Parliament. We intend to set up a working group to look at this issue. It would of course be easier for all lobbyists if we could get a kind of 'one-stop shop' where they could register and sign up to indicate that they intend to comply with the rules. That is the aim, but as the rapporteur, I must say that I am not certain at this stage whether we really will get a common register. At any rate, the registers need to be linked up so that it is a straightforward process, in terms of the bureaucracy involved, to set up this common register. Paragraph 21 also talks about the requirement of financial disclosure, which would be an entirely new element. We also talk about the option of sanctions which should apply to lobbyists who breach the code of conduct. Here, we have to consider what kind of sanctions we want. The Greens' idea is to have a black list, but in my view, this is reminiscent of a pillory in the Middle Ages. Black lists are really not appropriate in a democracy. What we would want instead is for inclusion in the register to confer such a high degree of prestige that serious-minded associations will want their name to appear in the European institutions' official register. It must be a prestigious and desirable aspiration, not only because they are then issued with a pass to grant access to the institutions' premises, but also because inclusion in the register would be sought-after in its own right, signifying that the association concerned is recognised as an important and useful interlocutor which is taken seriously enough by the institutions to warrant inclusion in the register. In the event of misconduct, the association would be struck from the register and the pass would be withdrawn: that would be the sanction.</p>
      <p sl="de">Yes, I will be as brief as possible. It is important that church organisations should not be defined as lobbyists. I am very disappointed by Amendment 3. Mrs in 't Veld from the Liberal Group has said that churches should be lobbyists. That really would run counter to everything we have agreed in Parliament to date. According to the Treaties, the churches are partners for our institutions, but they are not lobbyists.</p>
      <p sl="de">Overall, my assessment is that this is a major step forward towards a situation which is more transparent, correct and fair. I hope that we will thus set an example that can be followed around the world, showing how lobbying can and should be taken seriously.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-009" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Siim Kallas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I am really glad to attend this plenary session where your discussion on the European Transparency Initiative will come to a conclusion. I have been following your debates and have participated in your debates in different committees. I am convinced that the report as it stands is a real step forward to improving transparency in the European decision-making process.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission welcomes the positive reaction of the European Parliament to its suggestion to consider an interinstitutional approach for a register and a code of conduct for interest representatives, who think that such a one-stop shop for registration would best serve the purpose of enhancing transparency, while avoiding an unnecessary administrative burden. I think that your report is an excellent starting point for discussions in the future interinstitutional working group that you suggest.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to underline one point. The European Commission is convinced that the activities of interest representatives are legitimate and offer valuable input in the decision-making process, but things have to happen in a transparent manner. This is why the European Transparency Initiative aims at opening what is too often perceived as a black box. Citizens, stakeholders, decision-makers and the public at large can then form their own views of what is going on in Brussels.</p>
      <p sl="en">When I look at what information Parliament and the Commission expect registrants to disclose, I observe that, here again, we largely agree. The Commission considers that it is important to know who the interest representatives are, what interests they represent and against what financial background. It goes without saying that non-respect of the rules of the code of conduct must be followed by sanctions. Sanctions would mean suspension or even withdrawal from the register.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission announced that it would launch its European Transparency Initiative Register in spring 2008. I can assure you that we expect to meet this deadline. Having recently talked to the services, I expect the register to open in six weeks’ time. We have also decided that the register is a pilot project and that we shall review it after one year, which means in early summer 2009. The European Commission is ready for discussions with Parliament and the Council of Ministers, as well as the two consultative committees, in working towards the development of a shared system.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-010" speaker_id="1882" name="José Javier Pomés Ruiz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="draftsman of the opinion of the Committee on Budgetary Control">
      <p sl="es">Firstly, Mr President, it is a shame that the Finnish Foreign Minister, Alexander Stubb, is not here today as he contributed so much in the Committee on Budgetary Control and to this report.</p>
      <p sl="es">I am here to give the opinion of the Committee on Budgetary Control. Following on from the final words of Commissioner Kallas, I would stress once again that the role of the Members of the European Parliament is to remain in as close contact as possible with all citizens – with interest representatives and with non-interest representatives – and that this Parliament therefore has to have its own rules. My office is open to anyone wanting to have a coffee with me or invite me for a walk. I cannot demand that people are registered in a special register. I cannot tell someone who is not registered that I cannot receive them in my party, the Unión del Pueblo Navarro . I cannot say ‘you must be registered’. No, indeed: administration is one thing, but the political function of this Parliament is something else entirely.</p>
      <p sl="es">We would therefore do well to have two ways of ensuring transparency. I was the rapporteur on transparency, that great project which has brought Commissioner Kallas here. Transparency must not prevent our contact with real life, with interest representatives or non-interest representatives.</p>
      <p sl="es">Thank you. I am sure that Commissioner Kallas understands this.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-011" speaker_id="1985" name="Pervenche Berès" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="draftsman of the opinion of the Committee on Economic and Monetary Affairs">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, Commissioner, I am in a paradoxical situation, as has happened on a number of occasions, for example when the rapporteur, Mr Pistelli, who was in the vanguard of what will undoubtedly be the European Parliament’s position on transparency, was unfortunately disregarded by our committee. I am therefore delighted with what I am sure will be our final result today. It is impossible to imagine the markets functioning properly with transparency being anything other than the fundamental rule. We, the legislators, must apply that rule to ourselves, particularly as we know all too well that in our legislative process – and I say this to the previous speaker – our relations with external representatives, be they pressure groups or religious organisations – and that is directed at Mr Friedrich – play a decisive role in our European legislative process. It is our duty to set an example in this area, including going as far as ensuring the systematic use of this idea of a ‘legislative footprint’, which I think would be extremely beneficial.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-012" speaker_id="4432" name="Claude Turmes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="draftsman of the opinion of the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, without transparency, there can be no European democracy. Brussels already has a reputation for allowing the major corporations to call the shots and pull the strings. That is dangerous for the European project, and it is an issue which is of great concern to me on a personal level and to the Greens as a whole. As the European Parliament, we therefore have a responsibility to show our hand to voters in the run-up to the next European elections. We have a good report in front of us, but there are dark forces at work and they want to suppress two of its core elements.</p>
      <p sl="de">Firstly, they want to prevent financial transparency. Without financial transparency, we can never be sure who is really behind the campaigns. I am astonished to find that it is actually the Socialist Group which is opposed to financial transparency and is thus undermining one of these core elements. As for the second core element which is being undermined, there are people in Parliament who assume that lawyers should not be regarded as lobbyists, even if they are not defending people in court, but instead are trying to pull strings to influence legislation in Europe.</p>
      <p sl="de">Let me quote from the website of a law firm in Brussels. It says that because we are not currently regarded as lobbyists under this legislation,</p>
      <p sl="de">‘Therefore lobbying by lawyers will be more and more effective and goals are more likely to be achieved with legal support. Alber &amp; Geiger as a law firm exclusively specialised on lobbying and government relations will be at your side to assist you in reaching your goals within the EU.’</p>
      <p sl="de">As you see, even the law firms themselves are admitting that they are lobbyists. Ladies and gentlemen, that is unacceptable. If we allow that to happen, we will undermine our own credibility.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-015" speaker_id="4544" name="Diana Wallis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Draftsman of the opinion of the Committee on Legal Affairs . − Mr President, the Committee on Legal Affairs was very supportive of the Commission’s initiative and of the rapporteur’s stance. I think we supported without question that there should also be a coordinated approach between all the institutions. But, having said that, we would wish to emphasise the particular openness of this institution as a democratic decision-making body; further, that lobbyists should be treated equally. In that sense, in the longer term, we would want to move towards a mandatory register where everybody is treated equally.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to return, if I may, to the issue of lawyers as lobbyists, which Mr Turmes has just raised. There is an issue here, and I would ask everybody to have careful regard to the very nuanced definition that the Committee on Legal Affairs gave in relation to when is a lawyer a lawyer, and when is a lawyer a lobbyist? That definition was very carefully thought through, and I would ask that that is the one that be taken into consideration.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-016" speaker_id="37676" name="Søren Bo Søndergaard" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="draftsman of the opinion of the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs">
      <p sl="da">Mr President, the report that we are considering here is a good one. It is a step in the right direction – not a big step, but a step nonetheless. There is also a need for action, not because all lobbying is harmful, or because all lobbyists are evil, but because it is completely unacceptable that lobbyism has such a major influence without there being any binding rules in place on maximum openness in the area. Lobbyists have a major influence within the EU system. This is apparent from the sums that are spent on lobbying and from the number of lobbyists around.</p>
      <p sl="da">However, the report could be better and the controls on lobbyists could be strengthened if you were to adopt the amendment proposal, which is partly an extension of the statement from the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs. We must have a mandatory common register, which ensures full clarity and full transparency with regard to the amount of money that is being spent on lobbying. We must have a register and an ethical code of conduct for all lobbyists, including legal companies carrying out lobbying, that can enter into force before the elections in 2009. We must have effective controls and visible sanctions to be imposed on those who breach the adopted rules.</p>
      <p sl="da">However, it is also a matter of looking inwards. It takes two to tango. We are therefore proposing that lobbyists must be obliged to disclose the same information on expenses for an individual member that that individual member is obliged to disclose in his or her financial declaration. A little more control over ourselves would not harm our reputation amongst the electorate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-017" speaker_id="4540" name="Philip Bradbourn" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, this House should welcome all initiatives which increase the transparency of the EU institutions, which is why I support the proposals before us today.</p>
      <p sl="de">However, we must ensure that the nature of the work of each institution is also taken into account. Parliament to this end works in a wholly different way to the Council and at a different stage in the legislative process from the Commission. Taking this into account, a common single register for all institutions would, I believe, be very difficult to achieve and would in fact put in place an over-bureaucratic procedure for applying for access when lobbying only the Parliament. We are also an autonomous institution and I do not feel it is therefore appropriate for other institutions to dictate our policies in this area.</p>
      <p sl="de">I would also like to raise an issue which has previously been brought up in this Chamber by a number of colleagues: how NGOs, in particular, are financed by the Commission and, in turn, use this money to lobby MEPs into taking certain positions. If the end result of what we are debating is to increase transparency, the House must be provided with a certain amount of non-commercially-sensitive data on how these organisations who lobby us are financed.</p>
      <p sl="de">On a more general note, I express concern at the free access that some lobbyists have to Members’ office floors in this Parliament. Once in the building, people are freely able to walk around and have unrestricted access to private offices. Having the right to freely roam the building does nothing for transparency, but leads to malpractice by some individuals. I am sure Members have all experienced this. In many of our national parliaments, there are central lobby areas where lobbyists who have appointments can be greeted and escorted to Members’ office areas. We should, in my view, try to implement a similar system. Overall, I am pleased to see Parliament addressing the issue of transparency, but we must also ensure that the organisations who lobby us are just as transparent as we are.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-018" speaker_id="1973" name="Carlos Carnero González" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PSE Group">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, firstly, on behalf of the Socialist Group, I must say that I support the report we are debating this morning and will very likely adopt later on in plenary.</p>
      <p sl="es">I believe this represents a major step towards transparency and control in an area which is undoubtedly surrounded by a great deal of myth. Lobbyists are not bad or good by definition; it depends on how they act and on how they are controlled.</p>
      <p sl="es">I must say that we Socialists have been at the forefront, right from the start, in reinforcing transparency and control and, as a result, democracy with regard to lobbyists.</p>
      <p sl="es">Mr Turmes, it seems that you have a fixation with the Socialist Group. Focus on other groups. I wonder, did the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety decide, in its opinion, to criticise the Socialist Group? You are speaking on behalf of the Committee on the Environment. I would ask you to please give your opinions on other groups when you are speaking on your own behalf and not when you are speaking on behalf of a committee.</p>
      <p sl="es">We believe that the definition of lobbyists contained in the report is correct, although we should like more differentiation. Profit-making private companies are clearly not the same thing as non-governmental organisations or trade union federations.</p>
      <p sl="es">However, the footprint is legislative. The common and mandatory register and code of conduct, the corresponding sanctions and financial disclosure are key issues which are correctly included in this report.</p>
      <p sl="es">I would also draw your attention, Mr Turmes, to the fact that you insist that we Socialists are against financial disclosure, when some of your group’s amendments set limits on this financial disclosure, whereas we do not want any limits.</p>
      <p sl="es">We also want entry into force before the 2009 European elections and for the planned working group to complete its deliberations before the end of 2008.</p>
      <p sl="es">Do you know, for example, that the Socialist Group will support two of your amendments in this respect? You must be unaware of this.</p>
      <p sl="es">Myth and reality are being mixed up in this issue, but we Socialists, having been at the forefront of the fight for transparency and control, are not going to allow anyone to perpetrate a false myth that we have a hidden agenda. We have an open agenda which involves the citizens and transparency in the European Union.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-019" speaker_id="28314" name="Anneli Jäätteenmäki" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="fi">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, the increase in the power of the European Parliament under the Lisbon Treaty will put pressure on the aim of greater openness in legislative work. It is vitally important that the work of the EU is transparent and that the public knows who has had a say in the content of laws. The purpose of registration is not to restrict or hamper the work of lobbyists. Their work is important. The current system of registering lobbyists in the European Parliament is more, however, and above all, a matter of security rather than one of openness.</p>
      <p sl="fi">The report by the Committee on Constitutional Affairs has changed a good deal since the first drafts presented by the previous rapporteur, now the Finnish Foreign Affairs Minister Alexander Stubb. I am particularly pleased, as is my group, that the report’s wording is now a lot more forceful than it was initially and that the mandatory system of registration that my group supports is to come into being, because it establishes impartiality.</p>
      <p sl="fi">I would like to refer to Amendment 3, which has already been discussed here. Some of the Members in my group support it, but as the current rapporteur said, and I am with him on this, churches are not lobbyists. On this matter my group is divided and it will probably vote two ways.</p>
      <p sl="fi">The report by the Committee on Constitutional Affairs proposes that the rapporteur may attach a list to his or her report of the registered interest representatives who were consulted during the preparation of the report. I hope in future this will be made an official practice. It would cause rapporteurs to listen objectively to the various points of view expressed. This way it might also come to light if someone was eating directly out of another’s hand.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-020" speaker_id="28372" name="Ryszard Czarnecki" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the UEN Group">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, I am glad to have the opportunity of taking the floor after the former President of Finland as we debate a report by the current Finnish Foreign Minister, Mr Stubb, who was until recently a Member of this House. The Lord does seem to move in mysterious way where Members are concerned!</p>
      <p sl="pl">The latest report by NGOs indicates that lobbyists’ influence on the European Commission’s decision-making process has become a serious problem. For example, lobbyists hold a significant number of experts’ posts in various bodies close to the European Commission. Five thousand lobbyists out of the 15 000 operating in Brussels have access to the European Parliament. These 5 000 need to operate according to very clear rules. The proposal to set up a common register of lobbyists is a good idea, as is the threat of sanctions. It is high time our electorate knew who the lobbyists are. Voters are entitled to know how lobbyists are financed, and which of them attempted to influence certain reports in various ways. This report is a step in the right direction. It is an attempt to regulate a situation that already exists.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-021" speaker_id="4254" name="Monica Frassoni" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, for the Greens/European Free Alliance Group the watchword on the ex-Stubb report is transparency. There is undoubtedly a tendency – and we have heard from some of its exponents here – to underestimate, probably in good faith, the effects and effectiveness of lobbyists' work, possibly in ways that none of us can even imagine as serious Members who operate in good faith and are decent and respectful of others. The facts are clear and keep coming to light daily: for example, we have known for a few weeks now that 34 officials within the Commission are being paid directly by private firms.</p>
      <p sl="it">Some recent research has found that most of the Groups – with the exception of just one, my own, but probably others too – that most of the amendments they tabled on REACH originated from a lobby. Furthermore, it emerges that some of the officials assisting Members with their work in certain committees are or have been employed by firms and are now working for us as national experts; Members are obviously unaware of this.</p>
      <p sl="it">In our opinion, therefore, the work we are doing today does not put an end to the issue of lobbies, and I do not believe that the work of Commissioner Kallas ends with the report we are adopting today. That is why we have emphatically backed all the amendments and all the work done by everyone – including the Socialist Group, the GUE/NGL Group and the Liberal Group – on those amendments and texts aimed at improving the situation and enhancing transparency.</p>
      <p sl="it">However, there are still some problems concerning the Stubb report which we hope can be resolved at the vote. The first relates to lawyers: when lawyers work with us and seek to influence legislation they are lobbyists, even when giving a legal opinion. We hope that this amendment will be rejected.</p>
      <p sl="it">Next, there is obviously the question of determining when this code of conduct should enter into force. It absolutely has to do so before the forthcoming European elections, because otherwise we will be starting off another term, another excessively long period of time.</p>
      <p sl="it">Finally, Mr President, I really do not think that this question of lobbying can be settled by stating that we dislike it, or by criminalising lobbies. In our opinion the problem with transparency is finding out whom we are dealing with, what they are doing and who is paying them: that is, the issue of financial disclosure. The report perhaps does not yet make all of this absolutely clear, but it can be clarified, and here I agree with Mr Carnero about the tasks of the working group which is to be set up.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-022" speaker_id="1849" name="Sylvia-Yvonne Kaufmann" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, of course lobbyists should not be made a scapegoat. Of course it is perfectly legitimate, in a thriving democracy, for the various groups in society to represent their interests and concerns pro-actively and bring these interests to bear on social processes. It is also entirely legitimate for them to address these issues to the men and women in the institutions which prepare and take the decisions. Indeed, as legislators, we have a duty to inform ourselves as fully and accurately as possible before taking decisions on any legislative initiative that we are dealing with, and take account of the concerns of stakeholders with all their conflicting views. It is also clear, however, that transparency is essential to ensure the fair representation of interests, and is crucial for the European Union's credibility. That is why our Group believes that the three institutions must at last set clear rules which must apply to all interest representatives. In our view, this is long overdue.</p>
      <p sl="de">We have a duty to demonstrate very clearly to our citizens that the European institutions are not acting as accessories to 'dark forces'. Lobbyists should therefore be required to disclose publicly whose interests they represent, what their objectives are, and above all, where they get their funding from.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-023" speaker_id="1275" name="Jens-Peter Bonde" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the IND/DEM Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, Parliament’s working group on reform has been in Washington to study the US Congress.</p>
      <p sl="de">We saw how all lobbyists have to register their function and their income from their different clients. It is mandatory in the US and Canada and not voluntary, as the Commission proposes. We also saw how each member of Congress documented their budget, including every paid cup of coffee. If they can do it, why cannot we? Why cannot we be fully transparent with our secretarial allowances in the EP, and then demand transparency in the other institutions?</p>
      <p sl="de">At the last meeting of the Conference of Presidents we became aware of organised lobbyism in our own House. In a very big and nice room on the fifth floor of the Spinelli building, 28 multinational companies have their own office, the telephone numbers and e-mail addresses paid for by Parliament. This may be a very good scheme linking companies to MEPs, but no one presented this proposal for us; it was established behind our backs.</p>
      <p sl="de">The views of the small and medium-sized companies are missing; the views of the consumers, trade unions, green organisations are missing. It may be a good idea to rent facilities to lobbyists, but then everyone should be invited and an elected board could supervise the activities.</p>
      <p sl="de">Multinational companies are not those who most need our financial support. Support for the scheme has been hand-picked and not elective from the political groups. This is the latest lobbyist scandal I hope you will redress.</p>
      <p sl="de">This is my last political speech in the European Parliament. If I may have one wish, it will be for the adoption of the proposal from the Convention signed by 23 governments and every single member from the national parliaments, every MEP except one: make all documents and meetings open unless you decide a grounded derogation. This simple proposal will also solve most problems that bias lobbyism.</p>
      <p sl="de">We would then be able to see what they write to us or to the Commission and we would take part in the decisions on derogations from transparency, so we would know what is hidden from us and why. We need the lobbyists to raise and improve the laws. We need their knowledge and advice and counter-arguments from other interests. We need balanced or pluralist information since we were elected to serve all citizens equally.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-024" speaker_id="1405" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Thank you, Mr Bonde. I am sure you have the best wishes of many colleagues in your retirement.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">We may not always agree with what you say, but you are always worth listening to.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-025" speaker_id="28255" name="Andreas Mölzer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, it is no secret that we live in a European Union in which events are bypassing citizens and increasingly benefiting the major companies. This is undoubtedly due, first and foremost, to the influence of lobbyists in Parliament, the Commission and the Council. Who would be surprised to hear, then, that the Alpine-Adriatic Convention which is so unpopular with the freight lobby is still not being implemented? Who would be surprised to hear that more and more small and medium-sized enterprises are being forced to throw in the towel because they are snowed under with paperwork and regulations, and because they are literally being starved of any support from the funding opportunities available, while industry giants – the multinationals – understand only too well how to exploit these opportunities and, grasshopper-like, constantly relocate from one Member State to another, leaving a trail of devastated jobs in their wake?</p>
      <p sl="de">Let us take the debate and the decision-making process on the much-discussed and contentious topic of the REACH draft legislation, which aims to improve safe use of chemicals, as an example: if citizens hear that out of 132 proposed amendments, 32 were identical and were accompanied by written recommendations from the chemical industry associations, if citizens hear this, they will of course steadily lose faith in Europe, and they will have the feeling that European policy-making is simply there to do the multinationals' bidding.</p>
      <p sl="de">If we want to prevent that, if we want to curb the growing Euro-scepticism, we must achieve a situation in which it is clear who is influencing decision-making in Europe, who is lobbying on behalf of donors and who these donors are, and who is seeking to bring influence to bear on the legislative process.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-026" speaker_id="2206" name="Reinhard Rack" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, number one: we congratulate Alexander Stubb on his elevation to Foreign Minister in Finland. Number two: we congratulate Ingo Friedrich and thank him for taking over the report and, hopefully, bringing it to a good end this afternoon. Number three: we support the concept and the direction of the Stubb/Friedrich report. But …</p>
      <p sl="de">I will now continue in German. After this twofold tribute to Alexander Stubb, a 'but' is necessary. It is good to have rules on lobbying, but in Parliament, we already have good rules, and I am not entirely sure that this attempt to achieve a combined arrangement is really a wise move. Transparency is a good thing, but it cannot work miracles, especially if it is essentially piecemeal in nature.</p>
      <p sl="de">Registration and disclosure of the financial interests of registered lobbyists are all very well, but what about the numerous letter-writers, experts, and our other contacts? How should we deal with them? Will we expect them all of them to be registered in future, and to disclose their financial interests? I do hope not!</p>
      <p sl="de">Then there are the exceptions: in particular, two exceptions are proposed in two of the amendments which certainly do not promote transparency. Amendment 3 has already been mentioned. The aim is to bring about a situation in which the churches will be deemed to be official lobbyists. In my view, this is not about transparency; it is simply the reflection of an anti-clerical attitude, and we should say 'no' to that.</p>
      <p sl="de">A similar attempt is made in Amendment 10, namely to achieve an arrangement, via an exception to the exception, which also does not serve the matter at hand. In reality, this is simply an attempt to penalise certain sectors. We should ensure that we have a transparent system and that we improve it. However, we should not assume from the outset that this now represents a major change compared with the current situation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-028" speaker_id="2309" name="Richard Corbett" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, we can be proud of the fact that the European Parliament in many ways is already at the forefront when compared to some national parliaments in terms of how we handle these issues. We already have a register of interests. We have a code of conduct for lobbyists, and we have an absolute prohibition on Members of Parliament receiving gifts. That is good. What the issue is here is whether we can extend this system to cover the other institutions. We are willing to embark on negotiations to attempt to do so, to try and reach agreement – because that would be better – and, secondly, whether we can upgrade the requirements and be even more at the forefront of openness and transparency.</p>
      <p sl="en">My group supports the report, which attempts to do that. We also support many of the amendments which would improve the report and would indeed increase the transparency requirements. We are even supporting some of the amendments from the Green Group, but not an amendment which would actually limit the way it is written and would actually set a ceiling on the transparency requirement.</p>
      <p sl="en">So I was somewhat astonished to hear the spokesman of the Committee on the Environment attack the Socialist Group for being less transparent than the Greens, when in fact the Greens have an amendment which, if you read it literally, would actually put a ceiling on the transparency requirement. That is the position of our group. We are at the forefront of openness and transparency on this, and we do resent unwarranted attacks on our position by groups who are trying to portray themselves in public opinion as being the champions of all this, ahead of everybody else, when they are not.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-029" speaker_id="28457" name="Luca Romagnoli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I agree that there needs to be a compulsory register, a register accompanied by a code of conduct for lobbyists, but it should apply to all the institutions and above all, if I may say so, to the Commission. It is obviously vital that the code of ethical behaviour should lay down sanctions in the case of impropriety and make financial disclosure mandatory. These records should be easy to access and available for consultation via the internet; that would be ideal.</p>
      <p sl="it">The Friedrich report recognises that there are thousands of lobbyists seeking to influence the institutions' decisions, even though it should be acknowledged, all things considered, that in many instances they do provide MEPs with detailed information on various aspects of the measures under discussion. Personally, as those who know me will confirm, I am highly unlikely to be influenced by anyone at all. Notwithstanding that, in order to guarantee independent decision-making and oversee activities which are often geared to influencing the allocation of Community funds as well as the monitoring and implementation of legislation, rigorous ethical criteria must be scrupulously applied. I shall therefore vote in favour of the Friedrich report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-030" speaker_id="1186" name="Astrid Lulling" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, in order to clear up certain misunderstandings and correct the populist statements made by some Members here and in the press, I wish to point out, too, in my capacity as a Quaestor, that the European Parliament has had rules to govern our relations with lobbyists for 12 years. These rules, set out in Rule 9(4) of the Rules of Procedure – which would be worth reading at least once! – stipulate that access to the European Parliament for lobbyists is controlled, regulated by access badges. In order to obtain a badge, lobbyists must fill out an accreditation form and provide a character reference and a letter signed by the police. The European Parliament keeps a register of all lobbyists, which is published on the European Parliament’s website. Accredited lobbyists must also comply with a code of conduct. Mrs Frassoni and others are thus stating the obvious. Any infringement of this code is punished by withdrawal of the lobbyist’s badge and exclusion from the register.</p>
      <p sl="fr">As regards the proposal for a single register, I do not think that there is any need for such a register with the Commission since the European Parliament and the Commission operate in completely different ways and, consequently, have different relationships with lobbyists. In the interest of the separation of powers at European level, Parliament must at all costs continue to be the sole body responsible for its Rules of Procedure. The Commission can copy our excellent system but we must have the last word when it comes to our own Rules. The report adopts a cautious approach to this register and I agree with that.</p>
      <p sl="fr">As regards financial disclosure, I do not see why accredited lobbyists should have to provide detailed financial information indicating the source of their funding and the allocation of these resources. Such a measure would be totally impracticable and counterproductive. I am also of the opinion that the scope of the lobbying is not always reflected in the financial means. An organisation’s good reputation and level of expertise are also crucial. I fully subscribe to the description of lobbying provided in recital D of the report. I must pay tribute to our former colleague, Alexander Stubb, with whom I did a lot of work on this issue, and I want to distance myself completely from the sweeping accusations made by the Greens who have spoken in this debate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-031" speaker_id="1405" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">I long ago learnt it is not worth trying to stop Mrs Lulling from speaking.</p>
      <a text="(Laughter)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-032" speaker_id="4262" name="Jo Leinen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, the longer our esteemed colleague Mrs Lulling spoke for, the more points she offered for attack. The committee would like to have a common system in place in Brussels, because citizens do not make a distinction between Parliament, the Commission and the Council. To them, it is just Brussels; it is the EU! I think that a common system would be good, and, Mr Kallas, we appeal to you to allow the working group to convene swiftly after today's debate and to draw up common rules which would still leave the individual institution the requisite autonomy to make its own decisions.</p>
      <p sl="de">I would also like the Council to be involved. The Council is a legislative body, just as we are, and of course lobbying plays a part in its ranks too. For that reason, the call to participate in this initiative goes out to the Council as well.</p>
      <p sl="de">Overall, we want a new system of transparency – a new culture of transparency – in Brussels, so that we can thus demonstrate openness and build confidence. Lobbying is good, and representation of interests must of course take place, but the rules must be clear. It must be a fair and honest process. We must ensure, above all, that it is not about selling opinions.</p>
      <p sl="de">With today's decision, we are taking a major step forward; that is beyond question. However, there is still a great deal of work to be done, because the devil is in the detail, for example on questions such as: who is a lobbyist? The definition which we have provided in the report is very broad. In essence, we are saying that a lobbyist is anyone who wants to influence us. Nonetheless, there are exceptions. The municipalities, the regions, the social partners, the political parties: all of these are institutions which are enshrined in the Treaties. They are involved in lobbying as well, but they are not defined as lobbyists in our system. We will have to define the boundaries for lawyers and the churches as well. These are questions which have yet to be resolved.</p>
      <p sl="de">In my view, financial disclosure is important, Mrs Lulling. This is the new step forward which has been lacking until now. Money is not everything, but money is used to achieve a great deal. It is time to start work, and I would like to thank Mr Stubb and Mr Friedrich and, indeed, everyone else who has made a contribution to this process so far.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-033" speaker_id="39318" name="Costas Botopoulos" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, I think the topic we are discussing today is extremely interesting. I should say that for once the European Parliament is showing the way on an issue not discussed at all in our national parliaments, least of all in the Greek Parliament, and one to which no solution has been found.</p>
      <p sl="el">There are three important political problems involved here. Firstly, how do we deal with the issue? Are we afraid of the way informal lobbyists go about their business or are we trying to operate transparently?</p>
      <p sl="el">I believe we must do as follows. We must operate transparently; we should not be afraid of the lobbyists or of their existence, and we should lay down some rules.</p>
      <p sl="el">Secondly, how is transparency best achieved? The answer is with very strict rules, regulating even sums of money, or in a general compulsory framework. I must emphasise here that this register could very usefully be mandatory and shared by all three EU institutions.</p>
      <p sl="el">Thirdly, we are talking about groups operating informally, but within an institutional process. It is crucial to distinguish between different types of lobbyists. Greenpeace and Shell have nothing in common when they act as lobbyists. That is why this distinction is essential, at least in the register.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-034" speaker_id="28173" name="Zita Pleštinská" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="sk">Lobbying is a legitimate part of every democratic system. Wherever democracy is not to be anarchy, clear rules must also apply to lobbying.</p>
      <p sl="sk">American lobbyists consider their law to be too strict; on the other hand, in the new Member States, no rules exist, to the point where people often think of lobbying as having negative undertones. Therefore the new EU model should be somewhere between these extremes.</p>
      <p sl="sk">My view is that the proposal to establish a common interinstitutional system for the mandatory registration of EU lobbyists, the disclosure of financial background and the ‘legislative footprint’ will contribute to the transparency of rules on lobbying. However, I also believe that after today's vote the churches will remain our partners and will not be classified as lobby groups.</p>
      <p sl="sk">I am convinced that the Stubb/Friedrich report will eliminate all kinds of prejudices and negative views about lobbying and that European citizens will view lobbyists as specialists who bring knowledge based on practical experience, helping to prevent European legislation from having a negative impact.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-035" speaker_id="28377" name="Lidia Joanna Geringer de Oedenberg" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, lobbying at the European institutions is a complex issue. On the one hand, access to the institutions’ activities is a consequence of the principle of transparency of their operation laid down in the founding treaties. It is also a way of bridging the gap involving the so-called democratic deficit, because expert organisations provide valuable expert analyses which have a beneficial impact on the quality of European legislation.</p>
      <p sl="pl">On the other hand, however, large international corporations can resort to specialist lobbying companies to influence the institutions’ work, aiming to promote the corporations’ own interests first and foremost.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The problem of lobbying at the European Parliament is gaining prominence as the competences of this House increase. We should therefore support the Commission’s initiative proposing cooperative interinstitutional work to define a framework of operation for lobbyists, including the creation of a common register of lobbyists. The principle of transparency pursuant to which lobbyists can access the work of the institutions should also be applied to the lobbyists themselves. Voluntary registration is not enough. It should become compulsory for lobbyists to register in order to gain access to the institutions of the European Union.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-036" speaker_id="2278" name="Paul Rübig" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, I have been a Member of the European Parliament for twelve years. I must say, I feel I should thank many of the lobbyists, for they have proved to be a source of considerable expertise in our day-to-day work. In my view, it is always good for Members to listen to all sides and keep their door open to citizens.</p>
      <p sl="de">If we currently have 5 000 lobbyists registered with Parliament – all of whom we can recognise by their badges and who are accredited or certified, as it were – that works out at an average of six lobbyists for every Member. I think it is extremely important for us to utilise this expertise appropriately in our legislative work, for the fact is that Members cannot be specialists in every area. That is why it is important to listen to the practitioners and recognise that in reality, lobbyists do enhance our parliamentary work.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-037" speaker_id="28139" name="Carl Schlyter" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="sv">Mr President, as Mr Bonde pointed out, Europe is one of the world’s most underdeveloped regions when it comes to rules on lobbying. However, we can make things better today by supporting the amendment calling for a mandatory register of financial interests and real sanctions for those who break the rules. In addition, we need to clarify what those people working in the Commission who are paid externally are actually doing.</p>
      <p sl="sv">As many people point out, lobbying is not bad in itself, but the problem is that when we centralise decisions it becomes easy for large companies to turn economic power into political power. At least four fifths of lobbyists are paid by big companies. That imbalance affects our legislation. Transparency must therefore mean that all amendments to legal texts submitted by lobbyists must be registered openly so that we can see who is behind them.</p>
      <p sl="sv">When the register of those who are allowed to come here is set up, I call upon Mrs Lulling to ensure that one third of the places are given to companies, one third to non-governmental organisations and one third to others. That will enable us to have a balance.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-038" speaker_id="28345" name="David Hammerstein" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, when we talk about transparency, we cannot talk in the abstract. Our voters should know who is in the seats of the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy when we are discussing REACH or the telecommunications package; they should know who is tabling amendments; they should know who is preparing many of the reports of this Parliament, which they can find out through this Parliament’s webpage, and they should know, through a register, who is spending hundreds of hours in the corridors of Parliament. This is all possible. Just as they should know who attends a committee meeting and who attends plenary – through Parliament’s website – our voters should know which lobbyists are spending hundreds of hours at our meetings.</p>
      <p sl="es">We want transparency, but we want this to be truthful. We want it to be known, after the vote on each report, which lobbyists have tabled the amendments that are shaping our future, word for word, amendment by amendment. Thank you.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-039" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Siim Kallas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the debate about lobbying is always interesting and exciting. I enjoyed very much hearing the observations of the honourable Members, which reflect the understanding which was also mentioned here by Mr Leinen: the devil is always in the details. I totally agree with Mrs Frassoni that work will not be finished with this report or even with the opening of the Commission’s registers.</p>
      <p sl="en">I can assure Parliament that we are very cooperative and we are doing everything we can to start this interinstitutional group and to work out a common approach as soon and as smoothly as possible. I would like to say that, in my view, this common register is not some kind of heavy animal which will threaten everybody. It is a common package of information, common storage of all necessary information so that all interested representatives do not need to submit different applications to different institutions, with these applications not being interoperable. This was your suggestion for how not to create a burden. But all other details have been discussed over the years since we started our debate about this in 2005.</p>
      <p sl="en">I shall only say – in answer to one point you raised – that there are, of course, a lot of complicated details in defining who is lobbying and on what subject. In our discussions we have met lawyers’ organisations. They have accepted our approach that, when and if they are really acting as lobbyists, then they must declare this as lobbying and they have no need to declare their activities as legal advisers or something like that.</p>
      <p sl="en">There is just one thing that I must say in connection with what was raised: the issue that some people are working in the Commission and receiving salaries from the private sector. This is finished. We have still some finished contracts, but this practice has ended.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-040" speaker_id="1264" name="Ingo Friedrich" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, thank you for what has, for the most part, been a focused and well-informed debate. Serious and transparent lobbying activities help to enhance the efficiency of the decision-making process. Mr Turmes, you were not correct in what you said: financial disclosure is covered in paragraph 21. To that extent, you were wrong to attack the Socialist Group. I feel compelled to point that out.</p>
      <p sl="de">Secondly, as regards the issue of lawyers, we cannot make the sweeping assertion that every lawyer is by default a lobbyist because he or she has studied advocacy and all that it entails. We have the correct definition before us: anyone who seeks to influence the policy formulation and decision-making processes of the EU institutions is a lobbyist, and that includes lawyers.</p>
      <p sl="de">May I point out one error in the translation: 'municipalities' has been translated as 'Städte ' in German. The US system is very detailed; indeed, it is so detailed that some senators produce 300-page reports at the end of the year, with the result that it is almost impossible to gain a clear insight into what is really happening in terms of lobbying activities in the US.</p>
      <p sl="de">From my perspective, it was interesting that the ultra-left and the ultra-right virtually converge in their fundamental criticism. 'Les extrêmes se touchent' , as the French would say, and this situation is typical. We want to arrive at a serious solution which is an improvement on what is happening in America, and also improves upon what is happening in most, or indeed all, of the Member States.</p>
      <p sl="de">Many thanks, once again, to Mr Stubb. Minister, we are thinking of you! Thank you, too, for the serious debate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-041" speaker_id="1405" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">I would like to thank Mr Friedrich for taking over the report from Mr Stubb, who has our congratulations on being appointed Finnish Foreign Minister.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place at 11 a. m.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 142)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-042" speaker_id="39763" name="Urszula Gacek" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">The pluralism of interests is an important feature of democracy. It is therefore legitimate that members of society organise and lobby for their interests. However, lobbying does lead to the risk that democratic principles may be corrupted. The power of corporations to influence politicians can lead to unequal access to law- and decision-making processes vis-à-vis the ordinary citizen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Very few European countries have regulated lobbying. This parliamentary report on lobbying will be a valuable step in strengthening transparency, accountability and citizens’ participation in the democratic process at the European level. However experience in countries that have implemented lobbying legislation shows that this should only be one part of a broader range of guidelines and measures.</p>
      <p sl="en">From non-transparent lobbying it is only a short step to corruption and the distortion of the market to the detriment of those companies who play by the rules.</p>
      <p sl="en">The involvement of industry representatives in preparing this report is welcome. They should now be urged to take up the initiative and show that responsible corporations have a vital role to play in the process of regulating lobbying.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-043" speaker_id="28373" name="Bogdan Golik" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pl">Special thanks and congratulations are due not only to the rapporteur but also to Commissioner Kallas, who took the lead regarding new regulations for the principles of lobbying. This is particularly important in view of the new competences to be acquired by the European Parliament pursuant to adoption of the Lisbon Treaty. Nonetheless, I wish to express my concern as to the effectiveness and credibility of a voluntary register of lobbyists. The register should be compulsory and common to all European institutions. In view of its nature, Parliament should retain its autonomy, however.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Compulsory registration should apply to the whole range of lobbying bodies. I have in mind, amongst others, regional representations, sectoral organisations, lawyers undertaking a lobbying role and research institutions. All those who exercise influence in order to obtain economic or social benefits should be registered. The requirement to submit only financial information is not always reliable and does not enable a full assessment to be undertaken as intended.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-044" speaker_id="23717" name="Genowefa Grabowska" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pl">Regulation of lobbying should certainly be welcomed. At last there is a chance of transparent cooperation between Parliament and interested groups, namely lobbyists. It is proposed to create a compulsory register of all lobbyists interested in presenting and defending their interests at the European institutions. This proposal deserves our support. Entry on the register would allow interested lobbyists to access the European Parliament’s premises, attend committee meetings and also to make contact with Members in their offices, but without disrupting their work.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The effectiveness of civilised and therefore transparent lobbying largely depends, however, on the lobbyists’ behaviour. It will therefore be necessary to draw up a code of ethical practice for lobbyists at the same time.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Parliament should also monitor implementation of these provisions, especially as regards checking the veracity of the information on the register. Lobbyists providing inadequate or untrue information should be sanctioned. The sanctions imposed should be in proportion to the offence and serve as a deterrent, ranging from suspension of registration to permanent exclusion from the register inclusive.</p>
      <p sl="pl">It should be remembered that this new proposal was drawn up at the European Parliament’s own initiative. The proposal will also prove very helpful to other European institutions and to the national parliaments of Member States of the European Union that have not yet adopted measures in this regard.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-999" speaker_id="38846" name="Roselyne Lefrançois" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">I welcome the adoption of this report, which, in my view, will enable us to improve significantly the relations between interest representatives and the EU institutions.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Rather than trying to establish and keep up-to-date a comprehensive list of these representatives – a tedious and perhaps even impossible task – it proposes, in particular, establishing a global definition of the term ‘lobby’, which will ensure that any bodies that are not on the list cannot get around the rules we have laid down.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Another major step forward is the harmonisation and simplification of the regulatory framework applicable to lobbyists, and in particular the creation of a single register that is common to all the institutions, which will list all lobbyists and will, in the long term, become a reference and a pledge of seriousness and credibility for all accredited organisations.</p>
      <p sl="fr">However, this register will also promote greater transparency vis-à-vis the general public because it will be accessible online in its entirety and will include for each body its complete identification details, including details of its staff, as well as all of the pertinent financial information relating to it.</p>
      <p sl="fr">In addition to this ‘one-stop shop’ a common code of ethical behaviour, Members of the European Parliament who draw up a report will have the opportunity to list in the report the names of the organisations that have helped them with their work.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-045" speaker_id="33982" name="Marian-Jean Marinescu" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="ro">Consulting and involving as many groups of interests as possible in drafting, implementing and monitoring the enforcement of European laws is an objective requirement for the good development of the legislative process, for correcting errors and avoiding biased opinions.</p>
      <p sl="ro">The open dialogue with the representatives of all the actors involved in this process lays at the basis of our democratic system and represents an important source of information, provided that this happens in total transparency.</p>
      <p sl="ro">For this reason, the initiative of introducing a “legislative imprint”, even if voluntary, both for the documents drafted by the Commission and for the European Parliament reports, is welcomed.</p>
      <p sl="ro">Consulting as many interested parties as possible, including antagonistic parties, as well as making the process itself transparent, is essential for drafting a complex and honest legislation that would cover all aspects of the field, guaranteeing the balance and efficient harmonization of all the points of view, avoiding conflicts of interests and preventing subsequent deficiencies.</p>
      <p sl="ro">The correct exchange of information regarding the lobby organizations attached to the European institutions will determine, in the long term, not only the facilitation of the legislative process, but also the transparent and equitable cooperation between the Commission, the Parliament and the Council, a cooperation whose ultimate beneficiary is, without any doubt, the European citizen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-046" speaker_id="37200" name="Katrin Saks" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">The lobbying report which we have been discussing is an important step toward transparency. When we can show who has been consulted on any one legislative package, it gives legitimacy to the process which is so important for us here.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is equally important to make sure that all interests that approach Parliament have to register. We cannot allow any loopholes which would let some interests go unregistered. For one, lawyers and think-tanks that take part in lobbying activities are for all intents and purposes lobbyists and should therefore be registered.</p>
      <p sl="en">In short, I would like to welcome this report which is a good first step in the move for greater transparency.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-047" speaker_id="28980" name="Andres Tarand" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="et">The report tabled by Alexander Stubb is extremely important as the number of lobbyists in Brussels will soon be the same as the number of European Commission officials.</p>
      <p sl="et">I welcome the fact that, unlike the European Commission, Parliament is supporting the idea that a register of lobbyists should be mandatory. If that were not the case the report would not fulfil its primary objective and indeed would fail in its task.</p>
      <p sl="et">On the issue of including lawyers on the list, which is currently the main bone of contention, I favour inclusion in a mandatory register. There is no reason to exclude them from the register as lobbying of European Union institutions is increasingly conducted through law firms. Law firms should not be given the opportunity simply to classify any activity as legal consultation and thereby eschew the register and the requirement for transparency in lobbying.</p>
      <p sl="et">The idea of a ‘one-stop’ register is a good one. It is important for the Council to be involved with the register as well as the European Parliament and the Commission. In the interests of usability of the data collected, a single data base, available on-line and accessible to all the institutions, should be established as a matter of urgency.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. White Paper on Sport (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-049" speaker_id="1405" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report by Manolis Mavrommatis, on behalf of the Committee on Culture and Education, on the White Paper on Sport (2007/2261(INI)) (A6-0149/2008).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-050" speaker_id="28574" name="Manolis Mavrommatis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, let me first thank the Commission and Commissioner Figeľ for their initiative in drawing up the White Paper on Sport and the Pierre de Coubertin Action Plan. This is the EU’s first effort to deal with sporting matters.</p>
      <p sl="el">May I also thank Commissioner Špidla for being here today in place of Commissioner Figeľ, who is travelling outside Europe.</p>
      <p sl="el">My thanks also go to my colleagues from the Committee on Culture and Education and to the Committee on Economic and Monetary Affairs, the Committee on Employment and Social Affairs, the Committee on the Internal Market and Consumer Protection, the Committee on Legal Affairs, the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs, the Committee on Regional Development and the Committee on Women’s Rights and Gender Equality. They have cooperated excellently in drafting the report on the White Paper on Sport.</p>
      <p sl="el">In the European Parliament report, the key points of the White Paper were covered by 16 conciliation amendments jointly agreed by all the political groups in the Committee on Culture. The main points were also covered by 426 amendments tabled to the lead committee and to the other seven committees, which gave their opinions.</p>
      <p sl="el">Doping is once again the focus of attention because there are unfortunate examples of it every year in almost every sport. Through the White Paper, the European Parliament seeks to adopt measures allowing athletes not be forced by their heavy schedules to resort to performance- and stamina-enhancing substances.</p>
      <p sl="el">In addition, internal and external independent checks on professional associations and sports organisations, as well as educating male and female athletes on the side effects of doping may help to curb this problem.</p>
      <p sl="el">Debates have focused on two issues of the financial side of sport. The first is sports betting. We in the Committee on Culture all agree that the possible deregulation of the gaming and lotteries market will be problematic for the funding of amateur sport so long as the existing system of state betting agencies provides it with considerable income.</p>
      <p sl="el">For this reason, the White Paper calls on Member States and the Commission to adopt regulations which ensure that amateur and professional sport is protected from any improper influence relating to betting.</p>
      <p sl="el">While continuing to protect the betting market, we are thus increasing transparency, and also guaranteeing the state aid for amateur sport, culture and other social activities.</p>
      <p sl="el">The second issue is the sale of media rights. As we all know, the 27 EU Member States go about selling television rights for major sporting events in different ways. This is especially true of Champions League matches and the UEFA Cup.</p>
      <p sl="el">Rights can be sold either individually or collectively, but they are the main source of income for professional sport in Europe. Similarly, rights to sports events are a vital source of programme content and income for many media owners.</p>
      <p sl="el">Parliament’s report also recognises the importance of fairly redistributing income among sports associations, however small, and between professional and amateur sport.</p>
      <p sl="el">The collective sale of media rights, which the Commission presents as incompatible with competition law, is therefore important for the redistribution of income. It may thus help to achieve greater solidarity among sports.</p>
      <p sl="el">We therefore call on the Commission to recognise collective sales and accept that such practical solidarity among small sports clubs is sanctioned by law.</p>
      <p sl="el">Lastly, as we stated in the Belet report on professional football, UEFA and FIFA should reach agreement and work with the agencies of the Commission. They must ensure that football is universally accepted by the citizens and Member States of the EU without losing its independence; it must not overstep the powers conferred on it by the statutes.</p>
      <p sl="el">It is important for everyone that UEFA and FIFA recognise in their statutes the right of recourse to common courts. We must, of course, accept the principle of self-regulation and the structures of the European model of sport governing the organisation of sports events.</p>
      <p sl="el">Let me end by reaffirming the satisfaction we all feel at the official recognition of sport by the Member States in the reformed Lisbon Treaty. We do of course recognise and respect the special nature of sport. It is of great significance for Member States and the sporting world in general that the EU will in future be able to substantially contribute to and promote European policy on sport.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-052" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Vladimír Špidla" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="cs">In the first place I should present apologies from my colleague Commissioner Figeľ, who cannot take part in this sitting because of a long-planned working visit to Egypt. I accepted the proposal that I should deputise for him with pleasure, inter alia because much of what falls within my competence is closely related to sport.</p>
      <p sl="cs">I would like to thank the rapporteur for the excellent report that he and his colleagues in Parliament have spent six months preparing. I am convinced that the report is a balanced document and deals with all the relevant themes. Thank you for the European Parliament's support for the White Paper on Sport and for your high level of cooperation with the European Commission.</p>
      <p sl="cs">As the European Parliament has emphasised, it is important to recall the principle of the applicability of Community law to sports in Europe, whilst also respecting the specific nature of sport. Therefore the European Commission remains active on sport, and from now on will apply Community law, including the competition rules, to that area. The White Paper and its annexes are useful aids for sporting organisations and for Member States in the concrete application of the acquis communautaire to decisions in the area of competition and to judgments of the European Court of Justice.</p>
      <p sl="cs">On the question of the specific nature of sport, the European Commission will lead and support open dialogue with sports organisations, Member States and the European Parliament within the framework of the structured dialogue on sport. This dialogue will be conducted in such a way that issues of the specific characteristics of sport will be dealt with concretely.</p>
      <p sl="cs">The European Commission does not have any general objections to the amendments to be discussed at this plenary session, especially if their aim is to preserve the proper and equal participation of representative structures in controlling sport. However, we cannot agree with an unconditional obligation for young players to sign their first professional contract with the club that has trained them, because this infringes the fundamental freedom of free movement of workers.</p>
      <p sl="cs">Meanwhile, as you know, the implementation of the White Paper is continuing according to plan. Twenty-six of the 53 actions in the Pierre de Coubertin Action Plan have already been carried out; this year, for example, three studies will be initiated (with results in 2009), on the following themes: sports funding, players’ agents, and volunteering in sport.</p>
      <p sl="cs">In autumn last year, under the leadership of my colleagues, Commissioner Frattini and Commissioner Figeľ, a conference took place on the high level of violence in sport, which identified concrete methods that could achieve an improvement in combating this phenomenon. The results of measuring the impact of sport on the economy can also be viewed as a significant success.</p>
      <p sl="cs">As far as the matter of ‘home-grown players’ is concerned, a short time ago the European Commission was handed the results of an independent expert report analysing UEFA’s rules. The European Commission is at this very moment examining the compatibility of these rules with Community law.</p>
      <p sl="cs">New possibilities for funding sport and physical activities have also been opened up by various EU programmes, especially the lifelong learning programmes ‘Youth in action and ‘Europe for citizens’. We hope that the Lisbon Treaty will soon come into force and we are delighted with the European Parliament’s support for the preparatory actions in the field of sport, which contribute to implementation of the new EU competence in this area.</p>
      <p sl="cs">Allow me to thank you once again for your contribution, support and splendid cooperation in this important, sensitive and very popular area.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-053" speaker_id="28171" name="Emine Bozkurt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="draftsman of the opinion of the Committee on Employment and Social Affairs">
      <p sl="nl">Well, Mr Špidla has said it all. An important role has been set aside in sport for employment, for social affairs. Sport does indeed have an important social function, for example fighting problems such as racism. Racism in society is reflected by racism in sport.</p>
      <p sl="nl">I am extremely glad of the attention that this White Paper pays to eliminating racism and discrimination, in both professional and amateur sport.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Sport also has many advantages for, to take some examples, social inclusion, integration of migrants or reintegration into the labour market. For this reason I welcome the Commission’s recommendation to direct the Member States to make use of the EU’s existing funds.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Furthermore, sport is becoming more and more professional, and there is a need for good training for sportswomen and sportsmen so that after their careers they can return to society.</p>
      <p sl="nl">I have one final point: it is also important to improve the professional qualities of sports managers and for this reason we support a licensing system at European level.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-054" speaker_id="4560" name="Toine Manders" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="draftsman of the opinion of the Committee on the Internal Market and Consumer Protection">
      <p sl="nl">I would like to thank the Members for their extremely pleasant cooperation on this report. I think, however, that it must have taken a great deal of time to achieve this proposal.</p>
      <p sl="nl">I find, sadly, that in some matters it does not go far enough. It is very important, in my opinion, to create guidelines to which sporting organisations can commit themselves. When it comes to State support, we should aim for the same treatment throughout Europe, particularly where professional sporting organisations are concerned.</p>
      <p sl="nl">I also find that the distinction between the specific characteristics of sport and the economic activities that frequently accompany sport is a little too explicit, because I believe that economic activities – including those that protect sport – cannot have exceptions made for them in the Treaty. That is fortunately also not mentioned in this report. That is also the reason why I wholeheartedly support it. I think it is good that sporting organisations have started talking more than they did formerly about this subject, and that is a significant step forward. Thank you very much.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-055" speaker_id="2001" name="Gerardo Galeote" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="draftsman of the opinion of the Committee on Regional Development">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, I am convinced that the subsequent legislative development of Article 149 of the Lisbon Treaty will positively benefit sport in the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="es">However, in territorial terms or, in other words, on the ground, I believe that the European Commission, in exercising its legislative initiative, must act carefully with regard to the different local situations and the differences between sporting disciplines.</p>
      <p sl="es">Its contributions should be general and should respond to an overall European interest, and not to a thirst for interventionism. It must therefore be respectful of the principle of subsidiarity.</p>
      <p sl="es">This is what the Committee on Regional Development thought. As a result, I welcome the amendments tabled by various parliamentary groups in this same respect and I hope that, this morning, the House can adopt these through a positive vote.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-056" speaker_id="4533" name="Neena Gill" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Draftsman of the opinion of the Committee on Legal Affairs . − Mr President, I welcome the white paper on sport and I particularly support the emphasis on securing greater legal certainty, because relying on a case-by-case approach in the courts has led to an inconsistency of approach in terms of governing sport. I note the actions that the Commission has outlined this morning, but I would like to ask the Commissioner to comment on whether it intends to propose guidelines to clarify which aspects of sport are governed by EU law and which are exempt and should be dealt with by sporting bodies.</p>
      <p sl="en">Another issue which I believe the Commission needs to tackle urgently is that of illegal trafficking of children, especially from West Africa, to the European Union due to demand in Europe for talented African players. This has sparked a growth of unlicensed football academies in some African countries and I am deeply concerned that young children are being exploited by ruthless agents and then sold on to clubs as if they were commodities. Some find themselves abandoned in Europe, having sacrificed their family’s entire savings to pursue their dreams. Stronger action by Member States, European clubs and African governments should be taken to ensure that they do not participate in this.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, I would like to ask the Commission what deliberations it has engaged in on the issue of sports and intellectual property rights, especially with the growing accessibility of sports footage on the internet.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-057" speaker_id="38398" name="Esther de Lange" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="draftsman of the opinion of the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs">
      <p sl="nl">I would first of all like to thank the rapporteur for his outstanding report and in particular, on behalf of the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs, for the attention that he pays to civil liberties, justice and home affairs in the area of sport. In particular, then, I call for the strengthening of cross-border cooperation between police forces, based on the exchange of information, while still respecting data protection, of course.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Secondly, it is our opinion that in stimulating the licensing systems, explicit attention should be paid to protecting minors and reducing discrimination, racism and violence.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Thirdly – and this has already been said – there is the matter of reducing trafficking in human beings. I am thinking primarily of the trade in children and the exploitation of talented young people, often from the third world, but also of the trafficking of women, in the context of forced prostitution at large sporting events.</p>
      <p sl="nl">In the run-up to the new Treaty, the time has now come, Mr President, to translate this report into definitive action. I would therefore like to end with an appeal to the European Commission – and I know that I am now taking up the Feyenoord club song, ‘not words, but actions’ – an appeal for the White Paper and the outstanding words of Mr Mavrommatis to be put into action. As FC Groningen say: ‘let us once again shout for joy’, Commissioner.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-058" speaker_id="28133" name="Pál Schmitt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group">
      <p sl="hu">Thank you, Mr President. Few people know that sport accounts for 4% of the European Union’s gross domestic product and provides employment for some 15 million people. If this statement is true, then it is likely that revenue and employment indicators for sport will be similar in the statistics for individual Member States. This stands in stark contrast, however, to the fact that some countries, unfortunately including my own country Hungary, spend only a tiny fraction of their national budget – something like a half of one per cent – on promoting sports and healthy lifestyles. There are therefore good grounds for asking who exactly is supporting whom? If we take the role of sport seriously, then sport should not just be a profit-generating sector; we should be seeking to ensure that governments not only put their moral weight behind sport but also much greater financial support than previously. In my opinion, the next generation’s health, their physical and emotional health, capacity for work – their sense of wellbeing if you like – is a strategic issue, and so I welcome the White Paper on Sport and the fact that the Lisbon Treaty is dealing substantively with this issue. Let us not forget that sport is an important educational tool; it is important for social cohesion and for maintaining health, and it contributes to our quality of life. In this case, however, the amount spent on sport – barely half of one per cent in some countries – is out of all proportion to the significance of sport as a social phenomenon. I sincerely hope that the ‘Pierre de Coubertin’ Action Plan that forms part of the White Paper will be taken seriously by the Member States and that the Commission will provide the necessary guidance and, where appropriate, economic assistance from the development funds at its disposal. I also hope that from now on no one in Europe will be able to say that they do not really know what we mean when we talk about sport, as the White Paper provides excellent guidance in this regard for all governments and sports ministers. As a sports leader myself, I am delighted that the document also refers to the autonomy, self-regulating capacity and specificity of sports organisations. I congratulate my honourable friend Mr Mavrommatis. Thank you.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-059" speaker_id="28316" name="Hannu Takkula" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="fi">Mr President, first I wish to thank the rapporteur, Mr Mavrommatis, for his excellent work and commitment to this report.</p>
      <p sl="fi">To begin with, I want to say that I think it is very important that during the implementation phase of the White Paper the policies on sport as a general-interest, non-profit, voluntary activity should remain priorities in Europe. It is also vital that through this document we are able to say we have respect for the specificity of sport, self-regulation and structured dialogue, and we therefore want to lay down guidelines for the application of European Union law in sport.</p>
      <p sl="fi">Furthermore, there is a crucial link between sport, exercise and public health. Current problems we have in Europe that we are trying to control are metabolic syndrome, type II diabetes and obesity. Healthy exercise enables us to prevent these problems in the best possible way.</p>
      <p sl="fi">Secondly, we need to realise that it is important for the European Sport for All policy to retain national gambling systems. They need to be preserved because they have created a unique opportunity to finance amateur sport, as well as culture, science and research. Other social sectors have thus benefitted from sport. This needs to be taken into consideration in the future.</p>
      <p sl="fi">Thirdly, I want to mention that sport will acquire a firmer legal basis under the Lisbon Treaty. We also have to prepare for this new situation, with a pilot programme and budget headings for 2009 being planned now. We have to move on from words to deeds, and that also holds true for sport.</p>
      <p sl="fi">We can achieve much overall with the document being discussed. I would once again like to thank Commissioner Figel, and, in particular, that great man of sport, Mr Mavrommatis, who has done pioneering work to promote sport’s new march forward in the context of European culture and society.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-060" speaker_id="28391" name="Zdzisław Zbigniew Podkański" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the UEN Group">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, the development of sport and support for its many facets is rightly considered to be one of the European Community’s strategic aims.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The report deals with some very important issues related to regulation of the organisation of sport, and emphasises its economic dimension. I am very pleased to note also the prominence given to so-called sport for all. Supporting this notion is particularly important, because a large proportion of sporting ventures at club and association level are not undertaken for financial gain. For that reason they are in fact in danger of disappearing as the market has become so commercialised. Recognition of the importance of amateur sport is therefore in line with the idea of bringing sport close to the citizens.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The report rightly draws attention to negative phenomena in the sporting world. I refer for instance to doping and to the exploitation of sports people. Even young sports people at the start of their careers are at risk, and protecting them is a priority issue. Hence the restrictive provisions concerning the transfer of young sports people and the approval of the principles regarding signature of the first contract with the club that trained the young person. This is a step in the right direction, as is joining forces to combat doping and coordinating activities at international level. Guaranteeing professional sports people the same rights as contracted workers is also important. Finally, I should like to congratulate Mr Mavrommatis on preparing a good report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-061" speaker_id="28214" name="Jean-Luc Bennahmias" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, the White Paper on Sport, following on from the own-initiative report on the future of professional football, known as the Belet report, is a substantial and necessary document. It was time for the European Parliament and the European Commission to tackle the issue of sport. However, good intentions are not enough to cope with the scourges and problems threatening our sports. In the face of scourges such as racism, mafia-style groups, violence inside and outside sports facilities, doping and the purchase of young disposable players from Africa or elsewhere, action is needed!</p>
      <p sl="fr">Given the difficulties such as the management of huge sums of money – notably in football but in other sports, too – the existence of agents of all types – agents for players, clubs, coaches – the dictates of ratings, the liberalisation of gambling, we need clear directives that allow for continuity and the development of European sports federations and leagues at both amateur and professional level.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Sport, the economy, finance, employment, diplomacy: today these are all closely related. Athletes should not have to pay the price even if they are also citizens who can and must act in good conscience. It is up to the politicians to assume their responsibilities. The European Union will have to do so at the Olympic Games in China in order to reaffirm that respect for cultures, for local religious beliefs and for democracy are essential and non-negotiable.</p>
      <p sl="fr">We will vote in favour of the report by Mr Mavrommatis on the White Paper on sport as it is an excellent report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-062" speaker_id="28336" name="Věra Flasarová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group">
      <p sl="cs">The Olympic flame is presently travelling across all the continents of the world, reminding us of the message of sport, for which we are indebted to the Greeks. They were of course the first to understand what a purifying role sport can play in human culture. Sport teaches us that people can compete with one another without causing harm, injury or even death; sport teaches fair play and offers everybody the same chances and the same rights. But modern times have made sport into a business, a milieu pervaded by the negative influences that we already encounter almost everywhere: money, corruption, lobbying, racial prejudice and also the new phenomenon of various performance-enhancing drugs, factors that damage the integrity of sport and reduce the positive potential that sport has for bringing up young people or breaking down barriers between peoples and races.</p>
      <p sl="cs">Therefore I welcome the Commission’s work on the White Paper on Sport and I value Mr Mavrommatis’s report. Both documents warn of the need to protect sport as a cultural value. I would also personally like to emphasise even more the need to support sport at the amateur level too, to create the conditions needed for people to participate in recreational sporting activity, which is not easy, especially in large conurbations, as well as making it financially accessible, which is a limiting factor for the socially disadvantaged. Sport offers children and young people an alternative way of using their free time and being active. It can serve all the generations in the same spirit, so we should also not forget older citizens and should instead look for further ways of making it possible for them to join in sporting activity. Sport is a means of improving physical condition, but obviously it also influences the human psyche. Professional sport is only the apex of a pyramid whose base must be created by sporting activity involving the greatest number of people on our planet.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-063" speaker_id="28496" name="Thomas Wise" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the IND/DEM Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, it will not surprise you, but I do not welcome the conclusions of this report. The fact that it declares ‘sport is rightly subject to the application of the acquis communautaire’ flies in the face of all current evidence. It ignores the most public lament of sports bodies throughout Europe: that the Bosman and Kolpak rulings have left then unable to foster the development of home-grown sports talent. As a direct result, national teams are underperforming on the international stage.</p>
      <p sl="de">Even the president of FIFA, Sepp Blatter, believes the rules need to be changed. But if sports bodies thought the current situation was bad, the Lisbon Treaty is going to make things even worse by providing the Commission with the treaty heading it requires to start interfering – I am sorry, legislating – over sport directly.</p>
      <p sl="de">The UK Government’s refusal to honour its promise to hold a referendum on the Treaty means we do not have the opportunity to save sport in the UK from the impending doom of Commission interference. Perhaps the vote in Ireland will save us all.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-064" speaker_id="38610" name="Slavi Binev" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="bg">Mr. President, dear colleagues, those who know me can tell for sure that sport and everything related to physical education is a way of life for me. I accept the publication of the White Paper on Sport with the hope that it will provide the foundations of a future consistent policy. I believe that when we speak of an European policy in this field, we should think, first and foremost, of our children, their health, future and social integration.</p>
      <p sl="bg">The encouragement of sport in the educational standards is an important factor for the psychological and physical development of our children, a major tool for the protection of their health. The adoption of the White Paper and the establishment of an integrated structure at the European level to develop, promote and implement common policies in each type of sport, starting from sport for the youngest all the way to professional sport, not forgetting, of course, people with disabilities, will offer all citizens opportunities for participation and personal involvement in the community and contribute to the encouragement of the intercultural dialogue.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-065" speaker_id="28257" name="Ivo Belet" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="nl">What should have been a memorable moment here this morning, namely the approval of the report on the White Paper, has been overshadowed by the tragic death of one of Belgium’s top footballers. The footballer François Sterckele was this morning involved in a traffic accident. He was one of the greatest talents in Belgian football. I would like to express my sincere condolences to the family and friends of François Sterckele and to the supporters of Club Brugge.</p>
      <p sl="nl">As a young footballer and a young talent, ladies and gentlemen, Sterckele got all his chances in various clubs in Belgium, and there he eventually developed into the top scorer in the Belgian league. He is excellent proof that investing in young talent, our own talent, really pays dividends. That is exactly, ladies and gentlemen, what we want to support by means of this report. For this reason, we support, too, the ‘home-grown’ regulations, such as those applied by UEFA. We also appreciate that the European Commission is prepared to support the training of young players.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Other than that, I would like to advise you to read the annual report of the Deutsche Bundesliga , which has just come out. The German league is, in my opinion and in the opinion of many others, a role model for Europe. Here are a couple of examples: it has very strict licensing regulations, it invests a lot in its own talent and it also has clear rules to prevent German clubs being sold off to investors who have no connection with either the club or the supporters.</p>
      <p sl="nl">The joint initiative of two representatives of the Council, the French and the Dutch Ministers for Sport, is a perfect answer. We expect, therefore, that the French Presidency in the autumn will work to introduce measures securing the future of professional and amateur sport in Europe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-066" speaker_id="28171" name="Emine Bozkurt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="nl">I would like first of all to begin by thanking Mr Mavrommatis for his outstanding report and excellent cooperation. I spoke a moment ago as the draftsman of the opinion of the Committee on Employment and Social Affairs, and now I am speaking as shadow rapporteur for the press.</p>
      <p sl="nl">I would like to underline three points, namely the importance of clear directives, the importance of the lotteries and home-grown players. First of all, I would like us to look at the specific aspects of sport and sporting organisations that require clear guidelines, where European legislation applies. I think that we must then give an answer in place of our hitherto preoccupied, case-by-case approach.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Secondly, let us consider home-grown players. We must ensure that professional players of a young age are protected and are trained in an atmosphere of stability. For this reason we support the so-called home-grown players rule so that young people are trained by a club and can get their first contract with the same club. In this way it will naturally be the case that many national players can play in a club, without us discriminating on the basis of nationality, which is not the intention. We must respect the free movement of players, and that is an important principle for us. For this reason we do not disagree with FIFA’s so-called ‘six-plus-five’ regulation.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Finally, we come to the lotteries. National lotteries have an important function. You could say that they perform a public service, as they support many social organisations, including sports structures. Liberalising the market has a positive impact, and therefore before any action is taken, its impact and viable alternatives must be carefully examined.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-067" speaker_id="39717" name="Ramona Nicole Mănescu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="ro">Mr. President, I congratulate Mr. Mavromatis for this report.</p>
      <p sl="ro">The initiative of a White Paper on Sport is not only opportune, but also necessary. Taking into consideration the great number of employees in the field of sport, as well as the revenues sport generates, we should pay more attention to the manner in which the labour law is implemented in this field; many times, performance is achieved at early ages, but this is only one step away from exploiting minors.</p>
      <p sl="ro">We should make sure that the revenues coming from sport activities are legally obtained and taxed according to the law.</p>
      <p sl="ro">Violence in sport represents another problem. Human lives are lost every year in confrontations between supporters. On the one hand, the police forces and the clubs should cooperate in order to ensure a comfortable and safe environment during the sport events, and, on the other hand, the legal system should toughen punishments for violent acts related to sport events.</p>
      <p sl="ro">In conclusion, Mr. President, I think that Mr. Mavromatis’ report proves that, at a European level, we need a coherent policy and concrete actions in order to turn to good account and make sport more efficient and I hope we will see more initiatives in this respect.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-068" speaker_id="1944" name="Sebastiano (Nello) Musumeci" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, the insertion of the new Article 149 into the Treaty of Lisbon constitutes recognition of the major economic and social role played by sport. The detailed report by Manolis Mavrommatis highlights the numerous areas of life affected by sport, and I should like to look at just a few of them.</p>
      <p sl="it">The first is the relationship between sport and health: although everyone is well aware by now that physical activity is essential in order to remain in good shape, there is a worrying tendency in certain EU Member States to reduce the number of hours devoted to sport in schools. This trend, combined with a poor diet, is creating an army of obese youngsters, with the possibility of negative repercussions on their physical condition.</p>
      <p sl="it">Sport is an original and enjoyable way to learn a language. Back in the early 1970s I learned of a very well-organised and widespread system of study vacations in the United Kingdom geared to learning the language of Shakespeare through the practice of various sporting disciplines. Sport ought to support brotherhood among nations, but unfortunately that is not always the case: we regularly witness scenes of indescribable violence inside and outside of stadiums, especially in the case of football.</p>
      <p sl="it">Amateur and professional sport, uncontaminated and unpolluted sport, sport as a personal development tool, an instrument of cohesion and solidarity among peoples: we are still a long way away from satisfactory standards in Europe, Mr President, and the responsibility lies entirely with politics. We can only hope that the White Paper on Sport will act as a wake-up call and reverse the trend once and for all, so as to make up for an excessive lack of sensitivity and too many sins of omission.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-069" speaker_id="1191" name="Doris Pack" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I would like to start by congratulating Mr Mavrommatis on his good report and his excellent cooperation with all our fellow Members who were interested in this issue, and there were many of them. Sport plays a more important role than had previously been recognised in the Commission and Council.</p>
      <p sl="de">In my view, this White Paper and the report are a good basis for developing all future activities and policies in the field of sport, especially since the Treaty of Lisbon finally gives sport the legal basis that it deserves. The White Paper and this report endeavour to strike a balance between competing interests, different types of sport, amateur and professional sport, between the specific characteristics of sport and the requirements of EU legislation, between social and cultural, economic and financial interests, and between profit and voluntary participation in these fields.</p>
      <p sl="de">I believe, therefore, that this endeavour deserves our genuine recognition. It opens up the opportunity to promote and cultivate the European model of sport. It thus maintains the specific characteristics of our sports organisations, which, after all, largely work on an autonomous basis and wish to continue doing so, especially as they tend to be highly reliant on volunteers' input.</p>
      <p sl="de">Secondly, we must try to support and promote the implementation of self-regulatory mechanisms at national and European level. May I recall paragraph 16 here, which I believe is extremely important.</p>
      <p sl="de">Thirdly, the report offers greater legal certainty with regard to the application of EU legislation to sport. Fourthly, the role of sport in education is an issue which has been mentioned frequently, and I would remind you of my report on this topic which dates back to 2004.</p>
      <p sl="de">Fifthly, the report discusses economic aspects, including the requisite financial commitment, particularly through lotteries, which has not been ruled out for the various sports here.</p>
      <p sl="de">Ten years ago, in my report on the role of the European Union in the field of sport, we called for a White Paper, and I am pleased that we are able to vote on it today.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-070" speaker_id="4239" name="Christa Prets" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, for a long time now, all the sports organisations have been calling for sport to be given greater significance and, indeed, greater visibility than has hitherto been the case, and we are acting on this call today. It will come into even sharper focus with the Lisbon Treaty.</p>
      <p sl="de">The many aspects of sport — its contribution to society, its role in personal development and fulfilment and in promoting social integration, etc. – have already been underlined. Sport is also a very important factor in promoting health, which is why it is worthwhile investing on a broad basis in sport, and particularly in physical education in schools. That is an investment that really would pay dividends.</p>
      <p sl="de">We are therefore appealing to every minister of education in the Member States to introduce a requirement for at least three hours of physical education in schools per week. That is the minimum, for otherwise, there is little point to it. There are 700 000 clubs and associations which are making an invaluable contribution to our society, and that is why I oppose the possible liberalisation of gambling and the lotteries, for at present around 10% of levies accrued from this industry go into sports, the arts and social amenities, and without this funding these organisations could not survive. I would ask everyone to be mindful of that.</p>
      <p sl="de">The important economic dimension of sport is borne out by the statistics: sport generated value-added of EUR 407 billion in 2004 and created 15 million jobs; there are other figures, too, which prove my point. That means that rules are needed. We need to strike a careful balance between the economic aspects of sport, transparency, sale of clubs, and licensing, as Mr Belet has just emphasised. Here, we need rules which are fair, so that 'fair play' has genuine and practical meaning.</p>
      <p sl="de">We need to make sure that there is appropriate redistribution between small and large clubs, so that we can develop the next generation of sportsmen and sportswomen. In my view, there should be a more equitable balance in the media. There really is more to sport than football. Nonetheless, I would like to extend a warm invitation to everyone to come and enjoy the Euro 2008 games in Vienna. That is a major sporting event which I am certainly looking forward to.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-071" speaker_id="33570" name="Sharon Bowles" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, in sport we must not let good intentions bring unintended consequences. Economic competition rules cannot always apply. Collective selling of television rights is the financial lifeline for many clubs that would otherwise be squeezed out by the famous. In a utopian world we could watch everything and never pay, but in the real world that would result in little of quality being left to watch.</p>
      <p sl="en">Observance of copyright protects the income that maintains high-quality events. Rising instances of ambush marketing and circulation of unauthorised highlights is as damaging as any other kind of piracy. It is also imperative not to inhibit flexibility in the means of raising income, movement of players or their ability to choose where to sign their first contracts. Finally, we should stick firmly to subsidiarity and keeping decision-making within the industry and close to fans.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-072" speaker_id="28372" name="Ryszard Czarnecki" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, the White Paper refers to long-standing problems such as doping, and to issues regarding financial disputes between television companies over broadcasting rights, which obviously have negative consequences for both fans and viewers. In addition, the White Paper deals with a much more serious problem that constitutes an increasing threat to honest sport, notably football. I refer to betting establishments. They may well represent the greatest challenge to contemporary sport. By way of example I could mention the latest scandal to affect the national football league of the country we are currently in. The Chinese Mafia is said to have fixed the results of Belgian football matches. The forthcoming liberalisation of the market in games of chance, including those related to the world of sport, will create further temptation to infringe the principles of fair play.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Finally, I have to say that I do not agree to the European Parliament’s proposal opposing FIFA’s stance on the principle of six players from a given country. FIFA’s proposal is sound. It will be the saving of national sport.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-073" speaker_id="28301" name="Tadeusz Zwiefka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, one of the fundamental difficulties I should like to highlight is the lack of legal certainty. The Commission has not established clearly which aspects of the organisation of sport are covered by Community legislation and which are of a purely sporting nature and therefore fall within the competence of the sports organisations.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I share the rapporteur’s opinion that relying exclusively on the European Court of Justice does not provide further legal clarity. The European Commission’s stance whereby regulation of the organisation of sport must comply with the Treaties does not do so either. This is not enough.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I therefore support the appeal to the European Commission to adopt interpretative guidelines that will bring clarity and precision to operations in this field. It should of course be emphasised that any action by the Commission must comply with the principle of self-regulation in sport. It must also respect the structures of the European sport model and the fundamental principles governing the organisation of sporting competitions.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I disagree with the views of certain sports organisations that believe that there would be more disputes in court following some kind of consolidation or codification of principles relating to the activities of sport beyond the strictly sporting context, complying of course with the principles of self-regulation. In my opinion, the opposite would be the case. Greater legal certainty can only be beneficial.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I should also like to appeal to sports organisations to accept the right of appeal to the common courts. Every individual has the right to appeal to the courts. The competence of tribunals of a strictly sporting nature is not at issue, but the restriction of these rights by certain sports organisations is unacceptable.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Finally, I should like to raise another very important matter. Sport plays a very important role in society. The Member States should therefore retain the right to take measures aimed at protecting the right to information and ensuring viewers’ access to television broadcasts of major sport events. I have in mind the Olympic Games and the European Championship or World Cup. Everyone should be able to access such events freely. Before I conclude, I must thank Mr Mavrommatis for his excellent work on this report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-074" speaker_id="2309" name="Richard Corbett" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, sport should, of course, be run by the sporting authorities themselves but, to the extent that it is also an economic activity, it unavoidably falls under employment law, competition law, copyright law, media rights and so on.</p>
      <p sl="en">The problem is that these laws have often been drawn up without the specific needs and requirements of sport in mind. Under the current Treaties, there is little leeway to take account of those specific needs. I am glad that with the Lisbon Treaty, there will be a greater margin to allow us to derogate, to make exceptions or to interpret laws with the specific needs of sport in mind.</p>
      <p sl="en">We cannot, for instance, apply competition law in its purely economic sense if that would ultimately destroy competition in its sporting sense. There is no better example of this than the collective sale of TV rights, as is practised by the English Premier League, for instance, with redistribution to all clubs. This is in contrast to Spain where two clubs pick up more than half of the TV revenue just for themselves.</p>
      <p sl="en">We should also accept that the UEFA scheme of home-grown players is a proportionate response and is acceptable under European Union law, unlike FIFA’s bull-in-a-china-shop ‘six-plus-five’ scheme.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-075" speaker_id="28388" name="Grażyna Staniszewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, as a member of the Committee on Regional Development, I should like to highlight the role of the regions and local government in developing sport infrastructure, organising widely accessible events, and promoting sport and a healthy lifestyle amongst the residents of local municipalities, that is to say, amongst European citizens.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I should also like to draw attention to an issue related to access to sport for the disabled. The Member States should at least guarantee disabled pupils access to basic physical education classes. Wherever possible, these pupils should also have access to higher level classes.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Ladies and gentlemen, it should be remembered that sport is one of the most effective methods of achieving social integration. It ought therefore to receive much more significant support from the European Union, by way of special programmes, especially for the organisers of international sporting events for young people, including those that make a particular contribution to integration by involving disabled persons. Sport involves more than physical activity and health. It makes an invaluable contribution to developing the spirit of tolerance, honesty and respect for the principles of fair play. All this is particularly important for the children and young people who are today’s young citizens of the European Union.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-076" speaker_id="4517" name="Christopher Heaton-Harris" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, before I speak I should declare that I have a number of financial interests related to this subject, which are listed in my declaration available on the internet.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would also like to congratulate the rapporteur, Mr Mavrommatis, for his concern and knowledge of this subject, especially regarding doping in sport.</p>
      <p sl="en">In fact, the first draft of his report, before the amendments came in, was probably as good a document on this subject as you will ever find in short form. As ever, though, the committees came in at this point, and the amendments that were adopted in the Committee on Culture ruined just about any good work that was done. For example, the bizarre call for a European police force for sport in paragraph 59, or the talk about ‘financial doping’ in paragraph 16, which is having a snipe against private investment and in some cases inward investment into the European Union. This report unfortunately looks at sport through the lens of professional football. As a soccer referee, mainly at the amateur level, for the last 28 years, I can tell you this report does absolutely nothing to address the problems that amateur football has, let alone those of amateur sport in general.</p>
      <p sl="en">This House says that we are not trying to influence the decisions of governing bodies, but already we have seen in the debate today an attack on FIFA’s ‘six-plus-five’ idea. Governing bodies should watch out. Giving the priority on sport to the European Union is not a good thing.</p>
      <p sl="en">Turning to sports betting, we have heard many views on this. Using this report to try and close down the debate on liberalising gambling and the lottery market is plainly wrong. This debate should go in a different direction and come from a different committee. Those that talk about it should just look at what is happening in Italy, where the gradual liberalisation of the market has grown the amount of money available to all.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have talked about the collective selling of television rights which I am in favour of because it has worked in the UK, but I strongly believe in subsidiarity and surely this should be left to the Member States.</p>
      <p sl="en">There are many good things in this white paper on sport, even if too little mention is made of the Special Olympics and the Paralympics movements. But, overall, this report is an insult to the Irish voters by talking about the Lisbon Treaty as if it were already here and as if their vote does not count. Therefore the UK Conservative delegation will have to vote against at the end.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-077" speaker_id="36394" name="Donato Tommaso Veraldi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I should like to thank the rapporteur for his excellent work on a report aimed at giving strategic guidance on the role of sport in the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="it">Sport is a social phenomenon which has always fostered values such as solidarity, team spirit and identity, as asserted by the Declaration on the overall significance of sport, annexed to the Amsterdam Treaty. Sporting activity helps to develop physical, intellectual and social skills, which is why sport should be practised both within the education system and in other aspects of social life.</p>
      <p sl="it">One point that should not be underestimated is the benefit to disabled people of practising sport: all the Member States, local and regional authorities, and sports organisations should guarantee and facilitate disabled access to sporting installations. Sport is having to confront new threats in contemporary society, such as the exploitation of young players, doping, racism, violence and money laundering. The problem of violence arises not only inside but also outside of the stadium.</p>
      <p sl="it">I compliment the Commission on its undertaking to prevent disorder by facilitating dialogue with Member States, international organisations, sports bodies and police forces. It is also important to emphasise the economic side of sport. Discriminatory tax systems applied by Member States in favour of players can result in distortions of competition. Rules therefore need to be adopted to ensure fair competition between sports bodies.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-078" speaker_id="28126" name="Christofer Fjellner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="sv">Mr President, the report’s eulogy of sport is something one can only agree with. Sport means a great deal for society, and it creates many important values to which I can hardly do justice in only two minutes. It also contributes to bringing Europe together. However, just because something is important, that does not mean it is political, and just because something contributes to bringing Europe together, it is not a primary responsibility of the EU.</p>
      <p sl="sv">That is something which I think is being lost in this debate, not least if people maintain that more sport-related initiatives should be taken at EU level. That is not what I think. Therefore I do not consider that we need a special European gambling police. I do not think that sports agents earn too much money, and that there should be an argument for us to create special training for sports agents. Nor should we even out incomes between successful and less successful clubs. Trying to limit what the report calls the excessively busy schedules of athletes will probably not get them to resist doping.</p>
      <p sl="sv">However, we must examine a number of false assertions made about the gambling market in Europe. There is no connection between private players in the gambling market and match-fixing. On the contrary, some of the biggest scandals we have seen in Europe have affected countries with monopolies. There is no connection between gambling monopolies and a restrictive gambling policy. On the contrary, many of the state monopolies in Member States are some of the largest advertisers. It is not countries with competition that have an unregulated gambling market. On the contrary, it is in many countries with monopolies that gambling services are most poorly regulated and monopolies can most frequently do as they will.</p>
      <p sl="sv">We should not attempt through incorrect facts to keep the EU out of an area in which the EU actually has an important role to play. We have free movement of services in Europe, which should, of course, also apply to gambling services. The Member States’ false figures about gambling addiction often conceal pure protectionism and protection of their own revenue from gambling monopolies. In fact, all this hypocrisy about gambling policy merely shows that it is the finance ministers in the Member States who are suffering from the worst kind of gambling addiction. That is why we Swedish Conservatives find it very difficult to support large parts of this report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-079" speaker_id="4393" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">I have just received eleven requests for the floor, which therefore cannot be granted. I would remind Members who do not speak during the debate that they may submit a written statement of no more than 200 words, which will be annexed to the verbatim report of the debate, or give an explanation of vote at the end of the speeches.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-080" speaker_id="39715" name="Mihaela Popa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="ro">Mr. President, dear colleagues, I would like to congratulate my colleague Mavromatis and, at the same time, to thank him for cooperation because I proposed several amendments to this report.</p>
      <p sl="ro">I consider it is essential to introduce free access to sport events for young people under 14 years old, to create European championships at the level of schools and universities, as well as a “European Day without Food Additives”. It is essential to adjust the sport and school infrastructure to the needs of disabled people, to introduce mandatory medical insurances for high-performance athletes, and to draft European projects for prevention of violence on sports fields. It is essential to create European projects designed for pupils with special physical qualities.</p>
      <p sl="ro">In conclusion, I would like to express my conviction that, by adopting the White Paper on Sport, we will contribute to promoting a healthier and more valuable European society.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-081" speaker_id="39318" name="Costas Botopoulos" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, all my life I have absolutely loved sport, both as a participant and as a spectator. I should of course add that for years my fellow Member and friend Mr Mavrommatis and I were writing sports articles for the same paper.</p>
      <p sl="el">However, I am hardly optimistic after today’s debate. Whatever we do and however much we try to put these matters in order, the events themselves show that the situation is pretty dire.</p>
      <p sl="el">Doping is a daily problem and there have even been fatalities. The commercialisation of sport has been taken to extremes. Owing to the success of sport there is a preoccupation with spectacular shows on a grand scale, and this has led to corruption. In sport, television reigns supreme.</p>
      <p sl="el">I therefore think a symbolic gesture is very important. Bearing in mind the problems with the Olympic Games, I think we shall have to consider whether the Games should be returned permanently to Greece.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-082" speaker_id="23864" name="Toomas Savi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, as the President of the Estonian Ski Association, I agree with the concern mentioned in the report on the decreasing number of hours in both primary and secondary education for physical education. Physical education helps schoolchildren to develop the habit of pursuing a healthy lifestyle. It is a great challenge for many people involved in sport to increase their interest in sporting activities.</p>
      <p sl="en">For example, the Estonian Ski Association has created a year-round system of participation for children and non-professionals, but this has been quite an expensive undertaking. In this connection, I should point out that the funding of sporting activities benefits greatly from gambling. Many sports are subsidised from the profits of state-run lotteries as well as licensed gambling. I think that we have to find some alternative sources of financial support if we do not use that money.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-083" speaker_id="36748" name="Antonio De Blasio" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="hu">Thank you, Mr President. I would like to congratulate the rapporteur on preparing this report. We have heard a great deal here today, but I would like to draw your attention to a few aspects in particular. Obesity is becoming endemic, and our largely sedentary lifestyle is in no small part to blame for this. The situation could therefore be helped, as the previous speaker also said, by making daily physical education classes compulsory in the Member States from primary school level right through to higher education. For this we need facilities, however, and we also need to change the curriculum. As regards facilities, the situation could be improved if the government were to take on a greater role, since at least half of the revenue from sports, accounting for 4% of the EU’s gross domestic product, would need to be reinvested to bring about a major change in this situation. I certainly recommend doing this. I hope that the White Paper will improve the situation. Thank you for listening.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-084" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Vladimír Špidla" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="cs">As the vote will begin in a few minutes, I cannot make a longer speech. However, I would like to say a few things and reply to some questions. In my opinion, it is clear from the debate what a complicated phenomenon sport represents in the life of a modern society. The other thing which I am pleased to say is that, following the vote on Mr Mavrommatis’s report, we will have a very solid base for Europe’s forthcoming coherent policy on sport: a base grounded in the White Paper and Parliament’s report.</p>
      <p sl="cs">Understandably, the debate has revealed a whole range of thoughts, which it will be necessary to take up and begin work on in the near future. I would just like to emphasise the things I have listed here and which occur to me as especially significant. One of the problems, which is actually covered in the White Paper, is the education of sportspeople, especially young people, so as to prevent the situation that has been described, where their careers come to an end but they still do not have an adequate long-term future established. It is also equally important to address problems of people trafficking or the risk of trafficking in some cases in sport. Similarly, the Commission must apply itself to the issue of intellectual property, especially in relation to the Internet, which when all is said and done is the business of the Commission; but because I can see that actually the atmosphere is not conducive to long speeches, I shall just quickly answer the questions that have been posed.</p>
      <p sl="cs">First there was the question of the so-called ‘guidelines’. The Commission is of the opinion that, as yet, it is still not the right time to formulate these; nevertheless the Commission considers that attention should be paid to this problem. Of the other issues, I would like to mention the question of lotteries, which is very often cited. Here I would like to state that lotteries fall outside the Services Directive; consequently they are subject to Community law and it is necessary to seek a decision in each individual case. Another important question was the collective sale of broadcasting rights for television programmes. The Commission envisages that a solution will be found everywhere that will contain a significant element of solidarity, as has been mentioned. I think that I have very quickly touched on most of the questions that have been posed. Otherwise, obviously this is just one step, although a very important one, taken by the Commission and Parliament together.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-085" speaker_id="28574" name="Manolis Mavrommatis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, let me once again thank all the Members who have spoken here today and all those who have submitted amendments to the report on the White Paper on Sport.</p>
      <p sl="el">A total of 520 amendments have been tabled in the eight committees. I have aimed for conciliation solutions as far as possible, and this has now been achieved. The mere fact that these amendments were tabled by eight committees and voted in shows how important this report really is. Of course, it also shows the significance of the text that is to be incorporated into the Reform Treaty.</p>
      <p sl="el">This is an important first step for sport and for the EU. Much can be achieved though our joint cooperation and assistance.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-086" speaker_id="1911" name="Martin Schulz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, I am not sure under which rule I should rise at this juncture, but I will do so nonetheless. I would ask you to inform the Bureau that for me personally, at least – but I am sure I speak for all the Group chairmen here – the atmosphere in the Chamber at present is totally unacceptable. We cannot even hear people through the headphones, there is so much noise; it is quite appalling.</p>
      <p sl="de">Much of Commissioner Špidla's speech and Mr Mavrommatis's comments were largely inaudible because of the dreadful noise in the House. That is quite unacceptable. Would you please make sure that the Bureau leaves at least five minutes between the end of the debate and the vote, because we should not have to put up with this situation here in the Chamber.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-087" speaker_id="4393" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Voting time is scheduled immediately and we shall now proceed to the vote.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 142)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-088" speaker_id="34174" name="Iles Braghetto" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="it">I applaud the work of the rapporteur, Mr Mavrommatis, and welcome the eagerly awaited White Paper on Sport adopted by the Commission. It is a useful and necessary measure, in that sporting activity constitutes such a significant dimension of European society.</p>
      <p sl="it">I would draw attention to the position of the Committee on Employment and Social Affairs, emphasising that sport must be valued socially, especially in the case of young people as a means of teaching them tolerance, respect and involvement. I believe that the Member States – backed by clear, transparent Community guidelines and policies – should make suitable spaces available for sport and involve society as a whole, including disadvantaged groups, in order that sporting activity can bring people together and help combat phenomena such as racism and xenophobia.</p>
      <p sl="it">Given that a lack of physical activity encourages diseases such as obesity and other chronic illnesses, I believe that cooperation between the sports sector and the health sector is crucial. The European Union has a vital coordinating role in informing citizens and encouraging them to take part in a range of sporting activities.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-089" speaker_id="39719" name="Magor Imre Csibi" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="ro">I would like to emphasize the importance of physical education classes in the EU schools and secondary schools. For the moment, physical education remains the only discipline in the school curriculum that aims at preparing children for a healthy way of life. I appreciate the EU initiative to increase the number of physical education classes in schools.</p>
      <p sl="ro">Together with the increase in the number of physical education classes, we should also take into consideration two important issues: I refer to attractiveness and the possibility to have differentiated physical education classes. My statement relies on the discussions I have had with pupils and sports teachers in Romania. Unfortunately, the fact that physical education classes are not attractive leads to an increase in absenteeism.</p>
      <p sl="ro">One of the reasons is the absence of an adequate material basis to diversify classes. Another problem is the absence of special physical education classes for overweight or obese young people. Physical education classes have the same degree of intensity both for healthy children and for children with problems. Thus, sometimes, young people are forced to remain off the sports field.</p>
      <p sl="ro">These are some of the problems we find in several European Union Member States and for which we have to find solutions. I invite the European Commission to come up with solutions and even with examples of good practice in the Member States.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-090" speaker_id="23806" name="Gyula Hegyi" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="hu">The report on sport by my fellow Member from Greece is an important document on an issue that is close to my heart. Sport has been part of European culture for many thousands of years. Ancient Greece bestowed on humankind among other things the joy of the Olympic Games. Today many people are concerned about whether it will be possible to protect the Olympics from a boycott, and from political passions that may be justified in other respects. I am pleased to say that in Hungary the key forces in politics and public opinion alike are against a boycott of the Beijing Olympics. As far as I can see, the mood is similar throughout the whole of Europe. It is therefore to be hoped that this time, after previous unfortunate boycotts, politics will not spoil the enjoyment of sportsmen and women and the many hundreds of millions of people who love sport. Participation by politicians at the opening ceremony is another matter entirely. This is a matter for politicians to decide in their capacity as politicians, and neither sport nor sportspeople should be drawn into it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-091" speaker_id="33987" name="Monica Maria Iacob-Ridzi" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="ro">When speaking about the reviewed Lisbon Strategy, we cannot ignore a sector that employs 15 million people and produces around 4% of the European Union GDP. Indeed, sport can be an important component for our 2 big objectives: economic growth and employment</p>
      <p sl="ro">This is why I would like to emphasize some budgetary aspects of the European Union’s support for the sport sector. For the moment, we have no clear reference in the treaties in force that would allow our active involvement through programmes and funds. Nevertheless, until the Lisbon Treaty becomes effective, we can still initiate preparatory actions in the Committee on Budget, which, although limited to insignificant amounts, could start very useful projects for European sport from 2009.</p>
      <p sl="ro">I regret that, during this week’s presentation of the new Preliminary Draft Budget, we did not discuss more on the budgetary line that can be established at Chapter 3 – Citizenship of the EU Budget. I hope that, by the first Budget reading in the autumn, we will submit constructive proposals for this field.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-092" speaker_id="28141" name="Lívia Járóka" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="hu">Let me first of all congratulate my honourable friend Mr Mavrommatis on his report encouraging European Union Member States to exchange best practice in the interests of preventing violence, racism and xenophobia at and around sports grounds. Taking action to combat the racism that, unfortunately, is occurring increasingly at sporting events is a task to be performed jointly by the authorities in the Member States, sports associations and competition organisers. It is also in their common interests. Some superb initiatives that stand out in this regard include the Union of European Football Associations (UEFA)’s campaign ‘Football Against Racism in Europe (FARE)’, and the series of events entitled ‘Racism spoils the game’. The most effective mechanism for combating the racism and exclusion occurring in the sporting arena, however, is the game itself, as it fosters in individuals a sense of team spirit, cooperation and fair competition, as well as reinforcing cooperation and solidarity as social values.</p>
      <p sl="hu">According to statistics, however, certain groups in society, notably the most disadvantaged ethnic minorities, engage much less in sports activities and have less access to government-run sports facilities. For this reason, the European Union needs to establish an appropriate reference framework for promoting equal opportunities in the pursuit and funding of sports. The leadership of sports associations in the Member States, meanwhile, in cooperation with local and regional government, must give priority to participation by disadvantaged groups in their given branch of sport.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-093" speaker_id="38609" name="Roumyana Jeleva" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="bg">I would like to congratulate our colleague Mavrommatis on his excellent report. I commend the inclusion of sport in the Lisbon Treaty, the requirement for the 2009 budget to have a separate budget line for the activities in the field of sport, and the development of measures for its promotion in the Member States. I believe that today’s debate sets the beginning of the promotion of a consistent European policy in the field of sport.</p>
      <p sl="bg">Being a member of the Committee on Regional Development from Bulgaria, a country with underdeveloped sport infrastructure, especially in amateur sport, I would like to call upon the European Commission and the Member States to more actively use the European Regional Development Fund and the other financial tools for investment in the urban environment, and for development of sport-related infrastructure and projects. I do believe that sport should and can become part and parcel of the strategies for sustainable development of our regions, municipalities, cities and villages with the EU assistance.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-094" speaker_id="28263" name="Lasse Lehtinen" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fi">Sport is competition, but of a sort to which the EU’s laws on competition cannot be applied.</p>
      <p sl="fi">To preserve the specificity of sport, it should be given a chance for self-regulation in the future, in accordance with each sport’s best traditions. As legislators, we need to pass laws which guarantee that politicians and judges keep as far away from sport as possible. This seemingly contradictory requirement is dealt with more coherently in this report than it is in the Commission’s White Paper.</p>
      <p sl="fi">It is important for European sport for all and grassroots activity that Member States are able to preserve their national gambling systems, which are an essential ingredient in the specificity of sport. The by-products of gambling are also easier to prevent in countries where the state has a monopoly. In all sports, professional sport and businesses structured around it benefit from voluntary, unpaid, grassroots activity and public funding.</p>
      <p sl="fi">Parliament, for its part, needs to be able to ensure that the social basis for sport does not crumble under pressure from market forces.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-095" speaker_id="23781" name="Janusz Lewandowski" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pl">Sport is such an important part of daily life and is also so globalised that it merits the attention of the European Union’s institutions. A joint effort to combat certain related phenomena is more effective than action by individual Member States.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Doping is a recognised and widespread scourge of contemporary competitive sport. That is why the fight against doping is given precedence in the European Parliament’s report. Members who hail from the former Communist bloc recall how doping can become a nationalised method of breeding champions, sanctioned by the authorities of a country building its prestige on the basis of success on the sports field. The rapporteur made a wise remark, based on the reality of the situation. He stated that on its own, treatment of the symptoms through increased controls will not be effective. It has to be accompanied by measures to eliminate the underlying reasons for this phenomenon. I have in mind a schedule of events that is more than the body can stand and education.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Another noticeable scourge of mass sport events is the expression of racism and discrimination. I make a distinction between this and the restrictions imposed by FIFA concerning the number of national and foreign members of a team, for example. Such restrictions are governed by concern for the progress and development of young talent (instead of transfers), and are not an instance of discrimination against players on the grounds of their national origin.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I also welcome the attention paid to phenomena linked to the commercialisation of sport and its side effects such as games of chance and unequal access to broadcasts of sport events. I agree that these are important issues too.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-096" speaker_id="37524" name="Marusya Ivanova Lyubcheva" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="bg">Mr President, it is great that the EP is discussing the White Paper on Sport. We should pay attention to the need for balancing the policies aimed at the development of professional and amateur sport. Sport excellence costs a lot, but it is equally necessary to increase the funding of mass sport from childhood to retirement age. It is necessary to establish infrastructure enabling the integration of all social groups of citizens.</p>
      <p sl="bg">Sport calls for education from an early age and sport is instrumental in eliminating many other problems such as the abuse of drugs, alcohol, and tobacco. We should urge all Member States to set up areas for free sport and areas free of drugs, alcohol and tobacco. I have recently made a public opinion poll which makes it very clear that young people engaged in sport do not use drugs and alcohol. Their behavioural culture is very different; tolerance and solidarity are very important elements that sport nurtures in them. Therefore the involvement of education in sport is of special significance. There is also something else that I would like to share with you: there exist specialised sport schools and it is very important for their activities to be balanced with the work of sport clubs recruiting their athletes. It is necessary to have legislative regulation to this effect for both sport and education.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-097" speaker_id="26829" name="Siiri Oviir" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="et">Much has been said here about the role of sport in culture, its effect on health etc. Sport has a very big role to play both physically and psychologically. In recent years the social benefit of sport has been actively promoted in Europe to give everyone the opportunity to participate to the best of their ability in the life of their communities. I am extremely sorry that the same cannot be said for disabled sport. As President of the Physically Disabled Sports Association in Estonia I know how difficult it is to organise sports events for the disabled, to get them coverage in the media, and to obtain resources from government and from sponsors. Our sportsmen and women are aware that equal conditions and opportunities have not been established for them.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-098" speaker_id="36281" name="Silvia-Adriana Ţicău" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="ro">The cultural statistics published by Eurostat in 2007 were obtained based on the activities the Member States acknowledge to enter this category. Unfortunately, sport and tourism were excluded and I believe this should be corrected. I appreciate as positive the development of sport tourism over the last years, and the promotion of winter and nautical sports.</p>
      <p sl="ro">The existence of sport facilities in hotel complexes or the creation of tourist routes for bikers could have a beneficial impact both on the population’s health and the environment. In great European cities, there are already parking facilities that provide tourists with bicycles, free of charge, during the entire period of stay of the vehicles.</p>
      <p sl="ro">On May 1st , in Galaţi, the town where I come from, I waited for the people who decided to devote their time to participating in a cross-country race at the finish line. I was glad especially for the children and the disabled people who crossed the finish line. Education is essential in promoting sport. In Romania, the construction of several hundreds of sports halls for schools and high schools began in 2001, both in the urban and in the rural environment. I think this type of investment should continue.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. Voting time">
    <intervention id="4-101" speaker_id="4313" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">I first of all have the pleasure of telling the House that the Lithuanian Parliament ratified the Treaty this morning.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is voting time.</p>
      <a text="(For the results and other details of the vote: see Minutes)"/>
      <p sl="unknown">Before the vote:</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-102" speaker_id="1275" name="Jens-Peter Bonde" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, today is my last vote in Parliament. Tomorrow Hanne Dahl will represent the Danish June Movement. May I thank all of you for the good battles on constitutions and referendums and good cooperation in our joint fight for transparency.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have managed to open the secret telephone book in the Commission. We have their agendas and their minutes on the net. We will soon see who advises the Commission and who gets the subsidies. Such victories were only possible because we cooperated across political lines.</p>
      <p sl="en">In the Convention we had the signatures from 23 governments, every single MP and every MEP except one, for a very simple proposal to turn the procedure on transparency. Everything has to be open and transparent unless you make a derogation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Also, I thank you for the support on several amendments on F-gases, on the climate, pesticides and drinking water, transport, nitrate in ecological sausages.</p>
      <p sl="en">My second wish is that laws will no longer be established by civil servants behind closed doors. Please ensure that all European laws have to pass through this Parliament in a public vote.</p>
      <p sl="en">Thank you, colleagues, for 29 years in our joint assembly …</p>
      <p sl="en">… and thank you to the Danish voters who made it possible!</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem6" title="5.1. EC/Seychelles Agreement - fishing opportunities and financial contributions (A6-0085/2008, Josu Ortuondo Larrea) (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem7" title="5.2. Excise duty on beer produced locally in Madeira (A6-0146/2008, Sérgio Marques) (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem8" title="5.3. Exercise of implementing powers conferred on the Commission (A6-0107/2008, Monica Frassoni) (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-108" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="László Kovács" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the Commission welcomes the report by Ms Frassoni, which approves the conclusion of the bilateral agreement between Parliament and the Commission on procedures for implementing Council Decision 1999/468/EC, as amended by Decision 2006/512/EC. In this context, the Commission underlines that paragraph 11 of the agreement covers extremely urgent cases in general.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission would like to thank Parliament and in particular Mr Galeote and Mr Corbett for the excellent spirit of cooperation which prevailed during the negotiation of this agreement. Yesterday the Commission approved the agreement and President Barroso will sign it in the coming days.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem9" title="5.4. Implementing measures (amendment of Rule 81) (A6-0108/2008, Monica Frassoni) (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem10" title="5.5. Support schemes for farmers (support for cotton) (A6-0166/2008, Ioannis Gklavakis) (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="5.6. Transatlantic Economic Council (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-113" speaker_id="1898" name="Erika Mann" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, in our deliberations on the joint motion for a resolution which took place on a cross-party basis on Monday, we forgot that the IMF recommendations on financial crises are already available and that it is now a matter of their implementation. I would therefore recommend – and I very much hope that this will have the support of the House – that the following phrase be inserted in the text:</p>
      <p sl="de">‘To the implementation by both parties of the conclusions.’</p>
      <p sl="de">and then the remainder of the text. There would be no other changes to the text.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem12" title="5.7. Human Rights in the World 2007 and the EU's policy on the matter (A6-0153/2008, Marco Cappato) (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-119" speaker_id="2295" name="Hannes Swoboda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PSE Group">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, may I simply make the following statement on behalf of my group: we wish to withdraw this Amendment 3. We continue to take the view that non-violence is, unfortunately, not always enough to ensure respect for human rights – I would merely recall Kosovo and Darfur here – but that should not imply that we are against the principle of non-violence. We therefore wish to withdraw our amendment. We will vote for the amendment tabled by the PPE-DE Group and proceed on that basis.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-121" speaker_id="4740" name="Marco Cappato" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="it">Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, I wanted to thank Mr Swoboda of the Socialist Group for having withdrawn this amendment, for the sake of simplification, and also for clarifying that the proposal is not, in a manner of speaking, the only instrument.</p>
      <p sl="it">I should like to table an oral amendment on the amendment put forward by the PPE-DE Group, also aimed at simplification: the beginning of the paragraph would read as follows: ‘considers non-violence to be the most appropriate means’, and the rest of the paragraph would remain as it stands. I would also ask that the word ‘non-violence’ be written as a single word in all language versions, because it is not merely a negative concept indicating the absence of violence, but a positive concept of action, as the Dalai Lama, Gandhi and other historical figures have taught us.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-123" speaker_id="4385" name="Hélène Flautre" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="fr">Madam President, I wish to propose an oral amendment to paragraph 23, with the agreement of our rapporteur, to state the following:</p>
      <p sl="fr">‘notes with concern that during the last year of activities that new body has not proved its credibility but stresses once again the crucial role of the UNHCR within the overall UN architecture;’.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem13" title="5.8. EU Election Observation Missions (A6-0138/2008, Véronique De Keyser, José Ignacio Salafranca Sánchez-Neyra) (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-128" speaker_id="2341" name="Michael Gahler" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, in consultation with the two rapporteurs, I propose the following addition:</p>
      <p sl="de">‘Pays tribute to the participation of observers from third countries, such as Switzerland, Norway and Canada, in EU electoral observation missions’.</p>
      <p sl="de">Those concerned had requested that, and I think this encourages them to take part again next time.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem14" title="5.9. Trade and Economic Relations with the countries of South East Asia (ASEAN) (A6-0151/2008, Glyn Ford) (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-134" speaker_id="1413" name="Glyn Ford" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, following the debate last night, I have agreed to withdraw Amendment 11 and to have Amendment 12 to paragraph 17 as an addition. This is following an agreement with Mr Varela Suanzes-Carpegna from the PPE-DE Group.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem15" title="5.10. Management of deep-sea fish stocks (A6-0103/2008, Rosa Miguélez Ramos) (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem16" title="5.11. Framework for the activities of lobbyists in the EU institutions (A6-0105/2008, Ingo Friedrich) (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-139" speaker_id="1920" name="Hartmut Nassauer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, on behalf of my Group, may I request a roll-call vote on Amendment 1 and on the second part of the split vote on Amendment 11.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-140" speaker_id="4313" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">I would remind you that the deadline has passed. However, if there are no objections, we will agree to your request.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-142" speaker_id="4393" name="Mario Mauro" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, the purpose of this amendment is to delete the following words: ‘when they are acting in accordance with the role, and carrying out the tasks of such bodies, as provided for in the Treaties’. It has to do with the fact that regions and local authorities, unlike private lobbyists, represent the general interest: it would therefore be simplistic to liken regions and local authorities to private lobbyists. Indeed, the statutes of many European regions and local authorities allow them to intervene in a much broader manner than is provided for by the Treaties in order to safeguard at Community level the public interests in question. That is why I called for the last phrase of the amendment to be deleted.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-144" speaker_id="37324" name="Adina-Ioana Vălean" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, we have an oral amendment to Amendment 3. We want to replace the word ‘churches’ with the word ‘religious’ so the phrase will go like this: ‘[ …] should be considered lobbyists and treated in the same way: professional lobbyists, companies’ in-house lobbyists, NGOs, think-tanks, trade associations, trade unions and employers’ organisations, religious, philosophical and nonconfessional organisations [ …]’ and so on.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-146" speaker_id="4254" name="Monica Frassoni" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, this is proof that lobbies do work!</p>
      <a text="(Applause from the centre and from the left)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-148" speaker_id="4254" name="Monica Frassoni" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, it seems that European English has betrayed us. Therefore, because the text of this amendment is apparently not very clear, my group will withdraw Amendment 15 on the question of the bands of money requested to declare the financial disclosure of a lobbyist. But we really do hope, even if the vote is not going as we would like it to go, that, during the discussion of the working group, this issue will be clarified and will come back.</p>
      <p sl="en">Thank you very much, and I thank everybody for the work we did together.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem17" title="5.12. White Paper on Sport (A6-0149/2008, Manolis Mavrommatis) (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem18" title="6. Membership of Parliament: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem19" title="7. Composition of committees and delegations: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem20" title="8. Approval of Minutes of previous sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem21" title="9. Explanations of vote">
    <intervention id="4-157" speaker_id="28579" name="Katerina Batzeli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="el">Madam President, for a delicate and particularly important product in Greece’s agriculture, one would expect that with a reform yielding, if anything, to the pressure of the European Court of Justice rulings there would be a safeguard for the new CMO in cotton until 2013. This consolidation would be based on the principles of the CAP under the single payment scheme, the financial guarantee of Community funds in the national envelope of each country, and the possibility of flexibility in the Member States on the management of the national envelope.</p>
      <p sl="el">We should aim at the greatest possible area payments per hectare within the bounds of budget neutrality. We should also channel aid to producers who will improve the quality of their produce.</p>
      <p sl="el">However, this has not been achieved. Indeed, in a proposed formation of a restructuring fund, as has been suggested in the report in the framework of the 1st pillar, it is suggested that there should be funding to modernise the sector, especially the ginning industry, as stated primarily in amendments 9, 14, 16, 23, 26, 31 and 39. There is a reconstruction to counterbalance the losses that the ginning industry will suffer as a result of any decrease in production or disturbance in the cotton market.</p>
      <p sl="el">For these reasons, the PASOK Parliamentary Group has voted in plenary against the report on the direct support scheme for cotton.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-159" speaker_id="33569" name="Syed Kamall" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, thank you very much for this opportunity to explain the way I voted on the TEC agreement.</p>
      <p sl="en">I think it is fair to say that we all welcome regulatory cooperation, especially where this will help to facilitate more trade and especially where it helps facilitate transatlantic trade, because all too often, our two large trading blocks – the EU and the US – are at loggerheads on trade issues.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, we should ensure that any agreements that we come to on common regulatory standards are not used as an excuse for joint protectionism. We have to make sure that any global standards that we arrive at together are not used as an excuse to shut out producers and suppliers from other world markets.</p>
      <p sl="en">Therefore, as we seek to adopt common global standards, let us make sure that we are also in a position to help producers from poorer countries to adopt those standards as well, so that we are not using these standards as an excuse to shut them out from world markets.</p>
      <p sl="en">Altogether I think on both sides we welcome this agreement, and for this reason I voted in favour.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-161" speaker_id="28239" name="Milan Horáček" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, I voted in favour of Mr Cappato's report because it deals with one of the European Parliament's most important functions, namely to perform an oversight function in respect of the Council's and the Commission's performance on human rights policy. This strengthens the European Union's role as the guardian of human rights worldwide. As part of this process, it is essential, for example, for the Subcommittee on Human Rights to undertake a systematic evaluation of the relevant instruments, and for Parliament to be involved in the European Union's human rights dialogues.</p>
      <p sl="de">Nonetheless, any policy pursued in this area will simply be window-dressing unless it takes, as its starting point, the basic premise that these fundamental rights are indivisible. That is the only way to ensure that credibility wins out over double standards.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-162" speaker_id="28424" name="Tunne Kelam" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I voted against paragraph 141, which declares full support for the Yogyakarta Principles. Now, these principles are anything but clearly defined, especially on such delicate issues as sexual orientation and gender identity.</p>
      <p sl="en">Instead, I supported Amendment 15, which ‘takes note of’ these principles. The point is that these principles should not be interpreted as something like a norm for the Member States.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-163" speaker_id="34254" name="Dimitar Stoyanov" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="bg">Thank you, Mme Chair. I am taking the floor on the Cappato report because of the amendment proposed by the rapporteur himself; namely, the first amendment in which the rapporteur all of a sudden begins to philosophize on the adequacy of the modern national state and national sovereignty in modern times. Mr. Cappato may not be very clear about these things; it is up to him but absolutely the same ideas were promoted by the communist totalitarian regimes that did not care for human rights at all. The same thing which features in his amendment was explained by the communists in Bulgaria and the other Eastern European countries. Therefore I would suggest to Mr. Cappato that he visit Kim Chen Ir in North Korea if he would like to continue in the same vein. There his ideas would be shared and, I am sure, warmly welcomed.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-165" speaker_id="4536" name="Martin Callanan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I voted in favour of this report. I think the EU’s work in election observation missions is extremely powerful, it is extremely important, and it is conducted with a great degree of professionalism. It contributes to the democratic process and to democratic development in many underprivileged and developing countries.</p>
      <p sl="en">I had the privilege of being chairman of Parliament’s election observation mission in Sierra Leone, a very difficult country, a very poor country, a country that presented many logistical difficulties, particularly weather difficulties in the rainy season, with the mission that was conducted. It was conducted with great professionalism by all of the staff, both EU staff and locally-recruited staff.</p>
      <p sl="en">It was indeed very humbling to see the enthusiasm with which the election was viewed by many ordinary Sierra Leoneans, queuing up for many hours in the rain to cast their votes in a democratic election. Our contribution to that is well worth the relatively small amount of money, and I am delighted to welcome this report and vote in favour of it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-167" speaker_id="33569" name="Syed Kamall" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, thank you very much for giving me this opportunity to give my explanation of vote on the Ford report on the agreement with ASEAN.</p>
      <p sl="en">In general I think we prefer to improve and increase international trade through the multilateral framework of the World Trade Organisation, but I think we have to recognise the role that bilaterals play in extending trade and the benefits of globalisation throughout the world.</p>
      <p sl="en">I thought it was particularly important in this report that we highlighted human rights issues. Generally I am rather sceptical when we do this, because quite often it is an excuse for protectionism against products from other countries. But in this context it is particularly appropriate, given that Burma is a member of ASEAN.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, I did have a real problem with this, because I did initially put an amendment to committee, which was accepted, saying that if particular ASEAN countries did not want to be part of this agreement, we should still go ahead with agreements with those countries that did want to. We should not let the most protectionist country hold up agreements.</p>
      <p sl="en">Unfortunately the EU is hell-bent on trade-block-to-trade-block negotiations, and for this reason I abstained.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-169" speaker_id="4413" name="Carlo Fatuzzo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="it">Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, it gives me great satisfaction to make this explanation of vote while you are in the Chair, Mrs Morgantini, and especially with the welcome sound of Members applauding behind me. I wish to say in my personal capacity, and this relates to me personally as an individual Member and also as a representative of the Pensioners' Party, that I voted against this report on the regulation of lobbies. The reason is this: I am unimpressed by the fact that it is taken for granted that Members of the European Parliament are influenced in their decisions by other people, and that, consequently, regulation is deemed necessary.</p>
      <p sl="it">True enough, I have always been influenced in my decision-making by Carlo Fatuzzo, by Carlo Fatuzzo alone and by none other than Carlo Fatuzzo. I therefore find it very odd that any such possibility can be accepted. If anything at all were to be done, or should be done, to help us better understand the documents on which we vote, we ought to have experts available who each say the opposite of the other, and then we can use our own intelligence to decide.</p>
      <p sl="it">I would conclude by asking myself and asking you this, Madam President: who influenced the decision to regulate lobbies? There is obviously a lobby – the lobby of lobbies – which has influenced the rules on lobbies!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-170" speaker_id="4453" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">I see that you are still an individualist: I hope you will have an opportunity to compare notes with others.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-171" speaker_id="4517" name="Christopher Heaton-Harris" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, firstly it is a huge pleasure to see you in the chair today. You should be chairing more sessions. It is also a huge pleasure to follow Mr Fatuzzo in an explanation of vote. Fortunately, I did not do it through my first mandate, otherwise I would never have had lunch in Strasbourg.</p>
      <p sl="en">I was wondering, when we were voting on this report, whether we were actually targeting the correct audience. It is good that we are honest about the lobbyists that we see in this place, and it is good that we get a record of who the Commission is seeing. But I do wonder if we should not get a record also of who the Commission is influencing to try and influence parliamentary votes on directives it is sending through.</p>
      <p sl="en">Already we have had exposed by my illustrious colleague Mr Hannon, in Commission Questions, the amount of money that charity organisations like the NSPCC in the UK get directly from the European Commission, and then it comes as no surprise when they write to us to say: actually, we should be in favour of the Lisbon Treaty.</p>
      <p sl="en">There are a whole bunch of organisations that received EU money when it came to the Citizens’ Agora in the build-up to the Lisbon Treaty, yet they were all on one side of the argument. There is a small problem with democracy in this place: the people we fund tend to be the wrong ones, and actually it would be better if we cut all this money out altogether.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-172" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel Hannan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, lobbyists love Brussels. They arrive in the European institutions and they perceive at once that the system was designed by and for people like them.</p>
      <p sl="en">They can get legislation through here that would never pass through a popularly elected legislature. I am thinking of bills such as the ban on higher-dose vitamin and mineral supplements that was the subject of intense opposition in all the Member States but that was pushed through here by a few large pharmaceutical corporations in backroom deals.</p>
      <p sl="en">So much, I think, is well known outside this Chamber. What is perhaps less widely appreciated is the extent to which these lobbying organisations, as my colleague Mr Heaton-Harris has just said, are themselves creatures of the European Union, wholly dependent on the Commission for their funding.</p>
      <p sl="en">And so, when the European Commission goes through the motions of consulting civil society, what it actually means is that it is consulting the European Union of Journalists, the European Women’s Lobby, the European Trades Unions Congress and a bunch of other organisations that depend on the European taxpayer for every euro of their income.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am bound to ask whether there is anybody out there in the nation states who genuinely supports this project without, on some level, being paid to. The way of testing whether I am right about that is to put your Lisbon Treaty to the people in a referendum. Pactio Olisipiensis censenda est!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-174" speaker_id="23787" name="Czesław Adam Siekierski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, in the context of this important report I would like to draw attention to the issue of sport amongst young people at local level.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Actions aimed at making physical activity more attractive to children and young people should be promoted, as should schools that actively support sport. It is therefore essential to support projects aimed at the development of sporting facilities in schools and beyond, together with plans to involve children in extra-curricular activities.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I believe that it is important to support sporting activities at grass roots , that is to say, at the level that is closest to the citizen. This can be achieved by providing appropriate financial support to smaller clubs and sport facilities.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-175" speaker_id="4517" name="Christopher Heaton-Harris" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I did speak in the main debate on this subject. But what I did not do was actually explain why I voted against. This was because of all sorts of reasons I explained in my vote. I would have loved to have voted in favour of this, if only the European institutions were doing something useful in sport.</p>
      <p sl="en">Last year in the budget debate, we actually voted as a Parliament against a line of money which had been match-funded for the Special Olympic Movement for Unified Sports, a programme which would have run across 10 countries of the European Union involving 3 000 people with intellectual disability.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am bringing this proposal back – and I have been talking to all the different rapporteurs in this place – but you do wonder actually how interested this place is in sport. Maybe it just wants to suck the power up so it can dabble in people’s everyday lives. But it does not want to actually do anything positive sometimes when it comes to people with disabilities.</p>
      <p sl="en">I think we missed an opportunity last year. I will be pressing this again this year and I record this interest with the Special Olympics, a wonderful organisation, here today.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-176" speaker_id="39022" name="Ewa Tomaszewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, I voted in favour of the report by Mr Mavrommatis. I did so not only because I consider it to be a comprehensive and well-prepared report, but also because I am particularly grateful to the rapporteur and to the Committee on Culture and Education for incorporating the amendments I tabled to the document. These amendments aim to ensure equal treatment for disabled sportspeople in the context of social solutions. Certain national legislative systems provide for financial support of Olympic athletes experiencing financial difficulties after the end of their sporting careers, but the provisions concerned do not apply to Paralympic athletes. Involvement in sport heightens the sense of personal dignity and self-esteem of the disabled.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-177" speaker_id="1429" name="Christopher Beazley" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I do not know whether I am in order or not. I have not made a written application for an explanation of vote. But if I may just very briefly reply to my good friend and colleague, Mr Heaton-Harris, I think we all have our own points of view about the value of the European institutions, but I do not think it is fair to attack the European Union, national governments, local government, for being interested or disinterested in the question of the disabled and sport.</p>
      <p sl="en">I have many examples in my constituency where the European Union quite frankly has brought enormous benefits to people – disabled and, indeed, not disabled. I just think it is unfair to attack any institution in that way. I think all of us want to do what we can to encourage sport, to encourage everybody to take a fair part. Whether you are pro-European or anti-European, that is another issue.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-178" speaker_id="28316" name="Hannu Takkula" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="fi">Madam President, I would like to say a few words about Mr Mavrommatis’ report. I voted in favour of it and I consider it to be excellent. What is especially good about it in my opinion is that it recognises the specificity of sport and gives attention to special needs groups, including the disabled. I agree with Mr Beazley and I do not completely understand my good friend Mr Heaton-Harris’s logic in this matter, as it is exactly in this way that we can ensure that special needs groups and the disabled receive equal treatment. Healthy exercise is one of the specific priority areas in this report. Sport has also proven to be a very good way to prevent racism and xenophobia.</p>
      <p sl="fi">I also want to say that there was something wrong with my voting machine and, for example, at point 42 I could not get it to work properly. I hope that the technical department will look into why my voting machine sometimes jammed. I noticed that others had the same problems, and I wish to send a message to the technical department that hopefully next time it will be working properly.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-180" speaker_id="4246" name="Othmar Karas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, may I begin with the Mavrommatis report. I voted in favour of the report because it particularly emphasises the contribution made to the financing of sport by the lotteries and Austria's casinos. I welcome the paragraph in question. I voted for the Friedrich report because it rejected the attack on the unique and wide-ranging role played by the recognised churches in society, and also offers a more nuanced view of the role of lawyers. I attach great importance to the expertise and information that we derive from our exchange of experience and dialogue about possible solutions with citizens, interest groups, lawyers and lobbyists.</p>
      <p sl="de">I would like to take this opportunity to express my thanks for the hundreds of discussions, as well as the countless e-mails and ideas that I receive. A few of them are irritating because they simply take up valuable time, but I have found the majority to be both informative and useful. Once again, I would like to express my thanks for that, but I would also like to say that the responsibility for the way we deal with lobbyists ultimately lies with us. We decide who we want to talk to, how much of our time they take up, what we talk about, and how we develop a working relationship. I say 'yes' to clear and transparent rules, but 'no' to overregulation which makes this working relationship more difficult and bureaucratic.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-183" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro Guerreiro" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">As we believe it is important to maintain and improve, as necessary, the agreement with the Republic of Seychelles, we agree with the assessment describing as inadequate the inclusion in the text of the protocol (setting out the fishing opportunities and their financial contribution) of considerations on the state of local port infrastructures and the possibility of changing aspects (including the objectives in using the financial contribution) under the exclusive competence of the Seychelles authorities.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Likewise, we regard as negative the proposal to include measures, such as those on the suspension of licences by the European Commission, which do not take into account, in particular, respect for and protection of the competences of the Member States.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Furthermore, the principle of equal pay for equal work is still not ensured as the agreement only specifies that the wage conditions of crews from the Seychelles, on board vessels originating from EU countries which will benefit from the agreement, cannot be worse than those of crews from the Seychelles carrying out similar work on board vessels from that country.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-184" speaker_id="2338" name="Ian Hudghton" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted against the report of Mr Ortuondo Larrea relating to a fishing agreement with the Seychelles. The CFP has been an unmitigated disaster and has not promoted a sustainable fishing industry around our coasts.</p>
      <p sl="en">As a result of this, hundreds of Scottish boats have had to be scrapped and fishing communities have suffered. The answer to this is not to export other Member States’ over-capacity in the form of third-country fishing agreements.</p>
      <p sl="en">If other Member States have too many boats to fish their own traditional fishing waters they should address this issue themselves – and not depend upon the EU to find more waters for them to plunder.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-185" speaker_id="4340" name="Margie Sudre" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">I am pleased that the European Parliament approved the amendments to the Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Community and the Seychelles for the period 2005-2011.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The changes do not modify the fundamental elements of the Agreement. They are merely a reflection of the success achieved and allow a practical adaptation that corresponds to actual needs. That is why, given the average level of catches over the past three years, the reference tonnage has been increased from 55 000 tonnes to 63 000 tonnes. Moreover, in order to balance the situation, the fee paid by shipowners has been increased to EUR 35 per tonne to bring the protocol into line with other tuna agreements, hence reducing the Community contribution from EUR 75 to EUR 65 per tonne. The total annual financial contribution thus increases from EUR 4 125 000 to EUR 5 355 000.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The success of this Agreement reflects the European Union’s clear and mutual interest in concluding partnership agreements, notably in the fisheries sector. The Réunion fleet has been able to benefit from these fishing possibilities and I hope that the vote today will help to strengthen and stimulate our maritime economy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-186" speaker_id="34720" name="Bernard Wojciechowski" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pl">The sea and maritime resources are very important for the European Union in terms of employment and economic growth. They are a source of food and energy. In addition, coastal regions are experiencing significant development of the tourist industry, which represents an important sector of the economy. Maritime resources should be exploited in a responsible manner.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The EU's fishing sector is the second largest in the world. The fisheries and aquaculture sector supplies approximately 7.3 million tonnes of fish a year; 360 000 people are employed in the fisheries and processing sector. I therefore believe that the EU should reach agreements with third countries on common fisheries policies, or improve existing arrangements.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-188" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro Guerreiro" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">We support the application of more individual rules, with derogations and specific, different and tailored measures duly adapted to the economic realities of the outermost regions and more favourable to their production capacities.</p>
      <p sl="pt">This report aims to apply a special rate of excise duty to beer produced in Madeira. This rate, which is lower than the national rate fixed, will apply in those cases where the annual production of the brewery does not exceed 300 000 hectolitres.</p>
      <p sl="pt">As pointed out by the Commission, the price of locally produced beer, even with the tax benefit of 50%, is still 7.5% higher than the retail selling price of beer brewed in mainland Portugal and sold on the market of Madeira. If the benefit of the tax reduction is lost, local breweries will be unable to match the competition.</p>
      <p sl="pt">As a result, bearing in mind the specific characteristics and demands of the situation in the outermost regions, we support the measures which therefore aim to guarantee the right of production in line with the region’s specific potential, which recognise the regional economy and, as a result, which guarantee the survival of the local brewing industry faced with the national and international market.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-189" speaker_id="28251" name="Jörg Leichtfried" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="de">The only reason why I am voting in favour of this decision on excise duty is its limited local scope, so it cannot adversely affect the Brauerei zu Göss brewery in Austria, which – as is well-known – produces the best beer in Europe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-190" speaker_id="34720" name="Bernard Wojciechowski" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pl">The issue dealt with by the rapporteur invites reflection on how to reconcile support for consolidation of a system of genuine competition with the principle of equality before the law. Clearly, the free market is the best mechanism for regulating the economy until something better is thought up, to paraphrase a certain statement. From that standpoint, the rapporteur's initiative may indicate interventionism, which would have negative implications for the economy. On the other hand, ensuring sustainability of the market involves protecting subdivision and preventing monopolisation. Broader debate and more expert research are required before taking a decision as important as the one involved. The report does not deal with all aspects of the subject. That is why I decided to abstain.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-998" speaker_id="33775" name="Jean-Pierre Audy" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">I voted in favour of the report by my Italian colleague Monica Frassoni on the conclusion of an interinstitutional agreement between the European Parliament and the Commission on procedures for implementing the Council Decision laying down the procedures for the exercise of implementing powers conferred on the Commission, as amended by Decision 2006/512/EC of 17 July 2006. Unfortunately, the comitology procedure is not working well and it is becoming urgent to put in place measures to enable the Commission to exercise its implementing powers and the European Parliament to monitor it. When applicable, reference in the texts to the regulatory procedure with scrutiny is obligatory for all three institutions. I am pleased that the new agreement defines more precisely the Commission’s obligation to inform Parliament in accordance with arrangements that ensure that the transmission system is transparent and efficient and that the information forwarded and the various stages of the procedure are identified. I welcome the introduction of an ‘early warning system’ whereby Parliament is informed of draft implementing measures. I support the idea that the Commission should make all draft implementing measures public as soon as they are formally proposed.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-192" speaker_id="28427" name="Alessandro Battilocchio" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="it">Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, I am in favour of the Frassoni report concerning the new comitology procedures.</p>
      <p sl="it">The new powers attributed to Parliament in the scrutiny procedure, enabling Members to block the passage of a text approved by the committee if the experts have not complied with their mandate, constitutes a major success for this House and an important step towards improving the balance of power between the European institutions.</p>
      <p sl="it">I agree that it is advisable to heighten the efficiency of the procedure by making committee decisions clearer and more accessible. Similarly, I am in favour of establishing an electronic register making it easier to verify decisions taken through comitology.</p>
      <p sl="it">It is of course essential that the three-month limit envisaged for Parliament’s right of scrutiny should be confined to exceptional cases only, in keeping with the letter of the July 2007 Interinstitutional Agreement: a shorter period should be admissible only where justified on grounds of urgency or efficiency.</p>
      <p sl="it">Some EP committees have already successfully threatened to use the right of veto in order to obtain an immediate response and clarification from the Commission. I therefore believe that this is an instrument which Parliament should increasingly use to exercise political control, too, over technical decisions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-997" speaker_id="33775" name="Jean-Pierre Audy" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">I voted in favour of the report by my Italian colleague Monica Frassoni on the amendment of Rule 81 of the European Parliament’s Rules of Procedure on the so-called ‘comitology’ implementing measures. Rule 81(4) of Parliament’s Rules of Procedure stipulates that where the implementing measures envisaged by the Commission are subject to the regulatory procedure with scrutiny, the time for scrutiny shall start to run when Parliament receives the draft measures in all official languages. I support the proposal to add that where shorter time limits apply, as provided for in Article 5a(5)(b) of Decision 1999/468/EC, and in cases of urgency, as provided for in Article 5a(6), unless the Chair of the parliamentary committee objects, the time for scrutiny shall start to run from the date of receipt by Parliament of the final draft implementing measures in the language versions submitted to the members of the committee established in accordance with Decision 1999/468/EC.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-194" speaker_id="1164" name="Bruno Gollnisch" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, Mrs Frassoni’s report highlights the somewhat cavalier attitude the Commission adopts, when it has power, in relation to the European Parliament. The rapporteur is right to remind the Commission of its duties and we support this attempt to restore a minimum of democratic scrutiny of the Commission’s activity.</p>
      <p sl="fr">It is doubtful, however, whether this will result in better application of this scrutiny in the future, if only because of the Commission’s secret desire to prevent Parliament from holding consultations on the measures it plans to implement.</p>
      <p sl="fr">We also regret that there is no mention of the fundamental problem, namely the extent of the Commission’s implementing powers, which resemble those of a genuine legislative and regulatory authority but entrusted to civil servants, and the democratic fraud that is the comitology procedure.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-196" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Charlotte Cederschiöld, Christofer Fjellner, Gunnar Hökmark and Anna Ibrisagic" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">We consider that the common agricultural policy should be abolished. At the same time we consider that agreements which have been entered into should be complied with. In today’s vote we have therefore voted in favour of the Commission’s proposal to comply with the accession treaties with Portugal, Greece and Spain in which the EU unfortunately committed itself to guaranteeing support for cotton production which also includes production support. We therefore regret that the Commission has not had the opportunity to present a proposal in this area which is in line with the policy for other agricultural sectors in which support has been de-coupled from production.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Parliament’s report (A6-0166/2008) proposed an opportunity for an even lesser de-coupling of support, and we therefore chose to vote against that report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-197" speaker_id="4466" name="Ilda Figueiredo" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">Given that the cotton sector is of great socio-economic importance to certain regions of the European Union, particularly Greece and Spain, the European Commission and the European Parliament should pay particular attention to this.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The truth is that, with the reform of the common agricultural policy which began in 2003, the introduction of the single payment of aid decoupled from production led, in 2006, to the Commission putting this principle into practice in the cotton sector.</p>
      <p sl="pt">However, Spain referred the matter to the European Court of Justice on the grounds that no impact assessment had been carried out prior to the reform. The Court found in Spain’s favour and annulled the new support scheme for cotton.</p>
      <p sl="pt">However, the proposal now presented by the European Commission is practically identical to the previous one. In addition, barely more than a year after the implementation of the reform of the common organisation of the market in cotton, the disastrous consequences of this can already be seen: production in this sector has fallen almost 20% in Greece and over 50% in Spain. Likewise, the number of farms has dropped by 11% in Greece and 25% in Spain. Even the ginning plants are threatened.</p>
      <p sl="pt">That is why we voted against this resolution.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-198" speaker_id="28586" name="Dimitrios Papadimoulis" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I have voted against the Gklavakis report, as did my political group, because, despite a limited number of positive amendments to the Commission’s original motion, the overall balance is negative. Greater support for cotton growers is necessary without further cuts in production. At the same time, substantial measures for environmental protection and viable agricultural development must be adopted.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-996" speaker_id="33775" name="Jean-Pierre Audy" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">I voted in favour of the European Parliament resolution of 8 May 2008 on the Transatlantic Economic Council, which underlines that a close transatlantic partnership is a vital instrument to shape globalisation in the interest of common values and towards an equitable political and economic global order. I share the view that a functioning and competitive transatlantic market is the base on which to anchor the transatlantic partnership so as to enable the EU and the US to jointly tackle global political and economic challenges. Secure trade is particularly important in an ever more integrated global economy, but I agree that the proposal to scan 100% of foreign containers as part of the fight against terrorist threats is unjustified and unrealistic. There is an urgent need for cooperation on the application of intellectual property rights, including measures to strengthen cooperation in the fight against counterfeiting and piracy, with a clear roadmap to facilitate mutual recognition of international patent law. I regret that monetary cooperation on the dollar/euro was not developed.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-200" speaker_id="5735" name="Anne Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">I abstained during the final vote on this resolution for the following reasons in particular.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The resolution contains positive points, such as the reference to the precautionary principle. However, I cannot support certain proposals and objectives.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Although I can accept the principle of a transatlantic market, it will be impossible, and even less desirable, to complete it by 2015.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Completing this market implies the elimination of non-tariff barriers (para. 17), i.e. social, health, environmental and other standards. The provisions the EU has adopted in these areas through its legislation provide satisfactory protection for European consumers and citizens, and they must be maintained if not improved.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Similarly, labelling and traceability are not enough to enable consumers to make informed choices (para. 28). A consumer protection policy cannot be reduced to this type of measure. Consumers’ choice of agricultural products must also be guaranteed by preventing the contamination of traditional and organic crops by GMOs.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Finally, as regards the import of American poultry treated with chlorinated water, the wording in the text is too ambiguous. Imports must be banned if we want to preserve the Community’s food safety policy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-201" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro Guerreiro" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">At a time when the crisis of capitalism is deepening and its contradictions are increasing, this resolution and the goals set for the (‘long-term’) creation of the ‘transatlantic market’ are presented as a real escape route, pointing to the increasing liberalisation of the markets in these two poles of the ‘triad’ and pillars of NATO as a ‘way out’.</p>
      <p sl="pt">In addition to reaffirming the ‘transatlantic’ strategic partnership, the resolution acts as a genuine roadmap to the liberalisation of the financial markets and trade relations between the EU and the US, by listing the obstacles to greater competition and capitalist concentration, to the joy and benefit of large financial and economic groups.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The resolution, in an (impossible) attempt to hide the true aims, contradictions and consequences of realising the ‘transatlantic market’, highlights certain potential social or environmental concerns. However, these seem to arise only as a function and variable of capitalist competition, particularly in the World Trade Organisation.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Despite trying to mitigate the situation by confronting the brutal reality of ‘capitalist globalisation’, the resolution conceals the profound consequences for workers and people in general, and for small and medium-sized enterprises, not only in the EU and the US but also internationally.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-202" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Kartika Tamara Liotard and Erik Meijer" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">We have voted against Amendment 4, because it states ‘is of the opinion that any possible solution should not lead to distortion of competition’.</p>
      <p sl="en">In the light of the issue, this underlines that economic interests are more important than public health concerns. We find this reasoning unacceptable. We believe when it comes to matters of food safety the European Union should adhere to the precautionary principle.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-203" speaker_id="4461" name="Luís Queiró" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">The realisation that there is a great deal of life in relations between the United States and the European Union, aside from third-country issues (although, even in these, the disagreement is not necessarily insurmountable), is vitally important. This debate, the indicated texts and the document adopted today may therefore prove to be very useful.</p>
      <p sl="pt">As a result, it is essential to complete the steps needed to achieve the goal of reinforcing transatlantic economic integration. In that respect, the efforts that have been made, particularly those aimed at removing non-customs barriers (obscure general rules which severely inhibit international trade) are, as demonstrated by recent studies, extremely useful. This must therefore result in greater commitment from both parties.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Apart from that, in this same area of international trade, the commitment on both sides of the North Atlantic must be intensified and made more consistent.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-204" speaker_id="2081" name="Peter Skinner" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">As a co-author of this resolution, I am in support of the realistic intentions of the TEC process.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is necessary for the EU and the USA to undertake this search for barrier-reducing initiatives. In particular I welcome the steady progress that has been made on financial services, IFRS and the broker/dealer agreement.</p>
      <p sl="en">More has to be done and other avenues should be explored, including the multilateral approach. I am concerned, however, that both sides should not wait for remedies which may or may not close differences between us. This will take hard work instead, and this is no more apparent than in the area of insurance and, in particular, the collateral issue.</p>
      <p sl="en">The TEC is not a trade issue per se. It is about a deepening of our relationship at the regulatory level which improves the openness and efficiency of our industrial performances and which does away with the weak excuses of the past.</p>
      <p sl="en">We now face a mounting challenge in the world where the interest for the EU and the USA is in having systems which promote growth rather than protectionism and isolationism.</p>
      <p sl="en">TEC helps to bring the EU and USA closer together, but it will not do to rely on the outcomes of TEC by themselves. More needs to be done to fold this kind of approach into our day-to-day considerations at this level. Failure is all too easy to predict based on our political economies – hard work is needed to overcome this fear.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-995" speaker_id="33775" name="Jean-Pierre Audy" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">I voted in favour of the own-initiative report by my Italian colleague Marco Cappato on human rights in the world in 2007. I support the statement that the Commission and the Council should take priority action – along the same lines as for the establishment of the ICC – to support the activities of the international courts involved in protecting human rights. The new United Nations Human Rights Council (UNHRC) has the potential to develop into a valuable framework for improving the human rights situation in the world. I am in favour of promoting non-violence as an essential means of ensuring respect for fundamental human rights and in favour of the fight against the death penalty. Like my colleagues, I am surprised that a number of European countries have not yet ratified the Optional Protocol to the Convention Against Torture. I am pleased to see how effective the European Instrument for Democracy and Human Rights (EIDHR) has been but its budget falls drastically short of the expectations of it, and I support an increase in the EIDHR budget from 2009.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-206" speaker_id="28427" name="Alessandro Battilocchio" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="it">I am explaining my vote in favour of the report on the protection of human rights, given that they are still being infringed all too often today.</p>
      <p sl="it">The European Union lists human rights among its founding principles, so much so that their observance rightly constitutes a prerequisite for EU accession.</p>
      <p sl="it">The European Union therefore has a responsibility to act as a guarantor of human rights in Europe and in third countries, by means of a coherent common foreign policy that is independent of the Member States’ interests and positions. The EU must promote ratification of the Statute of the International Criminal Court around the world to protect individuals from so-called crimes against humanity and to prevent genocides and other atrocities being perpetrated in future without fear of sanction; it must also help increase the efficiency and effectiveness of the UNHCR. I likewise think that the United Nations resolution on the universal moratorium on the use of the death penalty must be put into practice.</p>
      <p sl="it">The European Union must also contribute to the observance of human rights by its major trading partners. I hope China will discontinue its practice of torture as an important sign of openness to a culture that is respectful of human rights and consistent with the spirit of peace which has always symbolised the Olympic Games.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-207" speaker_id="28183" name="Patrick Gaubert" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">I welcome the adoption today of Mr Cappato’s motion for a resolution on the Annual Report on Human Rights in the World 2007 and the EU’s policy on the matter.</p>
      <p sl="fr">This report looks at the progress made in all parts of the world in the area of human rights and assesses the efforts made by the EU to promote human rights in its actions and policies.</p>
      <p sl="fr">It rightly underlines the need to improve the consistency of internal and external policies in this area.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The report focuses, in particular, on the question of the death penalty, on the fight against all forms of torture, and discrimination and violence against women, and on the need to strengthen the protection of children’s rights.</p>
      <p sl="fr">It reiterates the EU’s responsibility to promote the role of civil society in order to make the fight more effective and more pertinent and to strengthen the means envisaged for that purpose.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-208" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Hélène Goudin and Nils Lundgren" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">The June List supports the important work for human rights which is taking place all over the world, but we consider that this Annual Report is yet another attempt by this Parliament to extend the EU’s competence in areas of foreign policy.</p>
      <p sl="en">The situation in many countries is very disturbing, and the international community must of course react. However, this must take place through the UN and its various bodies which, unlike the EU, have legitimacy and broad support among a majority of states.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have therefore chosen to vote against the report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-209" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro Guerreiro" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">Every year we are confronted with this exercise in hypocrisy of the European Parliament on human rights in the world.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Obviously the report contains points which we support. However, in essence, it is a perfect example of the instrumentalisation of human rights and their unacceptable use as a political weapon in favour of the interests of the EU’s major powers, and their large financial and economic groups, and against those people who reject their dictates.</p>
      <p sl="pt">As such, there is a total absence of any references to and denouncements of the flagrant violations of human rights in Palestine, Iraq, Afghanistan, occupied Cyprus or the Western Sahara, as perpetrated by EU countries and/or their allies such as the US, Israel, Turkey or Morocco.</p>
      <p sl="pt">As such, there is once again an attempt to dissociate human rights, by subordinating them to economic and social rights. The defence of human rights – including the fact that they are indivisible and cannot be ranked – and their status as a prerequisite for respect for the rights of people and for genuine social justice, peace, freedom and democracy must form the framework of our political action. For us they are about defending the rights of people, not exercises in hypocrisy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-210" speaker_id="2338" name="Ian Hudghton" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted in favour of the Cappato report on human rights. Human rights abuses take place around the world and we in the EU must always act as advocates for those who suffer as a result.</p>
      <p sl="en">We must also be alert to human rights abuses taking place within our own borders – with the example of rendition flights serving to show us how easily these abuses can happen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-211" speaker_id="4260" name="Eija-Riitta Korhola" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fi">Mr President, I voted against the group on Amendment 12 to paragraph 94 of Mr Cappato’s report, by which the concept of ‘sexual and reproductive health’ would be deleted. Although the term ‘sexual and reproductive health’ also covers abortion, which I do not support as an absolute right, in my view it needs to be mentioned in this context. Paragraph 94 is a reminder that health programmes, including sexual and reproductive health, should be prominent in the EU´s development and human rights policy, in particular where gender-based violence is pervasive and women and children are put at risk of HIV/AIDS, or denied access to information, prevention and/or treatment.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-212" speaker_id="28251" name="Jörg Leichtfried" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="de">I voted in favour of the report on the state of human rights in the world in 2007 and the EU’s policy in this area. Human rights are universal rights and must apply without restriction. The EU has the opportunity to champion the cause of human rights globally. An accurate analysis of the current situation is the prerequisite here, which is why I welcome Mr Cappato's initiative.</p>
      <p sl="de">Harmonisation of the EU's human rights policy is especially important in order to achieve a common approach, for example against the death penalty or torture. A unified stance is also desirable in the international arena. Certain countries such as China, Russia and Iran appear to be making little effort to tackle the grave human rights violations occurring on their territory. The EU must present a strong and united front in its dealings with these countries, and that is only possible with a common human rights policy for the EU.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-213" speaker_id="1403" name="David Martin" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I welcome Mr Cappato’s report on the state of human rights in the world in 2007 and the EU’s policy in this area. The report highlights the need for the EU to increase its focus on human rights, particularly in trade negotiations.</p>
      <p sl="en">As well as recognising the shortcomings on human rights identified in the report I also support certain solutions Mr Cappato proposes such as a greater role for the Parliament’s Human Rights Subcommittee and Council involvement in such debates. I voted in support of the report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-214" speaker_id="28255" name="Andreas Mölzer" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="de">It is bizarre that the European Union is proposing to declare a 'European Year of Non-Violence' while the EU itself is deploying missions in Chad, where French interests make it impossible to achieve the requisite impartiality. When it comes to the CIA's secret prisons and rendition flights, too, just how non-violent and respectful of human rights was the EU's action then? To say nothing of the fact that accession negotiations are in progress with a country which tramples minority rights under foot, treats the female section of its population as second-class citizens, and cheerfully follows the US example and, with the US's blessing, embarks on a war of aggression against its neighbour. To say nothing, too, of the flouting of democratic rights – notably by disregarding the outcomes of referenda – and the sacrifice of more and more fundamental rights on the pretext of combating terrorism.</p>
      <p sl="de">If the EU is genuine and serious in its intention to champion human rights, then it must shed light on all the still unanswered questions regarding the US's torture prisons and the CIA's 'extraordinary rendition' programme, and immediately halt its negotiations with Turkey, for a key element of the EU's human rights policy must also be to uphold democracy and democratic values at home.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-215" speaker_id="28249" name="Tobias Pflüger" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="de">The reasons why I did not vote for the motion for a resolution on the human rights report are as follows:</p>
      <p sl="de">1. The report contains a number of points which are worthy of support. However, it completely ignores the absence of social and economic rights in much of the world, as a result of which millions of people are dying of hunger or lack housing and employment. The report reduces human rights to civil rights alone, and thus neglects the principle of the indivisibility of human rights, as enshrined in the UN Charter;</p>
      <p sl="de">2. The report does not deal with the human rights violations perpetrated or endorsed by EU Member States. However, in order to avoid any accusations of hypocrisy, the EU must investigate and shed light on the human rights violations committed with the participation or compliance of EU Member States in third countries or against third-country nationals; these include, for example, the accusations of torture levelled against troops engaged in the EU's Operation Artemis in Congo;</p>
      <p sl="de">3. War is still the worst of all human rights violations, but is completely ignored in the report. However, with the Lisbon Treaty and the announcements made in connection with France's assumption of the Council Presidency in the second half of 2008, there is a real concern that the EU will be involved in more military missions. Human rights should not be used as a pretext for these operations. This aspect is completely absent from the report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-216" speaker_id="4461" name="Luís Queiró" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">The report voted on today, which follows on from the Council and Commission report, has the virtue of generally being an up-to-date and critical depiction of human rights in the world. Unfortunately, however, it is not much more than this. Despite the effort made to list various European Parliament initiatives on certain situations, it seems that the goal of assessing the true impact of European policies on the promotion of human rights has not been adequately achieved. This assessment, in order to be effective, should have included a clear description of the specific objectives, a comprehensive view of all the political instruments used in this respect and then an evaluation of the results achieved. In other words, our report is an important and very significant list, but it will never be as much as it could and should have been. For this reason, I share the concern of various fellow Members, particularly in the PPE-DE Group, with regard to revising the terms under which this report and this debate occur every year.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-217" speaker_id="2002" name="José Ignacio Salafranca Sánchez-Neyra" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="es">The PPE-DE Group voted against and flatly rejects, in the Cappato report, the paragraph referring to the Yogyakarta Principles. Only a small number of countries have signed and applied these and their content is only taken into account by the international community. The same can be said about the broad concept of ‘sexual reproductive health’, a catch-all term within which some try to hide or introduce ideas in which anything goes. We cannot subscribe to this.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-218" speaker_id="4545" name="Catherine Stihler" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">With the dramatic rise in global food prices, the need to see having enough food as a human right is important. This food crisis, where the poorest in our world will suffer the most, needs immediate action. I call on the European Council and Commission to use all means necessary to help those affected by the dramatic increase in food prices.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-219" speaker_id="28134" name="Eva-Britt Svensson" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I chose to abstain from voting on this matter because Mr Cappato’s report contains parts which advocate that decisions should be taken by the EU (in particular paragraphs 15, 45 and 141). I believe that it is up to the Member States to decide on issues relating to human rights.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-220" speaker_id="28358" name="Konrad Szymański" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pl">The Cappato report gave priority to the issue of unspecified discrimination based on sexual orientation and to reproductive rights.</p>
      <p sl="pl">At the same time it paid scant attention to current widespread infringement of religious freedom.</p>
      <p sl="pl">That is the reason why I was unable to support this report during today's vote.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-221" speaker_id="4521" name="Charles Tannock" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">British Conservatives recognise the important role of the EU in promoting human rights and democracy in the world. We can support a number of important points that are contained in the Cappato report.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, there are a number of paragraphs that we fundamentally disagree with. For instance, paragraphs 2, 5, 14, 15, 30 and 38. In addition, British Conservative Members have, in accordance with convention, been given a free vote on matters relating to the death penalty and abortion.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have voted in favour on the final vote because we wish to make clear our support, in principle, for the cause of upholding and strengthening human rights throughout the world. We believe the EU’s Member States have an important role to play in this task.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-222" speaker_id="28250" name="Sahra Wagenknecht" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="de">I did not vote for the human rights report, for the following reasons:</p>
      <p sl="de">1. Human rights are inalienable, indivisible and universally applicable. Nonetheless, social and economic rights, and the massive violation of these rights worldwide, barely feature in the report. The fact that millions of people are deprived of their most basic rights, the fact that – partly as a result of the EU's highly problematical policies – they have less and less food available, and that hunger, disease and a lack of decent housing are their cruel reality, that many people have no access to education, and that workers' rights are being trampled under foot: all this is largely ignored.</p>
      <p sl="de">2. The report fails to make any mention of the human rights violations that are occurring in the EU itself and in which the EU is involved around the world, partly as a result of its military and armaments policy and its ever-expanding military missions. Only the human rights violations taking place outside the EU are criticised; the EU's own omissions and responsibilities are ignored. The internal and external effects of the EU's neoliberal policies, with their negative consequences for human and fundamental rights, are not mentioned in the report.</p>
      <p sl="de">3. The report adopts a highly selective approach to the voicing of criticism, as the choice of countries selected for criticism and the scope of this criticism demonstrate. Human rights policy cannot be based on political exigencies, however, if it is to retain any credibility.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-994" speaker_id="33775" name="Jean-Pierre Audy" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">I voted in favour of the own-initiative report prepared jointly by my Belgian colleague Véronique de Keyser and my Spanish colleague José Ignacio Salafranca Sánchez-Neyra on EU election observation missions (EOMs). The observation of elections, particularly in new democracies, must continue to be an EU priority because although elections do not constitute a democracy, they are a key component of it and, consequently, a fundamental right of the people.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Like my colleagues, I regret that the Union still lacks a common, comprehensive strategy for promoting democracy. It is essential to continue to carry out post-election operations because it is not enough, in some cases, to adopt a passive attitude towards countries whose election process has been harshly criticised by observers.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-224" speaker_id="1413" name="Glyn Ford" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I support De Keyser and Salafranca's report as someone who has been on two occasions a Chief Observer on behalf of the European Union; Indonesia 2004, Aceh 2006/7. I believe that the work done by the Union improving the integrity of the electoral process is vital. Our job is generally not to confirm the winners but to reassure those who have lost that they have lost fairly and can be vital in diffusing tension post election.</p>
      <p sl="en">While I agree with the participation of nationals from countries outside the EU like Switzerland, Norway and Canada, we do need to ensure that the majority of those present are EU nationals. On one occasion to my knowledge they were close to forming a majority of the missions observers.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is right and proper as paragraph 38 states that we should give support post election to new Parliaments. I am aware as someone who has behalf on the UNDP on advising the new Indonesian Parliament in 1999 on revisions to their Rules of Procedure, of exactly how useful this can be. I congratulate my two colleagues on their report which I am sure we will revisit in the new legislature after 2009.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-225" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Hélène Goudin and Nils Lundgren" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">We are opposed to the passages in the report which seek to turn the EU’s election observation missions into policy toward third countries. Irregularities found should be dealt with through bodies with greater legitimacy and broader support than the EU, in this case primarily the OSCE and the UN.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, the EU does have a role to play as an election observer together with these other international bodies. The experience and expertise which the EU has built up is of great importance and should also be used in future.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have therefore chosen to support the report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-226" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro Guerreiro" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">This own-initiative report must not be viewed in isolation, but rather as an integrated element of the EU’s common foreign and security policy. As a result, we would say that it is imbued with an attitude of arrogance and self-praise, one example of which is the self-assessment of the EU as ‘leading’ in the area of international election observation.</p>
      <p sl="pt">It is based on this attitude of the ‘superiority’ of the ‘values’ and conduct of the EU that frequent attempts are made to use election observation missions as an instrument of pressure and interference in the internal affairs of countries, mainly those which insist on development projects based on an affirmation of national sovereignty and independence.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Viewed in another way, what is the EU actually attempting to do with the ‘common, comprehensive strategy for promoting democracy’? What is the EU attempting to do with the financing of national parliaments and political parties in other countries? The answer is given by our own situation. The EU is attempting to impose a single model (of capitalism) on people. This model serves the interests of intensified exploitation and imposes the liberalisation of international trade. It accepts the sacrifice of progress for people and development for countries to the interests of multinationals.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-227" speaker_id="2338" name="Ian Hudghton" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I supported the De Keyser/Salafranca Sanchez-Neyra report, which deals with important issues. The EU’s commitment to reinforcing democratic processes is a worthy cause and the report rightly notes that democracy can only exist within the context of the long-term rooting of democratic values.</p>
      <p sl="en">This crucial fact was ignored when the US and UK decided to go to war in Iraq. The disastrous circumstances which now exist in that country merely go to prove that democratic values must be nurtured and cannot exist at the end of the barrel of a gun.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-228" speaker_id="28251" name="Jörg Leichtfried" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="de">I am in favour of strengthening the EU's election observation missions in order to provide effective support to young democracies.</p>
      <p sl="de">In this context, I welcome the call for a European consensus on the promotion of democracy, which could boost the effectiveness of election observation missions.</p>
      <p sl="de">Elections are an important step towards stable democracy and have great symbolic significance both for the country concerned and for the wider international community. The EU has taken on a leading role in election observation and should now develop this role intensively. In this context, improving post-election follow-up is especially important, in my view. The EU must identify the key challenges arising from the conduct of the elections and respond in a unified and comprehensible manner. It would also be sensible for the European Parliament to provide support for the newly elected parliament.</p>
      <p sl="de">I fully endorse all these objectives, especially as my own experiences as an EU election observer in Guatemala testify to their necessity.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-229" speaker_id="1403" name="David Martin" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">Election Observation Missions form a key part of the EU’s foreign policy role. As a Union of democratic states, the EU’s experience should be shared effectively and requests for our cooperation in the election process should be encouraged throughout the world.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is by improving the practices and methodology of the Union’s Observation Missions that we can effectively contribute to strengthening democracy throughout the world. I therefore voted in favour of Mr Salafranca Sánchez-Neyra’s and Mrs De Keyser’s joint report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-230" speaker_id="28255" name="Andreas Mölzer" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="de">This House flies the flag for democracy and sends its observers to various elections. For the citizens of the country concerned, it is vital that these elections are conducted fairly and in a proper manner. Our influence here also makes an important contribution to democratic progress, provided, of course, that our recommendations are genuinely taken to heart.</p>
      <p sl="de">However, let us not delude ourselves about our own adherence to democratic standards here in the EU: not as long as someone who voices unpopular truths is written off as a right-wing radical; not as long as a Treaty which was rejected in referenda in two Member States is pushed through the parliaments in a cosmetically enhanced form; not as long as the population is allowed to vote repeatedly until the desired outcome is achieved; and certainly not while there are plans to allow Turkey's accession to the European Union against the popular will.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-231" speaker_id="4461" name="Luís Queiró" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">The moment of an election is not in any way the only moment or the only exponent of democracy. However, it is often the turning point. In countries without an electoral tradition, the holding of elections can be and often is the occasion when the process of democratisation becomes irreversible. However, this is a process that we are talking about. For this reason, everything stated in this report on the success, difficulties, inadequacies and needs for reform of the European Union’s election observation missions (EOMs) is important and deserves our full attention, but it will always miss the essential point: the overall contribution of the various European instruments to the achievement of democracy (in which the EU’s EOMs are obviously involved). This, I believe, is the challenge raised by this debate which, having made us think about it, we must accept. The promotion and protection of democracy are not only part of the DNA of the European Union but are also part of its world vision, both in terms of principles and values and in terms of its own interests.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-993" speaker_id="33775" name="Jean-Pierre Audy" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">I voted in favour of the excellent own-initiative report by my esteemed British colleague Glyn Ford on trade and economic relations with the Association of South East Asian Nations (ASEAN), which is part of a broader strategy of bilateral and inter-regional negotiations with the trading partners.</p>
      <p sl="fr">A partnership and cooperation agreement (PCA), containing enforceable human rights clauses, is a prerequisite for the Union to conclude a free trade agreement (FTA) with any country. A resolution to the problem of banking secrecy in Singapore is essential if there is to be a real prospect of concluding a region-to-region free trade agreement. Like my colleagues, I attach particular importance to the fight against counterfeit pharmaceuticals, which represent unfair competition and a danger to consumers.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I regret the adoption of the principle of the maximum use of flexibilities set out in the Declaration amending the Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights Agreement (TRIPS Agreement) and access to medicines, given the lack of any serious evaluation of these mechanisms.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-233" speaker_id="28427" name="Alessandro Battilocchio" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="it">Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, I am backing this report because I am convinced that free trade is a necessary step towards global well-being.</p>
      <p sl="it">However, our support for any supranational economic agreement has to be dependent on stringent rules committing all parties to ratification of the fundamental ILO conventions, thereby guaranteeing that employees are safeguarded and protected.</p>
      <p sl="it">As the rapporteur has recalled, ASEAN as a whole is the EU’s fifth largest trading partner. This highlights our many trading interests in that region, which is without doubt a rapidly growing market.</p>
      <p sl="it">The region’s strong presence, and the absence of effective local employment legislation, obliges us to ensure that the new agreement lays down robust rules not only of an economic nature but also, above all, as concerns employment, the environment and human rights, thereby limiting the effect of social dumping.</p>
      <p sl="it">Product safety and the protection of employees and the environment cannot and must not be jeopardised by any kind of purely economic agreement.</p>
      <p sl="it">All of us, united by identical values, have a moral and institutional duty to find the courage to be much more rigorous and selective in choosing our trading partners: all of our partners must provide Europe with guarantees that they set an example to other peoples around the world.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-234" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Hélène Goudin and Nils Lundgren" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">We are opposed to the fact that the report contains a number of aspects which have nothing to do with trade policy. The political situation in Myanmar and the release of political prisoners are very important issues, but they should not be made part of the EU’s supranational trade policy. We see this as yet another attempt on the part of the EU to expand its powers in the area of foreign policy.</p>
      <p sl="en">On the other hand, the June List sees free-trade agreements between the EU and other regions as a natural consequence of having a single market and a common commercial policy. We have therefore, in spite of everything, chosen to vote in favour of the report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-235" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro Guerreiro" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">According to the report, obtaining commercial advantages by establishing free trade agreements (FTAs) with various regions is the best political strategy for Europe to overcome the crisis, at least while the impasse in the World Trade Organisation continues.</p>
      <p sl="pt">However, the report also looks to go further. In parallel with the FTAs, it argues for the economic integration of regions, in a similar way to the EU, and, if possible, subordinated economically and politically to the latter.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The broad rejection of the amendments tabled by our Group clearly reveals the ultimate goal: to liberalise without taking account of means or consequences. Even amendments which underlined the need to take account of existing disparities between the two regions and the objectives of creating employment and ensuring sustainable economic development, food sovereignty and security, and environmental protection were rejected. Not even the objective of facilitating access to medicines and to the transfer of technologies was accepted by the majority of the House without conditions.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The effects of this policy are evident, such as the rise in energy and food prices and the increase in social inequalities and regional disparities, poverty, hunger and disease.</p>
      <p sl="pt">We could therefore only vote against this report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-236" speaker_id="1403" name="David Martin" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I support Glyn Ford’s report on Trade and Economic Relations with ASEAN. It is essential that the Commission includes strong IPR clauses in the new generation of FTAs that it is proposing. Such a move would not only stimulate innovation and research in the ASEAN countries but also, more importantly protect consumers from unsafe counterfeit goods such as fake pharmaceuticals.</p>
      <p sl="en">Indeed, a recent OECD survey on counterfeiting, discussed in Parliament this week, states that trade in counterfeit goods in Malaysia and the Philippines has reached proportions similar to China. The report deals with these issues and I voted in favour of its recommendations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-237" speaker_id="1309" name="Brian Simpson" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I shall be voting in favour of this excellent report. Key for me were Amendments 7 and 14 and paragraph 42.</p>
      <p sl="en">These sections recognise the importance of ensuring accessible and sustainable public services - Amendment 7; the enforcement of labour standards through a dispute settlement mechanism - Amendment 14; and the need to treat environmentally friendly and fair trade goods differently when it comes to tariffs - paragraph 42.</p>
      <p sl="en">I congratulate the rapporteur, Mr Ford, on his report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-238" speaker_id="28382" name="Andrzej Jan Szejna" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pl">I voted in favour of the report by Mr Ford on trade and economic relations with ASEAN (the Association of the South East Asian Nations).</p>
      <p sl="pl">I should like to emphasise that for it to bear fruit, an agreement requires the commitment of both partners. In the light of reports on recent negotiating rounds, the prospects for an early and ambitious agreement with ASEAN may be undermined by a lack of negotiating capacity and difficulties in developing a common position. ASEAN would be the EU's fifth most important trading partner.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The report supports the concept of a free trade agreement with ASEAN provided that the agreement meets certain key conditions. It is important to ensure that consumer protection is not curtailed or environmental protection reduced.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Negotiating an agreement with a region composed of 10 independent countries is very complicated and time-consuming. At the same time, interregional agreements do offer significant gains because they promote regional integration, which strengthens partner countries' economies and reduces the number of regulations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-239" speaker_id="34720" name="Bernard Wojciechowski" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pl">The European Union should exercise particular care when handling trade and economic relations with third countries.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The rate of GDP growth in ASEAN countries is increasing year on year. Amongst other forecasts, the Bangko Sentral ng Pilipinas is anticipating an increase of between 4.8% and 5.5% in the Philippines' GDP. It also predicts an 11% increase in exports and a 10% increase in the value of remittances in foreign currencies from Filipinos working abroad.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Malaysia's GDP translates into USD 6 721 per inhabitant. It is forecast to increase to USD 7 596 in 2008. In 2007 the Malaysian economy recorded a 6.3% increase in GDP. Total GDP growth for all ASEAN member countries is estimated at around 6%. These are important indicators for assessing trade and economic relations with the countries of South East Asia (ASEAN).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-241" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro Guerreiro" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">A response is urgently needed to the problem of a lack of information on deep-sea fish stocks and also data on catches and fishing effort and their implications for the populations of each species.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Just as this information is vital for producing studies and scientific opinions, it can also decisively contribute to the establishment of adequate fishing management measures.</p>
      <p sl="pt">We therefore feel it is essential that this forms one of the priorities of the Member States’ action in terms of improving the collection and availability of reliable data, including the analysis of reasons for non-application or less correct application of the management measures in force, as mentioned in the report. The possibility raised by international organisations of some of these species suffering from overfishing reinforces this need.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The aim must be to adopt a precautionary approach which tries to balance fishing opportunities with stock stability. We therefore support the amendments tabled. We consider that the measures to be adopted must take account of the specific nature of each species, the fishing area and the fishing gear used, particularly those which are more selective and have less impact on the seabed.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-242" speaker_id="2338" name="Ian Hudghton" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted in favour of the Miguélez Ramos report on deep-sea fisheries. Deep-sea fishing is a fairly recent innovation and a number of previously unexploited fish stocks have been targeted with little scientific research or legal regulation. It is right therefore that these issues are addressed.</p>
      <p sl="en">I welcome the call in Mrs Miguélez Ramos’ report for fishermen and their associations to be fully involved in defining measures designed to safeguard the marine environment. Sustainable fisheries depend upon decisions being taken at a local level and involving those to whom they are addressed.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-244" speaker_id="23788" name="Adam Bielan" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, some 2 500 lobbying organisations are currently active in Brussels. More than 300 of these are representations of local and regional authorities operating as if they were embassies. They include the representation of Małopolska (Lesser Poland) which is my European constituency. I should like to take the opportunity provided by the debate on the report before the House to draw attention to the issue of the relationship between EU institutions and organisations of this type. As they strive to obtain reliable information from European institutions, the representatives of local and regional authorities also supply the most recent data on the situation in their regions. The rapporteur stated that transparency is a two-way street. Following on from that statement I should like to emphasise the importance of increased transparency on the part of the European institutions, and equal treatment of all organisations represented in Brussels.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I supported the aforementioned report because of the specific examples of how the European Parliament can improve the transparency of the procedures applied to external organisations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-245" speaker_id="4466" name="Ilda Figueiredo" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">It is well-known that the professional lobbying sector – with the aim of influencing EU policy making – is developing fast and constantly in Brussels. It is therefore necessary, at the very least, to lay down rules which ensure that information is provided on the interests represented by lobbyists, although, even so, it will always be difficult to ensure that there is transparency and that unethical practices are avoided. That is why we voted in favour of this report.</p>
      <p sl="pt">However, we can only regret that the proposals tabled by our Group were not adopted, specifically those arguing that interest representatives, in addition to being under an obligation to register, should also be obliged to disclose their expenditure on their activities, particularly by giving the same information on interest representation expenditure spent on Members of the European Parliament as the latter are obliged to disclose in their financial declarations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-246" speaker_id="1413" name="Glyn Ford" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I will be supporting this report, strengthening as it does the rules of the European institutions regarding lobbyists. I was the author of the first report on this subject more than a decade ago, in January 1996, produced by the then Rules Committee, and the legislations we currently have in place regarding lobbyist are those proposed in my original report.</p>
      <p sl="en">More than 10 years on it is clearly time to modify and strengthen these rules. We failed last time to have a common system for all of the institutions but this now seems possible. For me lobbyists are all those who want to come into the Parliament, Commission or Council to influence the decision-making process, whether employers or employees, consumer groups, producer groups or special interest groups.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is estimated there are around 5 000 lobbyist in Brussels – seven for each and every MEP. The vast majority do a good job – a very small number do not. We need to ensure that the few do not taint the many and that our work benefits from outside inputs rather than being distorted by it. I look forward to the proposals for a ‘common legislation’ by the end of the year.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-247" speaker_id="4429" name="Robert Goebbels" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">I abstained on the Stubb report on the framework for the activities of lobbyists because I believe that some of my fellow Members are making too much of a fuss over an activity that is as old as mankind, namely the attempt to influence decision-makers. It is normal for citizens to get together to defend their interests. Trade unions, employers’ associations and NGOs have the right to defend their interests to any legislator. The legislator has the duty to listen before making a decision. However, the legislator must remain independent, hence the importance of Members declaring their financial interests. Nevertheless, the report’s main shortcoming is that it remains silent on the funding of certain associations from the EU budget. That is an area where transparency should also come into play.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-248" speaker_id="1164" name="Bruno Gollnisch" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, it is perfectly normal to consult the parties affected by legislation that is being prepared or adopted. As parliamentarians who are called upon to make decisions on issues that are sometimes extremely technical, we are the first to recognise the very important informative role played by what are commonly known as lobbyists. Their activity is useful, but their relations with all the institutions must be governed by a strong, coherent framework, and that is why we will vote in favour of this report. I would, however, like to make a number of comments. It is important not to put all interest groups together: the representatives of multinationals or NGOs cannot be treated in the same way as the representatives of democratic local or national authorities. In our opinion, the ‘legislative footprint’, i.e. the reference to the groups consulted, must be compulsory, notably for the Commission. We know how much influence these groups have on the preparation of legislative proposals or the direction of a European policy, and how difficult it is for the legislator to amend such proposals or directions to any great extent. Finally, the financial information requested of lobbyists must be sufficiently detailed to enable us to identify clearly the financial interests at stake and the source of the funding.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-249" speaker_id="2025" name="Françoise Grossetête" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">I voted in favour of this report, which ensures greater transparency. Lobbyists are important actors who can provide useful expertise. It is, however, essential to be able to identify the organisations represented by the pressure groups. A compulsory public register for lobbyists, shared by the Council, the Commission and Parliament and listing all of their sources of funding, is a good initiative that will provide greater clarity. The establishment of a ‘one-stop shop’ where lobbyists could register only once in order to have access to Parliament, the Commission and the Council will also simplify the situation. It is normal, too, that sanctions should be envisaged for lobbyists who do not comply with the code of conduct.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-250" speaker_id="28124" name="Gunnar Hökmark" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">There should be a set of rules governing permanent access by lobbyists to the premises of the European Parliament. We support the current Code of Conduct. We support increased transparency in political decision-making.</p>
      <p sl="en">We voted against the report because it leads to a bureaucracy which counteracts its own objectives. Comprehensive regulation of the contacts of politicians obstructs natural and open contact between citizens and elected representatives. Citizens should be able to contact their representatives without their conversations and opinions being reported openly.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is not possible to provide a detailed account of how opinions and views are formed. The argument and responsibility for decisions must be transparent, not the dialogue between individuals. It is important to safeguard the integrity of individual parliamentarians and individual citizens.</p>
      <p sl="en">The transparency which is proposed in the report risks becoming illusory and misleading. Transparency must be based on politicians taking responsibility for their positions and accounting for their motives.</p>
      <p sl="en">Furthermore, a common register of lobbyists shared by the European Parliament and the Commission would be to give up Parliament’s independence.</p>
      <p sl="en">In summary, political decision-making should be based on the elected representatives having and being presumed to have integrity.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-251" speaker_id="2338" name="Ian Hudghton" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I welcome the proposed register of lobbyists. At a time when public confidence in politics is at a low, it is essential that the political institutions are as transparent in their operations as possible.</p>
      <p sl="en">I also welcome the fact that lawyers will be exempt from registration when giving legal advice; this is in keeping with the principle long recognised in the Scottish legal tradition of lawyer-client confidentiality.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, a number of my own group’s key amendments designed to make stricter rules were unsuccessful and accordingly both I and the group abstained on the final vote.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-252" speaker_id="33987" name="Monica Maria Iacob-Ridzi" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="ro">I voted in favour of this report, but I believe more actions could be adopted in order to guarantee a balanced representation of the citizens, without favouring the groups of interests around the European institutions.</p>
      <p sl="ro">The lobby activity has experienced an important evolution, currently reaching over 2,500 organizations with more than 15,000 employees in Brussels alone. Once the Lisbon Treaty comes into force and new competencies are created for the Parliament and the European Union, this tendency will intensify. While the groups of interests with headquarters in Brussels have easy access to the European political process, the groups of citizens and the nongovernmental organizations do not have the same means to make their voice heard when adopting the European legislative acts. It is obvious that we have to facilitate the dialogue between the European institutions and those organizations in the Member States.</p>
      <p sl="ro">For this reason, I believe the Commission and the Parliament representations should fulfil the function of transmitting the opinions and various initiatives of the citizens to the European decision-making institutions. We should also create the adequate budgetary lines for financing this activity.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-253" speaker_id="28355" name="Mieczysław Edmund Janowski" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pl">I am glad that the European Parliament is dealing with lobbying. This cannot be a taboo subject for public opinion. Certain rules are required, and transparency is essential. This is a sensitive area in political and economic terms. We are aware that lawmakers benefit from the subject-specific knowledge gained from contacts with experts. This is also a type of dialogue with society, and has a kind of reciprocal effect. After all, Members and officials of the European Commission and other institutions do not operate in their own isolated world. The knowledge gained enables them to create better and more user-friendly legislation.</p>
      <p sl="pl">On the other hand, the question of unfair influence on lawmaking arises. There are also instances when the law is slanted so as to favour the interests of specific pressure groups, such as pro-abortionists and large corporations. This leads directly to corruption and the final outcome is not genuine legislation but a hotchpotch of provisions.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Will we really contrive to make legal provisions stricter and tighten them up so as to prevent inappropriate lobbying and corruption? Sadly, the answer is obvious. We will be unable to do so. It will always be possible to find a loophole in the provisions or a way around them. We should also bear in mind that so-called bad lobbying is also possible through direct contacts in the Member States.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I am positively inclined towards the report, but cannot accept the amendments whereby churches are deemed to be lobby groups. We must consider ethics, compliance with transparency and morality as well as the letter of the law. Morality can never be the enemy of democracy!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-254" speaker_id="4260" name="Eija-Riitta Korhola" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fi">Mr President, it is a pity that Amendment 7, which was proposed on behalf of my group, was not adopted. The amendment would have been essential to understand the scale of the debate on lobbying, not just as a reminder to the Commission but also to a wider audience. A good example of this is the environmental organisations, whose resources are frequently compared to those of industry, though in an utterly peculiar way: the budget for a single organisation’s forest campaign might be compared to the totals for the entire budgets of all forest companies. This is to forget that forest companies cannot spend all their money on communications: they are actually engaged in producing timber and paper. It would be more reasonable to compare companies’ budgets for communications, but from that would have to be subtracted the stock exchange release, which is a drain on resources. Then on the other side one would have to calculate the forestry campaign cash for all the environmental organisations. When we look beneath the surface, therefore, the resources used are very often revealed to be on a more equal footing than the image created might suggest.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-255" speaker_id="28251" name="Jörg Leichtfried" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="de">I am voting in favour of the report on the establishment of a framework for the activities of interest representatives in the European institutions.</p>
      <p sl="de">In order to safeguard the transparency of the European institutions, a structured framework for the activities of lobbyists is required. I agree with the definition of lobbying as all areas of activity carried out with the objective of influencing the policy formulation and decision-making processes of the EU institutions, and that all players falling within that definition should be considered lobbyists and treated in the same way.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-256" speaker_id="28182" name="Kartika Tamara Liotard" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="nl">Half-baked measures will be no help at all with the problem of lobbyists. Only complete transparency and obligatory records can restrict the growing influence of the industrial lobby. We need this quickly, as all too often we see Members tabling amendments here which have literally been taken over by a lobbyist. Politicians should be influenced in the first place by their voters, their supporters and their own good sense, not by an army of professional lobbyists. I therefore call on the European Commission to come up with a much more far-reaching package of measures.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-257" speaker_id="28585" name="Diamanto Manolakou" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">The report on the ‘interest groups’, and well-known ‘lobbyists’, is a blatantly cynical admission of the deeply reactionary role of the European Parliament and the EU as a whole, and the class interests that it serves.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Parliament has for years officially sanctioned the right of representatives of monopoly groups to have free access to the European Parliament in order to apply pressure, bribe and insist on legislative interventions ensuring and increasing their profits.</p>
      <p sl="en">Using the transparency rules as a pretext, the report tries to whitewash the direct intervention of monopolies. It brands trade-unions, professional and mass organisations as ‘lobbyists’. The workers’ and popular movement is thus lumped together with capitalists, whom the report has the nerve to describe as representatives of civil society. The only difference is that they find the doors of Parliament wide open to them, while the workers are not allowed near them.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let the workers have no illusions. The European Parliament and its Members are not independent. They have been elected on a platform representing class interests which they represent in the European Parliament.</p>
      <p sl="en">For the workers, the course that best serves their own interests is to overturn political groupings, weaken the capitalist parties, and resist and oppose a capitalist-orientated EU.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-258" speaker_id="1403" name="David Martin" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted in favour of the recommendation contained within the report ‘Framework for the activities of lobbyists in the EU institutions’.</p>
      <p sl="en">These proposals for more transparency in lobbying place the European Parliament well ahead of almost any other parliament in the world in terms of regulating lobbyists and ensuring full financial disclosure.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-259" speaker_id="4508" name="Erik Meijer" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="nl">The politics of the EU are to a large extent becoming prescribed by the interests of large enterprises, which try to reinforce their global competitive positions by cutting costs in the areas of the environment, wages, industrial safety and consumer protection. It does not surprise us that these companies are doing this, but as long as they are doing it, it must be clear to everyone. That puts the trade unions, the environmental movements and the consumer groups in a position to do something about it.</p>
      <p sl="nl">For years I have been urging, in questions to the European Commission among other things, the strictest possible regulations governing transparency with regard to lobbyists. I see that the tough version has still not been adopted today. Then the 10 specific amendments tabled by the United Left and the Greens did not get a majority. These proposals related to a common register of all lobbyists who have access to EU institutions, openness regarding the aims and financing of lobbyists, further measures to be introduced in 2009, publication of unethical behaviour by lobbyists, clarification concerning special consultants to the European Commission, and a clampdown on civil servants acting as paid lobbyists while on leave.</p>
      <p sl="nl">In spite of the rejection of this better option, the decision that has been taken today is a step forward. On account of that, the two representatives of the Dutch Socialist Party voted in favour of it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-260" speaker_id="28862" name="Lydie Polfer" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">I voted in favour of the Stubb report on the development of the framework for the activities of interest representatives (lobbyists) in the European institutions. It provides a clearer definition of the activities of lobbyists, of whom there are an estimated 15 000.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I therefore support the initiative to establish a common register where lobbyists will be able to register just once to gain access to the European Parliament, the Commission and the Council. In addition, all lobbyists will thereby commit to observing a code of conduct. It is essential for Members and European officials to be able to identify the organisations represented by interest groups and for these groups to respect the principles of honesty and good conduct.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-992" speaker_id="28166" name="Vincent Peillon" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="fr">I voted in favour of this report aimed at providing a better framework for the activities of interest representatives in the EU.</p>
      <p sl="fr">There is an army of lobbyists in Brussels: it is estimated that are some 15 000 of them, representing 2 500 pressure groups. Their main aim is to influence Community decisions and their activity – although viewed with mistrust and suspicion by some citizens – is an important part of democratic life. For example, a Member will always have a better understanding of the issues involved in a legislative proposal after having listened to the opinion of the professional associations, NGOs, trade unions or regional representatives.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Nevertheless, lobbying can only serve democracy if it is transparent. Members, like citizens, must be able to determine the precise identity of these actors. Who finances them? What interests are they really defending?</p>
      <p sl="fr">By requiring lobbyists to join a public register shared by all the Community institutions and indicate in it the details of their funding, the text meets this requirement. In addition, lobbyists will from now on have to comply with a code of conduct and will be subject to sanctions if they fail to respect the rules therein.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-261" speaker_id="4461" name="Luís Queiró" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">The changes in our globalised world and their consequences on the institutions are undoubtedly resulting in ever-increasing exposure to various social actors. We are therefore seeing increasing numbers of groups contacting this Parliament or the Commission, providing specialised information which is recognised as important. It is thus necessary to act so that these new interest representatives are clearly identified and so that rules on their activities are laid down and observed.</p>
      <p sl="pt">This report provides a definition of ‘interest representatives’, together with measures for assessing the implications of a common register for Parliament and the Commission. It also aims to increase information measures with regard to the financial data needed to ensure that political decision-makers and the general public can identify the main driving forces behind a given lobbying activity. I believe that these measures are important steps for ensuring greater clarity and legitimacy of the decision-making process of European political decision-makers, particularly as, in the vote, certain amendments were rejected which would only have served to devalue the correct assessment of this activity, in the name of outdated ideological preconceptions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-262" speaker_id="4274" name="Olle Schmidt" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">A parliamentarian always has a great need to obtain relevant information in order to be able to make good decisions. It goes without saying that one person cannot be an expert in everything. In that sense, lobbying can be a valuable addition to information-gathering by providing expertise and relevant impact analyses.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, citizens are entitled to know what special interests are active. How influential a lobby group is does not necessarily depend on financial strength – animal rights activists and other social movements can be at least as successful as industrial interests. Registering interests is, of course, not entirely simple, not least when it comes to defining who or what groups are carrying out lobbying activities. However, as a decision-maker I consider it relevant continuously to monitor who is putting time and effort into influencing legislation. If you have nothing to hide, you also have nothing to be worried about. Trolls are destroyed by daylight.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-263" speaker_id="37676" name="Søren Bo Søndergaard" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted in favour of the lobby report in its final version because in spite of everything it is a microscopic step forward in relation to the current situation. The failure to progress further is in itself proof of the influence that lobbyists have over the EU system.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-264" speaker_id="4545" name="Catherine Stihler" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">The need for greater transparency of lobbying is essential in the European Parliament. I hope that this report will increase openness and transparency of lobbying in Parliament.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-265" speaker_id="28134" name="Eva-Britt Svensson" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted in favour of the lobby report in its final version because it is, in spite of everything, a microscopic step forward relative to the present situation. The fact that it did not succeed in going further is in itself testament to how much influence lobbyists have over the EU system.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-267" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Jan Andersson, Göran Färm, Anna Hedh, Inger Segelström and Åsa Westlund" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">Sport is part of the Lisbon Treaty and will therefore gain a more prominent role in EU policy with the entry into force of that treaty. We Social Democrats would like to emphasise that sport is already a cross-border activity, but that does not mean that European institutions like the Council, the Commission and Parliament should involve themselves in the detailed management of the sports movement. Instead, sport should govern itself as far as possible in order to retain its independence and autonomy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-268" speaker_id="28427" name="Alessandro Battilocchio" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="it">It is a great pleasure for me to vote in favour of the report by Mr Mavrommatis on safeguards for sport. Indeed, I believe that sport is an indissociable element of European culture and citizenship. Given that it is a significant way to promote social inclusion and intercultural dialogue, sport must be regulated at last so as to safeguard young people and protect them from dangers inherent in the sector: commercial pressure, fraud, the exploitation of minors and violence.</p>
      <p sl="it">Of course, the entire sporting system cannot survive without funding. In many instances funding comes from television rights, so for this reason I believe it is advisable not only to allow media organisations to pay to cover sporting fixtures but also to ensure broad public access, at least to major events.</p>
      <p sl="it">I am pleased to note that the report also contains a reminder of proper sporting conduct and appeals for measures to tackle racism and doping which, quite apart from its possible effects, is the most unsportsmanlike practice imaginable. It is therefore a good idea to have closer cooperation at every level to combat the problem, because doping undermines the very essence of sport: a love of competition, drawing on all one’s resources and performing to the best of one’s ability. Man has always risen to this challenge.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-269" speaker_id="23788" name="Adam Bielan" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pl">In the context of the debate on the role of sport in the European Union I should like to emphasise the importance of local activities. I believe they represent the first step towards the development of a European policy aimed at promoting sport.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I represent Małoplolska (Lesser Poland). In that region, more than 60 000 individuals suffer from diabetes. Circulatory diseases are the main cause of death, amounting to 51% in 2005. These conditions are largely the consequence of obesity and lack of activity. One of the main objectives of the Voivodship's development strategy is the promotion of a healthy lifestyle. Achievement of this objective will involve investment in infrastructure and the construction of new facilities in the area, such as swimming pools, sports grounds and indoor sports facilities. In addition, my region encourages sporting activities by arranging financial awards for the best young sports people. Over 120 young people have received awards so far.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Support for this type of action at regional level should be a key element of the effort to promote a healthy lifestyle across the European Union. I supported the report by Mr Mavrommatis because I believe it raises many important issues relating to the development of sport.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-270" speaker_id="28310" name="Edite Estrela" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">I voted in favour of the report on the White Paper on Sport.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Lack of physical exercise has negative consequences for the health of European citizens, leading to an increase in cases of excess weight, obesity and many chronic conditions, such as cardiovascular diseases and diabetes. For this reason, I defended the importance of medical advice for women on the potential benefits to be gained from physical activity during pregnancy and after childbirth.</p>
      <p sl="pt">I must also stress the importance of non-discriminatory rules governing sports competitions, by fixing equivalent prizes for men and women.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-271" speaker_id="4466" name="Ilda Figueiredo" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pt">The report contained proposals that we tabled in committee recommending that the specific associations for the different categories of persons involved in sport should also be appropriately represented in the decision-making bodies of international and national federations, and defending preventative measures and health checks for young sportspeople, ensuring that all the rights enshrined in the United Nations Convention on the Rights of the Child are respected.</p>
      <p sl="pt">More proposals that we tabled were adopted in plenary, in particular recommendations on: the need to provide ‘dual career’ training – sporting and academic – to young sportspeople to ensure the reintegration of professional sportspeople into the labour market at the end of their careers; the importance of encouraging people to play sports, by guaranteeing access to sport for all and equal opportunities and by investing in the training of teachers and sports coaches as well as in more public sports facilities, with the state having to assume the costs of safety at non-professional competitions organised by non-profit-making bodies; the importance of giving recognition to sporting successes achieved by women and the fight against discrimination in prizes; the defence of career opportunities for women in fields linked to the world of sport, including in decision-making posts, and drawing attention to non-professional sport.</p>
      <p sl="pt">However, we disagree with the references to the Lisbon Treaty.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-272" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Hélène Goudin and Nils Lundgren" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">The June List is firmly opposed to this report. First, the report refers to the Lisbon Treaty, which has not yet been ratified and is subject to a referendum in Ireland in a month or so. The European Parliament’s federalist majority is thus breaching fundamental constitutional principles. The Lisbon Treaty is also 96% identical to the Constitutional Treaty which has already been rejected in referendums in France and the Netherlands. It is therefore completely unprincipled to refer to the Lisbon Treaty in this report.</p>
      <p sl="en">Secondly, the report means that the EU will go into yet another policy area which the June List considers to be a matter for Member States.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are therefore voting against this report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-273" speaker_id="23717" name="Genowefa Grabowska" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="pl">I congratulate the rapporteur and am glad Parliament acted on its own initiative to take up an issue of such importance to citizens of the European Union. The section of the report emphasising the importance of the message sport conveys merits a special mention. The message generally reaches us through the well-known slogan stating that sport equals health. As a result of that slogan, millions of Europeans are taking more care of their physical and mental health. That is not all, however. From our earliest years, sport teaches us about fair competition and honesty, and helps us to understand that our so-called role in the match depends on our own commitment, and that all the work and huge effort devoted to preparing for competitions will be rewarded.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Foreign sportspeople take part in sporting competitions. This helps to counter discrimination and teaches us tolerance at the stadiums. Tolerance is a fundamental element of respect for human rights. It is mentioned in all EU documents.</p>
      <p sl="pl">There is a further feature of this report that contributes to its added value. Genuine sport must be free from violence, whilst individual efforts to achieve the best possible results must be free from the scourge of our times, namely doping.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-274" speaker_id="28131" name="Anna Hedh" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted against the report because I think it is too closely related to the Lisbon Treaty. I do not want to make sport supranational and instead think that it is fine as it is today. However, I do think that the amendment on women and sport was good.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-275" speaker_id="5846" name="Mary Honeyball" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">We accept the specificity of sport; however, the English version of recital I is extremely unclear and open to misinterpretation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-276" speaker_id="2338" name="Ian Hudghton" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted in favour of the amendments to the Mavrommatis report explicitly recognising the autonomy of sports organisations. My own country, Scotland, has a long tradition of autonomous, independent sporting bodies with organisations such as the Scottish Football Association being recognised as a full Member State organisation of FIFA and likewise the Scottish Rugby Union being a Member State within the IRB.</p>
      <p sl="en">This recognition of Scottish sporting independence has played an important role in my country’s past and will play an important role after the 2010 Scottish independence referendum – when Scotland will become a full, independent Member State of the EU.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-277" speaker_id="28251" name="Jörg Leichtfried" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="de">I am voting in favour of the White Paper on Sport in order to underscore the importance of sport in the European Union and foster dialogue on this issue.</p>
      <p sl="de">Sport is an effective means by which to promote social integration and mutual understanding at national and international level. Sport also has an important economic dimension. For these reasons, it is important to create a framework in which the Member States can support sports organisations and events. As sport operates to a large extent at national level, Member States must have the possibility of self-regulation. The White Paper underlines this point and is also an appropriate basis on which to deal with aspects of concern to all countries, such as youth development, anti-doping programmes and anti-discrimination in sport.</p>
      <p sl="de">I also welcome the creation of a special Sports Fund to support sporting activities and facilitate people's access to sport.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-278" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Kartika Tamara Liotard, Erik Meijer, Esko Seppänen, Søren Bo Søndergaard and Eva-Britt Svensson" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">We recognise that sport has a special role in society as an instrument of social inclusion and integration, and as a promoter of local democracy. We acknowledge the considerable importance of sport in health terms as a preventive measure for obesity and chronic conditions.</p>
      <p sl="en">We fully support the notion of strengthening the role of women in sport; the importance of protecting athletes of all ages during and after their sports career; the promotion of sports in society, including physical activities in the school curriculum; the need for redistributive measures in sports financing; and the citizens right to information and wide access to broadcasts of sports events.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, we do not support the enhanced role of EU-level policy in sport. We therefore cannot support the steps taken to further increase EU policy in this area. Specifically, we cannot support the idea of setting up a European police force for sport.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-279" speaker_id="28585" name="Diamanto Manolakou" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">The report, like the Commission’s White Paper, treats sport as yet another area of business activity designed to rake in money. The EU is trying to convert sport wholly into a commodity so that it brings even greater profitability to sports business groups and multinationals. This is why the EU is using the Lisbon Treaty to extend its powers to cover sport.</p>
      <p sl="en">This is tantamount to the systematic dismantling of amateur sport, even at school level. Amateur sport provides raw material for the sports industry and commercialised championships. Young people and the public as a whole are being treated as spectators and customers of sports entertainment organised by the commercially oriented federations. The fine words about the values promoted by sport, the fight against doping, etc. seem a mockery when the desire to emulate is replaced by ruthless competition. Corruption, doping, bigotry and intolerance are integral parts of commercialised sport; they are used to promote the products of the companies that control it.</p>
      <p sl="en">The sporting and physical exercise needs of young people can be met only by creating infrastructures and developing mass popular sport. The values of collectivity and solidarity must be promoted to oppose the corrupt model of sport produced by the capitalist system, which subordinates everything to profit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-280" speaker_id="1403" name="David Martin" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I generally support Manolis Mavrommatis’ white paper on sport. I believe that most of its recommendations will benefit sport at all levels across the EU. Indeed, I feel that encouraging football clubs to focus on nurturing talent is a positive step for the game.</p>
      <p sl="en">Every club – even the big ones – must accept some responsibility for training and not rely solely on their financial muscle in the transfer market to acquire players who were trained by others. Football should not be merely a financial contest.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-991" speaker_id="33984" name="Ioan Mircea Paşcu" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">The White Book on Sport is like a Russian "matrioshka" puppet: the first is amateur sport, the second is professional sport and the last is football (where the big money is). Thus, it gives the impression that amateur sport which is its declared "raison d'etre" is only an alibi for approaching professional sport, especially football, which seems to be the main target. The White Book is also unequal in its approach: tough on extending the existing rules in traditional fields like discrimination, illegal immigration, illegal drugs, and competition to sportive activities, but soft when it comes to devising special rules for them, as if the people involved should not be scared somehow. In any case, the White Book is heralding a new era of active involvement on the part of the EU bodies in regulating professional sport, mainly European soccer. The good news is that it intends to do it by first talking to the people involved.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-281" speaker_id="28457" name="Luca Romagnoli" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="it">I welcome the report by Manolis Mavrommatis on the White Paper on Sport. Indeed, I recognise the important role played by sport in the life of every individual and society, in that it is a means whereby everyone can overcome personal challenges, discover their own passions and talents, identify with a group and understand the importance of abiding by rules. By extrapolating these values to an international level one can understand why sport is able to break down geographical barriers and promote social intercourse and peace.</p>
      <p sl="it">I believe it necessary to point out that any kind of infringement of civil or moral ethical rules in sport – such as doping, deliberately racist gestures or gambling – must be punished, in an attempt to return to the ideals and ultimate purpose of sport.</p>
      <p sl="it">Last of all, I would point out that there is often a tendency to justify the growing importance of certain types of sport to the detriment of others, through huge wage differentials between the players of various sports.</p>
      <p sl="it">For this reason, I believe that support measures should be introduced in favour of less widespread and well-known sports.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-282" speaker_id="4274" name="Olle Schmidt" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">The report on sport contained a lot of interesting and sensible things. No one can reasonably be opposed to EU Member States taking strong action against doping and xenophobia within sport. It was more controversial, but in my opinion sensible, to support the Commission’s idea of a common European police force to cover sporting events. To that extent I was prepared to support the report. Unfortunately, the really big issue, the one concerning the liberalisation of gambling monopolies in Europe, missed the target. Personally, I believe that liberalisation, under controlled forms and with licensed gambling and lottery companies, would be able to satisfy both the interest of consumers in a range of gambling options and the sports movement’s need for resources. I therefore abstained from voting.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-283" speaker_id="1309" name="Brian Simpson" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">Sport is an important part of everyday life. Most EU citizens either participate or spectate at a number of sporting events and it is often seen as more important than life itself at times.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sport should not be above the law, but we as legislators should also recognise the unique position sport has within the European Union and the role played by various governing bodies.</p>
      <p sl="en">We should also recognise that whilst Association Football is the dominant game, it is not the only game being played, and we must recognise that other sports and pastimes as diverse as rugby league and hurling or crown green bowling and pigeon racing have an important part to play.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is not the role of the EU to govern these sports nor indeed act as some kind of sports police. That role should remain with the appropriate governing body. However, the EU can be complementary in nature and help in developing all kinds of sport by speaking out against sporting discrimination which still happens when one sport feels threatened by another. I cite the Greek Rugby Union as a classic example.</p>
      <p sl="en">I will be supporting the Mavrommatis report, perhaps not as enthusiastically as I support Wigan Warriors rugby league team or St Mirren and Blackburn Rovers, but then again this is only politics when all is said and done.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-284" speaker_id="4545" name="Catherine Stihler" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">This report on the White Paper on Sport needs to recognise that there is a subsidiarity issue over sport in the EU. That is why I support Amendment No 2.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-285" speaker_id="28134" name="Eva-Britt Svensson" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">We recognise that sport has a special role in society as an instrument of social inclusion and integration, and as a promoter of local democracy. We acknowledge the considerable importance of sport in health terms as a preventive measure for obesity and chronic conditions.</p>
      <p sl="en">We fully support the notion of strengthening the role of women in sport; the importance of protecting athletes of all ages during and after their sports career; the promotion of sports in society, including physical activities in the school curriculum; the need for redistributive measures in sports financing; and the citizens right to information and wide access to broadcasts of sports events.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, we do not support the enhanced role of EU-level policy in sport. We therefore cannot support the steps taken to further increase EU policy in this area. Specifically, we cannot support the idea of setting up a European police force for sport.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-990" speaker_id="35743" name="Glenis Willmott" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">On behalf of the EPLP. We accept the specificity of sport, however, the English version of Recital I is extremely unclear and open to misinterpretation.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem22" title="10. Corrections to votes and voting intentions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem23" title="11. Decisions concerning certain documents: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem24" title="12. Forwarding of texts adopted during the sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem25" title="13. Dates for next sittings: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem26" title="14. Adjournment of the session">
    <intervention id="4-291" speaker_id="4453" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">I declare the session of the European Parliament adjourned.</p>
      <a text="(The sitting was closed at 12.25)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
</text>
