<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20080117.EN" lang="en" date="2008-01-17" place="Strasbourg" edition="OJ edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Opening of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. The role of women in industry (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-007" speaker_id="4346" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Miguel Angel MARTÍNEZ MARTÍNEZ" nationality="Spain" birth_date="30-01-1940" birth_place="Madrid" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report (A6-0519/2007) by Ilda Figueiredo, on behalf of the Committee on Women’s Rights and Gender Equality, on the role of women in industry (2007/2197(INI)).</p>
      <p sl="unknown">This report is very important and is likely to receive a great deal of media attention.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-008" speaker_id="4466" name="Ilda FIGUEIREDO" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="30-10-1948" birth_place="Troviscal - O. Bairro" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left - Vice" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">I must start by thanking the members and staff of the Committee on Women’s Rights and Gender Equality and the draftsman of the opinion of the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy for their support and valuable contributions, particularly through their proposals on this report which enabled its unanimous approval. This work took several months and included a public hearing with valuable contributions being made by members of both parliamentary committees and external guests, particularly social organisations.</p>
      <p sl="pt">This report seeks to highlight the role of women in industry. On average, over 14% of women in employment in the European Union work in industry. In some countries this percentage exceeds 25%, such as in Bulgaria and the Czech Republic, and in others it is around 20%, such as in Portugal, Greece and Hungary.</p>
      <p sl="pt">We know that in some industrial sectors women represent the majority of workers, such as in textiles, garments and footwear, areas of the food industry, cork, cabling, and electrical and electronic equipment, whereas their participation in cutting-edge technology sectors is limited. This means that we need different approaches, but with one common goal of promoting the women working in these sectors, guaranteeing non-discriminatory practices in access to employment and contracting, wage equality, creation of career opportunities, vocational training, good working conditions and better pay, and respecting maternity and paternity as fundamental social values.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The need to guarantee employment with rights for women working in industry and to keep facilitating their access to jobs in this important sector of production also requires more attention to be paid to the situation in various industries in the European Union, to the challenges facing them and to the appropriate responses which must be found, including in international trade and in monitoring the situation of imports of sensitive products such as those in the textile sector.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Particular attention must be paid to the restructuring and relocation of multinationals which significantly affect the employment of women and increase their unemployment, particularly in regions where there is no alternative employment. The fight against the wage discrimination which still exists and which affects female workers, in particular indirect discrimination, requires us to look into establishing a methodology for analysing exactly what jobs entail, which will guarantee the right to equal pay for women and men, give proper recognition to individuals and occupations and, at the same time, establish work as a structural factor, with a view to increasing the productivity, competitiveness and quality of undertakings and improving the lives of workers, both women and men.</p>
      <p sl="pt">We must therefore encourage initiatives that contribute to the development in companies of positive measures and human resources policies promoting gender equality. We must also encourage information and training measures making it possible to promote, transfer and incorporate successful practices. I would highlight in this respect certain projects developed with the support of the EQUAL programme which I have had the opportunity to experience in Portugal. This programme deserves the European Commission’s full attention to ensure its continuation and expansion.</p>
      <p sl="pt">As underlined in the report, negotiations and collective bargaining are vitally important in the fight to abolish discrimination against women, in particular with regard to access to employment, wages, occupational health and safety conditions, career progression, and vocational training. However, the Member States and the Commission have a particular responsibility and an important role to play in promoting equality and fighting all kinds of discrimination, in guaranteeing employment with rights and in combating the precariousness of work which particularly affects women.</p>
      <p sl="pt">We therefore call on them to act, whether by defining high standards for health protection at work that take account of the gender dimension, notably maternity protection, or through working time and organisation that respect family life, or by creating effective inspection mechanisms ensuring respect for employment rights and trade union freedom, or by guaranteeing comprehensive access to good public social security and affordable social services, in particular crèches, nurseries and support for elderly people.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-009" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Meglena Kuneva" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the Commission warmly welcomes the motion for a resolution on the role of women in industry. I congratulate the rapporteur, Ms Figueiredo, on addressing this issue of the situation and role of women in industry, which is complex. One of the several reasons is that, as shown in the report, the gender equality challenges in industry are even more acute than in other sectors.</p>
      <p sl="en">In industry, the problems of working conditions, the pay gap and the reconciliation of work and private life tend to be even more pronounced.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is also a complex issue because it goes beyond equality policy to relate to the general situation in industry in Europe and the way Community policies can support industry and workers – both men and women – in the difficult context of globalisation. As you know, the adoption of the Roadmap for Gender Equality in 2006 underlined the Union’s full commitment to do its utmost to make progress towards a situation of real equality between men and women.</p>
      <p sl="en">The six priorities of the roadmap are linked to improving the situation of women on the labour market. The first is economic independence for women and men, the second is reconciliation of private and professional life, the third is equal representation in decision-making and the fourth is the elimination of stereotypes. The Commission welcomes the fact that Parliament’s motion for a resolution highlights precisely these areas. Whilst the progress made in the area of gender equality is unquestionable, major challenges remain. The Commission shares the rapporteur’s view that we must continue our efforts and consolidate what has been achieved.</p>
      <p sl="en">As far as women’s participation in industry is concerned, two issues should be tackled. Firstly, there are still very few women in industry compared to the services sector. Secondly, those women who work in industry tend to be in typically female sectors which are very labour-intensive and characterised by poor working conditions and low wages. The Commission is conducting various policies to meet these challenges. Combating stereotypes in education will, in the long term, lead to there being more highly skilled women in technical and scientific occupations and will also help to meet the needs of certain industrial sectors for manpower or womanpower. It is also important to support the careers of female engineers via networking, mentoring and measures to balance work and private life.</p>
      <p sl="en">In order to diversify women’s employment in industry, it is vital to provide every opportunity for training and retraining. The European Social Fund provides essential support in this area. It is also vital to improve the current situation of women working in industry. For example, there is still an unjustifiably large gap between women and men. In industry, this gap is as much as 30%.</p>
      <p sl="en">For this reason, in July 2007 the Commission adopted a communication on tackling the pay gap between women and men. The communication examined all the resources that must be mobilised to achieve this aim. The involvement of enterprises is an important way of making progress in the areas of equality between men and women at work, the gender pay gap, training, work-life balance and career development. In addition to the laws on equal treatment, which all enterprises must obey, it is important to encourage them to adopt voluntary measures to promote equality, in particular in the context of corporate social responsibility.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, the Commission will shortly relaunch an awareness-raising campaign for enterprises about gender stereotypes. The report on women in industry underlines the vital role of work-life balance in order to achieve real gender equality and the Commission shares this analysis. This point was mentioned during the adoption by Parliament of the Kauppi report in September 2007.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission will report in 2008 on progress towards the Barcelona objectives in the area of childcare. The second phase of the consultation of social partners on work-life balance concluded in July. The Commission takes the view that this issue should be tackled using a combination of different instruments, including the amendment of current Community legislation in order to better take account of new challenges.</p>
      <p sl="en">As I stressed, the issue of women in industry also reflects the general situation of industry in Europe. The Commission will continue to pursue all the necessary policies to face up to globalisation, ensure a future for industry in the Member States and help workers of both sexes when the companies for which they work are restructured.</p>
      <p sl="en">European laws on employee information and consultation, social dialogue and the European Social Fund are all instruments designed to achieve this. The European Globalisation Adjustment Fund, launched in 2007, will provide assistance of up to EUR 500 million per year and its rules provide specifically for gender equality to be taken into account. The Commission is, therefore, responding to all the challenges identified by the report on the role of women in industry by taking measures of various kinds: improving equality, working conditions and the role of women in industry, combating stereotypes, creating better conditions for reconciling work and family life and providing general support for companies and workers in industrial sectors in difficulty.</p>
      <p sl="en">I should like to make a personal statement: I sincerely support this way of tackling the difficulties in this specific area.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-010" speaker_id="4552" name="Den DOVER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="04-04-1938" birth_place="Warrington" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Draftsman of the opinion of the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy . − Mr President, I warmly welcome this report, which I fully support. The British Conservatives support it, as does the PPE-DE Group. If Europe is to play a leading part in a very competitive, a fiercely competitive, global world, we need all the resources available at the highest possible level.</p>
      <p sl="en">Whilst I disagree that there should be quotas saying how many ladies there should be at various levels in companies – and I particularly disagree with any compulsion in that regard – what I do want to see is as many ladies as possible rise to the highest possible levels based on their ability. It often depends on what we define as ‘industry’, and industry is changing; everything is much more flexible nowadays, and I am delighted that ladies are playing their role in industry in their various positions.</p>
      <p sl="en">I do not agree that there needs to be any handicap or under-representation in the new technologies, because ladies have the brains, the intelligence and the know-how to more than make their worth felt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Firstly, I would endorse the view that we should always go for equal pay wherever possible. Regarding this report, I was extremely pleased that the rapporteur embraced the views of people from the various groups and that we reached unanimity. I wanted to see better facilities for pensions for ladies – for portability within pensions from one employer to another to make sure they get higher pensions as they get through their working lives, and more flexibility in terms of facilities so that ladies can balance their family lives with their working lives.</p>
      <p sl="en">As I say, I fully support this report. It is a step forward. We need ladies at all levels and I wish them well. I welcome in particular our new Commissioner, who is very capable indeed.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-011" speaker_id="23866" name="Edit BAUER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="30-08-1946" birth_place="Šamorín" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="sk">I would like to say thank you for the work that has been done on this report by Mrs Figueiredo. The report to some extent lists the problems facing women employed in various sectors of industry.</p>
      <p sl="sk">Some of the problems seem to be perennial problems, such as the gender pay gap, the inadequate representation of women on company boards of directors or the inadequate reconciliation of work and family life. The report also brings up issues that are less frequently discussed, such as the insufficient attention given to specific requirements for the protection of women in the work place or the social problems that arise as a result of transfers of production to areas with lower production costs.</p>
      <p sl="sk">Some of the proposals in the report interfere with the principle of subsidiarity or lay down requirements that encroach on the competence of the social partners and the processes of collective bargaining. The PPE-DE Group will not support these proposals.</p>
      <p sl="sk">Despite the fact that the report is more or less a summary of problems that are reasonably well known, it points at the fact that changes in these areas are slow, as can be seen, for example, in the development of differences between the salaries of men and women. The research clearly indicates that the turning point comes when children arrive: from that point the careers of men and women take different directions. Most difficult to break are the critical stereotypes, and this is the case even when we do not identify with them verbally any more. The report also highlights the issue of the transferability and flexibility of pension rights, which is becoming more and more sensitive with the progressive unification of the labour market, and with the requirement for higher mobility of the workforce. This, I think, is an issue that should be given appropriate attention.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-012" speaker_id="4239" name="Christa PRETS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PSE Group" nationality="Austria" birth_date="02-10-1947" birth_place="Diez " p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, Commissioner, I would first also like to thank the rapporteur for her help and cooperation. We made the most of our opportunities to work together across political boundaries and I would like to express my warmest thanks for this.</p>
      <p sl="de">I would begin by pointing out that we have already presented a large number of reports on this subject. The demand for equal pay for equal work goes back more than 30 years and we have still not been able to make it a reality. Of course we are taking small steps forward and we are producing paper after paper, but the situation of women in industry still remains a long way behind what we have been working towards all this time.</p>
      <p sl="de">In the manufacturing industry, for example, 85% of the employees are women, and in the ICT sector the figure is 15%, and indeed women are very poorly represented in the high-technology industries. This does not imply that women are less educated, it only means – and this applies especially to rural areas – that there are simply no opportunities to take up other jobs.</p>
      <p sl="de">Women continue to work in the low-wage sector and even here there is differentiation between male and female workers. There is still inequality and discrimination, and not just in respect of wage levels but working conditions too. We are therefore also appealing to the trade unions to do more to prevent this type of wage discrimination when taking part in pay negotiations.</p>
      <p sl="de">Support for professional and vocational training programmes is still lacking or is woefully inadequate. Education and training is needed in order to provide female employees with career prospects, even in low-skill sectors. We also call on companies to apply family and women-friendly policies in their workforce management plans, which will work to everyone’s advantage: when everyone has that feel-good feeling, business runs better and this also benefits the women who work in it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-013" speaker_id="28314" name="Anneli JÄÄTTEENMÄKI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group" nationality="Finland" birth_date="11-02-1955" birth_place="Lapua" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="FI">
      <p sl="fi">Mr President, I would like to thank the rapporteur for her excellent report and levels of cooperation, and, in particular, for highlighting the way men and women are treated differently, despite the fact that we hardly ever get a sympathetic hearing.</p>
      <p sl="fi">The Member of the Commission is, I am sure, personally committed to the issue, but when I was listening to your official reply in which you said that the Roadmap had been adopted, and that there was commitment to it, afterwards one might naturally have expected to hear an account of what had actually happened. Unfortunately, we have to say that hardly anything has happened in matters of equality during this Commission’s term. That is regrettable. It is perhaps not the sort of important issue the Commissioners or others could score points on; nevertheless, ladies and gentlemen, I would like to encourage us all to do more because we are responsible for the status of women in Europe.</p>
      <p sl="fi">I will give you one example. In Finland women got the right to vote when it was part of a very conservative Russia in 1905. That was amazing. Looking ahead now, I do not think it will be possible, now we are part of Europe, for women in the different Member States to earn the same pay and receive the same kind of treatment in the EU, even if the EU speaks of human rights and is progressive. I think the EU could take a look at the decisions that were taken in tsarist times and make bold decisions on equality of pay and equality in the workplace. The tsar had the courage to give women the vote, but the EU does not have the courage to do anything to bring about equality of pay in the Member States of the EU.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-014" speaker_id="28374" name="Wiesław Stefan KUC" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the UEN Group" nationality="Poland" birth_date="02-09-1949" birth_place="Sokołow Podlaskí" p_group="Non" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, I have clear memories of the 1950s in Poland. We used to see many huge billboards with pictures of smiling girls driving tractors. These were girls from the so-called Polish Service organisation. We saw them shouldering pickaxes and spades and marching joyfully off to work. There were also women tending looms and lathes. Times have changed. We now see women working in design offices, on computers, or on the new production lines for electronic equipment, mobile telephones and televisions. We also see the tired faces of women hurrying home after many hours of hard work to undertake other daily tasks. Those were the images that came to my mind as I read Mrs Figueiredo's report on the role of women in industry.</p>
      <p sl="pl">For many years now, efforts have been made to protect women, reduce their workload and treat them in the same way as men are treated. Unfortunately, differences persist to this day. The list of expectations is very appropriate, though perhaps not complete. Differences still persist in the way men and women are treated at work, both regarding pay and career development as well as assessment of their work and qualifications. The most unfortunate thing of all is that it has not proved possible to create the conditions for women's hopes and aspirations to be realised, so that they can be sure of job stability and opportunities for career development.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-015" speaker_id="28409" name="Raül ROMEVA i RUEDA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALDE Group" nationality="Spain" birth_date="12-03-1971" birth_place="Madrid" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance - Vice" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, the role of women in industry is clearly conditioned – this has already been stated, and I wish to remind you of it – as in many other cases, by a number of stereotypes, some of which are clearly pernicious.</p>
      <p sl="es">We need to make headway on overcoming such stereotypes and that is precisely why I feel the Figueiredo report is a fundamental and important concept and, similarly, why it enjoys the support of our group.</p>
      <p sl="es">There is much evidence to justify this report and the submission of a number of proposals, which we trust will be welcomed not only by the Community institutions, but by business itself, which, after all, has to adopt them and implement them.</p>
      <p sl="es">One such piece of evidence is the fact that the European Union average in terms of women employed in industry is a mere 14%. It must nevertheless also be borne in mind that, of this percentage, 21% accounts for part-time employees; indeed, women account for 65% of part-time employees in the industrial sector. I feel that this is one of the key aspects, and by no means a minor issue in this debate.</p>
      <p sl="es">The second piece of evidence is the fact that it is precisely women with precarious employment conditions, women working part-time, carrying out temporary employment in atypical conditions, that are most frequently affected by wage discrimination or, when they wish to take maternity leave, have fewer possibilities in terms of basic, permanent and vocational training.</p>
      <p sl="es">Thus the proposals in this report include the proposal for urgent measures to be adopted for full and effective application of Directive 75/117 EEC on the principle of equal pay for men and women as a means of opposing wage discrimination. We have been calling for this for some time now, and hope to see it implemented as soon as possible.</p>
      <p sl="es">Secondly, we want incentives to be provided for initiatives, positive courses of action and policies for human resources to promote equality. We want the Member States and the Commission to provide more and better tax breaks for companies in terms of compliance with codes of conduct and corporate social responsibility criteria in their day-to-day business. We want to see better working conditions, with particular emphasis on working hours, and maternity and paternity leave – here responsibility is shared on both sides by the couple or the family – thereby guaranteeing working men and women the opportunity to take up their posts again after such leave. Attention must also be paid to reconciling work and family life. Thus, for all this to be transformed into reality, the report calls for these rights to be implemented in legislation across the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="es">Finally, I beg to differ with Mr Dover on the subject of quotas. For some of us, female and male, these constitute a necessary instrument, and thus we feel the point must be made that the European Union ought to follow the Norwegian example of applying measures to increase the numbers of female board members of public utilities to at least 40%, and use regulations to impose a 40% quota of female representation on boards of private companies.</p>
      <p sl="es">It is obvious that this is not the solution, but I must insist that this is a path and a means that is proving useful in other aspects, which we would like to see copied within the European Union.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-016" speaker_id="28336" name="Věra FLASAROVÁ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group" nationality="Czechia" birth_date="19-12-1952" birth_place="Ostrava" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="CZ">
      <p sl="cs">Mr Chairman, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, my committee colleague Ilda Figueiredo has, as always, done an excellent job. She has documented facts that I myself consider fundamental, in particular the fact that working women account for the dominant share of employment in the processing industry, where the majority of jobs require fewer qualifications, are manual and are badly paid. The stereotype that it is a woman’s lot to do auxiliary work is well illustrated here. I had the opportunity to visit several production plants in the food industry in different countries. These plants are very similar, despite their geographical diversity. The men hold the managerial jobs and the unskilled work on the production line is done by women. They earn little, they work mechanically in a stupefying rhythm, without any motivation for professional growth, and they work under unfavourable conditions. This is, of course, wrong.</p>
      <p sl="cs">A great deal of work is still needed to put an end to gender inequality. We must realise that this area is still not sufficiently covered by statistics and that the gender issue is a relatively new statistical phenomenon. In the real world, the disadvantages experienced by women in industry, compared with men, are even more noticeable. However, it is necessary to focus on the issues that the rapporteur rightly designated as priorities: the disadvantages facing women in terms of pay and the fact that there are few women in technical fields that are, in comparison to the significant processing industry, technologically more demanding and better paid. Women need to be able to gain access to higher education; professional qualifications are of relevance here. They should also be given the opportunity to return from maternity leave to the labour market, but also to further studies. This right, of course, applies to men who look after children too.</p>
      <p sl="cs">Some regions of the European Union, particularly in the East, are undergoing changes in the structure of their industries. These changes are enforcing greater workforce mobility and retraining. I know about these trends from my own experience, because I come from the industrial part of the Czech Republic, which has been industrialised, and I am aware of their impact, especially on working women.</p>
      <p sl="cs">Another related problem is the transfer of factories to countries outside the European Union, where the workforce is cheaper. Women’s employment is also threatened by the influx of cheap goods from Asia, but also from other countries that produce high volumes of consumer goods for foreign markets, rather than supplying their own market, which does not have the purchasing power. All these factors have a noticeable influence on the employment of women in industry and their negative consequences should be gradually mitigated.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-017" speaker_id="28334" name="Urszula KRUPA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the IND/DEM Group" nationality="Poland" birth_date="20-10-1949" birth_place="Łódź" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, the statistics tell us that across the European Union there are more men than women in employment in every age group. This can be due to personal choice or to tradition, but is often the result of discrimination in the workplace. In addition, on average women earn less than men in every Member State of the European Union. It is therefore important to use legislative and regulatory means to remind entrepreneurs and employers of their duty to comply fully with the principle of equal treatment, and not just as regards pay.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The issue of the unequal participation of women in industry should be approached rationally, because the branches of industry defined as 'female' may involve less physical and mental effort. Women could be advised to consider them but that need not imply lower pay. It is difficult to imagine more men than women being employed in the embroidery industry or more women than men being employed in the smelting industry. Furthermore, the embroidery industry I referred to as an example may be better paid because of the artistic element involved than the food industry, for instance.</p>
      <p sl="pl">It is important to ensure that men and women receive equal pay across the different areas, and to eliminate exploitation and other unfair practices and conditions from the workplace. Opportunities for part-time work should be promoted, especially for women, alongside different types of flexibility facilitating retraining and learning.</p>
      <p sl="pl">In my speeches and in the amendments I have tabled I have repeatedly proposed not only that a return to one's job be guaranteed after maternity or parental leave, but also that such maternity or parental leave be classed as time at work, and the relevant monetary payment made in due course. This would pre-empt low retirement pensions and also help to reduce unemployment. Above all, it would ensure the proper upbringing and development of children, who are the future of every family and every nation and the future of the European Union.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-018" speaker_id="28211" name="Lydia SCHENARDI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="France" birth_date="27-06-1952" birth_place="Montreuil s/Bois" p_group="Non" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, on reading this report one might be tempted to say ‘All quiet on the western front’: nothing new, in other words.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The panorama is always the same: the persistence of stereotypes in the choice of educational and professional guidelines, over-representation of women in certain sectors such as the textile industry, the pay gap, working conditions and career prospects. The recommendations never change, however: promoting equality between men and women in professional spheres in terms of pay, their presence on company boards, or developing structures for child care and employment flexibility.</p>
      <p sl="fr">This is fine, but what then? What exactly is this umpteenth report on women’s rights going to change, within or outside the industrial sector? Despite coercive policies based on ‘positive action’ – a misleading formulation, since what it really means is compulsory quotas – gender mindsets have great difficulty moving forward.</p>
      <p sl="fr">It is not by imposing structures that may occasionally be unnatural, in the name of the principles of equality and non-discrimination, that women will more naturally take up their role within companies, whatever they may be. Women do not have such a severe handicap that they must be systematically imposed to be accepted. Incentive measures must not be coercion measures.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Moreover, when applying the Charter of Fundamental Rights we should not forget that we must also leave all entrepreneurs free to hire whomever they choose, as long as all employees are treated in the same manner, regardless of their sex.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-019" speaker_id="28173" name="Zita PLEŠTINSKÁ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="13-06-1961" birth_place="Nitra" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="sk">A higher concentration of textile and clothing industries on which female employment depends is typical for some European regions, and the Prešov region in north-east Slovakia is among them.</p>
      <p sl="sk">If we want to preserve work opportunities for women specifically in these disadvantaged regions, where the textile and clothing industries have their own tradition, we must support these industries as a productive industrial sector through suitable measures: creating new programmes focusing, for example, on the presentation and advertising of new products at specialist and international fairs. The wider application of the Strategic Research Agenda of the European Technological Platform and the need to introduce innovative technology and new business models are, in my opinion, a contribution to the future of the textile and clothing industries.</p>
      <p sl="sk">We all know that despite an increase in the number of females studying technical and scientific subjects, the obstacles they encounter in the workplace result in women abandoning scientific careers in industry. Given the importance of maintaining a certain standard in education and knowledge, scientific work must be continuous. In some scientific institutions no provision is made for women to work for part of their working time at home unless they absolutely have to be in the workplace. The mentality surrounding overtime may be one of the specific barriers. Those are the reasons why we are registering below average representation of women in high-tech sectors.</p>
      <p sl="sk">Primary responsibility rests with the Member States. We would therefore ask the relevant national institutions to prepare and introduce policies aimed at reconciling work and private life, to facilitate greater flexibility in working time and to improve the general approach to childcare services. It is also important to encourage employers – especially of small and medium-sized companies – to make sure that they put these policies and procedures into practice , through effective technical measures and if possible financial support too.</p>
      <p sl="sk">In conclusion, I would like to thank the rapporteur, Ilda Figueiredo, for her work and our shadow rapporteur, Edit Bauer, through whom we were able to enrich the report by way of our opinions. I also value highly the opinion of my colleague Mr Dover from the ITRE Committee.</p>
      <p sl="sk">Mr Chairman, in conclusion I would like to bring up one technical issue. It is very cold in this House during the debates, including today’s debate. The coldness of this Chamber does not create a good working environment for our work as Members and has serious consequences for our health. I would like to ask you to see to it that the conditions are improved.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-020" speaker_id="23805" name="Zita GURMAI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="01-06-1965" birth_place="Budapest" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="hu">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, our policies for industrial development and the manufacturing sectors can help the European economy become a leader in competitiveness, knowledge and sustainability, in line with the Lisbon objectives.</p>
      <p sl="hu">Lisbon stands for growth in employment rates, significant increase in the employment of women, demand for the provision of proper conditions for the employment of female employees, and wide-ranging support for equal opportunities – over and above the positive role of women in the economy.</p>
      <p sl="hu">Equal opportunities must be underpinned in every area of industry: in employment, pay, promotion, the provision of vocational education and training, the availability and monitoring of different forms of flexible work, and the reconciliation of work and private life.</p>
      <p sl="hu">Overall, decent working conditions must be provided for women in industry and proper representation in the organisations whose job it is to safeguard their interests. These areas do not constitute an exception from the requirements of ensuring gender equality and the principles and practice of gender mainstreaming must be applied consistently here too.</p>
      <p sl="hu">It is important that we have the right information about actual work relations in the many, essentially different sectors of industry and the differences between the sectors themselves. A wide range of statistical information is required for shaping and drafting strategies and concrete proposals. Innumerable international management research projects have shown that the special leadership qualities of women can make a big contribution to business success. Europe must not lose this opportunity. Thank you.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-021" speaker_id="28127" name="Lena EK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Sweden" birth_date="16-01-1958" birth_place="Mönsterås" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="SE">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I congratulate the rapporteurs and those who have been working on this report on the excellent mapping of the current statistics and the current situation in Europe when it comes to women in industry. Still, one cannot avoid being disappointed, because documents like this have been produced since the 1950s and we still have very little change. This applies to women in industry, the health situation and health care for women, and to career opportunities, learning opportunities and opportunities to improve their skills, not to mention the situation of the work and family combination.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like, therefore, to spend half of my speaking time on questions to the Commission. Firstly, it is appalling that, after decades, we still have such a bad statistics situation. This is something where the Commission can really ask for an improvement when it comes to European statistics. I see that responsibility for this lies mainly with the Commission.</p>
      <p sl="en">When I was a university teacher 25 years ago, I taught my students about the rules on equal pay deriving from Brussels and from the European Member States at the time. The cases from the Court (Danfoss I and II) happened more than 25 years ago. Is it not time for a new regulation with more teeth? This is also the responsibility of the Commission.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would also like a mid-term health check when it comes to the roadmap for gender equality, which contains a lot of nice words, but no regulation so far on the horizon.</p>
      <p sl="en">Fourthly, the Spring Summit will work with the Lisbon resolution. These issues should be mentioned in March. And fifthly, when the Commission – and Parliament – arrange seminars with high-level groups, we should apply the same rules as Norway for industrial boards, i.e. the 40:60 percentage.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-022" speaker_id="39022" name="Ewa TOMASZEWSKA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="14-04-1947" birth_place="Płock" p_group="Union for Europe of the Nations Group" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, the role of women in the economy is going to grow if only because of demographic problems. It is therefore worth giving careful consideration to this issue.</p>
      <p sl="pl">As a Pole, a woman, and a physicist by training, I can state that in my country the average level of education of women is higher than that of men. Women are also more involved in business in the SME sector. I have not observed any gender-based discrimination in the scientific world. Nonetheless, women earn between 15% and 20% less than men do and women’s involvement at managerial level in companies is significantly lower than that of men. In addition, more women than men are in insecure employment. The result, therefore, is that although training and different ways of improving one’s qualifications are important, they are not enough to reduce discrimination.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Female poverty is due not only to low pay, but also to the way pension schemes are devised. Following the reform of the Polish pension scheme, a provision was introduced whereby pension contributions for persons taking maternity leave and parental leave were financed from the State budget. This was a great help to women, as pension systems tend to penalise them heavily for motherhood. The report has noted the need to deal with the matter.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I also attach great importance to considering issues relating to health and safety from a gender-specific point of view, notably as regards burdening women with tasks causing musculoskeletal disorders. These issues have also been covered in the report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-023" speaker_id="28119" name="Kathy SINNOTT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Ireland" birth_date="29-09-1950" birth_place="Chicago " p_group="Independence/Democracy Group" m_state="IE">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, in 1996 an underwear company closed its factory in my constituency. It left 160 unemployed – almost all women – of middle age, with little or no skills outside the factory. Only 100 of these women managed ever to work again. The women who found work needed, after 30 years of service in this plant, to begin again at minimum wage, as they had not been given any continuous training and their previous experience went unrecognised. This factory moved to a less expensive area of the EU and has since moved to Asia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Companies will continue to relocate for cheaper labour forces, and we need to protect women – particularly in areas like textiles – by offering the opportunity to upskill and by giving continuous education.</p>
      <p sl="en">I also want to talk briefly about apprenticeships: in Ireland only 5% of women are in apprenticeships. It is a double problem. Are they encouraged to become plumbers and carpenters? Is there not also the problem that, in most areas, apprenticeships have now disappeared?</p>
      <p sl="en">Apprenticeships themselves were a very good way to pass on information and skills and be recognised for them, and with the loss of apprenticeships we are denying many people – both men and women – the ability to pass on skills and be recognised.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-024" speaker_id="23894" name="Anna ZÁBORSKÁ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="07-06-1948" birth_place="Zürich" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="sk">I would like to stress three key points in relation to this issue.</p>
      <p sl="sk">Employers must learn not to put women in unsuitable jobs or jobs where their abilities are not sufficiently valued. The European Union institutions must keep an eye on those bodies that are receiving their help to make sure they respect the acquis communautaire. Even though different opinions exist, society should respect the fact that men and women are different, but at the same time complement each other. It is the basic principle of life and it should also be the basic principle of the policy on equal opportunities for women and men.</p>
      <p sl="sk">Diversity and compatibility in the job market and in society are fundamental. The report by Mrs Figueiredo outlines our responsibility in implementing the Lisbon Strategy, in Europe’s ‘demographic winter’. The report correctly underlines the health risks and various types of occupational diseases that can be different in men and women.</p>
      <p sl="sk">I fully support the rapporteur in her request for a full analysis of the existing situations and their consequences. Such analysis must also include the specific impact on motherhood. Nothing can justify, for the sake of future careers, future mothers being exposed to health risks that can have a negative influence on motherhood. Equally, it is the responsibility of the industrial sector not to punish women if they want to have children, and the sector should make it possible for them to be able to return to their original position after maternity leave.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-025" speaker_id="28310" name="Edite ESTRELA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="28-10-1949" birth_place="Belver" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">Mr President, the Beijing Platform for Action asserts that, without the active participation of women and the incorporation of women’s perspective at all levels of decision-making, the goals of equality, development and peace cannot be achieved. Furthermore, to achieve the objectives of the Lisbon Strategy, the participation of women in the labour market needs to be increased. As women represent 59% of graduates, it is difficult to understand why the majority of new jobs for women are part-time, sometimes insecure and precarious, poorly paid and with few prospects of career progression.</p>
      <p sl="pt">This report by Mrs Figueiredo, whom I congratulate, contains two proposals that I must highlight: the first is the promotion of female entrepreneurship. Given that 61% of women take account of family circumstances when considering setting up a business, compared with only 49% of men, measures are needed to help reconcile professional with family and private life.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The other proposal concerns long working hours. It is essential for the Commission to carry out a study into the negative consequences of long working hours, namely the family, personal and social consequences, such as children being left alone for many hours, which often leads to failure at school and crime. The Member States should also be urged to improve the monitoring of undertakings that force their employees to work beyond the statutory working hours and to impose harsher penalties.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-026" speaker_id="38608" name="Petya STAVREVA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Bulgaria" birth_date="29-04-1977" birth_place="Plovdiv" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats" m_state="BG">
      <p sl="bg">Madam Commissioner, Mr. President, colleagues, equal participation of women and men on the labour market is a precondition for sustainable economic growth and harmonious social development.</p>
      <p sl="bg">Over the past decades Europe has made considerable progress in promoting gender equality. The report on the role of women in industry summarizes some of these achievements, while insisting for a stricter application of the principle of equality.</p>
      <p sl="bg">It can regrettably be noted, however, that despite the existing relevant legal framework, a number of EU directives and resolutions remain without proper implementation. The role of women in industry ought to be based on the principles of equal pay and equal involvement in decision-making.</p>
      <p sl="bg">The labour market situation in Member States shows that women are inconsistently represented in the various sectors. They account for a large percentage of those employed in the service sectors and are underrepresented in the high-tech area, for example.</p>
      <p sl="bg">Promoting decent jobs is an integral part of the European Union values and Member States need to take effective measures to ensure that standards are met and decent jobs are guaranteed in the various industry sectors.</p>
      <p sl="bg">I believe that we are all faced with the serious challenge of applying a set of policies with a focus of combining work, personal and family life. European citizens, both women and men, deserve to enjoy equal opportunities and should be equal not just on paper but in real terms. Thank you.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-027" speaker_id="28153" name="Britta THOMSEN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Denmark" birth_date="23-01-1954" birth_place="Aalborg" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="DK">
      <p sl="da">Mr President, I should very much like to thank the rapporteur for a very relevant report, which focuses on the growing gender inequality in the labour market at a time when we are all promising each other to combat wage discrimination and work towards genuine equality. Women currently hold the lowest-paid unskilled jobs in industry, and there is a risk that their conditions will deteriorate further if we do not immediately introduce targeted in-service training. We need to make it compulsory to compile gender-differentiated statistics on both wage levels and the gender balance in the individual sectors. It is totally unacceptable that we still have such a poor level of knowledge in these areas. How can we change things if we do not have a clear overview of what the status quo actually is?</p>
      <p sl="da">We also need to develop an industrial policy that takes account of the gender dimension and the specific challenges women face in terms of pay, childbirth, job insecurity and monotonous, repetitive work. This should be done in cooperation with the social partners, and the latter must also ensure that women are sufficiently represented in their organisations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-028" speaker_id="4382" name="Avril DOYLE" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Ireland" birth_date="18-04-1949" birth_place="Dublin" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats" m_state="IE">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the proposal before us deals with a very important issue, one that continues to spark debate globally. The role of women in industry affects all facets of society and has wide-ranging implications for employment and welfare policy, family and child policy, not to mention economic policy. Yes, equality legislation ensures women get maternity leave, but all the evidence shows that they expose themselves to promotional and financial discrimination, albeit subtly (to comply with the law) but nonetheless pervasively in an inflexible business culture.</p>
      <p sl="en">There was an outcry in Ireland in recent weeks when a media accountant made this very point and he was roundly handbagged. There is no point denying the blindly obvious. Perhaps this report before us should be subtitled, ‘Motherhood and misogyny’, as an editorial in the Sunday Tribune at home screamed last week.</p>
      <p sl="en">We in the European Parliament must endorse the proposal before us – with which I largely agree – because, on the one hand, industry needs women at all levels and, on the other hand, society needs children. We all – including employers and industrialists – must respect maternity and paternity leave as fundamental social values. While I still baulk at compulsory quotas for women’s participation, albeit in politics or business, my faith in a meritocracy is being sorely tested the older and, hopefully, the wiser I get.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to congratulate the rapporteur. There might be one or two paragraphs that I have to think about, but I will be supporting her report, and I think it behoves all of us in the House to support a very good report on which an awful lot of work has been done.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-029" speaker_id="28349" name="Teresa RIERA MADURELL" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Spain" birth_date="13-10-1950" birth_place="Barcelona" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, I also wish to congratulate the rapporteur for her work and her open disposition, which has allowed us all to transform the general duty of companies in terms of respect for the principle of equality between working women and men into specific measures.</p>
      <p sl="es">Her report includes measures to guarantee equal opportunities in terms of access to employment, training and professional promotion; measures to respect women’s and men’s employment rights, including – and this must be emphasised – protection against sexual harassment; and measures to enhance the reconciliation of personal and family life and employment relations.</p>
      <p sl="es">Perhaps, however, the most novel contributions have been, firstly, power-sharing measures: this could, for example, produce a balanced number of women and men on company boards and in all decision-making posts in line with the new law introduced in my country, Spain.</p>
      <p sl="es">Secondly, there is the recommendation that each company implement its own negotiated equality plan. This makes it a key report for a strategic sector for the European Union.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-030" speaker_id="38846" name="Roselyne LEFRANÇOIS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="France" birth_date="20-06-1950" birth_place="St Malo" p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, I welcome the fact that Parliament has taken the initiative of producing this report since, if the role of women in industry is utterly crucial, their professional situation overall remains much more precarious than that of men.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Thus the report points to a considerable number of discriminatory situations involving women that must be tackled immediately, especially their confinement to certain sectors and certain types of jobs with low pay and limited career prospects, their over-representation among atypical employees, particularly those subjected to part-time employment, or the difficulties they encounter in rejoining the labour market after maternity leave.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I feel that one of the courses of action mentioned to rectify this circumstance, the idea of a reward for companies encouraging reconciliation between professional life and family life, is quite interesting, and indeed the improvement of women’s career prospects ought to be encouraged by enhancing life-long learning.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I must, however, voice certain regrets as to the format of the report. I feel that the text is too long and not properly structured, and this impairs its readability and effectiveness.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-031" speaker_id="33977" name="Gabriela CREȚU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="16-01-1965" birth_place="Târgu Frumos" p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">The report may create the impression that we are talking about the absence of women in industry. This is indeed one of its topics. However, what the report emphasises is the presence of women in industry: women have low-paid jobs in low-paid industry branches, they are in the majority where there are no trade unions, and consequently no guarantees under collective agreements; women work in vulnerable industry branches, and they are the first to be laid off in the event of mass redundancy. Women are present at the workplace, but they are nowhere to be seen in management. They only get to do the work; they don't get to decide.</p>
      <p sl="ro">This report talks about what is missing, but it also talks about the things that women have. Women have an education, but hold no qualifications; they suffer from occupational diseases which are not recognised as such; they are willing to learn after they've turned forty, but they have no opportunity to do so. They are mothers, but there are no nurseries available. Men become parents and have no nurseries either, but they have their wives.</p>
      <p sl="ro">What is to be done? Existing regulations, our reports, the Commission’s roadmap on gender mainstreaming, all these show that we know what should be done. What we and the Commission should remember, and most importantly what we should remind Member States of, is that citizens, especially women, do not judge our efficiency by the number of decisions we pass, but by our ability and will to enforce them. And the latter seem to be lacking.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-033" speaker_id="28377" name="Lidia Joanna GERINGER de OEDENBERG" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="12-09-1957" birth_place="Wrocław" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, only between 14% and 25% of working women in the European Union are employed in industry. In addition, their participation in different sectors of industry is uneven, due to the stereotypes affecting educational and professional choices.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Women are employed mainly in the textile, clothing, footwear, food and food processing sectors, where pay is generally low. Women are significantly under-represented in the more highly-paid advanced technology sectors. The Member States should develop programmes aimed at educating women and fostering their entrepreneurial spirit. They should also offer financial support for such programmes. In addition, incentives should be provided for women working in industry to improve their qualifications on a regular basis.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Every Member State has a duty to comply with the principle of equal pay, to provide dignified working conditions and the opportunity to develop a professional career, while at the same time respecting social values such as motherhood and fatherhood. Compliance with social standards such as the right to safety, social protection and freedom of association will help to eliminate all forms of discrimination against women in the workplace.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Finally, I should like to congratulate Mrs Figueiredo on a very well-prepared report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-034" speaker_id="28294" name="Ljudmila NOVAK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovenia" birth_date="01-08-1959" birth_place="Maribor" m_state="SI">
      <p sl="sl">What we are saying about women in industry could equally be said of women in business and health care. By nature men and women have different physical abilities and therefore some work is more suited to women and some more suited to men. However, in cases where the quality of work and effectiveness are not dependent on physical strength, it is not permissible for women to be paid less than their male colleagues. Moreover, it is precisely female occupations that are automatically less well paid as it is, even though they are by no means easy and require a great deal of effort.</p>
      <p sl="sl">We have heard our fellow Member who said that we adopted similar reports on the inequalities of women 30 years ago. Why has nothing changed? Or why is change very slow? Or are businesses guilty of this? I believe that we must clearly identify the guilty parties and make a responsible and more decisive effort to ensure that the situation in this area finally takes a more positive direction for women.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-035" speaker_id="36281" name="Silvia-Adriana ȚICĂU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="14-11-1970" birth_place="Galaţi" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">When talking about women in industry, we should also be talking about education, research, and entrepreneurship. In the Committee on Women's Rights we’ve had a presentation from the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy concerning the role of women in industry. 15% of people with higher education are women. In 2006, women made up 33% of the total number of European researchers and only 18% of researchers operating in the private sector. However, it should be emphasised that only 28% of women researchers have children. Wages are higher in industry, particularly in the oil and chemicals industries, transport, electricity, and the automotive industry.</p>
      <p sl="ro">However, throughout Europe there is a gender gap as far as payment is concerned (roughly 20% in corporate management and 19% in engineering/science). 34% of women working in industry have children and we should stress that only 20% of industrial entrepreneurs are women. Therefore, we should concern ourselves more with women’s education and training and in particular with child-care facilities.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-036" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Meglena Kuneva" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I wish to thank Members of for a very interesting discussion, and will take this opportunity to answer some of their questions.</p>
      <p sl="en">In reply to Ms Figueiredo, it is true that the Equal programme finishes in 2008, but the European Social Fund Regulation for 2007-2013 incorporates gender equality as a horizontal priority.</p>
      <p sl="en">In reply to Ms Bauer, we had the first reading of the important legislation issue you mentioned – the transferability of pension rights – in June 2007, and the EPSCO Council dealt with it in December 2007. We hope to make quick progress during 2008.</p>
      <p sl="en">In reply to Ms Jäätteenmäki – I realise that she is not in the Chamber, but her question was very important, so I would like to answer it – the Commission adopted, in July 2007, the communication on ‘Tackling the pay gap between men and women’. In that communication, the Commission announced that in 2008 it would examine the relevance of current legislation from the point of view of the relevance of legal instruments with regard to the causes of the pay gap and, where necessary, propose amendments to the Community legal framework. Following this examination the Commission could propose any necessary changes to the current legal framework.</p>
      <p sl="en">In reply to Ms Romeva i Rueda, anti-discrimination and gender equality legislation does not preclude Member States from developing and implementing positive actions. The Commission supports there being a higher proportion of women in decision-making. We will create a network of women in decision-making posts, probably during 2008.</p>
      <p sl="en">In reply to Ms Flasarová, we cannot prevent companies from delocalising, but we have instruments to tackle that issue. In 2007, the European Globalisation Fund was quite promptly set up for this purpose.</p>
      <p sl="en">In reply to Ms Ek, concerning statistics, the Commission continues to cooperate with Eurostat to develop specific statistics on equality. The Dublin Foundation for the Improvement of Living and Working Conditions takes into account gender equality in its regular reports. In 2009, there will be a regular publication on the research statistics on women.</p>
      <p sl="en">In reply to Mrs Doyle, concerning maternity leave, the Commission is to prepare an impact evaluation on possible legislative measures introducing new forms of leave – adoption leave, and leave to care for family members other than children.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-037" speaker_id="4466" name="Ilda FIGUEIREDO" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="30-10-1948" birth_place="Troviscal - O. Bairro" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left - Vice" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">Madam President, I firstly want to thank my fellow Members and also the Commissioner for their words today and for their contributions which have enabled this debate to assume even greater consequence.</p>
      <p sl="pt">However, as others have already done, I must also of course call for further practical measures to be taken. These proposals that we have made must be felt on the ground, in the lives of undertakings, female workers and families, because it is not acceptable, as various people have said here today, that 30 years after a directive provided for equal pay, we still have this clear disparity of 30% between the average wages of men and women working in industry. This figure is double the average wage difference in the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="pt">We cannot therefore allow this situation to continue for a further 30 years and that is why I call on the Commission, and also the Member States, to take concrete measures. These could be legislative or they could involve better monitoring, but they must ensure increased promotion of equal rights and opportunities and increased promotion of this objective which must be put into practice through education and training. We must also fight stereotyping, as highlighted here today, and we must ensure that the organisation of working hours, working time and jobs better responds to women’s rights, and also to the right to maternity and paternity which are recognised as fundamental social values of the European Union.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-038" speaker_id="1237" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Mechtild ROTHE" nationality="Germany" birth_date="10-08-1947" birth_place="Paderborn" p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place today.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 142)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-039" speaker_id="23806" name="Gyula HEGYI" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="30-04-1951" birth_place="Békéscsaba" p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="hu">I welcome this important report and would stress that women in particular suffer from occupational illnesses. One new study mentions that in the EU 140 000 people, three and a half percent in this context, die every year as a result of occupational illness, and one of the main causes is chemicals. And chemicals are implicated in 86% of cancer-related occupational illnesses.</p>
      <p sl="hu">An important point here is that women, who generally live longer than men, are, as a group, more sensitive to chemicals and more vulnerable, as chemicals gradually build up in their adipose tissue and can be transferred to their unborn children. So we need to have a properly thought out European strategy to minimise the occurrence of occupational illnesses and the number of deaths and give women maximum protection.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-040" speaker_id="4412" name="Véronique MATHIEU HOUILLON" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="France" birth_date="28-10-1955" birth_place="Nancy" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="fr">Although the report on the role of women in industry rightly emphasises the many difficulties facing women in the labour market and certain economic sectors, the proposals in the text raise two questions.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Firstly, the report appears to neglect the boundaries of the legislator’s action. Europe’s legal arsenal is currently one of the world’s most lavish in terms of women’s rights and gender equality. Therefore, it is up to the elected representatives and the citizens to ensure respect for the rights of women in the European Union. In consequence, the usefulness of an umpteenth declaration of intent is somewhat limited.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Secondly, the report contains one proposal that is, to say the least, curious indeed: suggesting that a quota of women on boards of private companies ought to be established by law points to a serious attack on individual liberties and does women little service. Treating women in a fashion that is closer to charity than equality tends to exclude them even more from certain sectors of society.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Our fellow citizens now expect us to support them by matching our words with actions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-041" speaker_id="28421" name="Marianne MIKKO" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Estonia" birth_date="26-09-1961" birth_place="Võru" p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="EE">
      <p sl="en">The Lisbon targets set in 2000 will certainly not be achieved by 2010 as originally intended.</p>
      <p sl="en">The current gender structures and attitudes play an important role in this failure. Europe is not adequately using the potential of the half of its population. Women do not have equal opportunities for achievement in the high-value-added industry.</p>
      <p sl="en">Moreover, women are not adequately represented in social dialogue. Neither employers’ organisations nor the trade unions and the public sector have enough women in high-level positions.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is remarkable and alarming that the future of work and the future of society are decided by the half of the population which does not take equal responsibility for raising the children and maintaining the household.</p>
      <p sl="en">Increasingly, antisocial measures such as increasing unreported overtime and uncompensated flexibility of workers are used to increase productivity. The price we pay for this illusory increase is too high.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Member States should significantly increase the emphasis on gender equality in social dialogue. Simultaneously, many Member States should strengthen the role which social dialogue has in setting the policy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Women have the highest potential to accelerate the development of our high-tech industry. Europe must use it.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Second Internet Governance Forum, held in Rio de Janeiro from 12 to 15 November 2007 (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-043" speaker_id="1237" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Mechtild ROTHE" nationality="Germany" birth_date="10-08-1947" birth_place="Paderborn" p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the statement by the Commission on the results of the Internet Governance Forum held in Rio de Janeiro last November.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-044" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Meglena Kuneva" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the idea of an Internet Governance Forum (IGF) was born at the World Summit on the Information Society in Tunis in November 2005 and defined as a non-binding forum for multi-stakeholder policy discussion.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission supports the Forum in this form. Two meetings have been held so far: in 2006 in Athens and 2007 in Rio. The Commission welcomes the forum in each form. The Commission also welcomes the participation of Parliament at the forum and is grateful for the excellent cooperation on both meetings.</p>
      <p sl="en">As in the previous year, the meeting in Rio provided an excellent framework for enriching exchanges which allowed the gathering of a range of views on the relevant issues.</p>
      <p sl="en">Therefore, the Commission sees value in upholding the main characteristics of the forum, notably the participation of the various stakeholders and its non-binding nature.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like also to thank you very much for giving me the opportunity to say something more concrete on the IGF (we have adopted this abbreviation) which took place in November in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
      <p sl="en">Firstly I would like to thank very much Ms Trautmann, Mr Harbour, Mr Badia i Cutchet and Mr Hökmark, who represented Parliament at this meeting, for their active participation and for the continuation of their excellent cooperation. This allowed us – this year again – together to highlight a number of European priorities such as freedom of speech, bridging the digital divide, security and child protection on-line.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is important for Europe to bring such issues to the forefront of the international agenda on a constant basis. The Commission supports the IGF. This concept, elaborated during the World Summit on the Information Society, is still very valuable, and all the issues which have been mentioned are very much in favour of what we are trying to step up as actions in this particular field.</p>
      <p sl="en">In fact, on a broad range of internet-relevant subjects, the number of participants – around 3 100 – clearly demonstrates that there is indeed interest in having such a place for discussions.</p>
      <p sl="en">The fact that there is no negotiated text as an outcome of the Forum should be seen as a strength rather than as a weakness of the process. The Forum allows for open exchange, without the pressure of defending a particular outcome in a binding document.</p>
      <p sl="en">This can serve as a basis for improving understanding of each other’s concerns and can pave the way for finding common solutions. Dynamic coalitions stemming from the Forum are, in fact, one example that the IGF can work as a platform where people who share common interests can further cooperate.</p>
      <p sl="en">Thus, the Rio Internet Governance Forum meeting again provided an excellent framework for enriching exchanges, which allowed a range of views on relevant issues to be gathered.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would also like to thank once again Members and hope we will continue our excellent cooperation, because this is one of the most promising areas for our future work.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-045" speaker_id="28124" name="Gunnar HÖKMARK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group" nationality="Sweden" birth_date="19-09-1952" birth_place="Ystad" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="SE">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, it is important to underline the rapid change that use of the internet and ICT has brought about, not only for individual societies, but also for the world. In all sectors of societies, the impact of the internet has changed patterns and opportunities. This is important in order to keep a perspective for the future, because the strength of the internet has been its independent nature, its opportunities and its ability to adapt to different opportunities and demands in societies, based on a number of different actors and operators.</p>
      <p sl="de">It is important because, when we look to the future, we must ensure that it can be used in order to bridge rifts between countries and people, and help to fight poverty and support development – it is of crucial importance for the Millennium Goals, for example. The emergence of new technology should also be used to ensure that it is easier for more people to use the internet, in more societies.</p>
      <p sl="de">We in the European Union have three important things to focus on. First of all, we should ensure we are committed to, and support, the IGF process and its independent and non-binding character. That is of deep importance, because it is a good process which is much more dynamic when it is independent and non-binding.</p>
      <p sl="de">Secondly, we should contribute to the preparations for the next IGF in New Delhi, and ensure that we hold discussions with parliamentarians and civil society in order to underline its independence, but also the opportunities. Thirdly, we should ensure that the internet is guaranteed freedom and freedom of expression.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-046" speaker_id="1129" name="Catherine TRAUTMANN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PSE Group" nationality="France" birth_date="15-01-1951" birth_place="Strasbourg" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="fr">Madam President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, the Second Internet Governance Forum was held in Rio from 12 to 15 November last year, and was attended by 2 100 people from all five continents representing interested Internet parties from all public and private sectors.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The forum provides a favourable context in which to seek solutions to future ICT problems. Through a common culture and a partnership format, it provides the decisions to be taken at future world summits on the information society, in addition to those to be taken by our own states.</p>
      <p sl="fr">It also provides the opportunity to hold an open reflection on the complex nature of the Internet and make timely provision for its technical, ethical and legal limitations, since there are major concerns in addition to the issues close to EU hearts: reducing the digital divide, freedom of expression on the web, cultural diversity and child protection. I could also RFID, radio frequency identification, in short, the formation of an Internet of things, the risks of network overload by 2010-2012, digitalisation, particularly of cultural goods, the consequences arising in terms of the protection of intellectual property and, above all, improvement of access to ICT for less developed countries.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Europe is certainly up to speed in terms of the legislative process. This is encouraging for us as Europeans, but we must not slacken off. Many of these legal or regulatory issues are likewise improved with the review of the Telecom Package.</p>
      <p sl="fr">In this respect, I would call for a new phase of targeted political and future-oriented work, notably through the creation of a European IGF involving the national parliaments and local authorities: a European forum implemented by 2009 and perhaps a world forum in Europe thanks to Lithuania’s application for 2010.</p>
      <p sl="fr">As delegation head, I wish to thank all Members, colleagues and officials for their work and their availability. The resolution we will be voting on constitutes a roadmap. I am pleased it enjoys the support of all of the groups in Parliament. More parliamentary committees are welcome to lend their weight to this course of action, and I would like to thank the Commission and ask its Members to lend their support to Mrs Reding. Finally, I would like to ask the Council to include in its agenda relations with India and preparations for the New Delhi forum, and I would urge all Member States to participate in enhanced cooperation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-047" speaker_id="23864" name="Toomas SAVI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group" nationality="Estonia" birth_date="30-12-1942" birth_place="Tartu" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="EE">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, among other items, the public service value of the internet was discussed in Rio de Janeiro on 13 November 2007. Nowadays, the most limited asset of European citizens is time, and it is vital for the governments of the Member States to introduce public services on the internet.</p>
      <p sl="de">My home country, Estonia, has done much in this field: e-voting, e-tax declarations, e-government and e-registry office are only a few examples of successful ‘e’-projects that could be implemented across Europe.</p>
      <p sl="de">I know that it is much easier to reform a small country, where approximately 66% of the inhabitants use the internet. However, moving public services to the internet is worth the effort.</p>
      <p sl="de">One of the prerequisites for the functioning of democracy is participation. ‘E’-solutions provide the possibility of participation with minimal effort: there are no queues or officials exercising the right of discretion. The internet gives citizens more independence and ensures impartial administration of their affairs.</p>
      <p sl="de">However, it is essential to start such education from an early stage in schools. On the other hand, computer literacy has succeeded where Esperanto failed – it has become the most universal language – and efforts should be made not only to bridge the digital gap at regional and global levels, but bearing in mind the different age groups and social strata.</p>
      <p sl="de">Last but not least, the European Parliament often seems to occupy itself with producing immense volumes of paper. Why not upgrade our tools of democracy and implement paperless administration?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-048" speaker_id="28372" name="Ryszard CZARNECKI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the UEN Group" nationality="Poland" birth_date="25-01-1963" birth_place="Londyn " m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, the Internet is rather like a knife. A knife may be used to slice our daily bread but it may also be used to kill. It is hard to imagine the contemporary world without the Internet, and our working lives without the Internet, but the Internet is also abused, for example by paedophiles.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The European Union therefore acted wisely in setting child protection on the Internet as a priority for the last Internet Governance Forum held in Brazil two months ago. We should strive to combine openness and maximum access to the Internet with safety not only for children but anyone else who might be as risk as a result of Internet abuse.</p>
      <p sl="pl">It is significant that the next Internet Governance Forum will be held in Delhi, the capital of India. India is a country that has become a leader in information science, despite being relatively poor. It services global enterprises thus enabling hundreds of thousands of people to improve their standard of living.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Two proposals appear worthy of support: the first is for an Internet Governance Forum to be organised in two years’ time in one of the new Member States, Poland for example, or perhaps Lithuania; the second is to consider creating an Internet Governance Forum of our own, I mean our own European forum, not a world forum. The European Parliament has a vital role to play in this regard. Clearly, Internet access in the Member States of the Union varies considerably. In my country, Poland, it is not very extensive, largely for financial reasons. The European Union should act to ensure that access is comparable, especially in rural areas.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-049" speaker_id="4538" name="Malcolm HARBOUR" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="19-02-1947" birth_place="Woking" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I would like to join with Ms Trautmann – and I think I am speaking for all my other colleagues as well – in expressing my gratitude to the Parliament Presidency for having enabled us to go as an official delegation.</p>
      <p sl="en">This was a fact well noted by the many participants. We were the most active of all the political delegations there, and there were more European parliamentarians than any others. However, we are now seeing signs that other parliaments are looking at the Internet Governance Forum and realising they need to engage with it, because it addresses crucial public policy matters on which they need to be involved.</p>
      <p sl="en">The speeches given by my colleagues have covered a number of the issues. I would just like to make some broad observations about how I see the process evolving, particularly because I am the only Member of this Parliament to have attended both the world summits on the information society, and have also been through the process from the very beginning. There is a feeling that the forum in Rio is now starting to come up with much more practical ideas, and people are beginning to realise the value of exchanging information and best practice from around the globe.</p>
      <p sl="en">That is based on an understanding that it is not actually going to be formal, international, legal structures that are going to deliver many of the benefits we are looking for. In fact, we are going to have to deal with many of these matters through intergovernmental cooperation, and in many cases through cooperation between voluntary or non-governmental organisations.</p>
      <p sl="en">In the case, for example, of child protection, which the previous speaker referred to, the most successful initiatives have been those carried out by voluntary-based organisations – such as, in my country – the Internet Watch Foundation. It was very important to actually talk to people about such organisations.</p>
      <p sl="en">I will close by giving you a clear example, at a broader level, of the value of such interchanges. I participated in a workshop on consumer protection data breach notification, which is about to be discussed in Parliament as part of European legislation. I have a whole dossier on what has been done in other counties, and would say to the Commission that their proposal is currently extremely weak and would benefit greatly from its looking at that information. This is the sort of practical benefit we can derive from such forums, and I am sure we in this Parliament will be able to contribute to the development of the agenda for the next forum, to make it even more effective.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-050" speaker_id="28326" name="Francisca PLEGUEZUELOS AGUILAR" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Spain" birth_date="28-06-1950" birth_place="Granada" p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">Madam President, I feel that the Commissioner and all of us who have spoken today agree on the importance and the social and political impact of these forums, which are being attended in increasing numbers.</p>
      <p sl="es">For this reason I feel we must congratulate ourselves on the commitment we are making in Europe. I also feel, however, that we ought to avail ourselves of the political opportunity at this time, as Mrs Trautmann said, to reflect on the new Telecommunications Package, and in that sense I think that both the Commission and Parliament must make every effort not just to offer the people of Europe access to the best digital services, but also to spearhead the extension of the information society as a social commodity to countries that are in need of European cooperation and leadership.</p>
      <p sl="es">In this sense, I feel that what has been said here is extremely important: we must work on common problems such as sensitivity, freedom of expression on the Internet and protection, priority issues in my view.</p>
      <p sl="es">At the present time I think it is vital – and I will end here, Madam President – that we make global issues compatible with local issues. I believe that this is a priority, and so the posture set out in the resolution we will be adopting today is relevant: I trust it will be sufficient incentive for the Commission to continue to include these priorities in its political agenda.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-051" speaker_id="28165" name="Lambert van NISTELROOIJ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Netherlands" birth_date="05-03-1953" birth_place="Nuland" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="NL">
      <p sl="nl">Madam President, I was not in Rio, but I was at the first conference in Athens, and there I saw the importance of the formula of the forum. In this forum stakeholders can explore together the limits that are very important and that will probably be applied in global relations later and also translated into EU regulations.</p>
      <p sl="nl">There are some quite difficult issues behind this dialogue. I am thinking of the domain names, the icon and the American influence on this. The idea behind it is that we feel that it is extremely important that the world wide web should continue to have a genuinely global, unambiguous approach. That is why it is important to see that signals from this debate reappear again in the new approach to the icon and that the ideas of partners are taken on board.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Madam President, I would like to throw some light on one particular aspect today. I very much support a European forum, a European interpretation of the forum for internet governance for the future, ideally before the 2009 elections. What we have to do is to make sure that we also bring our national parliaments on board in the debates. From the initiatives in some countries, such as the United Kingdom, you can see that these are live issues; given their importance for the future, for employment and welfare, as well as for freedom of information and participation, it is essential that we bring the national parliaments on board with other stakeholders in a European approach.</p>
      <p sl="nl">I am appealing to the Commission: I read in the files that it does not have enough instruments or funds to support one thing and another, to choose a different line of approach. There is plenty of money. Look in i2010, look in the programmes for research, etc. I would really like to a very generous position to be adopted in order to establish the European view of these problems even more clearly before the 2009 elections.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-052" speaker_id="28173" name="Zita PLEŠTINSKÁ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="13-06-1961" birth_place="Nitra" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="sk">Thank you, Madam Chairman, for giving me the opportunity to contribute to this interesting debate.</p>
      <p sl="sk">I strongly support the idea to establish forums on Internet governance with the participation of Members of the European Parliament. The Internet is today an unavoidable component of the life of European citizens regardless of their age. However, in disadvantaged regions it is almost impossible to get a fast Internet connection. With envy I often watch advertisements in our Slovak public and private media for Internet with four times the speed and its advantages. Where I live we do not have this advantage and our real options are limited only to local sources with insufficient speed.</p>
      <p sl="sk">Commissioner Kuneva, what can the Commission do to make sure that the disadvantaged regions and the people who live there will not be forgotten, to make sure that these people have an equal opportunity to participate in the digital world?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-053" speaker_id="28124" name="Gunnar HÖKMARK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Sweden" birth_date="19-09-1952" birth_place="Ystad" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="SE">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I just wanted to say one thing. I would like to thank Ms Trautmann, who led the delegation to Rio and did it in a very good way. I did not mention that in my first intervention, but I think it is important to state. We all found her to be a very good leader. I would just like that to be noted.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-054" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Meglena Kuneva" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, let me start with the next steps, which are more concrete. Following the Rio meeting, consultations will be held in Geneva next month to collect views on the outcome of Rio and the preparation for the next meeting in New Delhi. The Commission participates in the advisory group which assists the UN Secretary-General in the preparation of the IGF. As has been our practice since the World Summit on the Information Society, we will of course inform Members of the outcome of this meeting. I would now like to answer some of the specific questions raised by MEPs, starting with Ms Trautmann.</p>
      <p sl="en">We welcome the fact that Ms Trautmann addressed, in her speech at the opening session, the issue of the ‘Internet of Things’ and the possibility of bringing this up at the IGF next year. With regard to the second part of Ms Trautmann’s speech, regional IGFs have emerged in a number of places, and this appears to be a useful way to focus on questions of internet governance that are of particular importance for a specific region. The Commission strongly supports this idea.</p>
      <p sl="en">Moving on to Mr Savi, we could not agree more with his statement, and this is why the Commission is committed to the development of the e-application with the broad programmes and legislation.</p>
      <p sl="en">To Mr Czarnecki, the Commission is committed to all the initiatives on child protection. We promoted the item on the IGF agenda and we are about to propose a renewed programme on child protection on the internet.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-055" speaker_id="1237" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Mechtild ROTHE" nationality="Germany" birth_date="10-08-1947" birth_place="Paderborn" p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="unknown">To conclude the debate, I have received one motion for a resolution, signed by six political groups, pursuant to Rule 103(2) of the Rules of Procedure.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place today at 12 noon.</p>
      <a text="(The sitting was suspended at 11.40 a.m. and resumed at 12 noon.)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. Calendar of part-sessions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Voting time">
    <intervention id="4-059" speaker_id="1253" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Hans-Gert PÖTTERING" nationality="Germany" birth_date="15-09-1945" birth_place="Bersenbrück " p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="unknown">We shall now proceed to the vote.</p>
      <a text="(For the outcome and other details of the vote: see Minutes)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem7" title="6.1. (A6-0514/2007, Michael Cashman) Multiannual framework for the Fundamental Rights Agency for 2007-2012 (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem8" title="6.2. (A6-0447/2007, Agustín Díaz de Mera García Consuegra) EUROPOL (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-063" speaker_id="28246" name="Alexander Nuno PICKART ALVARO" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="26-05-1975" birth_place="Bonn-Bad Godesberg" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, now that Parliament in its infinite wisdom has adopted compromise Amendment 62, Amendment 61 as proposed by the ALDE Group is now superfluous and is therefore withdrawn.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem9" title="6.3. (A6-0516/2007, Lydie Polfer) A more effective EU policy for the South Caucasus (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-066" speaker_id="28862" name="Lydie POLFER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur" nationality="Luxembourg" birth_date="22-11-1952" birth_place="Luxembourg" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="LU">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, I just wanted to ask Mr Tannock if the addition he is proposing is in fact an addition, or whether his aim is to remove the section on violence and ill-treatment in police custody and penitentiary institutions. If his amendment is to be an addition, I can of course support it. If, however, he wishes part of the existing text to be deleted, I can only recommend that we vote against it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-067" speaker_id="4521" name="Charles TANNOCK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="25-09-1957" birth_place="Aldershot" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="fr">It is an addition. Thank you.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-069" speaker_id="28862" name="Lydie POLFER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur" nationality="Luxembourg" birth_date="22-11-1952" birth_place="Luxembourg" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="LU">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, in paragraph 32 we repeat the two conditions, i.e. territorial integrity and self-determination, even though they are already mentioned in paragraph 30. However, the author of the amendment has added ‘self-determination of the people who live there’. I strongly recommend that we delete the words ‘of the people who live there’ because that would exclude the refugees and persons displaced in their own country. Therefore, if the author of the amendment agrees to delete those few words, I will be able to support the amendment; otherwise, I recommend that we reject it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-070" speaker_id="4521" name="Charles TANNOCK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="25-09-1957" birth_place="Aldershot" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I have agreed to that change to the oral amendment.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-072" speaker_id="4521" name="Charles TANNOCK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="25-09-1957" birth_place="Aldershot" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, as we agreed at the beginning of the session, it will be an addition now. In the actual text it says to replace the words ‘in the Baku-Tbilisi-Erzurum gas pipeline’ with the words ‘in the trans-Caspian energy corridor projects’. But by negotiation at the beginning of the voting session, I have already agreed this should be an addition rather than a replacement, so can we include the words ‘in the trans-Caspian energy corridor projects’.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem10" title="6.4. (A6-0510/2007, Roberta Alma Anastase) A Black Sea Regional Policy Approach (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="6.5. Kenya (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-077" speaker_id="1965" name="Jan MULDER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Netherlands" birth_date="03-10-1943" birth_place="Diever" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="NL">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, since we formulated this resolution, some important changes have taken place in Kenya. Yesterday, the newly-elected Parliament – and according to all observers the elections to the Parliament were pretty honest – elected a new speaker. The speaker is from the opposition.</p>
      <p sl="en">We view that as an encouraging sign, and I would therefore like to propose an oral amendment, in the form of a new paragraph reading as follows: ‘Welcomes the fact that the newly-elected Parliament showed its independence by the election of Mr Kenneth Marende as its speaker, and underlines the decisive role to be played by that Parliament in restoring civil liberties in Kenya’.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem12" title="6.6. (A6-0519/2007, Ilda Figueiredo) The role of women in industry (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-081" speaker_id="4466" name="Ilda FIGUEIREDO" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="30-10-1948" birth_place="Troviscal - O. Bairro" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left - Vice" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">Mr President, this oral amendment is supported by female Members from five political groups and also by one male Member. It aims to amend the first part as follows: ‘Stresses the need to retrain those women who have had to stop their career, to enhance their employability’ and then continues ‘calls on the Member States to increase life-long learning possibilities’. This is the amendment that we are tabling.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem13" title="6.7. Second Internet Governance Forum, held in Rio de Janeiro from 12 to 15 November 2007 (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem14" title="7. Calendar of part-sessions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem15" title="8. Explanations of vote">
    <intervention id="4-086" speaker_id="1253" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Hans-Gert PÖTTERING" nationality="Germany" birth_date="15-09-1945" birth_place="Bersenbrück " p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="unknown">I would like to make the following proposal for the voting: we shall begin with the explanations of vote and then suspend the sitting at 1 p.m.. Any explanations of vote not dealt with can then be presented this afternoon at the end of the debate and after all the votes have been taken.</p>
      <a text="(Loud applause)"/>
      <a text="(Parliament approved the proposal)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-090" speaker_id="4516" name="Roger HELMER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="25-01-1944" birth_place="London" p_group="Europe of Freedom and Direct Democracy Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I have to say that on this particular measure, I voted against. While Mr Cashman is a very charming gentleman, I must say that whenever I see anything with his name on it, I do look on it with some degree of scepticism.</p>
      <p sl="en">The issue here is that we have a European Fundamental Rights Agency as if there were no such protection for human rights in the Member States. I question whether there is any need for this institution at European level. Is it not just a case of extending bureaucracy and creating new quangos, as we call them in Britain? This is a burden on the taxpayer which, in the view of many others, will not actually contribute to human rights.</p>
      <p sl="en">Furthermore, in the absence of the constitution which we were promised, which you are now proposing to drive through without a referendum, there is no basis for it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-091" speaker_id="28493" name="Derek Roland CLARK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="10-10-1933" birth_place="Bristol" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I voted against this report because the United Kingdom already respects human rights. It is a signatory to many international agreements; it does not need to be told how to behave by an EU that has overridden the results of the French and the Dutch referendums, which were perfectly constitutional.</p>
      <p sl="en">They rejected the Constitution. It has been replaced by an equivalent Treaty that has now been approved even before it has been seen in full by those who signed it.</p>
      <p sl="en">The EU clearly has no respect for democratic rights and cannot therefore be considered a safe or reliable custodian of human rights.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-092" speaker_id="28496" name="Thomas WISE" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="13-05-1948" birth_place="Bournemouth" p_group="Independence/Democracy Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, thank you for this opportunity to explain my vote. This is the first time I have done such a thing. I voted against this proposal because, whilst the committee in question may be called the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs, it does not offer liberties to civilians, it does not offer justice, and it interferes in home affairs. We in Britain were promised a referendum. We are not going to get one. What is the European Union going to do about that?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-093" speaker_id="33569" name="Syed KAMALL" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="15-02-1967" birth_place="London" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, thank you very much for giving me this opportunity to explain my vote on this important issue.</p>
      <p sl="en">You may not be aware of this, but I represent the constituency of London, the greatest city in the world, capital of the greatest country in the world.</p>
      <p sl="en">What one needs to understand is that London is actually a pretty diverse city. Let me explain: we already have 300 languages and 14 religions and, on the whole, we get along very well. So, the EU could actually learn a lot from London and how it has ensured human rights and that people’s dignity is respected.</p>
      <p sl="en">We do not need those issues to be resolved at EU level. What could London, the most diverse city in Europe – and perhaps even in the world – learn from this institution? What could it learn about human rights? What could it learn about fundamental rights? Absolutely nothing!</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me add the following. The forthcoming ratification of the European Constitution, despite its rejection in two referendums, is undemocratic, cowardly …</p>
      <a text="(The President cut off the speaker)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-094" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel HANNAN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="01-09-1971" birth_place="Lima" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group - Vice" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, on what legal basis are we constructing this agency? The Fundamental Rights Agency would have been given authority by the European Constitution. It would be given authority by the Lisbon Treaty. But the only legal base it has at the moment is a flimsy cat’s cradle of communiqués, of press releases, of resolutions in Council.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Union does not have a problem with the systematic violation of human rights. It does have a problem with the systematic violation of democratic rights. The problem we have is that a human rights charter written down on paper is meaningless unless there are also mechanisms to hold leaders to account.</p>
      <p sl="en">If you look at the constitutions of the former East Germany and of the Soviet Union, they were full of these wonderful promises of liberty. But, as the peoples of those unhappy countries found, it meant nothing without democracy.</p>
      <p sl="en">That is why, if you want to impose this human rights charter, you should consult the people first in a referendum. Pactio Olisipio censenda est !</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-095" speaker_id="28512" name="Jim ALLISTER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="02-04-1953" birth_place="Crossgar" p_group="Non" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I too voted against this ludicrous proposal of an agency in respect of human rights in the EU.</p>
      <p sl="en">We in the United Kingdom, like many other countries, are long-term signatories of the European Convention on Human Rights. Such rights as require external supervision are found there, and any court which is required is found in this city under that aegis, not under any aegis required by the EU.</p>
      <p sl="en">So this is totally unnecessary, an utter waste of public money. Its primary intent is to provide another layer of apparatus of statehood to the EU so that it can parade itself as some sort of a superstate within a Europe that gives rights to its citizens, rights they already have.</p>
      <p sl="en">If it wants to give rights, then let it recognise the fundamental right to vote on matters such as this: to say ‘yes’ or ‘no’ to a constitution.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-097" speaker_id="28178" name="Miroslav MIKOLÁŠIK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="11-09-1952" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="sk">Mr Chairman, since criminal activity is increasing continuously and the threat of terrorism is growing, Europol needs to become more flexible.</p>
      <p sl="sk">The three Protocols from 2000 to 2003 that amend and supplement the Europol Convention have still not taken effect. Surely an organisation that is promoting law cannot be effective if changes to its basic legislative instrument come into force only several years after a decision has been made to accept them. The proposal for a Council decision deals with this situation, which is why I voted for it.</p>
      <p sl="sk">One important change in relation to the present situation is the plan to finance Europol from the Community budget and give the staff the status of EU official. This will increase the European Parliament’s involvement in the management of Europol and simplify budget and personnel management. In addition, the European Parliament’s position will be strengthened as democratic control of Europol improves. Moreover, the Community’s financial expenditure will be comparable to the current expenditure of the Member States.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-098" speaker_id="28323" name="Oldřich VLASÁK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Czechia" birth_date="26-11-1955" birth_place="Hradec Králové" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="CZ">
      <p sl="cs">Mr Chairman, please allow me to explain why I did not take part in the vote on this report. Firstly, I think that Europol is functioning well on the basis of bilateral agreements and bilateral cooperation. Secondly, the Czech Republic has, together with other countries, joined the Schengen area. It is necessary first and foremost to get accustomed to this cooperation, analyse it and subsequently improve it. In addition, any further integration aimed at transforming Europol into a European police force will require ratification of the Lisbon Treaty. Only then we can talk about possible changes to Europol’s legal basis.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-099" speaker_id="4516" name="Roger HELMER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="25-01-1944" birth_place="London" p_group="Europe of Freedom and Direct Democracy Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I was interested to note that you cut off the microphone of my colleague, Mr Kamall, on the instant of 60 seconds, whereas you are much more generous when people are saying things you find more palatable.</p>
      <p sl="en">One of the errors we make in the European Union is to confuse ‘cooperation’ with ‘supranationalism’. I am all in favour of police cooperation – any sensible person would be in this day and age. However, I am absolutely opposed to the creation of supranational authorities – such as EUROPOL is intended to be – which, as one of my colleagues said of the Fundamental Rights Agency, is one of the attributes of statehood that the European Union is claiming.</p>
      <p sl="en">The trouble is that these organisations lack democratic legitimacy, and that is very dangerous. Both EUROPOL and the European Union will lack democratic legitimacy until you put the Lisbon Treaty to a referendum.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-100" speaker_id="28493" name="Derek Roland CLARK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="10-10-1933" birth_place="Bristol" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I could not disagree more with this report. I voted against. Cooperation between police forces, yes; forced cooperation and obligation, no; especially when this police force will have within its ranks armed police that can be sent anywhere in the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">We do not have armed police as a rule in the United Kingdom. We will not suffer armed police coming in at the behest of EUROPOL. We do not believe in it. We run our country in a different way!</p>
      <p sl="en">I am particularly disappointed to see that Amendments 56 and 57 were voted down, because, if passed, they would have removed immunity from that police force. In the United Kingdom, we are used to a police force which, if it causes damage to property or violates the individual or arrests without good reason, can be charged with offences afterwards. But then, I would not be surprised, because, after all, you are prepared to ram through a constitution without asking anybody either.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-101" speaker_id="28496" name="Thomas WISE" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="13-05-1948" birth_place="Bournemouth" p_group="Independence/Democracy Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, for the second time I rise to declare my vote opposing this motion.</p>
      <p sl="en">In Britain, there is a simple philosophy: no man is above the law; not even the Queen, the monarch of England, is above the law. It will take due process. We have in this legislation created a situation where there are people outside the law, incapable of being pursued legitimately.</p>
      <p sl="en">I have said in this House before: if the European Union is the answer, it must have been a bloody stupid question, and never was this so true as now.</p>
      <p sl="en">I give you Kennedy’s comments: ‘Those who make peaceful protest impossible, make violent protest inevitable’.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-102" speaker_id="4556" name="Nirj DEVA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="11-05-1948" birth_place="Colombo " p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, it is vital to cooperate across transnational boundaries on international crime, terrorism, drugs and so on. EUROPOL is doing that job right now with other police forces.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, creating a European police office which increases central powers will not solve the problems that have arisen in local communities around Britain. My country, my party, has voted against this resolution today as loyal Conservatives.</p>
      <p sl="en">My party has also requested that we have a referendum on the EU Constitutional Treaty. I have no place other than this House to protest at what Mr Brown is doing in reneging on a pledge he gave to hold such a referendum.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would therefore ask that we request Mr Brown to give the British people that referendum.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-103" speaker_id="33569" name="Syed KAMALL" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="15-02-1967" birth_place="London" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I understand that this proposal for a Council decision, as outlined in the report, provides for the conversion of EUROPOL into an EU agency.</p>
      <p sl="en">We must recognise that this will have two consequences. First of all, funding will have to be provided from the Community budget, and EUROPOL staff will acquire the status of Community officials. The report also contains provisions for coordination, which we all welcome, and organisation and implementation of investigations and operational activities carried out in conjunction with the Member States’ relevant authorities or by joint investigation teams.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Conservatives favour open cooperation between police forces across the EU and beyond in the fight against crime. But we really do not accept that the EU has any role in centralising such cooperation. Thus, EUROPOL is an agency which is not necessary since other organisations already exist to fulfil this function at a global level.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is for this reason that I would like to add that the coming ratification of the European Constitution, despite its rejection in two referendums, is undemocratic, cowardly and illegitimate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-104" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel HANNAN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="01-09-1971" birth_place="Lima" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group - Vice" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I am glad to have this opportunity to make an explanation of vote. I put in for speaking time in the debate on this issue, but one of the consequences of my party’s unhappy mésalliance with the European People’s Party is that British Conservatives are systematically denied speaking time in important debates.</p>
      <p sl="en">What I wanted to say was that this report is based on a conceptual misunderstanding. People say that, because we have cross-border crimes, and because crime is international, we need cross-border policing.</p>
      <p sl="en">We already have it. The police forces of the nation states have for decades been collaborating to great effect. We have Interpol, we have the Hague Convention, we have extradition treaties, we recognise the time spent in another country’s prison as constituting part of a sentence, and so on.</p>
      <p sl="en">The difference is that these things are based on democratic decisions between independent states, whereas what is being proposed with EUROPOL is the federalisation of what ought to be a sensitive national issue – namely the policing of criminal law.</p>
      <p sl="en">If we want to do that, we should first ask people in a referendum, which is why we need a referendum on the Lisbon Treaty.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-105" speaker_id="28512" name="Jim ALLISTER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="02-04-1953" birth_place="Crossgar" p_group="Non" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, some of the reasons propagated for this proposal on EUROPOL are quite bogus. It is suggested that we need to change the legal base; that we need to provide it with EU funding; that we need those it employs to be EU officials; that we need to expand its remit; and that we need an agency so that we can fight organised crime and terrorism. What utter nonsense! We have been fighting organised crime and terrorism quite effectively, through proper long-standing cooperation between police forces.</p>
      <p sl="en">This is all about creating another aspect of the apparatus of EU statehood, so that it has an effective EU police force. That is what those officials will be, meddling in the internal affairs of Member States and – as has been pointed out – with immunity for their actions, beyond the reach even of judicial review in nation states. It is a preposterous proposal and utterly unnecessary.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-107" speaker_id="4556" name="Nirj DEVA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="11-05-1948" birth_place="Colombo " p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, regarding the Polfer report, the Conservatives did vote with the rapporteur on the issue of the South Caucasus.</p>
      <p sl="en">But it is again rather curious, is it not, that, while we are so anxious to protect the democratic freedoms and the rights of the people of the South Caucasus, and to ensure that they have a legitimacy and that they can express their self-determination, when it comes to the serious issue of the Constitutional Treaty of the European Union, Mr Brown of the Labour Party, who promised to give us a referendum, has now reneged on a referendum.</p>
      <p sl="en">My party, the Conservative Party, is incensed that a promise has been reneged on and that is why I am standing here asking the Labour Government to give us a referendum on this important constitutional issue, just as we are concerned about what is happening in the South Caucasus.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-108" speaker_id="33569" name="Syed KAMALL" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="15-02-1967" birth_place="London" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I understand that this report welcomes the inclusion of Armenia, Azerbaijan and Georgia into the European neighbourhood policy and the endorsement of bilateral European Neighbourhood Policy action plans.</p>
      <p sl="en">I also understand that the rapporteur calls on the EU to develop a regional policy for the South Caucasus to be implemented jointly with the countries of the region. Of course, one of the watchwords that will appear in many of these reports is the word ‘democracy’. I represent London – you may not be aware of this. I represent London, the greatest city in the world, capital of the greatest country in the world, and we happen to have a very diverse community in London, including many people from Armenia, Azerbaijan and Georgia.</p>
      <p sl="en">One of the things that they welcome about living in London is democracy and the right to have their say on vital issues. They ask me all the time, ‘Why is it that you are preaching to us about democracy, yet you deny that very right to your citizens in Britain when it comes to a referendum on the Constitution?’. So the Constitution, despite its rejection in two referendums, is undemocratic, cowardly and illegitimate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-109" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel HANNAN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="01-09-1971" birth_place="Lima" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group - Vice" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, may I thank you for the patience and good humour you are exhibiting in this session. May I also, as yesterday, extend my thanks to the services and the interpreters for humouring us.</p>
      <p sl="en">The big issue in the South Caucasus region at the moment is the dispute over election results. The West more or less connived at the Saddam-like election victory of the current Georgian Government the first time around with its vote of well over 90%, and now, when it claims re-election, we are arguing about whether that vote was free and fair.</p>
      <p sl="en">What kind of example do we in the European Union hold up to these struggling democracies when we show such contempt for our own democratic process here in the European Union? It seems periodically necessary to remind this House that 55% of French voters and 62% of Dutch voters voted ‘no’ to the European Constitution, and yet we have the document coming back – this time without any referendums – as the Lisbon Treaty.</p>
      <p sl="en">I say it again: it is necessary to give the people a referendum on the Lisbon Treaty. Pactio Olisipio censenda est !</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-110" speaker_id="1838" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Gérard ONESTA" nationality="France" birth_date="05-08-1960" birth_place="Albi" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="unknown">Mr Hannan, my good humour is matched only by yours. I always wonder how you manage to fit in a reference to a referendum. You succeed in doing so every time, no matter what topic we are discussing.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-112" speaker_id="4516" name="Roger HELMER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="25-01-1944" birth_place="London" p_group="Europe of Freedom and Direct Democracy Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I voted in favour of this measure not because it was my considered wish to do so, but because, as a loyal Conservative, I was following the whip.</p>
      <p sl="en">Left to myself I would probably have abstained or perhaps voted against. I have to say that issues concerning the Black Sea are not the top priority for my electors in the East Midlands of the United Kingdom, and I suspect not the second or third priority either. Therefore, you could in a sense say that this was not a matter of the very greatest importance.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, I do not believe that the European Union should have a common foreign and security policy. I believe that nation states should have their own foreign policies, and am perfectly happy for them to work together in cooperation when that is in their interests – be this with states in the European Union or with states outside it.</p>
      <p sl="en">In any case, the common foreign and security policy can have no democratic legitimacy if there is to be no referendum on the Lisbon Treaty.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-113" speaker_id="28493" name="Derek Roland CLARK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="10-10-1933" birth_place="Bristol" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, without doubt this new policy is aimed at facilitating, amongst other things, the supply of oil and gas through that region to Western Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">That would be Russian gas and Russian oil, and you are now allowing yourselves to be possibly taken hostage. We all know that Russia cut off the supply of gas to Ukraine two Christmases ago; once they get an even bigger share of Western Europe gas supplies, perhaps they might do it to all of us at some time.</p>
      <p sl="en">At least here in France they have got the right idea, generating at least 70% of their electricity by nuclear power, and it is about time the EU formulated a policy to promote that right across the Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">But instead, of course, you go dabbling in the south Caucasus, around the Black Sea, with regimes that are not terribly stable; with regimes that may not want us there. But of course, you would rather do that than promote a referendum on the new constitution amongst your own people.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-114" speaker_id="33569" name="Syed KAMALL" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="15-02-1967" birth_place="London" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I am pleased to say that I am still here, even if you and others may not share my pleasure at being here. I would like to thank you all for your patience.</p>
      <p sl="en">I understand that this own-initiative report actually welcomes the Commission’s communication ‘Black Sea Synergy – a New Regional Cooperation Initiative’, which aims to enhance cooperation with and within the Black Sea region by supplementing existing bilateral policies with a new regional approach. It considers that, in order to adopt such an approach, the communication has to be followed by further consistent steps on the part of the EU to encourage a genuine regional dimension tailored to this era.</p>
      <p sl="en">What region are we talking about? Let me just clarify – the Black Sea region comprises the EU Member States Bulgaria, Greece and Romania, as well as Turkey and ENP partners Armenia, Azerbaijan, Georgia, the Republic of Moldova and Ukraine, as well as the Russian Federation. The great philosopher Brook Benton – followed and copied by the great philosopher Randy Crawford – once said, ‘It’s a rainy night in Georgia’. Indeed, when the people of Europe are denied their vote and the people of Britain are denied their vote in a referendum on the Constitution, it is a rainy night in the EU for democracy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-115" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel HANNAN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="01-09-1971" birth_place="Lima" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group - Vice" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I appreciate your courtesy. I am glad to be able to speak on this report because it seems to me that the European Union, in its treatment of Turkey, is making a generational, a possibly epical mistake.</p>
      <p sl="en">It now seems very clear that we are never going to admit Turkey to full membership. It is clear from the majorities in this House; it is clear from the promises of referendums in Austria and France, where there are majorities of 70% and 80% respectively against membership.</p>
      <p sl="en">Had we said initially to Ankara that this was the case and we were going to work out some kind of alternative, we might have been able to go ahead in amity and partnership. Instead we are stringing the Turks along, imposing tens of thousands of pages of the acquis communautaire on them, making them grovel about Armenia, about Cyprus, about the treatment of their minorities and then, possibly 10 or even 15 years from now, after all of this, we will flick two fingers at them. In so doing, we risk creating the very thing we purport to fear: an Islamist state.</p>
      <p sl="en">Turkey is more of a democracy than the European Union. It changed its government peaceably. I wish we would have the courage to consult our own people. Pactio Olisipio censenda est !</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-116" speaker_id="28178" name="Miroslav MIKOLÁŠIK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="11-09-1952" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="sk">The Black Sea region, an area of production and transit, has a strategic significance for the diversification and security of energy supplies to the European Union. I am convinced that regional cooperation should, in addition to Turkey and Russia, include the EU Member States as equal partners too. That is why I have voted in favour of the report.</p>
      <p sl="sk">I am concerned about the continuing conflicts in this region, which are a threat to the stability and development of the area. I would therefore call on the European Union to play a more active role in the efforts to resolve the conflicts in this strategic area, in particular to get involved in the peace operations and to cooperate more closely with the Russian and Ukrainian Governments. There are obvious problems as regards the uneven development of the private sector in many countries around the Black Sea. It is necessary to improve the investment environment in the region, for local and international companies, through measures to improve the fight against corruption and fraud and promote market economy reforms.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-117" speaker_id="1838" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Gérard ONESTA" nationality="France" birth_date="05-08-1960" birth_place="Albi" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="unknown">In accordance with the decision of this House, the explanations of vote will continue after this afternoon’s votes.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-120" speaker_id="28427" name="Alessandro BATTILOCCHIO" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Italy" birth_date="03-05-1977" birth_place="Roma" p_group="Non" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I wish to express my full support for this report, the fruit of a lengthy and excellent job by our colleague Michael Cashman.</p>
      <p sl="it">The European Monitoring Centre for Racism and Xenophobia was transformed into an Agency tasked with safeguarding and promoting human rights, the Agency being officially established on 1 March 2007. Ever since then, we must acknowledge, it has been wholly non-operational owing to the lack of a director and a multiannual framework.</p>
      <p sl="it">In response to this sluggishness and bureaucratic inefficiency, the rapporteur proposes amending the multiannual framework in a minimum number of areas. He urges the Commission and Council to speed up the process of selecting candidates for the post of director so as to facilitate a rapid agreement among the EU institutions, thereby reactivating this vital tool to safeguard citizens’ human rights.</p>
      <p sl="it">I would call upon my fellow Members to support this report, since it represents an initial step towards making the Agency operational.</p>
      <p sl="it">Support for EU human rights policies and their development cannot and must not be subject to considerations and delays of a political and economic nature.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-121" speaker_id="1892" name="Carlos COELHO" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="20-05-1960" birth_place="Lisboa" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">I obviously supported the creation in February 2007 of the European Union Agency for Fundamental Rights as I believe that this Agency could significantly help to increase the coherence and cohesion of EU policy on fundamental rights.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The Agency was officially established on 1 March 2007 but is still waiting for the basic elements so that it can become fully operational, in other words the appointment of its director and the approval of a multiannual framework.</p>
      <p sl="pt">This initiative aims to adopt this multiannual framework, which must guide the Agency’s work over the next five years by defining the thematic areas in which it must act.</p>
      <p sl="pt">I therefore welcome the enormous effort made by the rapporteur, Mr Cashman, to facilitate the negotiations, and I hope, like him, that this encourages the Commission and the Council to conclude both the discussions on this multiannual framework and the process of selecting candidates for the position of director as soon as possible.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The people of Europe will not understand the reason for further delays preventing this Agency for Fundamental Rights from becoming fully operational.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-122" speaker_id="28325" name="Sylwester CHRUSZCZ" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Poland" birth_date="22-08-1972" birth_place="Głogów" p_group="Independence/Democracy Group" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">I am opposed to the creation of a European Fundamental Rights Agency, and therefore I did not support the Multi-Annual Framework for 2007-2012.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I believe that the proposed creation of this agency and its functions are not only a waste of money but also a dangerous political initiative, whose long-term effects will be damaging to the Member States of the Union, The basic tasks assigned to this agency amount to a clear intrusion into the sovereignty of Member States. The agency’s existence cannot be justified. There are already institutions charged with safeguarding democracy and protecting human rights in every European country.</p>
      <p sl="pl">In my view, this agency’s activities will inevitably extend beyond the thematic areas for which it was established. For example, in the course of today’s vote on Amendment 6 to the recitals, the question of defining a human being and establishing the point at which it acquires human rights arose.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I consider this type of action to be an outrageous attempt to covertly impose dangerous ideological notions in the framework of the European Union.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-123" speaker_id="1413" name="Glyn FORD" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="28-01-1950" birth_place="Gloucester" p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">I support this report, despite my opposition and disappointment that the former European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia, set up following the recommendations of the Council of Ministers’ Consultative Committee on Racism and Xenophobia, where I represented the European Parliament, has now been dissolved into a wider European Union Agency for Fundamental Rights.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Monitoring Centre in Vienna did extremely valuable work on promoting best practice in combating racism, xenophobia and anti-Semitism and preventing their rise, as well as reporting on the current state of play across the Union and in applicant countries. The danger is that this will be lost, or at least diluted, in this new Agency. I will watch developments with care.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-124" speaker_id="28183" name="Patrick GAUBERT" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="France" birth_date="06-07-1948" birth_place="Paris" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="fr">The PPE-DE Group’s French delegation welcomes the adoption of the Cashman report on the adoption of a Multiannual Framework for the EU Agency for Fundamental Rights for 2007-2012.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Among other points, the text defines the precise thematic areas of the Agency’s activity to enable it to fulfil its mission and objectives successfully.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The majority of the French delegation, following the group line, rejected the amendments by the Liberals aimed at extending its missions to homophobia and homophobic violence, and to racism against the Roma. They did so not in order to express their opposition to this legitimate and justifiable goal, but because these missions are already covered by the proposal for a decision, which includes in the Agency’s thematic areas the issues of racism, xenophobia and related intolerance, in addition to discrimination based on gender, racial or ethnic origin, religion or belief, disability, age or sexual orientation or against persons belonging to minorities.</p>
      <p sl="fr">We welcome the adoption of this report, which will allow the Agency to become fully operational, thus enabling it to accomplish its task and safeguard the rights of EU citizens.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-125" speaker_id="28194" name="Ambroise GUELLEC" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="France" birth_date="26-03-1941" birth_place="Peumerit" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="fr">The PPE-DE Group’s French delegation welcomes the adoption of the Cashman report on the adoption of a Multiannual Framework for the EU Agency for Fundamental Rights for 2007-2012.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Among other points, the text defines the precise thematic areas of the Agency’s activity to enable it to fulfil its mission and objectives successfully.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The French delegation, following the group line, rejected the amendments by the Liberals aimed at extending its missions to homophobia and homophobic violence, and to racism against the Roma. It did so not in order to express their opposition to this legitimate and justifiable goal, but because these missions are already covered by the proposal for a decision, which includes in the Agency’s thematic areas the issues of racism, xenophobia and related intolerance, in addition to discrimination based on gender, racial or ethnic origin, religion or belief, disability, age or sexual orientation or against persons belonging to minorities.</p>
      <p sl="fr">We welcome the adoption of this report, which will allow the Agency to become fully operational, thus enabling it to accomplish its task and safeguard the rights of EU citizens.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-126" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro GUERREIRO" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="25-02-1966" birth_place="Lisboa" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">Leaving aside the aspects criticised, which we have already had the opportunity to highlight, once the European Union Agency for Fundamental Rights becomes operational in due course, its actual purpose will be clarified.</p>
      <p sl="pt">In the debate on the definition of the objectives and priorities for its Multiannual Framework for 2007-2012, its thematic areas were clearly restricted to the following was clear: racism, xenophobia and related intolerance; discrimination based on sex, racial or ethnic origin, religion or belief, disability or sexual orientation or of persons belonging to minorities; compensation of victims, prevention of crime and related aspects relevant to the security of citizens; protection of children, including the rights of the child; immigration and integration of migrants; asylum; visa and border control; participation in the Union’s democratic functioning; human rights issues relating to the information society; and access to efficient and independent justice.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The European Parliament has added extreme poverty and social exclusion. However, social rights, including the rights of workers, have not been regarded as a priority, even at a time when fundamental social rights are being called into question by the policies promoted by the EU.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-127" speaker_id="38596" name="Elisabeth MORIN-CHARTIER" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="France" birth_date="10-10-1947" birth_place="Ceaux-en-Couhé" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="fr">Like the French delegation in the PPE-DE Group, I welcome the adoption of the Cashman report on the adoption of a Multiannual Framework for the EU Agency for Fundamental Rights for 2007-2012.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Among other points, the text defines the precise thematic areas of the Agency’s activity to enable it to fulfil its mission and objectives successfully.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Like the French delegation and the PPE-DE Group, I rejected the amendments by the Liberals aimed at extending its missions to homophobia and homophobic violence, and to racism against the Roma. In fact, these missions are already covered by the proposal for a decision, which includes in the Agency’s thematic areas the issues of racism, xenophobia and related intolerance, in addition to discrimination based on gender, racial or ethnic origin, religion or belief, disability, age or sexual orientation or against persons belonging to minorities.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I welcome the adoption of this report, which will allow the Agency to become fully operational, thus enabling it to accomplish its task and safeguard the rights of EU citizens.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-129" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Bairbre de Brún and Eva-Britt Svensson" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I voted in favour of the amended proposal because it contains improvements in data protection.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, I do not agree with the increasing move of justice and home affairs issues from the Member States to the EU. For this reason, I voted against the legislative resolution.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-130" speaker_id="1473" name="Gérard DEPREZ" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Belgium" birth_date="13-08-1943" birth_place="Noville-Bastogne" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="BE">
      <p sl="fr">I strongly support the report by our excellent colleague Mr Díaz de Mera.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The transformation of Europol into a Community agency is a request I have always supported.</p>
      <p sl="fr">It means in fact that from now on Europol will be financed by the Community budget, and that the status of Community official will apply to Europol personnel. In both cases, the powers of our Parliament have been considerably enhanced.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Moreover, the Council decision substantially broadens Europol’s scope and capacity for action, which I also support.</p>
      <p sl="fr">In short, making Europol more operational and subjecting it to genuine democratic control is a decision I support unreservedly.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-131" speaker_id="1164" name="Bruno GOLLNISCH" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="France" birth_date="28-01-1950" birth_place="Neuilly-sur-Seine" p_group="Non" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="en">The Council’s wangling has been entirely successfully: transforming the European Police Office, Europol, from its status as an intergovernmental agency financed by the budgets of the Member States into a European Union agency financed by the EU budget, and applying the status of Community official, all on the grounds of technical, not political, requirements.</p>
      <p sl="en">Since Europol’s missions have in fact been extended significantly to encompass areas other than organised crime, the Council feels that the new objectives will be better dealt with at EU level than at Member State level. Thus, in the name of the extremely questionable principle of subsidiarity, the Europeanist logic of systematic elimination of competences of the Member State and deepening of the supranational model is applied.</p>
      <p sl="en">This is exactly the philosophy and the approach of the reforms in the Lisbon Treaty, which European and national leaders as a body wish to impose on the peoples and nations against their will.</p>
      <p sl="en">Europe is no longer listening to its peoples. Worse still, it is disregarding them and lying to them. Now that 26 European countries have already announced they will not ratify this Treaty by referendum, let us hope that the nations and peoples of Europe will be saved by a rejection of this ridiculous text by the Irish, the only people who are allowed to decide for themselves.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-132" speaker_id="23717" name="Genowefa GRABOWSKA" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Poland" birth_date="01-01-1944" birth_place="Przystań" p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">The Member States of the European Union created Europol as an institutional response through which to combat organised crime. We are today debating broadening Europol’s competences and streamlining its operations, 12 years after it was established.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The rapporteur has made an accurate assessment of Europol’s current legal and factual situation. He rightly criticises the overly complicated and lengthy procedure envisaged to change Europol’s status and include it in the Union’s organisational structure. The corrective measures proposed in the report are also worthy of consideration and support.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Earlier attempts to change Europol’s competences show how difficult it is for countries to reach agreement when they are bound by the principle of unanimity. I therefore believe that only when the Treaty of Lisbon is ratified and comes into force in all 27 Member States will we be able to introduce procedural changes and improve this situation, as the Treaty will also reform the decision-making process within the EU.</p>
      <p sl="pl">In addition, bestowing the status of an EU agency on Europol, with all the consequences that involves, including financial, will enable the European Union as a whole to combat organised crime more effectively.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-133" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro GUERREIRO" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="25-02-1966" birth_place="Lisboa" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">As neither the Treaty proposal nor this proposal to adopt by qualified majority decisions on regulations relating to the structure, operations, field of action and tasks of Europol have been ratified, the EU institutions are already tiring of trying to convert the European Police Office into a European agency.</p>
      <p sl="pt">In addition to our fundamental criticism of this process, we are concerned that we are facing:</p>
      <p sl="pt">the possibility that ‘special categories of data concerning racial or ethnic origin, political opinions, religious or philosophical beliefs, party or trade union membership, sexual orientation or health’ will not be excluded from processing;</p>
      <p sl="pt">the failure to adopt safeguards for the protection of personal data processed in the field of police and judicial cooperation at EU level and in relations with third countries, particularly with the US (e.g. air passenger data);</p>
      <p sl="pt">the failure to guarantee access by an individual to his data or even to be aware that his personal data is being processed by Europol;</p>
      <p sl="pt">the failure to clarify the control by national parliaments.</p>
      <p sl="pt">This would be a flagrant breach of citizens’ rights, freedoms and guarantees.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-134" speaker_id="28338" name="Antonio MASIP HIDALGO" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Spain" birth_date="03-05-1946" birth_place="Oviedo" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">I voted for the text agreed by consensus with the contributions of the groups. It is an issue that affects essential cooperation against crime. I must point out, however, as did my colleagues Mr Fava and Mr Moreno, that the lofty goals of the resolution are at odds with the recalcitrant attitude of the rapporteur, Mr Díaz de Mera, who was Director-General of the Spanish Police on 11 March 2004 and who refused to cooperate with the court that presided over the trial on Europe’s largest ever terrorist bombing.</p>
      <p sl="es">Moreover, the rapporteur is one of the major propagators or collaborators of the disgraceful theory that it was not Islamist cells, but ETA terrorists, that were responsible for this massacre. Mr Díaz de Mera and others who described themselves as ‘peones negros’ (black pawns) attempted to mislead international public opinion and, even though their standpoint was in the end not treated as a crime (it was subjected only to a sanction and serious admonishment from the Court), this Parliament should be acquainted with all the facts. Their personal attacks reveal their lack of arguments. Finally, I wish to express my regret that Mr Díaz de Mera did not even have the dignity of his colleague Jaime Mayor, who at least removed his name from the terrorism text.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-135" speaker_id="28457" name="Luca ROMAGNOLI" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Italy" birth_date="12-09-1961" birth_place="Roma" p_group="Non" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I wish to vote in favour of the Díaz de Mera García Consuegra report on the establishment of the European Police Office (Europol). Changing circumstances within the European Union, new forms of criminal activity and new terrorist threats mean that the existing body is in need of reorganisation. I nevertheless feel that certain points should be clarified.</p>
      <p sl="it">The transformation of Europol into an EU agency must not place an additional financial burden on Member States; above all, it must not consume any of the already insufficient state resources earmarked for national police forces. On the contrary, the investigative authorities and those responsible for law and order must be better looked after and reinforced. Indeed, Europol's activities must consist of supporting and coordinating the fundamental, irreplaceable work of the various Member States' police forces. I am therefore pleased that the proposal contains provisions for the coordination, organisation and conduct of investigations and operational activities in conjunction with the Member States' competent authorities or by joint investigative teams.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-137" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro GUERREIRO" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="25-02-1966" birth_place="Lisboa" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">This own-initiative report reveals the true ambitions of the ‘European Neighbourhood Policy’, specifically for the South Caucasus.</p>
      <p sl="pt">These are to set out the geostrategic agenda in its political, economic and military aspects, in other words the EU’s plan for intervention in this neuralgic area, with increased pressure being put on China and Russia.</p>
      <p sl="pt">This will result in more interference in, and manipulation of, the conflicts arising from the dismantling of the USSR, with the aim of ensuring that the EU’s major powers and financial/economic groups gain control over this region, with the inter-capitalist rivalries also being clearly evident.</p>
      <p sl="pt">You only have to look at the ‘recommendations’, such as the incentive to conclude free trade agreements and the pursuit of further liberalisation or the clear appeal for interference through ‘support’ for the action of ‘civil society’, ensuring that ‘the [Community!] funds are distributed … without … state interference’.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The approach to the energy issue is particularly significant as it highlights the importance of energy brokers who can bypass Russia and the control over energy infrastructures and sources.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Finally, we note the incoherence between ‘its unconditional support for the territorial integrity and inviolability of the internationally recognised borders of Georgia’ and the appeal to the principles of the United Nations Charter, when this is not being done for Serbia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-139" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro GUERREIRO" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="25-02-1966" birth_place="Lisboa" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">This is another own-initiative report which assumes the same logic as the report on the Southern Caucasus and the ‘European Neighbourhood Policy’: in other words, interference and pressure to guarantee access to (and control over) markets (particularly energy markets) and further liberalisation.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The report argues for the promotion of ‘market economy reforms’, encouraging ‘harmonisation and further liberalisation measures’ and supporting ‘the creation of a free trade area in accordance with WTO principles’. This is a process in which the EU allegedly has ‘a leading role to play’ in ‘encouraging the region to take the necessary steps’.</p>
      <p sl="pt">At the same time the report ‘stresses the crucial importance of establishing and developing good neighbourly relations among the countries of the Black Sea region and with their neighbours, based on mutual respect, territorial integrity, non-interference in each others’ internal affairs and the prohibition of the use of force or threats to use force, as fundamental principles for fostering regional cooperation’ and yet it argues for the promotion of ‘European values’, ‘irrespective of the degree of willingness shown by partner governments’. This is a clear contradiction/incoherence between what is recommended (for others) and what is done. The EU is demanding that others respect what it itself does not respect. What cynicism.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-141" speaker_id="4242" name="Karin SCHEELE" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Austria" birth_date="22-07-1968" birth_place="Baden" p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="de">Until a short while ago Kenya was a holiday paradise for many people. Visitors were well shielded from the massive corruption and terrible poverty in which a large majority of the population have to live. Since the events of late December and the fraudulent presidential elections, Kenya and its political problems have suddenly been on everyone’s lips.</p>
      <p sl="de">While the parliamentary elections were generally regarded as successful by the official observers, doubts were raised as to the accuracy of the results of the presidential election. In tabling today’s motion for a resolution on Kenya, we are once again condemning the widespread irregularities and the conduct of the incumbent President Kibaki, who in rejecting the offer made by President John Kufuor to help resolve the crisis has seriously undermined the mediation efforts. We call on Kenya’s political leaders to do everything in their power to prevent further violence in the country and to ensure respect for human rights. During the debate on this subject we again discussed and examined the question of the effectiveness of direct budgetary aid. This topic, like that of Kenya, is one that will continue to occupy us in the months ahead.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-142" speaker_id="31123" name="Pedro GUERREIRO" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="25-02-1966" birth_place="Lisboa" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">This explanation of vote is intended to point out that, by recognising the mediation efforts begun by neighbouring countries, by the Southern African Development Community and by the African Union, we believe that the Kenyan people will be able to find and define their own path. It is up to the Kenyan people themselves to find the solutions to overcome the current situation in their country.</p>
      <p sl="pt">As a result, we regard as negative any attempt by the EU to interfere, as indicated and proposed in the resolution, particularly bearing in mind the objectives proclaimed by the EU in its ‘Strategy for Africa’ and the framework of inter-imperialist cooperation/rivalry concerning this continent that is also clearly evident and that is so deeply felt in this region.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Finally, I must highlight the omission from the resolution of a reference to the severe and deteriorating socio-economic situation in this country – which is at the root of the expression of popular discontent manifested in the elections – and the deep responsibility for this situation of the neo-liberal policies promoted, in particular, by the international financial institutions, major capitalist powers and their transnational companies.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-143" speaker_id="28352" name="Zuzana ROITHOVÁ" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Czechia" birth_date="30-01-1953" birth_place="Praha" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="CZ">
      <p sl="cs">I fully support our resolution on the situation in Kenya, which is based on an up-to-date investigation by the EU observer mission in Kenya at the start of the year.</p>
      <p sl="cs">We must ensure that the authorities in Kenya investigate, without delay, the circumstances surrounding the elections and prevent further violence. We must insist on the return of live broadcasting and on the adherence to basic human rights and the rights laid down by the African Charter. However, this resolution detract from the responsibility of the European Commission to resolve the issue of the transfer of € 400 million to the Congolese Government. I think that we shall be returning to this issue soon.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-145" speaker_id="28310" name="Edite ESTRELA" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="28-10-1949" birth_place="Belver" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">I voted in favour of paragraph 20 of the report on the role of women in industry because it is essential that the Commission carries out a study into the negative consequences of long working hours on private, family and social life, such as children spending a lot of time alone, left to their own devices, which often leads to failure at school and crime. The Member States must improve monitoring of undertakings that force their employees to remain at work beyond the statutory working hours and they must impose harsh penalties on these undertakings.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-146" speaker_id="4466" name="Ilda FIGUEIREDO" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="30-10-1948" birth_place="Troviscal - O. Bairro" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left - Vice" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">The European Parliament today adopted my report on the role of women in industry. This is very positive, although I do regret certain minor amendments.</p>
      <p sl="pt">However, the report recognises the important role of women in industry and it calls on the Commission and Member States to take the necessary measures, including effective monitoring, to combat stereotyping and discrimination, particularly wage discrimination. This situation is even more serious when you consider that women’s wages are around 30% lower than men’s wages in industry, whereas the average for other sectors is 15%, despite the Equal Pay Directive having been around for more than 30 years.</p>
      <p sl="pt">It stresses the importance of collective bargaining in the fight to abolish discrimination against women, in particular with regard to access to employment, wages, working conditions, careers and professional training.</p>
      <p sl="pt">It stresses the importance of Community programmes that encourage the creation of trademarks, the protection of products’ designation of origin and the external promotion of Community products from industrial sectors where women predominate.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Finally, it is very important to ensure recognition of the right of female and male workers to take part in restructuring processes affecting industrial undertakings, by guaranteeing their structures, in particular the European Works Councils, full access to information and the possibility of decisive intervention, including the right of veto.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-147" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Hélène Goudin and Nils Lundgren" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="sv">This report deals with a number of aspects which, in themselves, are important but in respect of which the Member States retain the power to act and the responsibility to develop and improve their legislation. The gender ratio on company boards, the development of equality plans in large companies and the proportion of female members of company boards are not questions which are best and most effectively regulated at EU level. We have thus voted against the report in question.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-148" speaker_id="23717" name="Genowefa GRABOWSKA" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Poland" birth_date="01-01-1944" birth_place="Przystań" p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Clearly, European industry is undergoing far-reaching change. It is therefore hard not to recognise its strategic importance for the development of all Member States of the European Union and their citizens, regardless of gender.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The role of women employed in European industry and the opportunities available to them depend not only on a country’s level of economic development, but also on traditions regarding acceptance of equal opportunities and respect for human rights regulations. There is large-scale participation of women in industry and they make a substantial contribution in almost all sectors. Nonetheless, one has to agree with the rapporteur that the role of women in industries involving cutting-edge technologies, such as the aeronautical industry or the chemical industry, is very inadequate.</p>
      <p sl="pl">It is entirely appropriate, therefore, that the report highlights this aspect and focuses quite rightly on gender issues. The report also emphasises that women’s involvement in industry cannot be limited to work in sectors that do not require qualifications, where women are the first to suffer when restructuring takes place.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The rapporteur calls for support, especially for SMEs, to enable the relatively high level of female employment to be retained, particularly in the case of women who find themselves in an unfortunate professional situation. This suggestion is worthy of support, as is the entire report, if only for this reason.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-999" speaker_id="28116" name="Marian HARKIN" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Ireland" birth_date="26-11-1953" birth_place="Sligo" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="IE">
      <p sl="en">I support paragraph 33 because such proactive measures need to be taken - at least on an interim basis to ensure participation of women in the decision-making process at all levels. In addition to this I strongly support paragraph 20 as there is a real need for a full investigation into the impact that long working hours have on health, both physical and mental, as well as on family life. If we are to promote a work life balance and family friendly policies then we need such a study.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-149" speaker_id="28355" name="Mieczysław Edmund JANOWSKI" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Poland" birth_date="16-11-1947" birth_place="Zduńska Wola" p_group="Union for Europe of the Nations Group" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Human rights are the foundation of democracy. These rights include the very important principle of equality between women and men, allowing of course for the circumstances arising out of the biological differences between them. One aspect of this issue concerns the employment and role of women in industry. It is simply impossible to apply an arithmetical division into equal halves.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Above all, what we are concerned with is equality of opportunity, which is conditional on access to education and professional training in technical and economic subjects. Another very important issue is providing assistance to mothers bringing up children and ensuring they are not discriminated against in the workplace. It is essential to introduce flexible provisions regarding pensions for women bringing up children. The period of so-called parental leave must be credited in full and added to the period considered as time in employment under pension rules.</p>
      <p sl="pl">In many of our countries women are still being paid significantly less than men for work of equal quality and quantity. There can be no justification for creating obstacles impeding women from undertaking managerial and supervisory roles on company boards of directors or boards of trustees. Action is needed to do away with stereotypes in this regard. The report tabled represents a step in that direction, which is why I voted in favour of it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-150" speaker_id="1186" name="Astrid LULLING" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Luxembourg" birth_date="11-06-1929" birth_place="Schifflange" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="LU">
      <p sl="fr">In many recitals and paragraphs of this extremely long resolution, we are stating the obvious. We are calling for measures that were, fortunately, taken some time ago. It is true that certain directives on equal treatment and opportunities between women and men have been poorly applied, but if discrimination still remains in the areas covered by this set of measures, who is at fault? All these directives contain appeal mechanisms. Women who have experienced discrimination need only go to court, where they will win their case, as demonstrated in many cases in my country, thankfully.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Unfortunately, this report contains a number of incongruous claims that bear no relation to the role of women in industry.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Asking for a 40% quota of female representation on company boards is interference contrary to the principle of subsidiarity in issues reserved for Member States.</p>
      <p sl="fr">It is not for us to call for the ‘monitoring’ of company delocalisation. It is utopian to demand ‘more choice in the workplace’. If my company is based in the city of Luxembourg and has no other branches, I cannot put in a request to work in Schifflange where I live.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I voted for this report in accordance with these observations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-151" speaker_id="28352" name="Zuzana ROITHOVÁ" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Czechia" birth_date="30-01-1953" birth_place="Praha" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="CZ">
      <p sl="cs">I agree with many of the ideas in the report on women in industry. However, I am not happy that specific attention was not given to the regional unemployment among women who lost their jobs in European textile factories at the time when this was happening. I also think that no amount of quotas for the employment of women will solve the situation.</p>
      <p sl="cs">My second comment concerns the balanced division of time between work and family. This affects women as well as men. I do not think that the solution lies in resolutions. It lies in the implementation of the European concept of flexicurity. Holland is one example where an excellent legislative framework has been developed for part-time work. The result has been reduced unemployment, as well as giving men and women more time for family life. An effective use of shorter working hours also shows that it does not have to lead to a reduction in income.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-152" speaker_id="4274" name="Olle SCHMIDT" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Sweden" birth_date="22-07-1949" birth_place="Skärv" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="SE">
      <p sl="sv">As a liberal and a member of the Liberal Party of Sweden, Folkpartiet , I always find reports from Parliament on equality somewhat tricky. The Swedish Liberal Party has over the years taken the view that the best way to proceed in these matters is on a voluntary basis but we also realise that this is not always enough. Sweden’s positive engagement in this field has made us known as one of the world’s most equal countries. So do we not want to disseminate our successes across the EU?</p>
      <p sl="sv">Of course we do! The question is merely by what methods. In the report in question I felt obliged to vote against a number of paragraphs whose spirit I support but whose scope and approach seem dubious. I think that both equality plans and measurable targets may be important tools for enterprises. On the other hand, I do not believe it is something that the EU should concern itself with as a primary issue. The same applies to the establishment of an EU-sponsored ‘methodology for analysing exactly what jobs entail’ that will ‘guarantee’ equal pay. The Global Adjustment Fund, about which I had severe misgivings from the beginning, also should not take special account of gender – that would be to perpetrate a double injustice.</p>
      <p sl="sv">One cannot expect every report to be written as though one had drafted it oneself, but there is much to find fault with here. Yet the subject is so important that, in the end, I voted in favour of it as a whole.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-153" speaker_id="28382" name="Andrzej Jan SZEJNA" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Poland" birth_date="28-04-1973" birth_place="Końskie" p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">I voted in favour of the report by Mrs Figueiredo on the role of women in industry. I should like to congratulate the rapporteur on a very good and thorough report.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The issue of equal rights for men and women is a very important one and we must continue to give it as much attention as possible, since the European Union is based on the principle of non-discrimination. We should give priority to tackling all indications of failure to comply with this principle. This is particularly necessary because the nature of industry is changing as we strive to create a knowledge-based society. The sectors in which women were traditionally employed are linked to the processing industry, whereas the newest sectors of industry are based on the development of the latest technologies, such as information and communication technologies. We should make every effort to ensure that the principle of equal opportunity is complied with in these new sectors.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-155" speaker_id="1073" name="Cristiana MUSCARDINI" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Italy" birth_date="06-11-1948" birth_place="Cannobio " p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="it">The resolution on which we are about to vote cannot fail to receive the support and vote of the UEN Group. We hope that there will soon be better regulation of the Internet aimed at protecting children and taking more effective measures against providers that host child pornography websites. Immediate action must be taken by all EU Member States to close down illegal sites, by means of better coordination among the police forces responsible.</p>
      <p sl="it">In addition, we hope that it will be possible to tackle the sensitive issue of information exchanged by terrorist organisations thanks to the Internet, and that this matter might be the subject of future forums. There can be no freedom without rules and, most importantly, the Internet cannot and must not be an area of freedom for those who commit criminal acts and preach hatred and intolerance. An emergency must be tackled by means of decisive, urgent measures and not improvised ones. The fight against terrorism and hatred between peoples must be a rule and a goal of the European Union and all free, democratic countries.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem16" title="9. Corrections to votes and voting intentions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem17" title="10. Approval of Minutes of previous sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem18" title="11. Debates on cases of breaches of human rights, democracy and the rule of law"/>
  <section id="creitem19" title="11.1. Arrest of Chinese dissident Hu Jia (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-162" speaker_id="4482" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Rodi KRATSA-TSAGAROPOULOU" nationality="Greece" birth_date="14-11-1952" birth_place="Zakynthos" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the debate on five motions for resolutions on the arrest of the Chinese dissident Hu Jia .</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-163" speaker_id="28239" name="Milan HORÁČEK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Germany" birth_date="30-10-1946" birth_place="Ullersdorf Velké Losiny" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, our Group has nominated Hu Jia and his wife, Zeng Jinyan, for the Sakharov Prize. Because the couple are under house arrest they used a webcam link to take part in a hearing of the European Parliament on the human rights situation in China. The renewed arrest of Hu Jia has only served to demonstrate something that he himself warned of. Does China by its action wish to show its contempt for the opinion of the European Parliament?</p>
      <p sl="de">Human rights must be firmly enshrined as an issue that cuts across all the relations that exist between the EU and China. We too must act in a coherent and consistent way and should not simply sacrifice our values on the altar of good economic relations.</p>
      <p sl="de">We are therefore calling on the Council and the Commission not just to take up a position for Hu Jia but also to use the next EU-China summit to call for a commitment to human rights.</p>
      <p sl="de">China has to put a stop to the systematic intimidation of human rights activists. If China does not change its conduct we will again need to raise the issue of our participation in the Olympic Games. Moreover, Russia is set to host the next Winter Olympics and that country also has a poor record when it comes to human rights.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-164" speaker_id="4508" name="Erik MEIJER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Netherlands" birth_date="05-12-1944" birth_place="Amsterdam" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="NL">
      <p sl="nl">Madam President, the problem of human rights in China keeps coming up in these urgent debates, always with good reason. China’s economic growth and increased international standing have still not resulted in any real difference in the approach to civil liberties, abuse of power by the authorities, room for opposition and independence of the judiciary.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Harsh penalties are still being imposed, including frequent use of the death penalty. China is not the only country that sentences people to death and executes them, but it is the champion in this. The only progress that we have seen is that more care is now taken to be certain of the perpetrator’s guilt before the death penalty is carried out, so fewer people are being put to death who later turn out to be innocent.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Meanwhile, the international focus on the three great dramas in China has to a large extent disappeared. The bloodbath in Tiananmen Square in 1989, the persecution of the supporters of the Falun Gong movement and the changing of the composition of the populations of Tibet and East Turkestan are being given less and less attention.</p>
      <p sl="nl">All the attention is now going to economic growth, export opportunities to China, opportunities for cheap imports from China, the growing role of China in Africa and the coming Olympic Games in China. Under these circumstances the pressure to improve the human rights situation in China is dwindling. The Olympic Games have become an argument for pulling down residential areas and driving the residents away. Chinese ambassadors say that their national honour is violated when this is criticised from abroad.</p>
      <p sl="nl">The coming Olympic Games could have been an occasion for improvement. As things look at the moment, they will be good for tourism and good for the completion of major public works, but not good for improving human rights. In the Netherlands, meanwhile, a debate has started about the possibility of boycotting these Olympic Games.</p>
      <p sl="nl">A resolution about a single arrested human rights activist, Hu Jia, is necessary but it is not enough. The most important factor in the relations between Europe and China should not be economic self-interest but our concern about human rights in China.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-165" speaker_id="24087" name="Marcin LIBICKI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Poland" birth_date="02-02-1939" birth_place="Poznań" p_group="Union for Europe of the Nations Group" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">I agree with Mr Meyer who said just now that we should boycott the Olympic Games because of the persecution to which the Chinese people are subject in China. Indeed, it is not only the Chinese who are constantly being persecuted in that country. The persecution of the Tibetan people and other national minorities has often been raised in this House. We are today referring to the illegal detention and persecution of an activist in the cause of freedom, a person who is fighting for freedom in China, namely the politician Hu Jia. His wife and family have shared his fate.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Ladies and gentlemen, I can remember when the Olympic Games hosted by the Soviet Union were boycotted several decades ago. That action contributed to the fall of the Communist regime. We cannot now allow ourselves to be dazzled by China's economic success. Congratulations are due to China on the latter, but we must not turn a blind eye to the persecution of so many people and the violation of their fundamental rights. As I mentioned earlier, it is not only the Chinese who are affected, but also other residents of what is known as China. After all, Tibet, whose cause has repeatedly been raised in this House, is not China. I appeal for a boycott of the Olympic Games.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-166" speaker_id="1922" name="Thomas MANN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Germany" birth_date="28-01-1946" birth_place="Naumburg/Saale" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, seven months before the start of the Olympic Games, China is demonstrating how little account it takes of human rights. The hope that the IOC decision would help improve things in the Middle Kingdom has been an illusion.</p>
      <p sl="de">In October and November 2007 the State Security Services abducted and maltreated the attorneys Gao Zhisheng and Li Heping. At the end of December they imprisoned the human rights activist and cyber dissident Hu Jia on the charge that he had used the Internet to incite subversion of State power.</p>
      <p sl="de">On 10 October Hu Jia took part in a press conference on human rights, which was held at the European Parliament in Brussels. He was linked to us live from China by telephone. We must thank him for this courageous act. Last year he and his wife Zeng Jinyan were nominated by the European Parliament for the Sakharov Prize. In his Internet blog he reports on political prisoners and on the victims of land confiscations for the forthcoming Olympics.</p>
      <p sl="de">In a letter he thanked Chancellor Angela Merkel for having received the Dalai Lama. This clearly was too much for official China. In an open letter some 57 Chinese intellectuals called for the release of Hu Jia. Our President, Hans-Gert Pöttering, endorsed this. It is a slap in the face when human rights activists are arrested, especially because of their contact with the European Parliament. We have to use all diplomatic means at our disposal to ensure that he is released from prison immediately.</p>
      <p sl="de">China is promising the world the best Olympic Games ever seen. The price for this should not be censorship or contempt for the rule of law.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-167" speaker_id="28280" name="Filip KACZMAREK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group" nationality="Poland" birth_date="22-11-1966" birth_place="Poznań" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, back in 2001 when it was decided that Beijing would host the Olympic Games, many of us believed that despite the controversy surrounding it, this decision would help to bring about political change in Communist China. We felt that the host country would be moved to put an end to widespread violations of human rights and increase the scope of fundamental freedoms on its territory. I agree with Mr Mann that with 7 months to go before the Games open, all those hopes have proved in vain. The opposite is actually the case: the rule of terror in China has intensified.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Human rights defenders like Hu Jia and his wife are imprisoned and held illegally without trial in unknown locations, harassed, terrorised and denied the right of defence. The Chinese authorities are sending out a different signal to the world, indicating that there is no democracy or openness in their country. At the same time, the Chinese Olympic Committee has determined that the Games' main slogan will be 'One world, one dream'. They maintain that this dream consists of a common aspiration to flourish and live in peace. One is left wondering what kind of peace the Chinese have in mind and whether they really understand what the Olympic Games are all about.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-168" speaker_id="28392" name="Józef PINIOR" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PSE Group" nationality="Poland" birth_date="09-03-1955" birth_place="Rybnik" p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the Chinese activist Mr Hu Jia was arrested two days after Christmas during the afternoon at his home. It is very sad news, particularly because China, a great country, a great global player in the contemporary world, is the organiser of the Olympic Games this year.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Parliament and all the European Union must stress that China must challenge six issues relating to human rights: China’s failure to fully implement new regulations allowing greater press freedom; China’s superficial commitments to upholding the rule of law; limited Chinese support for international efforts to promote civilian protection in Darfur, Sudan; limited Chinese support for international efforts to promote human rights in Burma; the absence of transparency in Chinese aid to abusive governments; and, in particular, the release from prison of all political prisoners in China.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-169" speaker_id="39022" name="Ewa TOMASZEWSKA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the UEN Group" nationality="Poland" birth_date="14-04-1947" birth_place="Płock" p_group="Union for Europe of the Nations Group" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, Hu Jia and Zeng Jinyan have come to symbolise for us the fight for freedom of expression and human rights in China. Both husband and wife have been nominated by this House for the Sakharov Prize in recognition of their activities, whilst they are repressed in their own country because of those same activities. Hu Jia was arrested on 2 January.</p>
      <p sl="pl">In the 1980s, during the period of martial law in Poland, transparency served to protect against the most drastic forms of repression. The press and radio stations on the other side of the Iron Curtain named those imprisoned, which allowed us to hope we would be safe. I myself experienced what it meant to be helped in this way by people abroad who were not indifferent to our plight. That is why it is now so very important for me to ensure that our voice, the voice of the European Parliament, the voice of hundreds of Members from different European countries should be heard in China. The Chinese authorities must hear our appeal and stop repressing Hu Jia and the many other victims of persecution.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-170" speaker_id="28409" name="Raül ROMEVA i RUEDA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group" nationality="Spain" birth_date="12-03-1971" birth_place="Madrid" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance - Vice" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, the Olympic Games ought to be perceived by both the Chinese authorities and the rest of the world as a chance for China to change its international image, which has been particularly affected by continuous breaches of human rights, affecting very different groups, for very different reasons.</p>
      <p sl="es">The arrest of Hu Jia, and many others, show that China is not taking up this opportunity as it should. It also serves once again as a reminder to those who saw China as a country that was prepared and sufficiently open-minded to organise an international event supposedly focusing on solidarity such as the Olympic Games.</p>
      <p sl="es">China still has time to change that image, but to do this it must take issues such as freedom of expression and freedom of association more seriously, and put an end to its obsession with arresting, punishing and convicting Chinese men and women accused of an offence as difficult to justify as incitement to subvert state power.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-171" speaker_id="28119" name="Kathy SINNOTT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the IND/DEM Group" nationality="Ireland" birth_date="29-09-1950" birth_place="Chicago " p_group="Independence/Democracy Group" m_state="IE">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, every Olympics draws our attention to the preservation of human dignity as stated in the Olympic Charter. The 2008 Beijing Olympics will specifically draw our attention to that preservation – or otherwise – in China. Hopefully, this will bring pressure on the Chinese Government to rethink actions like the arrest of Hu Jia. It is an opportunity for the country to improve its poor record in this area.</p>
      <p sl="de">Instead, the Chinese Government seems determined to sweep human rights abuses under the rug, by arresting activists and protestors. Of concern is the purchase of Western high-tech security equipment by the Chinese authorities, obviously intended to step up security during the games. My concern is twofold. I fear that such security equipment will be used against the Chinese people this summer, and that it will remain in misuse after the summer. We must either use the Olympics to promote human rights in China, or boycott them, and one thing we cannot do is have a big celebration of China if human rights continue to be so flagrantly disregarded.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-172" speaker_id="38603" name="Desislav CHUKOLOV" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Bulgaria" birth_date="22-12-1974" birth_place="Ruse" p_group="Identity, Tradition and Sovereignty Group" m_state="BG">
      <p sl="bg">Colleagues, during the 20th century millions of people all over the world fell victims to communism. Regrettably, this extremely pernicious, misanthropic and mostly anti-Christian ideology continues to take its victims to this day and to have its representatives. Even here in this Chamber. I will give you an example to illustrate and make things somewhat clearer.</p>
      <p sl="bg">Currently Hu Jia is under house arrest in China because there are a sufficient number of people there who believe that he is a proponent of their ideas. This is what makes his dangerous for the Chinese regime. Here, at the European Parliament, thank God, there is a sufficient number of Members elected by millions of citizens to represent their views, yet the powers that be in this European Union, which many compare to a ‘pyramid’, have their own priorities and a referendum on the Lisbon Treaty is not among those priorities.</p>
      <p sl="bg">This makes us, those Members, just as dangerous as Hu Jia is for the Chinese regime. We are not placed under house arrest but Mr. Pöttering, if he is honest and open enough, would admit that he might go that far. However, I assure him that an honourable representation of our voters counts more than that prospect. Thank you.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-173" speaker_id="28424" name="Tunne KELAM" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Estonia" birth_date="10-07-1936" birth_place="Taheva" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="EE">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the case of Mr Hu Jia and his wife, unfortunately, is not an isolated one.</p>
      <p sl="en">In order to have the privilege to host this year’s Olympic Games in Beijing, the Chinese Government undertook additional commitments to meet internationally recognised human rights standards. Contrary to these expectations, Beijing sees the Olympic Games as a justification for increasing repression against human rights activists. So, by systematically violating its own commitments, the Chinese Government has demonstrated that it does not intend to respect the core values of the Olympic tradition. In fact, it is about to lose its credibility.</p>
      <p sl="en">Therefore, the democratic states cannot limit their reaction to mere complaints. If the Chinese authorities do not make credible changes to the situation, then the democratic participants in the Games risk their own credibility with regard to the values they advocate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-174" speaker_id="28377" name="Lidia Joanna GERINGER de OEDENBERG" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="12-09-1957" birth_place="Wrocław" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, in 2001 the Vice-President of the Beijing Organising Committee for the Games of the XXIX Olympiad, Liu Jingmin, stated that awarding the Olympic Games to Beijing would help to promote the development of human rights. In recent months, however, the Chinese authorities have been allowing themselves to violate freedom of expression more frequently than usual. They have also repressed journalists and activists. The arrest of Hu Jia, a leading human rights activist who was nominated for the Sakharov Prize in 2007 sent shock waves through society. Hu Jia was arrested on the pretext that he had been inciting others to overthrow the national government. He is still being denied the right to a lawyer and to medical care.</p>
      <p sl="pl">China must be forced to comply with international standards in human rights and to respect those rights. It must also put an end to exploitation of the Games as an excuse for the illegal detention of journalists and dissidents. We should remind the Chinese authorities of the idea inspiring the Olympic movement, namely linking sport with a vision of a peaceful society and the preservation of human dignity. At the same time we should call for the immediate release of Hu Jia and of all the other activists detained without trial, so that they can return to their families and access essential medical care.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-175" speaker_id="28300" name="Zbigniew ZALESKI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="29-04-1947" birth_place="Rogoziniec" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, I simply wished to establish whether the ‘catch-the-eye’ strategy also works here. If so, I wished to state briefly that when in China one cannot detect any obvious signs of how the control system operates, but it does. The citizens feel strongly bound up in the oppressive regime imposed by the system. We believe we are called to make the rest of the world aware of the situation, as other Members have already stated. That is the only weapon at our disposal. We can respect the economic development achieved in China, but hardly anywhere else in the world have people become so permeated by fear and self-censorship. I am therefore full of admiration for those courageous individuals in China who are brave enough to risk their careers, their freedom and their very lives to draw attention to the situation. It is our moral duty to stand shoulder to shoulder with them. There is no other solution, no other way forward.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-176" speaker_id="28372" name="Ryszard CZARNECKI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="25-01-1963" birth_place="Londyn " m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, further to the comments of my fellow Member from Poland, I should like to pose the following question to Commissioner Kuneva, taking advantage of her presence in the House. Against the background of the last few years, can we really say that genuine respect for human rights is on the increase in the People's Republic of China? Have the Games due to take place this July in Beijing really meant that Chinese dissidents can now feel more secure, and that relations with Taiwan are on a more civilised footing? Has free access to the Internet increased over the last two or three years? I would be grateful for the Commissioner's reply. After all, the Bible tells us: ‘Ask and ye shall receive’.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-177" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Meglena Kuneva" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, only a month ago my colleague, Commissioner Ferrero-Waldner, expressed in this Chamber the Commission’s deep concern at the continuous and systematic repression of human rights’ defenders in China. The Commission was, therefore, all the more concerned to learn about Mr Hu Jia’s arbitrary detention and recalls that he has been subjected to repeated acts of harassment in the past due to human rights activities.</p>
      <p sl="en">We also express our concern for Mr Hu Jia’s health. He suffers from hepatitis B and must take daily medication. It is not clear whether daily access to the medical treatment he needs is guaranteed and whether he can count on doctors’ assistance during his detention in the Beijing Municipal Detention Centre in Dougezhuang.</p>
      <p sl="en">In the Commission’s view, the detention of Mr Hu Jia places an obligation on the EU to act in a firm manner because of the clear inference that he was arrested as a consequence of speaking freely and honestly about the repression of human rights defenders via a telephone link to a meeting of the European Parliament’s Subcommittee on Human Rights in November 2007.</p>
      <p sl="en">As such, it has echoes of the case of Cao Dong, a Falun Gong petitioner, who was arrested and is still in prison after meeting the Vice-President of the European Parliament in Beijing in May 2006. The detention of Mr Hu Jia also calls for a reaction from the EU as an international actor for the protection of human rights defenders. Yesterday the EU troika carried out a firm démarche to the Chinese authorities asking for his immediate release. We sincerely hope that the Chinese authorities will understand that the issue of human rights defenders has an important impact on China’s standing with the European public and will act accordingly.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to reassure this Chamber that the EU will monitor very closely the evolution of Mr Hu Jia’s case.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission would like to use this opportunity to urge again the Chinese Government to permit expressions of all forms of opinion. This is an important factor in how the international public views China, especially this year, when the eyes of the world will be on China in the build-up to the Olympic Games. We are convinced that a far more stable society can be achieved by allowing freedom of expression.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me close by saying that the Commission will intensify its efforts to seek an improvement of the overall human rights situation in China. In this respect, we will continue to play an instrumental role within the troika in preparing the EU-China human rights dialogue and seminar so that discussions continue to become more target-focussed.</p>
      <p sl="en">Despite the slow progress in the human rights situation in China, we firmly believe that the EU-China human rights dialogue remains one of the most effective ways of engaging China in frank and detailed discussions with a view to achieving human rights reforms on the ground.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-178" speaker_id="4482" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Rodi KRATSA-TSAGAROPOULOU" nationality="Greece" birth_date="14-11-1952" birth_place="Zakynthos" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place at the end of the debate.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem20" title="11.2. Situation in the Democratic Republic of Congo and rape as a war crime (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-180" speaker_id="4482" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Rodi KRATSA-TSAGAROPOULOU" nationality="Greece" birth_date="14-11-1952" birth_place="Zakynthos" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the debate on six motions for resolutions on the situation in the Democratic Republic of Congo and rape as a war crime .</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-181" speaker_id="28409" name="Raül ROMEVA i RUEDA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Spain" birth_date="12-03-1971" birth_place="Madrid" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance - Vice" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">Madam President, sexual violence and rape in particular as a weapon of war is not, regrettably, a new issue.</p>
      <p sl="es">It is no minor issue that Articles 7 and 8 of the 1998 Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court provide that rape, sexual slavery, enforced prostitution, forced pregnancy, enforced sterilisation or any other form of sexual violence are to be treated as crimes against humanity and war crimes, and will equal, in terms of treatment and persecution, torture or serious war crimes, whether or not they are committed during an armed conflict.</p>
      <p sl="es">The war in the Democratic Republic of the Congo shows to what extent this issue merits much more attention than has been paid to date. There have been tens of thousands of reports of rape or sexual assault annually in the region. Many of these incidents, moreover, take place at camps for displaced persons or refugees, and are frequently perpetrated by government troops, rebel groups or other forces.</p>
      <p sl="es">I thus consider it extremely important that this Parliament not only condemn these practices, but that it urge the authorities in the Democratic Republic of the Congo to put an immediate stop to these practices, investigate, bring them to trial and secure convictions, and guarantee protection for the victims, witnesses and family members.</p>
      <p sl="es">We must also remind our own institutions that United Nations Security Council Resolution 1325 emphasises the responsibility of Member States to put an end to impunity, and pursue those responsible for crimes against humanity and war crimes, including crimes relating to sexual violence or other kinds of specific violence against women.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-182" speaker_id="4508" name="Erik MEIJER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Netherlands" birth_date="05-12-1944" birth_place="Amsterdam" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="NL">
      <p sl="nl">Madam President, European states brought tribes together in colonies in Africa that did not have good relations with each other, and divided other tribes by drawing boundaries right through the middle of their lands. The Democratic Republic of Congo, an enormous territory with a multitude of racial groups, was not given the opportunity to grow into independence by gradually building up self-rule during the Belgian colonisation before 1960. There was no preparation for decolonisation: it suddenly became inevitable after England and France had granted independence to their smaller neighbouring colonies at the end of the 1950s, partly as a consequence of the wars of liberation in Morocco, Tunisia, Algeria and Kenya.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Since then the Congo has been a permanent war zone. The early years were dominated by the conflict between Kasavubu from the west, Lumumba from the north-east and Tshombe in the south-east. They each represented different ideologies and interests but, more importantly, they were popular with limited sections of the Congolese population.</p>
      <p sl="nl">The harsh military dictatorship of the profiteer Mobutu kept the country united for years in apparent peace, but the differences were never bridged. The most recent elections also failed to produce unity or good cooperation. The country remains a conflict zone with flexible borders, where, just as in the 1960s, it is about the demarcation of ethnic territories and control of mining areas. Foreign companies have benefited from this. The conflict now seems to be about which group among this multitude of tribal groups will dominate the others. As things are now, the future of the Congo seems to be without prospects.</p>
      <p sl="nl">The atrocities to which the resolution refers, including the general lawlessness and frequent rape of women are all connected with this chaos. The 2006 law against sexual violence will not solve that problem, as long as the conflict continues and there are so many people without a permanent place to live.</p>
      <p sl="nl">The resolution rightly makes reference to the role of government representatives, peace forces, aid organisations; their people should do everything they can to prevent such atrocities without becoming drawn into them themselves. Recognition of rape, forced pregnancy, sexual exploitation and other forms of sexual violence as war crimes by the European Union and the United Nations is a prerequisite, but removing the breeding ground for this violence will have to happen on the ground.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-183" speaker_id="28372" name="Ryszard CZARNECKI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Poland" birth_date="25-01-1963" birth_place="Londyn " m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, I was in the Democratic Republic of Congo only three weeks ago, so my knowledge of the situation has not been gained exclusively from documents although the latter are very important.</p>
      <p sl="pl">This truly is an unfortunate country, which has experienced frequent name changes. It used to be called Congo, then it became Zaire and now it is known as the Democratic Republic of Congo. It has experienced mass movements of its population far more frequently than name changes, however. The documents before us state that last year alone 400 000 of its inhabitants were forced to leave their homes. The total number of people forced to do in recent years is four times greater, amounting to 1.5 million.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I should also refer to the use of rape as a weapon used deliberately for political purposes both by the partisans on the rebel side and by the police and the army on the government side. This is something unprecedented and the African Union is totally powerless to deal with it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-184" speaker_id="28301" name="Tadeusz ZWIEFKA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Poland" birth_date="28-12-1954" birth_place="Tuchola" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, it is my strong impression that the words 'Democratic Republic' that form part of the official name of Congo ring rather hollow nowadays, because it is precisely in that country that one the worst humanitarian crises of recent years is unfolding before our very eyes.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Over 650 000 people are constantly moving around the country. In just one province, Kivu, 80% of families have been displaced during the last five years, about 1 000 women a month are the victims of rape, and tens of thousands of children have become soldiers. In the Democratic Republic of Congo the passage of the armies is accompanied by all possible kinds of crime against the civilian population, such as rape, murder and pillage. Sexual violence is used to terrorise and punish the inhabitants of the Democratic Republic of Congo who supported the wrong side in the conflict. It is so widespread that, according to Médecins sans Frontières , 75% of all rapes in the world take place in the east of the Democratic Republic of Congo. Rape is accompanied by barbaric torture such as beating with clubs and mutilation with knives. Many young women have been forced into sexual slavery.</p>
      <p sl="pl">We should recall that the largest UN peacekeeping force in the world, consisting of over 17 000 soldiers, is currently deployed in the Democratic Republic of Congo. What is the main method of preventing sexual violence? It is slogans on walls stating that rape is inhuman. The most alarming fact is that the UN soldiers themselves have become involved in this scandal. On more than one occasion, UN investigators have discovered that UN soldiers themselves have forced Congolese girls into prostitution. It has proved simply impossible to punish the soldiers concerned, however, because their unit leaders did all they could to impede the prosecution. The soldiers have perpetrated violence instead of protecting against it on more than one occasion, and these occasions are becoming more numerous. This can only be defined as a scandal.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I would like to appeal to the international community to support immediate determined action aimed at identifying and punishing those responsible for crimes of a sexual nature. I should also like to emphasise that the countries sending military units into the field under the auspices of the UN are responsible for carrying out a proper investigation of any allegations of criminal behaviour by personnel involved in peacekeeping missions.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I realise that the European Union's options regarding the resolution of conflicts of this type are limited. Nonetheless, I call for funds to be made available for the organisation of a peace conference in Kivu. European Union aid should also be channelled towards the provision of medical, legal and social assistance to all victims of sexual crimes.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I trust the European Union and the UN will formally recognise that all types of crime of a sexual nature are crimes against humanity.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-185" speaker_id="28267" name="Josep BORRELL FONTELLES" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Spain" birth_date="24-04-1947" birth_place="Pobla de Segur" p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">Madam President, the description of sexual violence in Kivu, Congo, produces an unavoidable feeling of revulsion. Our fellow Members have described what is going on there, and I do not intend to repeat it. We must not merely agree to condemn it, since this could make us a voice crying in the wilderness: we have to do something to stop it, and what we can do is put pressure on the Congolese Government, because it is not just the rebels, but also its armed forces, who are carrying out these kinds of atrocities, aimed at humiliating women and undermining the moral foundations of the society in which they live.</p>
      <p sl="es">We must make the United Nations and the European Union declare sexual violence a crime against humanity. We must ask the Commission to allocate development assistance funds to the Congo, fundamentally and as a priority as assistance for the victims: legal assistance, social assistance and medical assistance.</p>
      <p sl="es">We must make United Nations personnel on the ground consider defence of the victims and the search for those responsible priority tasks, and to do so we must extend the mandate of the United Nations Mission in the Democratic Republic of the Congo to constitute a more direct link to the prevention of such occurrences.</p>
      <p sl="es">Finally, we must call on those attending the Kivu Conference to produce a set of specific results demanding justice and acceptance of responsibility, because if, after all that has happened, rapists finally enjoy impunity wearing the uniforms of the official army of the Republic of the Congo, the victims will be humiliated twice – first during the rape itself, and again when they see it was carried out with impunity.</p>
      <p sl="es">That is what we can and must do. I trust the Commission will take due note of this, and rechannel development assistance funds for the Congo, as I have requested, to assist victims and prevent the continuation of this savage butchery of the dignity of women.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-186" speaker_id="39763" name="Urszula GACEK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group" nationality="Poland" birth_date="17-03-1963" birth_place="Urmston " p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, the text of the resolution before us contains alarming data. We should keep in mind, however, that behind these statistics lie the tragedies of individual women.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I would like to tell the House the story of Lumo. She was the victim of a mass rape in 1994. The attack was so brutal that this young woman sustained permanent internal injures. After years of treatment and four operations she has still not regained her health and will probably never fully recover. She has been rejected by her fiancé, by most of her family and by society. Her mother and the African charitable organisation HEAL Africa have been her only support. HEAL Africa runs a hospital in Goma, which is the rape capital of the Democratic Republic of Congo. The hospital specialises in treating the victims of brutal cases of sexual violence. The surgeons have been very successful, and so-called mothers provide psychological support for the victims.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The House should commend these people on their work, but commendation alone is not enough. We need to consider how we can provide them with practical assistance. We owe it to Lumo and to the thousands of her Congolese sisters to help.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-187" speaker_id="4242" name="Karin SCHEELE" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PSE Group" nationality="Austria" birth_date="22-07-1968" birth_place="Baden" p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, with today’s motion on the situation in the Democratic Republic of Congo and on rape and violation as a war crime, we are calling on the European Union and United Nations formally to recognise rape, forced impregnation, sexual slavery and other forms of sexual violence as a crime against humanity and as a form of torture. We are also calling for pressure to be put on the Congolese Government to bring an end to the situation in which these crimes are being committed with impunity. These measures are needed to improve the appalling situation in which hundreds of thousands of women find themselves.</p>
      <p sl="de">The violence being suffered by women in the Democratic Republic of Congo is unimaginable. In the province of Kivu more than one third of all women have been subjected to rape, and many have been violated repeatedly over long periods. This has been going on for many years. Most of the perpetrators are soldiers from both sides, members of the Congolese security forces and the police. The UN special rapporteur on violence against women submitted her report last September.</p>
      <p sl="de">The atrocities being committed by armed troops are of unimaginable brutality and are designed to ensure the complete physical and psychological destruction of women. The trauma of rape is aggravated by the fact that many of the victims then suffer social discrimination and ostracism by their families and communities. This is one of the reasons why only a fraction of the rapes actually committed are being reported.</p>
      <p sl="de">Echoing what my colleague Mr Fontelles has just said, we therefore want to see the UN mandate extended to include the protection of civilians against sexual violence. Reports of sexual misconduct by members of the UN peacekeeping mission must be looked into in greater depth and those responsible must be brought before a court.</p>
      <p sl="de">The Goma Conference on peace, security and development opened a few days ago. We urgently call on all the participants to tackle the problem of sexual violence against women and girls, to undertake to bring those responsible before a court and to end the current situation in which these acts can be committed with impunity.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-188" speaker_id="24087" name="Marcin LIBICKI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the UEN group" nationality="Poland" birth_date="02-02-1939" birth_place="Poznań" p_group="Union for Europe of the Nations Group" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, we are today discussing rape as a war crime in the Democratic Republic of Congo. It is ironic that this country should be named the Democratic Republic of Congo. Nowadays it seems that the more democracy is referred to in names and in speeches, the less human rights are enjoyed by ordinary people.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I shall say once again that the only way to rein in African warlords who have been elevated to presidential office is on the one hand through economic sanctions, and on the other through armed intervention. Until the European Union creates a police force that would not, of course, intervene in every civil war but could at least supervise the camps, the so-called refugee camps where the very worst crimes are being committed in the Democratic Republic of Congo, all we will be able to do is continue debating the matter. People will continue to suffer and die whilst we debate endlessly.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-189" speaker_id="1059" name="Hiltrud BREYER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group" nationality="Germany" birth_date="22-08-1957" birth_place="Saarbrücken" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, the appalling mass rapes taking place in the Congo are being systematically organised and this means they are also being used as a military strategy, and that is not just war but sexual terror against women. The brutal rapes are now being used by each of the warring factions in eastern Congo, whether they are local tribal militia or national army soldiers, as a symbol or power and as a means of intimidation.</p>
      <p sl="de">It is precisely the weakest in society, namely women, children and even babies, who are being barbarously abused, deliberately injured, mutilated, infected with HIV and other infectious diseases and even killed. We know, and have heard, that the level of brutality exceeds the powers of human imagination and we now urgently need to see rape being condemned at long last as a crime against humanity, as a war crime and as a form of torture. Moreover, when the rape victims return traumatised and alone to their villages after painful operations – with many of the women losing all their genital organs – they find little or no shelter there.</p>
      <p sl="de">I can therefore only support the remarks made by Mr Borrell and Mrs Scheele: we must also use European money to set up women’s dormitories that can serve as a kind of refuge for those returning from their stay in hospital, and where they can then try to build a new life. Indeed, in addition to the physical violence endured, the psychological violence that the victims have suffered is terrible beyond measure.</p>
      <p sl="de">We know that most of these attacks have been carried out by rebels, but almost one fifth of the recorded incidents can be attributed to government troops and police, and it is indeed shameful that not a single culprit has yet been arrested or even charged. The time for empty talk is therefore past. We need political action from the UN and the European Union, for if we …</p>
      <a text="(The President cut off the speaker)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-190" speaker_id="28334" name="Urszula KRUPA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the IND/DEM Group" nationality="Poland" birth_date="20-10-1949" birth_place="Łódź" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, when I took the floor recently in a debate on sexual slavery in Japan during the Second World War, I also expressed my opposition to the brutal violence against women currently being perpetrated in the Democratic Republic of Congo. According to Médecins sans Frontières , 75% of all rapes committed in the world take place in the Democratic Republic of Congo. This is all the more alarming because the violence is accompanied by particular cruelty. Even three-year-old girls are affected.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Armed groups use rape as a tactical method to break down resistance and punish ethnic groups. This is true not only of armed rebels but also of the Congolese army. Along with food shortages and disease, sexual violence and aggression on an unprecedented scale have contributed to turning that area into a hell on earth. We should remember that the inter-tribal rivalry stems from colonial times, when one tribe was favoured over the other.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-191" speaker_id="28376" name="Leopold Józef RUTOWICZ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="18-10-1932" birth_place="Kraków" p_group="Non" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, the Democratic Republic of Congo is the largest country in Africa. It is rich in natural resources, such as water, tropical forests and agricultural land, but civilisation has long been in a state of collapse there. Over four million people have lost their lives in the Democratic Republic of Congo as a result of two civil wars, tribal conflicts, and the activities of armed groups and partisans. To compound the tragic situation of the people, there have also been mass deportations of citizens from their previous areas of residence, corrupt and inefficient governments, the AIDS epidemic and most recently the onslaught of the Ebola virus.</p>
      <p sl="pl">How can these people be helped? In addition to humanitarian aid and technical support, it is essential to deal with the leaders and organisers responsible for these horrific acts. They have been, and remain, unpunished and should now be excluded from Congolese society. Criminals responsible for genocide should be pursued by international special forces, so they can be tried before a court of law.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-192" speaker_id="28300" name="Zbigniew ZALESKI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="29-04-1947" birth_place="Rogoziniec" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, I do not wish to repeat what has already been said so I will simply state that as far as we are concerned there can be no question that aid must be provided. Hopefully the aid will be as substantial and widespread as possible.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I would also like to say that when I was in the Democratic Republic of Congo during the elections, I was shocked to discover that boys as young as 13 and sometimes even younger are taught two things: how to fight and how to rape girls even younger than themselves. Such is the image of the so-called soldiers of the group supporting the opposition presidential candidate, Mr Bemba. That is no exception, however. The situation is similar in all factions. I therefore support Mr Borrell’s statement that the funds and resources we have available should be directed to re-educating these young people, amongst other purposes. If these youngsters become set in their present ways, the only future they can look forward to is a life in gangs, committing rape and murder. Something has to be done with them. It seems we are being challenged to find a way to help these people change their attitude to life and to the opposite sex.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-193" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Meglena Kuneva" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the Commission remains extremely worried about the deteriorating human rights situation – especially about the widespread sexual violence – in the eastern Democratic Republic of Congo, and strongly condemns all acts of violence against women.</p>
      <p sl="en">In the prevailing climate of violence and insecurity all the armed groups present in the eastern Democratic Republic of Congo, including elements of the national armed forces, are to some extent involved in the dramatic rise of these types of acts. In this context, it is important to promote the fight against impunity, but also to address the root causes of the problem. It ought to be noted that sexual violence in the eastern part of the Democratic Republic of Congo is embedded within the context of persistent conflict and violence in the region.</p>
      <p sl="en">Peace is needed for sustained security and stability, the two key elements linked to the prevalence of sexual violence in the Democratic Republic of Congo. This is why the Commission, together with the EU Member States, has been continuously promoting a political solution for the crisis in the eastern Democratic Republic of Congo.</p>
      <p sl="en">The ongoing conference on peace, security and development in the Kivus, coupled with the recent agreement reached between the Democratic Republic of Congo and Rwanda in Nairobi in November 2007, could indeed represent a significant step forward in the process, while acknowledging that there are still many challenges ahead before a sustainable peace in the Kivus can be reached.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, these efforts are not enough and have to be complemented with active support to strengthen the capacity of the state in providing protection to its people. In this regard, the Commission works together with the Member States in strengthening the rule of law and the fight against impunity by supporting the security sector reform comprising the army, the police and the justice sector.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to reflect on some of the questions from Members and try to answer them. The Commission addresses, in particular, the problem of sexual violence and criminality through a multi-donor justice and rehabilitation project in the eastern part of the Democratic Republic of Congo, focusing inter alia on building the capacity of judicial actors and reinforcing the provision of legal assistance to the victims of sexual violence.</p>
      <p sl="en">In addition, the Commission provides significant humanitarian assistance – roughly EUR 40 million per year – to the Democratic Republic of Congo, especially to Uturi and the Kivus. Our humanitarian and health programmes take into consideration the gender violence they mentioned, both from a creative and awareness-raising perspective.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-194" speaker_id="4482" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Rodi KRATSA-TSAGAROPOULOU" nationality="Greece" birth_date="14-11-1952" birth_place="Zakynthos" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place at the end of the debate.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem21" title="11.3. Egypt (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-196" speaker_id="4482" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Rodi KRATSA-TSAGAROPOULOU" nationality="Greece" birth_date="14-11-1952" birth_place="Zakynthos" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the debate on six motions for resolutions on Egypt .</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-197" speaker_id="28409" name="Raül ROMEVA i RUEDA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Spain" birth_date="12-03-1971" birth_place="Madrid" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance - Vice" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">Madam President, I wish to begin by saying that this Parliament would be making a most serious mistake if it succumbed to pressure from those who prefer us not to discuss issues that could cause discomfort in certain countries, particularly when they denounce breaches of human rights.</p>
      <p sl="es">We have privileged relations with certain countries, such as those covered by the European Neighbourhood Policy, with whom we must have a particularly clear dialogue and remind them that business cannot and must not ever be disassociated from respect for human rights, either here or there.</p>
      <p sl="es">The situation in Egypt merited some reflection, and the relations between Egypt and the European Union also obliged such reflection. Thus it is more than legitimate to denounce, as we are doing in this resolution, the persecution of a number of non-governmental organisations, particularly human rights organisations, that is currently taking place in Egypt, and to lend support to the campaign for freedom of association led by a number of social movements in the country.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-198" speaker_id="4447" name="Paulo CASACA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="02-07-1957" birth_place="Lisboa" p_group="Socialist Group in the European Parliament" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">Madam President, I too must point out that there are of course no borders or sacred places where human rights are not a fundamental concern. However, we must take into account the fact that we had the opportunity to observe the willingness of Egypt’s Foreign Minister who came on purpose to the European Parliament, to the Committee on Foreign Affairs, and who was ready to answer all the questions on human rights’ infringements that were put to him. I was there and I put these questions to him and obtained some answers from the Minister.</p>
      <p sl="pt">In addition to certain negative factors, this motion for a resolution also highlights certain positive factors that I feel are important to stress, such as the undertaking to lift the state of emergency this year, in fact within the next few months, and the cooperation in the fight to end the arms smuggling in Gaza. However, in my opinion, the fundamental point is that we should take advantage of the willingness of the Egyptian authorities and encourage them to rectify certain serious infringements. I must highlight in this respect the continued imprisonment of the former candidate for the Presidency of the Republic of Egypt. I would repeat the call for this situation to be brought to an end as this would be coherent with the basic principles of a country that defends human rights, as Egypt has repeatedly advocated and to which it is committed.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-199" speaker_id="4508" name="Erik MEIJER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Netherlands" birth_date="05-12-1944" birth_place="Amsterdam" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="NL">
      <p sl="nl">Madam President, Egypt has no tradition of democracy. The young military men Nasser and Naguib, who overthrew the poorly performing regime of King Farouk over 50 years ago, brought hope for change and progress. Nasser gave his people pride and inspiration for the future; he was to put an end to their status as a backward and humiliated country. His successor, Sadat, gave them hope of permanent peace with their neighbour Israel, after a series of terrible wars.</p>
      <p sl="nl">The current president, Mr Mubarak, does not offer any hope at all. He has become the symbol of the stagnation. His only service has been to organise stability with a hard hand, so that he can be seen in the outside world as an ally against terrorism and Islamic fundamentalism. However, he has no progress and no democratisation to offer. Oppositions are permitted selectively, but they do not have the normal latitude that is customary in a parliamentary democracy. Consequently, he is cultivating a breeding ground for internal conflict from both fundamentalists and democrats.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Intolerance of religious minorities, including the large Coptic Christian minority who have been present in Egypt for centuries, is also on the increase. Long-term stability cannot be built on these foundations, where problems are not solved but covered up with violence. There is every reason for this critical resolution therefore.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Sabotage of non-governmental organisations, intimidation of opponents, discrimination against minorities, arrests and torture and all the other failings on record lead us to fear the worst for what will follow the Mubarak regime. Egypt seems in many respects to have stepped back into the backwardness of the reign of King Farouk, 60 years ago. European relations with Egypt ought to contribute to bringing this situation to an end as far as possible.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-200" speaker_id="39022" name="Ewa TOMASZEWSKA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Poland" birth_date="14-04-1947" birth_place="Płock" p_group="Union for Europe of the Nations Group" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, the progressive deterioration of the situation regarding respect for human rights in Egypt is causing increasing concern.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Changes to the constitution have facilitated violations of human rights. On the pretext of the need to provide protection against terrorist attacks and in connection with the alleged problem involving the smuggling of weapons into the Gaza Strip, additional powers have been vested in the Secret Service. It is now easier for the latter to evade responsibility for the use of torture. Repression on the grounds of religious belief, arrests and prolonged detention without proper trial are being resorted to ever more frequently.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Organisations like Amnesty International, which monitor respect for human rights, have drawn attention to the international community’s indifference towards the situation. I call on the European Commission to consider effective methods of bringing pressure to bear on the Egyptian authorities in order to halt this process.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-201" speaker_id="28350" name="Jana HYBÁŠKOVÁ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Czechia" birth_date="26-06-1965" birth_place="Praha" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats" m_state="CZ">
      <p sl="cs">Madam Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, Egypt is without doubt the most notable of the Arab countries. It is the cradle of ancient civilisation and it is the most important Arab state. Nobody in the European Union or in this Parliament doubts that Egypt is not only a key partner of the European Union, but also a dynamic partner, prepared and strong. These are the reasons why we consider a dialogue with this country very important and significant. New negotiations are starting next week on an action plan between the European Union and the Arab Republic of Egypt. It is good that our Parliament is unanimously and clearly expressing its support of these negotiations and that it is thus a player in international politics. We are stating clearly that a country that allows severe interference in the independence of an old democratic institution, i.e. the courts, that permits torture in prison and the killing of immigrants, that violates freedom of speech, blocks the Internet and sends members of parliament, such as the nephew of President Sadat, to a court martial, cannot be a partner of the European Union. Egypt is a key ally in the fight against terrorism, and it must remain a key ally notably in our struggle against the causes of terrorism and Islamic radicalisation. For that very reason, Egypt cannot act the way it did when it prohibited the registration of non-governmental organisations, it must not destroy freedom of speech and it must in particular defend the long-standing rule of law that has always existed in Egypt. We believe that Egypt can succeed in doing this and we believe, in particular, that our resolution will help the European Commission to establish a high-quality action plan with Egypt. Thank you for your support.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-202" speaker_id="2229" name="Bernd POSSELT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE-DE Group" nationality="Germany" birth_date="04-06-1956" birth_place="Pforzheim" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, I am one of the few people here in this Chamber who was present when President Sadat gave his famous speech in the European Parliament. This speech could be taken as a policy document for the Year of Intercultural Dialogue that has just begun. It was one of the greatest speeches ever made here in this House.</p>
      <p sl="de">Down through the years President Mubarak too has been an important and reliable partner for the European Union, and this is of course in spite of the many failings and mistakes that we have seen in Egypt. I therefore simply cannot understand the speech that the President of the Egyptian Parliament made in reaction to this motion. We are simply saying in a reasonable and restrained way that we consider Egypt to be one of the most important partners in the Mediterranean area, but we are criticising by way of a number of specific points and using categorical facts that some things still have to change as Egypt moves forward towards democracy and the rule of law.</p>
      <p sl="de">This is our commitment towards our own citizens and towards the people of Egypt. I certainly believe that breaking off relations, which is now being threatened, would be completely the wrong move. We need to keep talking to one another and for this reason I support this motion for a resolution, which has been drafted in reasonable language, and call on the Egyptians not to see this as a breakdown in the dialogue but as a clear signal for a more intensive dialogue to start: that is what we are trying to achieve with Egypt by way of this motion.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-203" speaker_id="28299" name="Bogusław SONIK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="03-12-1953" birth_place="Kraków" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, I should like to refer to two issues in the course of today’s debate on Egypt, and I am sure one of them will have been raised already in the House.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Whilst I believe that our relations with Egypt should be maintained and developed, and that Egypt should indeed become our main partner in that part of the world, I would like to begin by pointing out that Coptic Christians are second-class citizens in that country. This is true both of those who follow the Orthodox rite and those who follow the Catholic one, and should be borne in mind when making contact with Egypt. In addition, as I have already said on repeated occasions, we should study the situation of the religious minorities in that part of the world and prepare a report on the subject.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Secondly, there can be no talk of lasting peace, democracy and respect for human rights in the area in question until a solution is found to the conflict between Israel and Palestine in the Middle East. Therein lies the source of all that force, violence, terrorism and fanaticism that is also threatening Europe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-204" speaker_id="24087" name="Marcin LIBICKI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="02-02-1939" birth_place="Poznań" p_group="Union for Europe of the Nations Group" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, I should like to express a degree of satisfaction, in that as we debate the case of Egypt today, we do not have to refer to regular crimes. In general, during the debates on human rights on Thursday afternoons, when I usually take the floor, we find ourselves discussing extremely serious and dangerous cases indeed. They tend to be cases of violation of human rights, murder and rape. Today, however, we can feel a certain satisfaction because in comparison to so many other cases, we are intervening in Egypt at a stage when crimes have not yet taken place, although fundamental freedoms are being infringed. There is a chance that this timely intervention will therefore be more effective and will pre-empt more serious consequences. The usual pattern is for the first stage to be restrictions on the media – in this case we are referring to the arrest of journalists – and restrictions on the right of association. We also have in mind the trade unions and persecution of religious minorities. The next stage is the criminal one. Fortunately that stage has not yet been reached in this instance.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-205" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Meglena Kuneva" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the Commission is paying close attention to the democratic and human rights situation in Egypt, which is one of our partners in the European neighbourhood policy. It is following developments very closely through our delegation in Cairo, and in partnership with the Member States. It is also in regular contact with local and international NGOs dealing with human rights and democracy.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission shares your concern at the apparent deterioration of the human rights situation in Egypt, and at the number of reported cases of human rights violations, particularly in relation to freedom of expression, torture and ill treatment, as well as respect for religious minorities.</p>
      <p sl="en">It has called for greater political reform, and respect for human rights is an intrinsic part of the EU partnership with Egypt. The Commission is, therefore, using all the means at its disposal to encourage the Egyptian authorities to progress in this area.</p>
      <p sl="en">As a member of the UN Human Rights Council, Egypt has committed itself to upholding ‘the highest standards in the promotion and protection of human rights’. The EU consistently raises the importance of respecting human rights – notably on the basis of Article 2 of the Association Agreement – in its bilateral contacts with Egypt, including those at the highest level.</p>
      <p sl="en">With the adoption of the joint EU-Egypt action plan, under the European neighbourhood policy, in March 2007, we now have another political tool to foster respect for human rights and fundamental freedoms in Egypt, based on what we understand to be shared values. The action plan provides for the establishment of a formal and regular dialogue on human rights and democracy in the context of the Subcommittee on Political Matters: Human Rights and Democracy, International and Regional Issues. That subcommittee aims to facilitate dialogue within a context of mutual understanding, and respect for the positions of both parties, on all aspects of human rights and democracy, international and regional issues, in a comprehensive and non-exclusive way. It will convene for the first time next week – 23 and 24 January 2007 – in Cairo, and will be a constructive way for Egypt to demonstrate commitment to shared values.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission firmly believes that the dialogue with Egypt within the framework of the political arrangements set out in the Association Agreement and in the ENP action plan is the most effective way to impress upon the Egyptian Government the EU’s concerns regarding respect for human rights and international law.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission remains committed to contributing to Egypt’s reform process through financial and technical assistance, and support for political reform, human rights and democracy remains a priority in the national indicative programme 2007-2010, and under the European Instrument for Democracy and Human Rights.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am sure the European Parliament will be a strong ally in support of these efforts.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-206" speaker_id="4482" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Rodi KRATSA-TSAGAROPOULOU" nationality="Greece" birth_date="14-11-1952" birth_place="Zakynthos" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">We shall now proceed to the vote.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem22" title="12. Voting time">
    <intervention id="4-208" speaker_id="4482" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Rodi KRATSA-TSAGAROPOULOU" nationality="Greece" birth_date="14-11-1952" birth_place="Zakynthos" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is voting time.</p>
      <a text="(For results and other details of the votes: see Minutes)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem23" title="12.1. Arrest of Chinese dissident Hu Jia (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-211" speaker_id="2229" name="Bernd POSSELT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="04-06-1956" birth_place="Pforzheim" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, can it be that those who in recent days have been calling persistently for roll-call votes have not been doing so this afternoon because most of them are absent?</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-212" speaker_id="4482" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Rodi KRATSA-TSAGAROPOULOU" nationality="Greece" birth_date="14-11-1952" birth_place="Zakynthos" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="unknown">They had all been informed, Mr Posselt.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem24" title="12.2. Situation in the Democratic Republic of Congo and rape as a war crime (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem25" title="12.3. Egypt (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem26" title="13. Explanations of vote (continuation)">
    <intervention id="4-216" speaker_id="4482" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Rodi KRATSA-TSAGAROPOULOU" nationality="Greece" birth_date="14-11-1952" birth_place="Zakynthos" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="unknown">We shall now continue with the explanations of vote from midday.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Mrs Roithová, Mr Helmer, Mr Whittaker, Mr Clark, Mr Nattrass, Mr Wise, Mr Deva, Mr Hannan and Mr Kamall had asked to explain their vote on the remaining reports from this afternoon.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">I note that these Members are not present, but they may, if they wish, submit explanations of vote in writing.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem27" title="14. Membership of committees and delegations: see Minutes">
    <intervention id="4-219" speaker_id="2278" name="Paul RÜBIG" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Austria" birth_date="06-05-1953" birth_place="Wels" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, I would like to thank you especially for having read out the names of those who this morning alleged that there was no democracy in this House because they have not had a chance to speak. If you look across to the benches of those who have been loudly demonstrating and complaining that there is no democracy you will see that they have not even taken the time to stay until the end of the sitting. They themselves are hardly a role model for Europe. I would ask that this be specifically recorded in the Minutes.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-220" speaker_id="4482" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Rodi KRATSA-TSAGAROPOULOU" nationality="Greece" birth_date="14-11-1952" birth_place="Zakynthos" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="unknown">Mr Rübig, your comment will be noted.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem28" title="15. Decisions concerning certain documents: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem29" title="16. Written declarations for entry in the register (Rule 116): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem30" title="17. Forwarding of texts adopted during the sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem31" title="18. Dates for next sittings: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem32" title="19. Adjournment of the session">
    <intervention id="4-226" speaker_id="4482" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Rodi KRATSA-TSAGAROPOULOU" nationality="Greece" birth_date="14-11-1952" birth_place="Zakynthos" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="unknown">I declare the session of the European Parliament adjourned.</p>
      <a text="(The sitting was closed at 4.20 p.m.)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
</text>
