<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20100121.EN" lang="en" date="2010-01-21" place="Strasbourg" edition="OJ edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Opening of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. EU-Tunisia relations (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-006" speaker_id="28133" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Pál SCHMITT" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="13-05-1942" birth_place="Budapest" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the Commission statement on EU-Tunisia relations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-007" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neelie Kroes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to thank Parliament for inviting me to take part in the discussion on Tunisia.</p>
      <p sl="en">EU-Tunisia relations are governed by an association agreement signed in 1995. By the way, Tunisia was the first Mediterranean county to sign such an agreement and it has since then made significant advances.</p>
      <p sl="en">In international relations, Tunisia is close and a reliable partner for the EU. The views it expresses and the positions it takes within international organisations and in other fora are moderate and balanced. It is cooperative on issues such as security and migration and has good relations with its neighbours in the southern Mediterranean region. Furthermore, it has always played a constructive role towards regional integration in the Maghreb.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tunisia takes an active part in the European Neighbourhood Policy and the Commission’s periodic reports on implementation by Tunisia of the European Neighbourhood Policy Action Plan are clear in their assessment: Tunisia has achieved progress in a number of cooperation areas, including the action plan.</p>
      <p sl="en">Economic reforms have progressed, allowing for a steady growth of the Tunisian economy as well as of trade volume with the EU. Important results have been achieved in the social field, in areas such as health care, education, the fight against poverty and the protection of women’s rights.</p>
      <p sl="en">On the other side, the reports also highlight shortcomings, in particular, in the areas of justice, freedom of expression and association.</p>
      <p sl="en">Political dialogue with Tunisia has been continuous on all the subjects covered by the action plan, which are addressed in 10 subcommittees and in working groups. The EU-Tunisia Association Council has already met several times and the next meeting is scheduled in the next few months.</p>
      <p sl="en">On 1 January 2008, Tunisia became the first southern Mediterranean country to have a free trade area with the EU for industrial products, two years in advance of the date foreseen. The EU is Tunisia’s first trading partner: 72.5% of its imports come from the EU and the EU is the destination for 75% of its exports. EU financial cooperation amounts to some EUR 75 million to EUR 80 million per year, for which Tunisia has proved to have a good absorption capacity.</p>
      <p sl="en">Negotiations have also been launched on the gradual liberalisation of trade in services and the right of establishment, as well as on agriculture and fishery products. The conclusion of these negotiations, together with approximation of the relevant legislation, will mark a new stage in relations between the EU and Tunisia and progress towards the integration of the Tunisian economy in the EU single market.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tunisia has requested that its relations with the EU be given a new impetus through an advanced status. We believe that such an endeavour is in the interests of the EU. We also expect that Tunisia will show a real drive towards more democratic reforms and freedom of expression. Without progress in the important area of human rights, the country’s important achievements that I have mentioned would anyhow be perceived, despite their significance, especially by regional standards, as incomplete.</p>
      <p sl="en">In conclusion, I would like to say that we judge relations between the EU and Tunisia as solid and friendly and that we believe that there is indeed a potential for further strengthening of those relations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-008" speaker_id="28133" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Pál SCHMITT" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="13-05-1942" birth_place="Budapest" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the speeches of the political groups.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-009" speaker_id="28474" name="Ioannis KASOULIDES" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group" nationality="Cyprus" birth_date="10-08-1948" birth_place="Lefkosia" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) - Vice" m_state="CY">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, Tunisia contributes towards the stability of this region in its role as a partner in the Union for the Mediterranean, as the first country to sign the association agreement, and as the first country equipped with an action plan for the implementation of the Neighbourhood Policy. Tunisia is comparatively ahead in terms of gender equality and the protection of children and the family, and is now awaiting negotiations on the granting of an advanced partnership status.</p>
      <p sl="fr">In the aforementioned agreements, there are clauses on democracy, the rule of law and human rights. Plans are afoot for talks, to help us to achieve progress in what are very sensitive and important issues for us in the European Parliament. If we want tangible results, and if we are not necessarily to achieve them via controversy and criticism, we must be careful to avoid any condescension, to prove that we are talking as equals, not as superiors or inspectors, and to show that we are also prepared to take an interest in the concerns and sensitivities of our partners.</p>
      <p sl="fr">In a context such as this, I am certain that the Tunisian Government will respond with concrete steps forward in the areas under debate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-010" speaker_id="28365" name="Pier Antonio PANZERI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group" nationality="Italy" birth_date="06-06-1955" birth_place="Riviera D'Adda" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, if we had to give an opinion on the existing relations between the European Union and Tunisia, it could only be a positive one, including as regards the stabilisation of the region.</p>
      <p sl="it">It is true that important progress has been made in economic terms, and there are also encouraging signs from a social point of view. However, in political terms, following the presidential elections on 25 October, we are faced with the problem of supporting the journey towards democratic reforms with greater concrete action. As we know, the European Union’s objective, in pursuing its foreign policy, is to develop and consolidate democracy, the rule of law, and respect for human rights and fundamental freedoms.</p>
      <p sl="it">Tunisia has made some important commitments in the context of the Neighbourhood Policy Action Plan on democracy, governance and human rights. The action plan lays down a series of priorities and, amongst these, particular attention must be paid to implementing and consolidating reforms, and to strengthening political dialogue and cooperation, particularly in relation to democracy and human rights, foreign policy and security.</p>
      <p sl="it">It is within this framework that the institutions must be strengthened. The latter allow the increased participation in political life of the various members of Tunisian society, greater development of the role of civil society, continued support for political parties to broaden their participation in the democratic process, and greater respect for freedom of association, freedom of expression and media pluralism.</p>
      <p sl="it">We are convinced that these objectives can be achieved, and it is reasonable to expect tangible progress to be made. Our commitment is to safeguard the friendship which binds the European Union and Tunisia while consolidating the existing relationship, including in view of the conflict which could arise concerning the idea of an advanced status for that country. However, concrete steps really must be taken by Tunisia itself.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-011" speaker_id="96670" name="Louis MICHEL" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group" nationality="Belgium" birth_date="02-09-1947" birth_place="Tirlemont" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="BE">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I should like to begin by both thanking and congratulating the Commissioner for the position taken by the Commission on this matter. I am in complete agreement with this position, since it seems far more reasonable than the stance taken by those who called for today’s debate, and I am unsure exactly whose suggestion it was.</p>
      <p sl="fr">As has been said, Tunisia was the first Euro-Mediterranean country to sign an association agreement, and is an active partner in the European Neighbourhood Policy. It is worth pointing out, as Mr Kasoulides has done, that, on 1 January 2008, Tunisia became the only Mediterranean country to have a free trade relationship with the European Union. This cooperation is working very well, and Tunisia is proving to have an excellent absorption capacity. Tunisia has achieved substantial progress, which has resulted in a very high standard of development with socio-economic results acknowledged by international institutions. In economic terms, Tunisia achieved an average growth rate of 4.6% between the years 2002 and 2008. Moreover, it has succeeded in reducing its debt burden.</p>
      <p sl="fr">In social terms, it would be unfair to ignore the progress made, particularly on behalf of women. The indicators speak for themselves: 59% of students in higher education are female. Education is compulsory across the board for females aged from 6 to 16, and women account for almost a quarter of the working population in Tunisia.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I admit that these results obviously cannot obscure the urgent need to encourage the Tunisian authorities to make further advances in human rights and governance; we are well aware that there is still work to be done. Like other speakers, I am concerned about this issue, for the sake of the democratic values that we uphold. However, it is also important to remember that we are not the only ones to uphold these values. They are also at the heart of Tunisian society, which is a dynamic and pro-European society.</p>
      <p sl="fr">For these reasons, we must support Tunisia’s request to be granted an advanced status in this partnership with the European Union. I also believe that it is through this dialogue that we will find the appropriate framework for encouraging our partners to make further progress in the field of governance.</p>
      <p sl="fr">We must conduct the dialogue with our partners without complacency, obviously, but also without resorting to the kind of sanctimonious dogmatism in which Europe all too often specialises and which is, moreover, often counterproductive.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Obviously, I am not insensitive to specific cases that some people have raised. We clearly have the right to question our partners about circumstances that we believe to be unacceptable, but I would like to finish by highlighting Tunisia’s success in establishing a political system based on the principle of separation between church and state.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The public authorities in Tunisia have the capacity to provide the people with a package of basic services, services that other countries in the region have not yet been able to implement, and I believe that it is important to point this out, too. I am therefore extremely optimistic about the future of relations between Tunisia and the EU, since they are being forged against a backdrop of mutual respect between partners who respect one another and have an understanding on the fundamental issues.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-012" speaker_id="4385" name="Hélène FLAUTRE" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group" nationality="France" birth_date="29-07-1958" birth_place="Bapaume" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, I am disturbed by the speeches that I have just heard, from the Commissioner right through to my fellow Members. I feel that we really have our work cut out to gain an accurate and objective understanding of the present situation in Tunisia.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Frankly, when I listen to you, I feel as though I am listening to western intellectuals talking cheerfully, many decades ago, about the economic and social success in the countries of the USSR, with a complete inability to go and see what our shared values stand for in practice in those countries. What are our shared values, Mr Michel? They are human rights, democracy and the rule of law.</p>
      <p sl="fr">You have all rightly pointed out that Tunisia was our first partner to sign an association agreement. This is true, and that is why all this is very worrying, because we are not talking here about gaps, Commissioner, or about small steps. No. There is a huge, ongoing decline in human rights and democracy in Tunisia. Can you name one single newspaper, party or union that has been authorised in the last 20 years? No.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The truth is that fundamental freedoms are being systematically and utterly disregarded, and, with them, our own commitments. This is not about moralising; this is about respecting the values of the European Union, and respecting the commitments that we made by signing this association agreement.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Therefore, I demand that there be at least a shared analysis of this matter. I believe that we have worked hard to have this debate, but it would certainly be time better spent if we were to organise an actual delegation, one that really goes and meets this civil society in Tunisia and the various members of that society, in order to make an assessment of the continued harassment experienced by human rights defenders, students, trade unionists, workers and lawyers. There have been putsches in almost all of the associations that showed a certain degree of autonomy with regard to the authorities. I therefore believe that you are completely deluded on this matter.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Having listened to your speeches, I well understand why you do not want to see the real picture in Tunisia. You do not want to see it because you believe that there are economic interests at stake, and because you believe that there are interests at stake relating to the fight against terrorism and illegal immigration. You have expressed all this in the clearest of terms, and you go on about advances relating to equality between men and women and to the family, advances that date back to Bourguiba’s time. I repeat, these date back to Bourguiba. There has been no further progress since that time.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I therefore believe that, if we have any respect for ourselves, for the agreements we sign, for the Neighbourhood Policy or for EU values, we certainly cannot propose an advanced status for Tunisia. Therefore, I tell you straight: if you propose that and renounce all requirements and all commitments in relation to human rights and democracy with all the countries of the Mediterranean, that will be the guaranteed outcome.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-013" speaker_id="4521" name="Charles TANNOCK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ECR Group" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="25-09-1957" birth_place="Aldershot" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Tunisia is a friend and ally of the European Union, a prosperous, progressive, modern and meritocratic secular society unique in the Arab world. Tunisia also rightly takes an uncompromising approach to Islamist jihadi extremism.</p>
      <p sl="en">A multiparty political system is fast taking shape in Tunisia and it is a country where women are fully equal members of their society. Why then do we seek to alienate Tunisia and its 10 million people? Perhaps because of jealousy at its success, perhaps because it is small and possesses no oil, so, no, there is no economic leverage on the EU, unlike Libya or Saudi Arabia.</p>
      <p sl="en">In my view, those who have engineered this debate are making a deliberate effort to sabotage much of the progress in EU-Tunisia relations in recent years. It is especially galling that this debate is occurring at the same time as a visit of Tunisian parliamentarians to Strasbourg who are, I think, sitting up there watching this debate.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tunisia needs our support, encouragement and dialogue, not a constant stream of senseless invective. It is bitterly ironic that the Left, who claim to be so much in favour of women’s rights, attack Tunisia despite the fact that this country offers women opportunities and freedoms unprecedented anywhere else in the Arab world.</p>
      <p sl="en">The fact that the Tunisian authorities prohibit the wearing of the hijab in public places indicates their determination to protect Tunisia’s values of secularism, tolerance and liberty. We should respect Tunisia as our Euro-Mediterranean advanced partner.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-014" speaker_id="28133" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Pál SCHMITT" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="13-05-1942" birth_place="Budapest" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="unknown">Although I was not told that a Tunisian delegation is present, they waved when you mentioned it. I would like to welcome you to the gallery.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-015" speaker_id="96858" name="Marie-Christine VERGIAT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group" nationality="France" birth_date="23-09-1956" birth_place="Roanne" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I personally am very pleased that we are having this debate on the human rights situation in Tunisia. The Confederal Group of the European United Left – Nordic Green Left was instrumental in the organisation of the debate. All along, I have defended human rights, but human rights are the same all over the world.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I regret that this debate should not have been accompanied by a vote on a resolution. Words come and go; only the written word remains. As the EU’s oldest partner, Tunisia receives the highest amount of per capita aid of all the countries of the South, and is an enthusiastic participant in the setting up of the free trade area around the Mediterranean rim. So enthusiastic, in fact, that its leaders are beginning to claim their dividends and to demand the benefits of an advanced status.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I fully support the remarks made by Mrs Flautre, and share her alarm at some of the comments made. The EU partnership agreements henceforth include clauses on democracy and human rights. These clauses must be examined just as closely as economic ones. The fact is, Commissioner, the Commission’s report on the implementation of the Neighbourhood Policy is unsatisfactory in this regard; it is a clear case of double standards.</p>
      <p sl="fr">On 25 October, Mr Ben Ali was re-elected for a fifth term, gaining more than 89% of the vote. This figure alone reveals the state of democracy within that country. It is a locked democracy, where human rights defenders, magistrates, lawyers, journalists – in short, anyone who dares to challenge the regime – are harassed, imprisoned and, in some cases, even tortured.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Since last September, there has been a real drift towards an authoritarian police state, as the case of Taoufik Ben Brik, who will be tried next Saturday, shows. However, we could also mention Zouhair Makhlouf and Fahem Boukadous, one of whom was convicted for talking about the environmental conditions in his country, and the other for taking part in workers’ demonstrations in his country.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Yes, this is the social situation in Tunisia. Human rights defenders such as Kamel Jendoubi, Sihem Bensedrine, Sana Ben Achour, and Kemais Chamari are victims of a disgraceful press campaign. Sadok Chourou has been rotting in jail for the last 16 years, and Radhia Nasraoui, who acts as his lawyer, has been dragged through the mud, her career permanently damaged.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Students are being arrested and arbitrarily convicted, as are others. Their passports are held, or not renewed, and some human rights activists are being prevented from leaving the territory to act as witnesses. Meetings of associations independent from the ruling power are forbidden, their visitors are followed, and I do not have enough time to provide a true picture of the reality of Tunisia’s social policy.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Why is the Tunisian Government taking so long to respond to the UN report? Why did it refuse to host EU observers if the elections are as democratic as it says they are? The facts are there; they are being revealed more and more in our countries’ newspapers.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The Commission and the Council must take this into account. Tunisia must honour its commitments in relation to democracy and human rights. It is unacceptable, in fact, to go ahead with advanced status. Yes, I am in favour of equal partnerships! Yes, all the countries in the world must be treated in the same way, but on condition that they honour their commitments. I will end there, Mr President.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-016" speaker_id="28497" name="Gerard BATTEN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the EFD Group" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="27-03-1954" birth_place="London" p_group="Europe of Freedom and Direct Democracy Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Tunisia’s situation is overall a positive one it seems. They have the most stable society in North Africa. They have what is technically a democracy, though possibly only a semi-democracy by Western standards, but we should not criticise them for that, since they have made much progress. There is an official policy of working towards full democracy, and Tunisia is a stable society with a high level of personal security. This has been achieved by the suppression of their Islamist extremists and Communists, which is a price well worth paying. Its official policy is the pursuit of cultural unity – the creation of one nation. This is a lesson that many European countries – including mine, the United Kingdom – could well learn.</p>
      <p sl="en">Economically, they are progressing. Only 7% of the population lives below the poverty line. It has one of the best health standards among countries in North Africa, with a relatively high life expectancy. Politically, their Constitution limits the number of seats a party can hold in the Chamber of Deputies, with 20% of seats being reserved for minority parties. This looks positively enlightened when compared to the ‘first past the post’ electoral system used in the United Kingdom which, in my opinion, is a conspiracy against the voter to keep the Conservative and Labour parties in and everybody else out. So maybe we should learn something from the Tunisians.</p>
      <p sl="en">Speaking of the UK, my party, the UK Independence Party, came in for some criticism from some Islamic extremist and supposedly liberal quarters last week when we proposed a plan that people’s faces should be uncovered in public buildings, and in private buildings if those concerned wish to impose such a condition. But look at what Tunisia did. Law No 108 bans the hijab, which goes much further than anybody else has proposed. The Religious Affairs Minister, Boubaker El Akhzouri, has slammed the hijab as running counter to the country’s ‘cultural legacy’, regarding Islamic dress as ‘a foreign phenomenon’ in society. Well, that is very interesting, coming out of an Islamic country. The more I find out about Tunisia, the more positive an impression it makes. But I have seen some figures which indicate that EUR 70 million is to be spent on key projects in the EU neighbourhood scheme. My constituents, who are some of the poorest in London, cannot afford that kind of expenditure. We want trade, friendship and cooperation with Tunisia but not at the price of robbing the taxpayer in the UK. Let us help them increase their democracy and develop prosperity and, if they would like to take some free advice, let them keep well away from the European Union and preserve their freedom and independence.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-017" speaker_id="28255" name="Andreas MÖLZER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Austria" birth_date="02-12-1952" birth_place="Leoben" p_group="Non" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, trade relations between the EU and Tunisia are close and multifaceted. Tunisia, which receives EUR 80 million per year in financial aid, is a shining example of successful development policy. As an emerging economy, the country has assumed a leading position in the Maghreb, it was the first Mediterranean country to create a free trade area with the EU and it is reaping the benefits of this with sound economic growth. The Tunisian Republic is consequently expected to play a constructive part in the deliberations with regard to the EuroMed Roadmap for trade beyond 2010 and the cooperation with the Maghreb countries.</p>
      <p sl="de">Now we could be forgiven for thinking that it was sunshine all the way were it not for the presence of that paragraph linking European aid in connection with the partnership agreement to respect for human rights. This is precisely where we have a contradiction – the money that is to be used to stimulate the Tunisian economy is also used to finance and support a dictatorial, anti-democratic apparatus. That is a common problem in connection with our development and association aid. We need to do something about this, because the EU cannot promote human rights violations, even indirectly, in Tunisia, the Congo or, of course, Turkey, which is a candidate country.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-018" speaker_id="96818" name="Salvatore IACOLINO" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Italy" birth_date="18-11-1963" birth_place="Favara" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, Tunisia, like the entire Maghreb region, is an important strategic area. It has an enormous growth potential and is an attractive area with powerful interests, not only economic but, above all, European.</p>
      <p sl="it">Programmes with the European Union which promote cross-border cooperation have also recently been initiated. It is therefore time to revive, if we are ever going to do so, the relations established by the European Union with the African countries at our borders, starting with Tunisia, by fully enhancing the potential of this area and maintaining its associated social and economic development, but within a framework of freedom and security.</p>
      <p sl="it">The relationship between the countries of the Mediterranean is the key factor which gives cohesion and strength to an ambitious economic and social development programme. In political terms, it could be said that Tunisia is a country in which democracy is still relatively young; however, the action plan set out appears to be in line with the European Union’s expectations.</p>
      <p sl="it">The emergence of new parties and a reasonable female presence in parliament following the elections at the end of October 2009 confirm that significant progress has been made in terms of democratic participation. In any case, freedom of the press must be advanced and protected, as must equal opportunities for men and women and, more generally, fundamental human rights.</p>
      <p sl="it">It is in this framework that we can help Tunisia to conclude the efforts it has undertaken by removing all potential barriers to the full development of human beings in that country, and all this within the context of a more advanced status.</p>
      <p sl="it">Tunisia’s central role in the Mediterranean and the modernisation process under way in that country require a serious and balanced approach which results in the unconditional affirmation of the values upheld by the European Union. Now more than ever, the European Parliament cannot allow any mistakes to be made on the road to democracy.</p>
      <p sl="it">Constructive dialogue and careful diplomacy can instead further consolidate a relationship destined to be strengthened in a country which, in some sectors – such as justice and freedom of association – must be helped to grow, but a country which, I repeat, is absolutely central and pivotal to stability policy in the Mediterranean.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-019" speaker_id="96990" name="Carmen ROMERO LÓPEZ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Spain" birth_date="15-11-1946" birth_place="Sevilla" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">Respecting Tunisia means also respecting its democratic opposition, which is seeking to organise itself but is being repressed, and respecting its civil society, which is also the opposition of the future. I therefore wish to greet the members of parliament that are here now attending this sitting, but I also wish to send my greetings to those who may become members of parliament in the future, but who are currently threatened and may be imprisoned. We therefore think that it is very important for civil society to organise itself and for the democratic opposition to be respected, despite the fact that it is not currently organised.</p>
      <p sl="es">In Spain – I can say this as a Spanish MEP – we experienced a society in which the democratic opposition was tortured and repressed during the dictatorship. If the opposition is not terrorist, when it is democratic, it has values, which are the values of the future. Therefore, we need to help this opposition, which is currently not organised, but is democratic, and which is fighting for the values of the Tunisian transition and for the consolidation of those values. We also need to help it to organise itself.</p>
      <p sl="es">We also need to help the opposition so that they can be the leaders and protagonists of the future, possibly in opposition, or in government, but rotation is essential in a democratic society.</p>
      <p sl="es">Therefore, this escalation of violence that we are currently witnessing, which may intensify in the future, is not the best calling card for advanced status.</p>
      <p sl="es">We know that Tunisia has been a member of the Euro-Mediterranean Partnership, and has a Mediterranean inclination and a democratic inclination. Therefore, during this period, we also want it to contribute to this democratic consolidation and to be able to organise itself so that it can really be a loyal member and a member that contributes to the Mediterranean being an emerging area with democratic values.</p>
      <p sl="es">That is our desire for the future and that is what we want for Tunisia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-020" speaker_id="96801" name="Tomasz Piotr PORĘBA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, there is no doubt that Tunisia is a partner with which the European Union should maintain relations on behalf of the Mediterranean Sea Region and at bilateral level. However, while remembering economic matters, we, as the European Union, should insist on transparency of democratic procedures and the rule of law in that country.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Despite the fact that Tunisia is a stable country, it is not, unfortunately, a country where all democratic standards are maintained. International non-governmental organisations say that the security forces there torture prisoners and act with impunity, because they are protected by high-ranking officials. Freedom of the press and freedom of speech are drastically restricted, and the situation of journalists is said to be one of the worst among all Arab countries. Repression often has a religious background. Persecution of the Christian minority is becoming increasingly disturbing. The government in Tunisia does not tolerate expressions of protest or the existence of independent opposition.</p>
      <p sl="pl">Remembering that Tunisia was the first Mediterranean country to sign an association agreement with the European Union, we must resolutely insist on observance of the terms of the agreement. Respect for human rights and democratic standards in Tunisia must be a condition for further cooperation with that country.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-021" speaker_id="1759" name="Dominique BAUDIS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="France" birth_date="14-04-1947" birth_place="Paris" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, to avoid any caricatures – we have heard one or two this morning – I would like to mention some objective facts regarding Tunisia, a partner country of the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The social situation has evolved very favourably, with a spectacular increase in the average per capita income, and now the vast majority of Tunisians meet the criteria defining membership of the middle class. More than 90% of Tunisians enjoy welfare cover, and more than a quarter of Tunisia’s budget is devoted to education, with the result that the country is one of the very first to have achieved the Millennium Development Goals in the area of primary education.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Finally, as Mr Michel highlighted a little while ago, women’s rights are both recognised and guaranteed. At university level, female students outnumber male students, and 40% of teachers are women. A quarter of politicians, local officials and journalists are women. Many countries would be envious of these statistics.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-022" speaker_id="96952" name="Sylvie GUILLAUME" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="France" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, for my part, I would like to add my voice to those who have already spoken to denounce the particularly worrying situation in which the journalist and writer Taoufik Ben Brik finds himself in Tunisia.</p>
      <p sl="fr">In the wake of several arrests of journalists and trade unionists, who have suffered violence and mistreatment, and of the refusal to grant entry to foreign journalists during the presidential elections, the repression against political opponents and human rights activists continues. After a botched trial, and his incarceration far from his family, which makes visits difficult, Taoufik Ben Brik has been left in a state of health that makes one fear for his life.</p>
      <p sl="fr">How can one fail to regard this situation as a fierce attack against someone who upsets the apple cart? For this reason, we must not simply use trade as an answer to everything. On the contrary, I believe it is crucial for the EU to react quickly and firmly by demanding the release of Taoufik Ben Brik and other prisoners of conscience.</p>
      <p sl="fr">There has been an alarming decline in the human rights situation in Tunisia. It is affecting Europe’s cooperation with the country, and a tangible improvement in this situation represents one of the conditions for the opening of negotiations on an advanced status for the EU-Tunisia partnership.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-023" speaker_id="2341" name="Michael GAHLER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="22-04-1960" birth_place="Frankfurt/Main" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, we have a good foundation for our cooperation with Tunisia. The association agreement and the free trade agreement have been mentioned. Mrs Kroes said that we are talking about integrating the Tunisian economy into the single market. That is really as far as we can go with a country outside the EU, and therefore this forms a stable foundation. Tunisia is a solid and friendly partner with the potential for further strengthening our relations, to quote Mrs Kroes once again.</p>
      <p sl="de">Precisely because we have these close relations, we are also able to talk to our colleagues about all of the issues that may cause us some concern. I, personally, am in talks with our colleagues, who are here in the gallery, and my feeling is that we should talk about everything.</p>
      <p sl="de">However, in this connection, we should not throw the baby out with the bathwater. In Tunisia, we also have a situation where the country, as an Arab country that wants to develop in a secular manner, is threatened by extremists. I am sympathetic towards anyone who takes action against Islamic extremists.</p>
      <p sl="de">However, as regards other matters, I think that we will make progress in the ongoing talks. We can talk about anything with Tunisia because it is a reliable partner. I therefore look forward to continuing our dialogue.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-024" speaker_id="96838" name="Cristian Dan PREDA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="26-10-1966" birth_place="Bucureşti" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, as has already been highlighted, Tunisia is an important partner of the EU; mention was also made of the extremely important role played by the social field in Tunisia. I would like to add to that some political aspects that are significant, because, as has already been said, Tunisia is a society that practises multiparty politics, albeit in a limited fashion, with a quota for the opposition, no doubt, but nevertheless multiparty politics. The issue of gender equality has also been mentioned.</p>
      <p sl="fr">In all our countries, in the countries of Europe, all these political opinions coexist with freedom of the press, and this is what makes the difference, in fact, because, in Tunisia, such freedom exists, but it is limited, and there are in fact journalists who are in difficulty.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The following question then arises: could a rapprochement with the European Union increase this freedom or not? In my opinion, a rapprochement with the EU could help Tunisia to supplement the social progress made with some extremely important political advances.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-025" speaker_id="4318" name="Harlem DÉSIR" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="France" birth_date="25-11-1959" birth_place="Paris" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, Commissioner, you have stated your hope that Tunisia will make progress in the areas of democratic reform and freedom of expression. You are right to do so, since this is quite simply in line with the association agreement and with the commitments that Tunisia has made to the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="fr">That is why I am very surprised by the comments made by both Mr Baudis and Mr Michel, which seem to be encouraging you to ignore this aspect of our relationship and our cooperation with Tunisia, and to ultimately abandon Article 2 of the association agreement.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Moreover, there is a long way to go before these commitments are honoured, judging from the fate – as already mentioned by my colleague, Mrs Guillaume – of the independent journalist Taoufik Ben Brik, who has been in prison since last October, following a trial in which his lawyers and the procedure were in complete violation of the law. In addition to the unacceptable denial of his freedom, his health is deteriorating and his visiting rights have been restricted.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I therefore ask you, Commissioner: does the Commission intend to intervene within the framework of the Association Council to demand Mr Ben Brik’s immediate release and to ensure that his situation and his state of health may be taken into account, at the very least on humanitarian grounds?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-026" speaker_id="96732" name="Malika BENARAB-ATTOU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="France" birth_date="25-03-1963" birth_place="Aïn-Benian " p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, on 14 January, I met with members of the Tunisian delegation. We had a frank exchange and debated our respective views.</p>
      <p sl="fr">As a Franco-Algerian, I am committed to the Maghreb and I campaign for a united, pluralist and democratic Maghreb. The issue of human rights is crucially important to me, and it is one of the fundamental values of the European Union. The debate on this issue, as it appears in Tunisia, is crucial and relevant.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Yesterday morning, I met Mr Ben Brik’s wife, who is leading a hunger strike, as well as activists from the Euro-Mediterranean Human Rights Network, and I am concerned. It seems that Mr Ben Brik’s life is in danger due to his illness and his detention conditions. I am sure you realise that if this concern should become a reality, the responsibility will fall very heavily on the shoulders of the Tunisian authorities.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Aside from trade relations, we must also take account of social issues. The phenomenon of young Tunisians throwing themselves into the Mediterranean is the product of a closed society that offers no prospects to its young people. The defence against fundamentalism and economic imperatives must not serve as pretexts for ignoring human rights. Real progress in the field of human rights is now crucial. We are not talking here about sanctimonious dogmatism but about an urgent situation that the European Union must help to resolve.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-027" speaker_id="96678" name="Alf SVENSSON" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Sweden" birth_date="01-10-1938" birth_place="Götlunda" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="SE">
      <p sl="sv">The countries of north Africa are often lumped together, and as far as I can see, this does Tunisia a great disservice.</p>
      <p sl="sv">There has been mention of equality. In comparison with many other Arab countries, Tunisia is exceptional in having legislation to protect children and also women. As has already been pointed out, Tunisia has more female students than male at its universities, and the standard of living has increased. The country’s infrastructure is in good condition. Since the election, its parliament has elected – or appointed – a committee on human rights.</p>
      <p sl="sv">Tunisia’s willingness to cooperate with the EU is an opportunity that we should grasp with both hands. Now that Tunisia has a delegation that is visiting Brussels and Strasbourg, and is asking for support in its work on promoting human rights and with developing and deepening its links with the EU, in my opinion, it would be contrary to the EU’s principles not to give these requests a positive reception and develop relations further.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-028" speaker_id="96886" name="Rosario CROCETTA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Italy" birth_date="08-02-1951" birth_place="Gela" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, as someone who has visited Tunisia two to three times per year since 1982 and who, as a Catholic, on 6 January attended mass, as I regularly do, I find it truly difficult to think of Tunisia as a country which suppresses religious freedom.</p>
      <p sl="it">There are problems, but for Heaven’s sake let us not to look at these countries, countries which are trying to make progress, through the prism of Western countries, because if we were to use that parameter, a parameter which someone is using this morning with regard to Tunisia, then certain European countries would probably be denied entry into the European Union, because the violence and denial of freedom which exists there is on a greater scale than in Tunisia.</p>
      <p sl="it">Thus, the issue arises as a result of one concrete fact: namely, that we have before us a country which has abolished Islamic fundamentalism, which is making efforts to develop a cooperation and peace policy with Europe, which is trying to evolve. There are problems. I believe that the way to solve these problems is to strengthen dialogue and friendship and to help these countries to achieve more.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-029" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neelie Kroes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I am grateful to the honourable Members for being so open and straightforward and for making their remarks in such a way that, although certain groups have differing approaches, the emphasis is on how we can find a solution.</p>
      <p sl="en">Having said that, I want to start by making one remark in answer to the statement made by Mr Désir. He referred to a remark by Louis Michel. I am sure that Louis Michel can speak for himself, but we were on the same team in a former life, so to say, so I know what line he takes on this issue. If Mr Désir is saying that the suggestion is that we do nothing, that is not the impression I got, and I sincerely hope that you did not get that impression from my opening remarks either.</p>
      <p sl="en">There is indeed a difference in approach. Some are just calling for dialogue on an equal footing, and Mr Kasoulides advocates that. There have been calls for links of friendship. All these approaches imply sitting around a table discussing issues and trying to reach a mutual understanding on how to solve a couple of issues that we all agree on. There is no doubt about that, for human rights and freedom of speech are indeed a very important and essential part of any agreement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Having said that, I would like to touch upon a couple of the issues that were raised. Firstly, reinforced institutions. What we are trying to promote and encourage in all the meetings that are held or planned over the coming months is the establishment of a regular dialogue as a means of achieving essential progress in terms of human rights and democracy.</p>
      <p sl="en">In the course of the next couple of months, there will be a meeting of the Subcommittee on Human Rights, and you can be sure that there will be a dialogue of substance, which will deal with the issues that we are all concerned about and how to approach them.</p>
      <p sl="en">On the question of human rights violations in Tunisia, speakers have regularly referred to the fact that Tunisia has been criticised for its record on human rights. Since the presidential and legislative elections of October last year, there has been an intensification of repression against opposition parties, journalists and human rights activists. The international community has made it quite clear that that type of behaviour by the authorities is unacceptable and contrary to Tunisia’s international commitments. So, to reiterate what I have said already, within the EU, there should be no misunderstanding: commitments are commitments, and we have to maintain that line.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tunisia must indeed show stronger commitment to fundamental common values such as respect for human rights, democracy and the rule of law. It should, by the way, also respect its own international commitments in that field. The Commission will pursue our policy of engagement and dialogue on those issues, particularly in the framework of the bodies created by the association agreement.</p>
      <p sl="en">At the same time, the EU is providing support in order to improve governance and promote reforms in the field of justice through cooperation and technical assistance. It is our priority to make progress with Tunisia in that area, for example, by actively promoting human rights activists and civil society organisations under the European Instrument for Democracy and Human Rights.</p>
      <p sl="en">Efforts are also being made in the field of judicial cooperation The EU is providing EUR 17.5 million to fund a technical assistance project for the modernisation of the judiciary. That has been criticised by some Members of this Chamber because it provides funds for the President of Tunisia’s justice system.</p>
      <p sl="en">The project has many components. These include training for judges and lawyers, technical support for the courts, infrastructure and improved information for citizens. When the project is complete, we will assess the outcome. I certainly agree that working in that area exposes us to certain political risks. Nonetheless, if we want to encourage reform, we need to act; otherwise, EU cooperation will be confined only to the economic sector. We all agree that that is not the right approach, and would be inconsistent with our own general policy objectives as regards relations with Tunisia.</p>
      <p sl="en">On the issue which Mrs Flautre and Mrs Vergiat were touching upon, the advanced status of Tunisia, I consider that priority should be given to the continuation and reinforcement of dialogue with Tunisia. We are aware that it is an important ally of the EU in the region and has achieved considerable progress in terms of economic and social modernisation. Perhaps it comes down to whether one regards the glass as half-full or half-empty. Having said that, we believe that we need to continue our policy of supporting those forces in Tunisia that are working for the political, economic and social modernisation of their country. We are in favour of Tunisia’s proposals with a view to strengthening the relationship between the two partners. The Council and the Commission will look into these issues very carefully, and I am prepared to report any further developments to you.</p>
      <p sl="en">On the other hand, while it is in the EU’s interest to reinforce relations with Tunisia, I consider that the granting of advanced status should entail strong commitment on the part of Tunisia in terms of human rights and governance, so there will be no ‘free lunch’.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-030" speaker_id="28133" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Pál SCHMITT" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="13-05-1942" birth_place="Budapest" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 149)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-031" speaker_id="96671" name="Edward SCICLUNA" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Malta" birth_date="12-10-1946" birth_place="Naxxar" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="MT">
      <p sl="en">This debate seems to me to be untimely at a moment when the dialogue between Tunisia and the EU is resuming at both Commission and Parliament level. Dialogue with the Commission has included the programming of several subcommittees’ meetings within the framework of the Tunisia-EU Association Agreement (including the Human Rights and Democracy Subcommittee), while dialogue at the level of the European Parliament took the form of the recent visit to Brussels of an important Tunisian parliamentary delegation representing four political parties represented in the Tunisian Chamber of Deputies, along with the Tunisia-EP Interparliamentary Meeting scheduled for March 2010 in Brussels. At a time when important and constructive dialogue between Tunisia and the EU is resuming, I think it is unfortunate to have held a debate that could undermine progress. Let us ensure that Tunisia and other non-EU states conform to EU standards in the economic, social or political sphere. But let us do that in a well-planned and structured dialogue.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Debates on cases of breaches of human rights, democracy and the rule of law"/>
  <section id="creitem4" title="3.1. Recent attacks on religious minorities in Egypt and in Malaysia">
    <intervention id="4-034" speaker_id="28133" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Pál SCHMITT" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="13-05-1942" birth_place="Budapest" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the debate on the motion for a resolution on the recent attacks against religious minorities in Egypt and Malaysia .</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-035" speaker_id="96945" name="Marietje SCHAAKE" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Netherlands" birth_date="28-10-1978" birth_place="Leiden" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="NL">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, in the week of Egyptian Orthodox Christmas, an attack took place killing and wounding 20 Coptic Egyptians. Although the attack can be seen as a criminal act of individuals, various other troubling incidents require our ongoing focus on respect for all minorities in Egypt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Violence and hatred cannot be accepted in the name of religion. People have a universal right to freedom of religion as well as freedom from religion. Ethnic and religious diversity asks for a vigilant society that is able to reconcile differences in open debate, a society where people of any background or conviction know that their freedoms are guaranteed.</p>
      <p sl="en">An open society can only be realised when the separation of religion and state is implemented in the constitution and throughout the system of government. Security measures cannot be the only means to manage a pluralist society. Yet state emergency laws have been in place in Egypt for the past 28 years. A free debate is perhaps the most powerful medicine against extremism and violence. Therefore, freedom of expression, both online and offline, can be seen as the Egyptian Government’s best tool to resolve tensions in society.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is therefore very difficult to understand or accept that around 30 activists, politicians and bloggers were arrested by government forces while travelling to the southern Egyptian town of Nag Hammadi to express their condolences to the families of those killed during the sectarian violence. The arrests are a particularly striking example of what has become a pattern of the Egyptian Government’s interference in citizens’ rights to freedom of expression.</p>
      <p sl="en">Something is desperately wrong when people are treated like criminals merely for attempting to show sympathy and solidarity with fellow countrymen. In too many cases, the argument of maintaining public order is abused. Since 2008, Egyptians have been unable to get an unregistered phone line, but the control is not total. New rules are now in force, under which users of Wi-Fi have to pay for a connection, for which they need to provide an e-mail address to have a password and a username sent. This allows for active control of users by the government. Moreover, a draft law is under debate in the parliament about net regulation, providing for prison sentences for ‘publication of multimedia content without government permission’.</p>
      <p sl="en">Yet the Egyptian Constitution says, ‘freedom of expression or freedom of opinion is guaranteed. Every individual has the right to express his opinion and to publicise it verbally or in writing or by photography or by other means within the limits of the law’. Self-criticism and constructive criticism are the guarantee for the safety of the national structure.</p>
      <p sl="en">I urge the Egyptian Government to refrain from introducing emergency laws limiting fundamental freedoms in light of the sectarian tensions present. An adequate response to crimes committed in the name of religion is only appropriate. However, this should not be used as a reason to repress the population as a whole, with laws limiting free speech and expression. Only when fundamental freedoms are safeguarded by the Constitution and all layers of legislation are free will an open society in Egypt be possible. The Egyptian Government should lead its citizens on this road to freedom, and Europe should be its strongest partner in this.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-036" speaker_id="96994" name="Fiorello PROVERA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Italy" birth_date="31-03-1946" birth_place="Vigevano" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, the resolution that I have tabled is in response to some tragic events which have recently taken place in Egypt and in other countries of the world – just yesterday in Nigeria – and is intended to bring to this House’s attention an increasingly serious and intolerable situation whereby members of the Christian community are being persecuted and killed.</p>
      <p sl="it">This is not a resolution against the Egyptian Government, which has acted to ensure that those responsible are brought to justice; rather, it is a time to reflect on a vast and concerning issue. Every year, thousands of Christians are killed around the world, in Vietnam, North Korea, China, Nigeria, Malaysia, and millions of others are persecuted in the most diverse ways for their faith on a daily basis. These attacks are increasing in number and in virulence, amid silence or indifference, and they warrant urgent action.</p>
      <p sl="it">First of all, everyone must make a commitment to change the climate of religious hatred which is spreading and to encourage tolerance and acceptance of diversity. Europe is well acquainted with the tragedy of wars in which, for centuries, Catholics and Protestants have fought against one another, not to mention the Jewish Holocaust. Precisely because of its history, Europe must commit itself on this front.</p>
      <p sl="it">Another initiative could be to examine national laws within the context of which we find rules which persecute Christians or other religious minorities. The cooperation of non-governmental organisations could be very useful in this project, but vigilance is also required to ensure that, where a right to religious freedom exists, it is actually implemented.</p>
      <p sl="it">This debate could be an opportunity to launch the proposal to draft a European Parliament report on religious freedom in the world.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-037" speaker_id="4393" name="Mario MAURO" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Italy" birth_date="24-07-1961" birth_place="S. Giovanni Rotondo" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, religious freedom is, in fact, the subject of this resolution. It is therefore not an identity crusade or an attempt to cause problems for this or that government, but a denunciation of the fact that, in today’s world, people are dying because they believe in Christ or are being discriminated against because their faith is different from someone else’s.</p>
      <p sl="it">All the political groups therefore agree that there is a problem concerning religious freedom and that it needs to be addressed seriously and firmly within the international community.</p>
      <p sl="it">We therefore ask the Council and the Commission and, above all, the High Representative for Foreign Affairs, to pay particular attention to the situation of minorities, including the Christian minority, so that initiatives aimed at promoting dialogue and respect between communities are supported and undertaken, urging all the religious authorities to encourage tolerance and to prevent episodes of hatred and violence from occurring.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-038" speaker_id="22097" name="Véronique DE KEYSER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Belgium" birth_date="23-03-1945" birth_place="Etterbeek" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament - Vice" m_state="BE">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, the incident that took place in Egypt could undoubtedly have happened elsewhere. A car passes by the doorway of a Coptic church, shots are fired into the crowd. The outcome: seven deaths (six Copts and one police officer). The Egyptian authorities react quickly. The public prosecutor decides – and I quote – that the three accused of the events in Nag Hammadi will be tried before the State Emergency Security Court on a charge of premeditated murder.</p>
      <p sl="fr">In Malaysia, it is the name Allah that the Christian and Muslim communities argue about, a dispute that results in the ransacking and pillaging of churches.</p>
      <p sl="fr">These news stories, which could be described as commonplace, have impacts elsewhere, throughout the world, including in Europe. The rise in religious intolerance and fanaticism jeopardises a fundamental freedom, freedom of belief for all, whether they are religious or agnostic. All over the world, crimes are being perpetrated against minorities, be they Christian, Jewish or Muslim. All over the world, too, non-religious men and women are being killed or imprisoned because they do not respect the rites, dogmas or religious practices from which they have freed themselves.</p>
      <p sl="fr">As a non-religious person, I firmly support this resolution, which is an appeal for tolerance and not a stigmatisation of Egypt or Malaysia. However, leaving aside the cases that have been mentioned, I would like to point out the responsibility of a state that is mindful of its citizens’ right to freedom of expression. I believe that a secular state, by virtue of its structure, is the greatest guarantee of the space required for a diversity of beliefs. This is the form in which a state can best protect its citizens and promote a dialogue between its communities.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-040" speaker_id="96796" name="Ryszard Antoni LEGUTKO" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Poland" birth_date="24-12-1949" birth_place="Kraków" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the information about violence against Christians in Egypt and Malaysia is just the tip of the iceberg. There are three points I want to raise.</p>
      <p sl="en">First, Christians have become the victims of brutal violence in many countries of the world, not just two. Second, Christians have become the single most persecuted religious group in the world. The numbers are astounding – in the millions, not thousands or hundreds of thousands. Third, the reaction of European societies, European governments and the EU has, so far, been unsatisfactory: timid, faint-hearted, pusillanimous, politically correct, or no reaction at all.</p>
      <p sl="en">We must act resolutely, or else those who persecute Christians will think they have our tacit blessing. Do we really want this?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-041" speaker_id="2054" name="Heidi HAUTALA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Finland" birth_date="14-11-1955" birth_place="Oulu" m_state="FI">
      <p sl="fi">Mr President, it is regrettable that there are so many different conflicts in the world dressed up in the guise of religion. In this connection, it has to be said that there are very many different fundamentalist trends in the world in connection with the Christian, Islamic and other religions. Personally, I have encountered fewer of these fundamentalist aspirations with Buddhism. In any case, it is important that the European Parliament adopts a position when these kinds of violent episodes between religious groups occur.</p>
      <p sl="fi">I would like to say, however, that yesterday it was brought to Parliament’s attention that 33 human rights defenders were arbitrarily arrested when they tried to support the Coptic Christians referred to in this resolution and who were suffering violence against them. I would now like to say to the Egyptian authorities that we need to ensure that people are not prevented in this way from coming to the defence of others. We must insist that human rights defenders in other situations are not imprisoned or treated unjustly. In this case, it is an undeniable fact that these 33 defenders of the Copts were treated inhumanely in prison. They were kept in inhumane conditions.</p>
      <p sl="fi">I hope that in future, Parliament will always give its attention to cases whenever there is violence against any religious group, and not just concentrate on the persecution of Christians.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-042" speaker_id="2229" name="Bernd POSSELT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group" nationality="Germany" birth_date="04-06-1956" birth_place="Pforzheim" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, Tunisia, Egypt and Malaysia have a great tradition of tolerance. Evidence of this is provided by names like Tunku Abdul Rahman, the founder of the independent state of Malaysia, or President Sadat, whose speech here in the European Parliament was like a Magna Carta for Christian-Islamic coexistence.</p>
      <p sl="de">This is precisely why we must support the governments of these countries in their fight against Islamic extremism and anti-Christian attacks. Of course, we in Europe, as a mainly Christian continent, have a special obligation to stand up for Christians throughout the world, because if we do not do so, who will?</p>
      <p sl="de">However, this is clearly about the freedom of religion itself and I would like, for example, to thank the Malaysian Government for the fact that His Majesty, the Yang di-Pertuan Agong, and the Prime Minister, made their position on this matter clear on 9 January. We wish them success in their fight for religious tolerance, for which this country was and still is a shining example, and it is something that, as partners who can speak openly on matters to do with human rights, we must preserve in Egypt, Tunisia and Malaysia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-043" speaker_id="96809" name="Peter van DALEN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ECR Group" nationality="Netherlands" birth_date="03-09-1958" birth_place="Zwijndrecht" m_state="NL">
      <p sl="nl">Mr President, freedom of religion is an essential element of human rights. Unfortunately, what we are seeing is that Christians have a particularly hard time in many countries where the faith of Islam dominates. That is the case, amongst other places, in Egypt. Coptic Orthodox Christians, but also Roman Catholic and Protestant Christians and Jews are placed at a disadvantage in an institutionalised way in Egypt. Muslims who convert to Christianity, for example, are oppressed. This can be seen from their identity papers, which continue to state that they are Muslims, as religious disaffiliation is legally prohibited.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Over the last 10 to 20 years, specifically, violence against Copts has grown enormously. More than 100 attacks, with thousands of victims, have already been reported. The Egyptian Government’s attitude, in my view, is spineless. Three men have been taken into custody, but, generally speaking, the violence against Christians is tolerated. I call on the Council and the Commission to engage Egypt directly in dialogue in order to ensure that the government there takes a different approach. If Cairo refuses to do so, I think that needs to have consequences for our bilateral relations with Egypt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-044" speaker_id="96669" name="Joe HIGGINS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group" nationality="Ireland" birth_date="20-05-1949" birth_place="Ciarraí" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="IE">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, all who are committed to democratic rights and freedom of religious expression will condemn outright the murder of Christians in Egypt and also the firebomb attacks on Christian churches in Malaysia. We should also note the growing numbers of attacks on religious minorities in Europe itself and equally condemn that.</p>
      <p sl="en">In Malaysia, the tactic of divide and rule on racial and religious lines has long been used by various elements of the economic and ruling elites. The present National Front government is guilty of hypocrisy in this regard: while publicly proclaiming a ‘One Malaysia’ policy claiming to embrace all religions and minorities, it manoeuvres behind the scenes, using religious and racial divisions to try and bolster its own position among the majority Muslim Malay population, as it did in relation to the ‘Allah’ ruling.</p>
      <p sl="en">There are also huge divisions economically in Malaysia. It is the most unequal society in South-East Asia. The current government rules on the basis of crony capitalism. This is the result, with exploitation rife in the workplace and trade union rights severely limited. The best background for religious freedom and democracy in Egypt and Malaysia and elsewhere is, indeed, economic justice and democracy, where wealth and power are in the hands of the big majority of working people and the poor and removed from major corporations and crony capitalists.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-045" speaker_id="96946" name="Daniël van der STOEP" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Netherlands" birth_date="12-09-1980" birth_place="Delft" p_group="Non" m_state="NL">
      <p sl="nl">Mr President, yesterday, a terrible political trial began in the Netherlands against the leader of our party, Geert Wilders. Mr Wilders, as a Dutch parliamentarian and leader of the Party for Freedom in the Dutch Parliament, is being prosecuted for expressing his opinion. Mr Wilders is being persecuted by the leftist elite because he warns the Netherlands, Europe and the world about a fascist ideology that goes by the name of Islam. This is an outrageous disgrace!</p>
      <p sl="nl">Mr President, the Islamification of the Netherlands and of Europe threatens Europe’s Judeo-Christian and humanistic culture, and where many, including in this House, bend over backwards and allow the tsunami of Islamification to wash over them, the Party for Freedom fights for European culture. Mr President, the barbaric acts that have taken place in Malaysia, Egypt and in many other places around the world, as just this week in Nigeria, are the result of the intolerant and fascist ideology known as Islam. In Islamic countries, non-Muslims are systematically humiliated and murdered. The events in Malaysia and Egypt cannot be regarded as isolated incidents, but have their origin in the ideology that demands respect but does not give it. This Parliament can ensure that these terrible events never take place in Europe by taking up the fight, alongside the Party for Freedom, against the Islamification of Europe. We ask all of you to do so.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-046" speaker_id="28280" name="Filip KACZMAREK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="22-11-1966" birth_place="Poznań" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, quite often in Parliament, we talk about different phobias and their detrimental social effects. I am thinking of xenophobia and homophobia. Unfortunately, these two cases do not exhaust the list of phobias. There is also a phenomenon called ‘Christianophobia’ – a phobia of Christianity. Just as in the case of other phobias, the social effects here are also detrimental and sometimes tragic, and it is precisely for this reason that we should take up cases of violations of the rights of Christians in different places around the world.</p>
      <p sl="pl">We take up cases involving followers of different religions, and even of people who do not profess any religion. Christians, too, must not be deprived of our care. We do this because religious freedom is one of the European Union’s fundamental values. It is precisely for this reason that we condemn and will condemn every form of violence, discrimination and intolerance towards the leaders or adherents of any religion. Violence perpetrated because of the beliefs of the victim is abominable and there is no doubt that it deserves our criticism.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-047" speaker_id="28358" name="Konrad SZYMAŃSKI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="06-12-1969" birth_place="Kalisz" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, religious freedom is a right which has been acknowledged in international and European conventions on human rights for over 50 years. At the same time, we have, for many years, been facing a rising wave of religious hatred, which has most often affected Christians all over the world. The place of anti-Christian Communism has today been taken principally by militant Islam. Egypt and Malaysia have constitutional guarantees of religious freedom, but under pressure from radical Islamic circles, the religious freedom of Christians is not being sufficiently protected by the governments there.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The European Union, which has new instruments of foreign policy at its disposal, must become involved, to a greater degree, in opposing Christophobia, which is the source of beatings, looting and murders. It is only ideological prejudice which causes the European Union to do this, today, with hesitation. At stake is our credibility.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-048" speaker_id="28299" name="Bogusław SONIK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="03-12-1953" birth_place="Kraków" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, I would like to support the idea of my fellow Member, Mr Provera, who said that a report should be drawn up on religious freedom. I would like to remind everyone that in the previous parliamentary term, Mr Mauro and I submitted a proposal to draft a report on the situation of Christians in countries where they are a minority, in countries where Islam is the dominant religion. Unfortunately, the Bureau did not adopt the proposal, but perhaps such a report would be worth writing. Here, I make the same proposal again.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The resolution we are adopting today should give a clear message. The Coptic minority makes up 10% of Egypt’s population, but even if it were only 0.5%, the role of the European Parliament is to react, especially in a situation in which human rights are being violated so drastically.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I read carefully the letter sent to Mr Buzek by the Marshal of the People’s Assembly. In the letter, he gives his assurance that the events of which I have spoken were isolated incidents. I find this difficult to believe. The Copts have been persecuted in Egypt for many years. Let us try, this time, to ensure that our help for this oppressed minority does not end with empty declarations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-049" speaker_id="28372" name="Ryszard CZARNECKI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="25-01-1963" birth_place="Londyn " m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, it is not only Egypt, and it is not only Malaysia, but also Sudan, Nigeria and many other countries in Africa, many countries in Asia and many societies which treat Christians as a necessary evil, and sometimes as an enemy. Let us not hide these facts, let us not act like an ostrich, which buries its head in the sand. This is a real problem, and the Parliament of a Christian Europe, Christian traditions and a Christian heritage must speak about it.</p>
      <p sl="pl">However, we should also beat our own breast. A moment ago, the Member who spoke before me rightly spoke of Parliament’s sins of omission in the previous term. I recall the debate we had a few weeks ago, when we rightly condemned the attacks and the oppression experienced by the Uighur Muslim minority in China. However, at that time, certain political groups rejected amendments which were intended to emphasise that Christians are suffering in China, too, and are the victims of discrimination. We cannot allow a situation in which we defend some religious minorities but defend others less or not at all.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-050" speaker_id="4260" name="Eija-Riitta KORHOLA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Finland" birth_date="15-06-1959" birth_place="Lahti" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="FI">
      <p sl="fi">Mr President, we have heard worrying news from a number of sources about crimes against Christians in Egypt and Malaysia. With regard to Malaysia, I would first of all like to say that we are deeply concerned about the attacks on churches in what has traditionally been a tolerant and moderate country.</p>
      <p sl="fi">Secondly, I wish to mention the exemplary work of Islamic NGOs on behalf of religious tolerance. The Malaysian Prime Minister’s statements about using the name of Allah triggered a show of public discontent targeted at Christian communities. The exemplary attitude on the part of Islamic NGOs and an uncompromising public stance on the statements by the Prime Minister have nevertheless calmed the situation. It is unfortunate that we did not have it recorded in our final resolution, because in my view, we pay attention too rarely here to positive situations. Should not Muslims also be lauded when there is cause to do so?</p>
      <p sl="fi">Religious tolerance needs to be promoted both by those that hold political power and at grassroots level. It is equally important to realise that there have been failures as it is to acknowledge progress and offer support for it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-051" speaker_id="1759" name="Dominique BAUDIS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="France" birth_date="14-04-1947" birth_place="Paris" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, the acts of fanatic criminals, who have killed some Christians in Egypt, cannot be ascribed to an entire population and its government. It would be unfair to hold Egypt and the Egyptians responsible for this appalling massacre, for which the perpetrators will be brought to justice.</p>
      <p sl="fr">We must not confuse the acts of one criminal with the policy of an entire country! Let us not tar fanatics and an entire population with the same brush. Finally, by seeking to intervene between the Coptic Christians and their fellow Muslim citizens, we are adding fuel to the fire of the extremists, who want to portray Eastern Christians as agents of the West.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-052" speaker_id="39726" name="László TŐKÉS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="01-04-1952" birth_place="Cluj" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="hu">There is very recent news that a few days ago, the Egyptian regime arrested several Coptic rights activists who were travelling to the site of the crimes that took place at the Nag Hammadi settlement in order to defend and support the Coptic Christian communities there who had seen several of their members murdered on Christmas Day. The Egyptian authorities, partial towards the Muslim majority, are trying to downplay the violent acts committed against the Coptic minority, and are now blocking the Christians’ lawful self-defence with discriminatory bias towards one side of the issue. The United States administration has unequivocally spoken up against this. Knowing that the Coptic Christian community, who are considered native Egyptians, have, for over 1 500 years, often been subjected to cruel oppression, the European Union must step up in its defence even more forcefully and unambiguously than it is doing at present.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-053" speaker_id="23894" name="Anna ZÁBORSKÁ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="07-06-1948" birth_place="Zürich" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="sk">Thank you for bringing attention again to the breaches of religious freedom in certain countries, just like back in 2007 and 2008. I wonder whether it is the EU’s weakness or indifference that prevents it from promoting the observance of human rights in this area more consistently. We keep hearing the same complaints and proposing the same measures.</p>
      <p sl="sk">Egypt and Malaysia are among those countries where Christians live in extremely dangerous conditions, face persecution, expulsion from their homes, abductions and murders, and their churches are being closed. This is happening from the Maghreb to Iran, in India, China, Pakistan, and many other countries. Christians are usually persecuted by extremist groups. However, this presents a danger to all Christians, Jews and Muslims. I request that representatives of the EU and delegations of the European Parliament make use of every opportunity to improve dialogue, religious tolerance and respect, and the coexistence of different cultures.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-054" speaker_id="96686" name="Mitro REPO" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Finland" birth_date="03-09-1958" birth_place="Heksinki" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="FI">
      <p sl="fi">Mr President, I am especially worried about the situation in Egypt because of the historical, ethnic and political background connected with it. Actually, the Coptic Christians are still a considerable minority. In Egypt, around 10% of the population, eight million, are Coptic Christians, and it is for that precise reason that they are a former majority. They are proud of this and also of their oriental Christian tradition. This is why the provocation that occurred at the Christmas celebrations last January was particularly blatant and premeditated. Furthermore, many Copts have been pressurised through violence to change their beliefs and there have been cases of rape and other crimes.</p>
      <p sl="fi">The situation in Egypt is a very bad example for other countries where there is a chance of the same sort of spiral of revenge taking place, and that is precisely why the EU has to be vigilant, intervene immediately when there is trouble, and stress the importance of peaceful dialogue between religious groups.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-055" speaker_id="97019" name="Ivo VAJGL" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovenia" birth_date="03-03-1943" birth_place="Maribor" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="SI">
      <p sl="sl">When a murder takes place, in particular, a religiously motivated one, we naturally can do little but recoil in horror and condemn it.</p>
      <p sl="sl">However, this new incident and this new crime in the Middle East is, in fact, evidence of general developments and ongoing intolerance of religious freedom and lack of respect for those who are different. That is to say, there are many quarters where religious values are not respected.</p>
      <p sl="sl">The reason why the Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe has proposed that this debate be postponed, or rather, that debates on the respect of human rights and religious freedoms in Egypt and Malaysia be held separately, is that we need to deal with this issue with a great deal of sensitivity and address every country individually. Egypt is certainly not one of the worst examples of religious intolerance. Quite the contrary.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-056" speaker_id="4521" name="Charles TANNOCK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="25-09-1957" birth_place="Aldershot" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, sadly, there has been a general climate in the Islamic world of increasing jihadi militancy aimed at non-Muslim communities in their midst – in particular, and more often than not, this means the Christians.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Copts, who represent one of the oldest Christian churches in the world, have a large diaspora in London, which I represent. Their leaders have come to me and complained of a worsening situation, regrettably, in Egypt, orchestrated by the Muslim Brotherhood. In spite of the best efforts by President Mubarak’s government to protect them, matters have deteriorated.</p>
      <p sl="en">We witness a similar story with the Assyrian Christians in Iraq, the Christians of Palestine and Pakistan, and now, as we see for the first time, even in Malaysia.</p>
      <p sl="en">This House has – for too long, in my view – ignored Christian minority rights in the rest of the world, but they look to the European Union and to the United States for protection. So I welcome this resolution.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-057" speaker_id="28497" name="Gerard BATTEN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="27-03-1954" birth_place="London" p_group="Europe of Freedom and Direct Democracy Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the persecution of Christians and other religious minorities is growing in Islamic countries. Christians who have lived in countries such as Egypt and in the Mediterranean area for almost 2 000 years are increasingly being persecuted and driven out of their ancestral homelands. This is because of the growing power of intolerant fundamentalist and extremist Islamist ideology – Islamo-fascism.</p>
      <p sl="en">The persecution of Christian minorities and others across the Islamic world is vastly under-reported by the West’s media. The media should not only report the persecution as it happens but they should explain to the general public the reasons why it is happening. They should explain who is doing this, namely Muslim fanatics, and why they are doing it – because of the intolerant and violent fault lines in Islamic ideology.</p>
      <p sl="en">Democratic governments worldwide should put maximum diplomatic pressure on countries such as Egypt to suppress this intolerable persecution.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-058" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neelie Kroes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the Commission is deeply shocked and saddened by what happened on Coptic Christmas Eve in Nag Hammadi in southern Egypt, the tragic deaths of six Copts and a Muslim policeman in a drive-by shooting.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are positive that the authorities took rapid action to find and arrest those suspected of committing this awful crime, and a thorough investigation and bringing those responsible to justice will send a clear signal that violence based on religious influence is not acceptable in Egyptian society.</p>
      <p sl="en">Egypt’s Constitution provides for freedom of belief and free practice of religion. However, we do hear complaints of discrimination against the Copts and against other religious minorities such as the Bahá’í in the workplace and by the judicial system. We are aware of difficulties encountered by several Christian converts, such as Maher El-Gohary and Mohammed Hegazy, in Egyptian courts. We raised those issues in our regular political dialogue with Egypt.</p>
      <p sl="en">We understand that the government is seeking to address some of the grievances of the Copts, for instance, by removing the obstacles that delay and limit the building and refurbishment of churches. We welcome and encourage such moves and urge the government to identify and tackle the root causes of religious tensions in Egyptian society and to end all forms of discrimination against those belonging to other religions.</p>
      <p sl="en">The acts of vandalism against churches in Malaysia following a High Court ruling on the use of the word ‘Allah’ give rise to serious concerns. The government, as well as the opposition, including the Pan-Malaysian Islamic Party and 130 Muslim NGOs, have all strongly condemned those attacks. The government has increased security measures to safeguard all places of worship and has also reconfirmed its commitment to protect Malaysia’s social and religious harmony and a culture of religious and ethnic diversity.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Malaysian Federal Constitution states that Islam is the religion of the Federation but other religions may be practised in peace and in harmony in any part of the Federation.</p>
      <p sl="en">We encourage the authorities to initiate as soon as possible an all-encompassing inter-faith dialogue with all religious beliefs to promote mutual understanding so that Malaysia can continue to develop peacefully in ethnic and social harmony. In that regard, the Malaysian Home Ministry has a particular responsibility to explain thoroughly and objectively to its citizens the issue at stake.</p>
      <p sl="en">We strongly condemn all acts of intolerance against any person because of his religion of belief wherever they occur. Unfortunately, no country is immune from this. We call on public authorities to fully protect all religious communities, including Christians, from discrimination and from repression.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission gives high priority to freedom of religion or belief as central tenets of the EU’s human rights policy by raising the issue in political dialogue with countries where the problem persists, by supporting local human rights projects and by actively promoting freedom of religion or belief at the UN forums.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-059" speaker_id="4308" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Alejo VIDAL-QUADRAS" nationality="Spain" birth_date="20-05-1945" birth_place="Barcelona" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place at 12.00.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 149)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-060" speaker_id="988" name="Carlo CASINI" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Italy" birth_date="04-03-1935" birth_place="Firenze" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, in voting in favour of the joint resolution, I am highlighting the particular seriousness of the violence carried out in Malaysia in response to an exclusively nominalistic issue.</p>
      <p sl="it">Indeed, it is certain that both Christians and Muslims believe in only one God, who is the God of all men, believers and non-believers alike. The fact that He is referred to by different names is absolutely secondary. To claim that the Muslim God is only Muslim and can therefore be invoked only by Muslims, using a traditionally Muslim name, means returning to the ancestral and tribal view that there is a God for each group of human beings. In other words, it means contradicting the monotheistic idea that makes universal religions which, like Christianity and Islam, oppose idolatry and polytheism, great religions that are close to people.</p>
      <p sl="it">No less serious is the persecution of the Copts in Egypt. It was on the shores of the Mediterranean that monotheistic religions, which claim to be, and are, forces for promoting brotherhood and peace, were born. However, it is remarkable that it should be precisely on the shores of the Mediterranean, in Jerusalem – a holy city for those who believe in God, Allah and Jehovah – that the main breeding ground for conflict is found.</p>
      <p sl="it">It is precisely Egypt that is the most powerful country in the area, where Christians and Muslims must coexist peacefully in order to play a peacemaking role throughout the southern Mediterranean area.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-999" speaker_id="28310" name="Edite ESTRELA" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="28-10-1949" birth_place="Belver" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">I support the joint motion for a resolution on the recent attacks against Christian communities because it strongly condemns all kinds of violence, discrimination or intolerance that is based on religion or beliefs. I think that it is vital to support all initiatives that are aimed at encouraging dialogue and mutual respect between communities and which seek to safeguard fundamental rights such as freedom of thought, conscience and religion.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-998" speaker_id="96977" name="Diogo FEIO" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="06-10-1970" birth_place="Porto" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">Men and women all over the world continue to suffer the most brutal forms of persecution simply because they believe in God in the same way that He is venerated from the Atlantic to the Ural Mountains. Following statements by China, India, Iraq, Pakistan, Turkey and Vietnam, among others, Parliament today condemned the harassment of Christians in Egypt and Malaysia.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Europe views all this with relative indifference. There are even those who defend this failure to act by invoking respect for other people’s culture and freedom to worship. Europe’s silence on this issue, truly astonishing in a region whose origins, culture and traditions are imbued with the Christian faith, threatens to become deafening …</p>
      <p sl="pt">This brings to mind the Cardinal Archbishop of Bologna’s comment on earlier persecutions, which aptly illustrate the spirit of our times, whereby he noted that people are quicker to worry about the fate of polar bears than about the thousands of Christians who live their lives under threat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-997" speaker_id="96795" name="Jacek Olgierd KURSKI" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Poland" birth_date="22-02-1966" birth_place="Gdańsk" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="en">Another year, 2010, has started with the bloody persecution of Christians in many parts of the world. We cannot, as the European Parliament, be passive in the face of these crimes and acts of violence. The situation of Christians is equally dramatic in countries not mentioned in today’s resolution, such as North Korea, Iraq, India and Sudan. Attacks on Catholics are increasing in Vietnam. As a Member from Poland, a country with a deep-rooted Christian tradition and a country with a long tradition of respect where many religious communities coexist, I would like to express solidarity with the families of the victims. The Egyptian and Malaysian authorities must guarantee Christians and members of other communities and religious minorities the possibility to enjoy all human rights and fundamental freedoms, or face sanctions from the European Union. For this reason, we should endorse the resolution on recent attacks on Christian communities.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-061" speaker_id="39724" name="Csaba SÓGOR" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Romania" birth_date="12-05-1964" birth_place="Arad" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="hu">The recent attacks against Christian communities in Egypt and Malaysia can be viewed from two different perspectives. First, we must emphasise that the European Union, as a community of European States that have reached a high level of democracy and the rule of law, must not, in the spirit of religious tolerance, human and minority rights, pass over such events in silence, regardless of where in the world they may occur. We must make it clear to governments that strive to continue to maintain good relations with us that Europe demands that the widely accepted norms of universal human rights be respected by its partners, and that the future development of relations can be affected by problems involving human rights. At the same time, we must not forget the infringements of human rights that occur on the territory of the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="hu">In some cases, religious tolerance, human and minority rights – including those of members of minority churches – need to be developed further in EU Member States as well. If Europe wants to set an example to the world, it cannot allow anyone on its territory to suffer discrimination for his or her religious convictions, ethnic origin or membership of a national minority. We can see that the legislation in force in Egypt similarly guarantees religious freedom, but in practice, the experience of Christians is that the opposite is the case. Unfortunately, we can find similar examples of a discrepancy between the law and daily practice in EU Member States as well.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem5" title="3.2. Human Rights violations in China, notably the case of Liu Xiaobo">
    <intervention id="4-063" speaker_id="4308" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Alejo VIDAL-QUADRAS" nationality="Spain" birth_date="20-05-1945" birth_place="Barcelona" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the debate on seven motions for resolution concerning violations of human rights in China, notably the case of Liu Xiaobo .</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-064" speaker_id="39713" name="Renate WEBER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Romania" birth_date="03-08-1955" birth_place="Botoşani" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, last month, Mr Liu Xiaobo, the very well-known writer and political activist, was sentenced to 11 years’ imprisonment for ‘incitement to subvert state power’. He was arrested over a year ago after drafting Charter 08, a charter which was signed by more than 10 000 ordinary Chinese citizens, demanding the most normal things in a democratic society: the right to free speech, open elections and rule of law.</p>
      <p sl="en">The prosecution of Mr Liu Xiaobo, based solely on his peaceful initiatives, and the judicial harassment he faced are undoubtedly incompatible with internationally acknowledged norms of human rights and fundamental freedoms. Therefore, we should call strongly for Mr Liu Xiaobo’s unconditional release, which should take place immediately.</p>
      <p sl="en">In the last few years, relations between the European Union and China have focused mainly on the economic dimension, which has overshadowed the country’s democratic record and the gross human rights violations which have systematically occurred in China.</p>
      <p sl="en">A few days ago, for the first time, a police official admitted that the famous human rights lawyer and 2008 Nobel Peace Prize nominee, Mr Gao Zhisheng, had gone missing after a year in the Chinese authorities’ custody. Many people fear that he might be dead. A few weeks ago, the Chinese Government disregarded an EU appeal not to execute a British citizen.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is particularly disturbing to see how the Chinese Government ignores its international commitments in the field of human rights. One is entitled to wonder why, under these circumstances, China submitted its candidacy to the UN Human Rights Council – was it simply to legitimise the way it suppresses human rights?</p>
      <p sl="en">In April 2009, the Chinese Government issued a national human rights plan, a lengthy document which appears to be nothing but a piece of paper. There must be no doubt. This House, the European Parliament, has the obligation to thoroughly evaluate the results of the EU-China human rights dialogue.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-065" speaker_id="28424" name="Tunne KELAM" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Estonia" birth_date="10-07-1936" birth_place="Taheva" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="EE">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, China has demonstrated impressive economic progress. However, part of this progress has been achieved by the use of methods that are in flagrant conflict with universally accepted human norms. Hopes that events like the Olympic Games would motivate the Chinese authorities to show more respect for democratic norms have proven to be in vain. On the contrary, acts of repression have increased and we need to draw conclusions from this fact.</p>
      <p sl="en">Today, the European Parliament voices concern over the fate of the prominent human rights activist and scholar, Liu Xiaobo, signatory of Charter 08, which urges constitutional reform and the safeguarding of human rights. This Charter has been bravely co-signed by more than 10 000 Chinese citizens. Last month, Liu Xiaobo was sentenced to 11 years’ imprisonment. We ask today for his immediate and unconditional release. We express our solidarity with the peaceful actions of Chinese citizens in favour of democratic reforms and the safeguarding of human rights, to which the Chinese Government has committed itself.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-066" speaker_id="22097" name="Véronique DE KEYSER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Belgium" birth_date="23-03-1945" birth_place="Etterbeek" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament - Vice" m_state="BE">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, urgent resolutions are always a difficult exercise because more often than not, they reflect political impotence rather than a humanitarian emergency. The naming and shaming strategy that we apply every month is a last resort. It clearly means that all the other means of dialogue or of exerting pressure have proved ineffective and that, finding ourselves powerless to act, we condemn.</p>
      <p sl="fr">In the case of China, I am not sure that increasing the number of urgent resolutions as we have been doing – in March 2009, in November 2009, in January 2010, and in March 2010, with the other planned resolution – is productive. This is not because I underestimate the difficulty that China is having in managing its transition towards democracy; it is because I believe that, in constantly being on the offensive, it is not the target that is wrong but the strategy. There are other more convincing political tools.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I was the first person to request resolutions on the Uighurs and to harbour the sadly vain hope that capital punishments would in this way be avoided. On behalf of our group, I would like to give my support to Liu Xiaobo, the recently convicted Tiananmen dissident, whose only crime is his passion for democracy. However, I refuse to pillory China every two months, quite simply because that will not make it give in. Quite the contrary, in fact, because this key trade partner, this country which has a permanent seat on the United Nations Security Council, which is seeing intensive growth and is in the midst of democratic change, which we need in order to combat climate change, this country must be a partner to which one tells a few home truths but which one respects for the efforts that it undertakes. It is this respect that is missing in the resolution.</p>
      <p sl="fr">It is for these political reasons that my group has withdrawn its signature. However, to ensure that there is no ambiguity on the issue of human rights, which I value at least as much as you do, my group will vote in favour of all the amendments that relate to it. As regards the final outcome of the vote, that will depend on the amendments that we have tabled.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-067" speaker_id="96858" name="Marie-Christine VERGIAT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="France" birth_date="23-09-1956" birth_place="Roanne" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, China is a large country with a rich history and with huge development potential. The hosting of the Olympic Games in Beijing last year did not have the results that some had expected.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The relationship that the European Union is able to maintain with China is of particular importance. It is our duty as MEPs to say loudly and clearly what we consider important and what is unacceptable.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The fact is, the human rights situation in China is unacceptable. The case of Mr Liu Xiaobo, found guilty of demanding democratic reforms in his country, along with more than 10 000 of his fellow citizens, exemplifies this. Dare I say that, in my opinion, making such mobilisation possible in that country is an achievement rather than a crime?</p>
      <p sl="fr">We must demand the release of Mr Xiaobo, and of all the men and women who, like him, are being harassed and imprisoned for having committed just one crime, that of defending human rights, and more specifically, one of the most fundamental of those rights, namely freedom of expression.</p>
      <p sl="fr">As one of my fellow Members said, just recently a British citizen was actually executed, despite the fact that he was mentally ill. This is the first time in more than 50 years that a European has been executed in China. Indeed, freedom of expression is being flouted a little more each day, as recently revealed to us by Google, which nonetheless has a reputation for being the operator that provides if not the best protection, then at least the least worst protection for Internet users.</p>
      <p sl="fr">It is common knowledge that, to establish themselves in China, operators must comply with the Chinese authorities’ request to install software filters, which even Google has ended up agreeing to do. We cannot accept a government engaging in Internet piracy and denying Internet users their freedom of expression.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The European institutions must join forces and take action on this matter. Chinese Internet users must be able to access uncensored information. The European Union has a duty to support Internet businesses that refuse to help the Chinese authorities to censor the Internet or, worse still, to arrest human rights defenders, democrats, or even journalists, as was the case with Mr Xiaobo in April 2005.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Finally, ladies and gentlemen, I cannot end my speech without asking you to remember the deaths in Tiananmen Square; many hundreds of young Chinese people met their deaths on the night of 3 June 1989. It was 20 years ago now, a sad anniversary which we would be honoured to commemorate by paying tribute to those young victims. Not all the events of 1989 have deserved the same attention, however.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-068" speaker_id="4521" name="Charles TANNOCK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="25-09-1957" birth_place="Aldershot" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the fact that yet again in this House, we are debating human rights abuses in China indicates that the Communist authoritarian leadership of Beijing remains determined to suppress any political dissent.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, that fact should not stop us from raising these issues in Parliament. I believe not only that we have a duty to do so, but that we owe it to the victims of human rights abuses in China such as Liu Xiaobo, most of whom have been denied a voice. This is why we are debating this matter again today.</p>
      <p sl="en">Indeed, the award of the Sakharov Prize in 2008 to Hu Jia showed the world how seriously we MEPs take the issue of human rights in China. We take it seriously because China really matters. Its vast size and global outreach, its military muscle and economic power compel the EU to seek a strategic partnership based on mutual respect and security.</p>
      <p sl="en">Perhaps eventually our relationship with China will also be based on our common values of democracy, human rights and the rule of law: we can but hope. I think all of us hope, nevertheless, to see the day when we will really see this in practice in the People’s Republic of China. It has been suggested that such ideals are somehow alien to Asia. I always look to democratic Taiwan and vast India with its democratic secular traditions, where these flourish in a free society, to basically put a lie to the idea that the PRC cannot be democratic.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-069" speaker_id="2054" name="Heidi HAUTALA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Finland" birth_date="14-11-1955" birth_place="Oulu" m_state="FI">
      <p sl="fi">Mr President, what is significant about the Liu Xiaobo case is that now as many as 10 000 people have openly expressed their support for him, and I think that the European Parliament should acknowledge the bravery of these people and praise them for it.</p>
      <p sl="fi">At the same time, we have to remind ourselves that China itself has given promises to improve the human rights situation. China tried to join the Human Rights Council saying that it would be committed to the promotion and protection of human rights and would uphold the highest standards in this area. Thus, these are China’s own promises before the United Nations and it is to these that we ought to refer.</p>
      <p sl="fi">This resolution also speaks of human rights dialogues between the EU and China, and however optimistic we would like to be, the end result is that they have hardly been of any benefit. The institutions of the European Union also need between them to think about how they can improve their own strategies and make China understand that its commitments in matters relating to human rights are our business too and that the future of cooperation between us depends crucially on them.</p>
      <p sl="fi">Finally, we might ask why the European Union’s policy on China is so incoherent and inconsistent, and what we can do about it. The European Parliament, for its part, will certainly support the Commission in a combined effort to establish a new strategy with China.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-070" speaker_id="96838" name="Cristian Dan PREDA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group" nationality="Romania" birth_date="26-10-1966" birth_place="Bucureşti" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">‘We should end the practice of viewing words as crimes’. This is what Liu Xiaobo asserted in Charter 08, the political manifesto which he launched and which was supported, as has already been said, by thousands of Chinese people. Liu Xiaobo has been sentenced to 11 years in prison and will be deprived of his political rights for a further two years for making such a statement and for continually supporting human rights. I believe that this punishment is symptomatic of the Chinese authorities stepping up their campaign against human rights activists. Further proof of this is highlighted by the announcement this Sunday that Tzu Yong Jun, a leader of the Tiananmen Square movement, was also sentenced to nine years in prison.</p>
      <p sl="ro">As a result, I believe that it is vital to raise the subject of human rights as part of the next European Union-China Summit, as specified in Article 9 of the resolution.</p>
      <p sl="ro">I believe, as also suggested by Mrs Hautala earlier, that dialogue is not sufficient for human rights. This human rights issue needs to be dealt with as part of summit meetings because dialogue has not yielded any results so far.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-071" speaker_id="96680" name="Zigmantas BALČYTIS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group" nationality="Lithuania" birth_date="16-11-1953" birth_place="Šilutė" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="LT">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the European Union is now negotiating a new framework agreement with China, which will set a further path for the development of economic relations with the country.</p>
      <p sl="en">Those relations are very tight, but we must not close our eyes before repeated human rights violations and with respect for the rule of law.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Union must strengthen the EU-China human rights dialogue. This dialogue, established in 2000, proved to be inefficient. The EU, and especially the High Representative, should ensure coordinated and effective EU common foreign policy towards China. Respect for human rights must serve as a basis for this policy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-072" speaker_id="28240" name="Helga TRÜPEL" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group" nationality="Germany" birth_date="21-07-1958" birth_place="Moers" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, when China was selected to host the Olympic Games, I initially hoped, after all China’s promises to improve the human rights situation, that this would perhaps actually happen.</p>
      <p sl="de">However, during and after the Olympic Games, we, unfortunately, had to admit that there was no improvement, but rather a worsening of the human rights situation. Now, following the judgment against Liu Xiaobo, we have even seen a homosexual party banned by the police, which clearly threatens to result in a political ice age in China for dissidents, human rights defenders and homosexuals.</p>
      <p sl="de">For this reason, we demand the immediate release of Liu Xiaobo and other human rights defenders and we call on China in particular – if it wishes to be a recognised partner in the international community – to put an end to its hysterical censorship measures and monitoring methods.</p>
      <p sl="de">This, of course, applies in particular to the Internet. We cannot accept political filtering of the Internet. It is an essential element of fundamental rights that the freedom of expression must be defended in all nations of the world. Human rights are universal and indivisible, whether here in Europe, in the US, in Sudan or in China. The People’s Republic of China will have to get used to that if it really wants a different role.</p>
      <p sl="de">I am firmly convinced that we, as Europeans, need to make it clear to China within the framework of our official relations at summits – precisely because we have an interest in cooperation in the areas of climate protection policy, environmental policy and regulation of the financial markets – that it urgently needs to change its human rights policy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-073" speaker_id="96993" name="Lorenzo FONTANA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the EFD Group" nationality="Italy" birth_date="10-04-1980" birth_place="Verona" p_group="Non" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, one of the most significant problems regarding human rights in China is the exploitation of forced labour in the Laogai, the Chinese concentration camps.</p>
      <p sl="it">This issue, apart from being a true form of modern slavery, specifically concerns the European economy. It is, in fact, certain that very many goods coming out of the Chinese market are produced by detainees in the Laogai, with an obvious slashing of labour costs that leads to unfair competition with respect to European goods.</p>
      <p sl="it">Going by the experience, also, of the United States, which has already passed certain laws prohibiting the import of Chinese goods produced in the Laogai, Europe can and should do everything possible to prevent the entry of goods produced wholly or partially by forced labour.</p>
      <p sl="it">Firstly, a campaign should be conducted to raise public awareness about this issue; and secondly, the same hygiene and safety parameters that are required of European products should be demanded of all products imported into Europe, and legislation on labelling should be introduced to ensure the traceability of goods.</p>
      <p sl="it">Moreover, entrepreneurs who invest in China must be asked to follow precise rules regarding workers’ rights. Finally, we need to establish rules and, above all, ensure that they are respected so that there is an absolute ban on the import of goods produced by forced labour.</p>
      <p sl="it">I am convinced that this is the only way we can genuinely help the Chinese people in their fight for human rights. If this does not happen, we will remain accomplices who wish to deny these people their freedom.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-074" speaker_id="1405" name="Edward MCMILLAN-SCOTT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="15-08-1949" birth_place="Cambridge" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I have the honour to be the European Parliament’s Vice-President responsible for democracy and human rights. Rightly, the resolution focuses on Liu Xiaobo, the principal author of Charter 08. An English version is available on my website charter08.eu.</p>
      <p sl="en">After my last visit to Beijing in May 2006, all the dissidents with whom I had contact were arrested, imprisoned and, in some cases, tortured; Hu Jia, for example, who is still in prison and needing medical treatment. In particular Gao Zhisheng, who reportedly has disappeared after three and a half years in prison, under house arrest and under torture, which caused him twice to try and commit suicide. Gao’s open letters to the regime in 2005 set the tone for Charter 08. His investigation into the persecution of the spiritual Buddhist group, Falun Gong, led to widespread support across China. I believe the authorities should now produce Gao Zhisheng and release him.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nobody should be in any doubt that the European Parliament will not give up on reform in China and, of course, in Tibet.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-075" speaker_id="4260" name="Eija-Riitta KORHOLA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Finland" birth_date="15-06-1959" birth_place="Lahti" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="FI">
      <p sl="fi">Mr President, it is intolerable that commercial interests should have drawn the longer straw in relations between the EU and China and that the insistence on respect for human rights and democratic development has been more or less put in the role of cordial greetings.</p>
      <p sl="fi">I have been following with interest the boldness showed by the search engine company, Google, and its plans to end cooperation with the Chinese authorities with regard to the filtering of Internet web pages and censorship, and even to leave the country. At the same time, Google is visibly calling for freedom of speech for Chinese Internet users.</p>
      <p sl="fi">I share the concern of my fellow Members regarding the treatment of Liu Xiaobo and other Chinese prisoners of conscience, and I hope that the Council and Commission will take up Xiaobo’s case at the next summit meeting between the EU and China. The agreements being negotiated right now should make it quite clear that the future development of commercial relations with China will be tied more effectively to political dialogue and a respect for human rights.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-076" speaker_id="96870" name="Gesine MEISSNER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="22-02-1952" birth_place="Uelzen" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, we have talked about various different things as regards what would be the right way to go about talking to China and putting it under pressure, because clearly, very little makes much of an impression on this country. Mrs De Keyser said that, for this reason, her group had withdrawn its signature. I do not think that that is the right way forwards. As the EU, which has enshrined human rights in the Charter of Fundamental Rights and in the Treaty of Lisbon, we of all people should keep on pointing out violations of fundamental human rights. There are no other options available to us at the moment. When we think of something better, I will be there straight away to give it my support.</p>
      <p sl="de">However, it is not only about Liu Xiaobo; it is also about Gao Zhisheng, who has disappeared and, from what we now hear, has allegedly committed suicide. Everyone assumes that he has probably been killed in one terrible way or another. That is not acceptable. In connection with the Olympic Games, we discovered that if we go to China and make contact there, absolutely nothing changes with regard to the human rights situation. We all hoped that it would, but it did not work. Therefore, we should not let up with our urgent appeals.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-077" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neelie Kroes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the EU has clearly expressed its deep concern at the disproportionate sentence against the prominent human rights defender Liu Xiaobo of 11 years’ imprisonment for his role as the author of Charter 08, a blueprint for democratic and rights-based reform in China, and for publishing a number of essays relating to human rights issues on the Internet.</p>
      <p sl="en">We attach great importance to freedom of thought and expression: cornerstones, as we are all aware, of our democratic system. The verdict against Mr Liu is entirely incompatible with the right to freedom of expression enshrined in the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, to which China is a signatory. We are also attached, by the way, to the protection of the right to sexual expression and orientation, as mentioned by Mrs Trüpel.</p>
      <p sl="en">The EU attempted to observe the trial, and we deeply regret that our observers were barred from the courtroom. The details of the trial, which we have nevertheless been able to learn, indicate clearly that Mr Liu was not afforded the opportunity to present a proper defence and that he did not receive a fair trial. The EU will continue to call on the Chinese Government to unconditionally release Mr Liu and to end the harassment and detention of other signatories of Charter 2008.</p>
      <p sl="en">Our overall policy towards China is one of constructive engagement in the framework of our strategic partnership. On several occasions in the past, we have welcomed China’s progress with regard to social and economic rights, as well as the recent launch of China’s human rights action plan, but, on the other hand, there are extremely serious concerns with regard to civil and political rights and a number of recent developments, such as those that the honourable Members of this House have raised in the draft resolution.</p>
      <p sl="en">The EU’s commitment to human rights is conveyed during our regular political contacts and, in particular, during our human rights dialogue with the Chinese authorities. The last session, as you are aware, was on 20 November last year in Beijing. The strength of our relationship allows us to discuss those matters frankly. Last year, at the 12th EU-China Summit in Nanjing, human rights were raised, both during the discussions and in the press conference.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mrs Vergiat and Mrs Korhola touched upon the cyber attacks against Google. The Commission thinks that this is another worrisome development in the framework of freedom of expression in China. We are obviously monitoring the situation closely. We understand that there are ongoing consultations between the company and the Chinese authorities. We will remain vigilant in case similar attacks target EU companies.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me reassure this House that we will continue to raise those issues, including at the highest level, recalling the international human rights obligations of the People’s Republic of China. We also recall the Chinese constitutional guarantees on freedom of expression. We all share the goal of a more open, transparent China, adhering to international standards on human rights and working together to address global challenges. To achieve this, we must continue to work on the development of our strategic partnership.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to react to a question from Mrs De Keyser. Regarding the execution of the British citizen, Akmal Shaikh, the European Union has condemned his execution in the strongest possible terms. It deeply regrets the fact that China did not heed repeated calls by the European Union and one of its Member States for the death sentenced passed against Mr Shaikh to be commuted.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-078" speaker_id="4308" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Alejo VIDAL-QUADRAS" nationality="Spain" birth_date="20-05-1945" birth_place="Barcelona" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place at 12.00.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 149)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-996" speaker_id="96857" name="Cătălin Sorin IVAN" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Romania" birth_date="23-12-1978" birth_place="Galaţi" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">The right to life, the right of free expression and thought form the bedrock of European integration and our world vision. When one of our partners, in this instance, China, repeatedly violates these rights, we are obliged to respond. However, we must not do it based on the ‘shame and blame’ model, and accuse China and ignore the differences in culture and civilisation which separate us. This resolution relating to the violation of human rights in China, particularly in the case of Liu Xiaobo, is proof of a simplistic approach to the issues which Chinese society is facing. We certainly did not adopt our position in the face of the principle of the inviolability of human rights underlying the resolution, which we wholeheartedly subscribe to. It was, in fact, about the way in which it was conveyed. In order to achieve the results we want, we need to maintain an atmosphere devoid of conflict between ourselves and China. This is the only way in which we can contribute to China’s development towards a society with a deep attachment to the importance of respect for human rights.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-079" speaker_id="28314" name="Anneli JÄÄTTEENMÄKI" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Finland" birth_date="11-02-1955" birth_place="Lapua" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="FI">
      <p sl="en">‘Don’t be evil’ is the well-known motto of Google. There has been criticism regarding their policy in China over the years, questioning the motto. Human rights groups have accused Google of helping the Chinese Government in repressing its citizens and particularly human rights activists. Apparently, Google will be less evil in the future. Their decision to start to operate an unfiltered search engine in China deserves the warmest congratulations. By announcing the change in their China policy, Google risks profits from the biggest Internet market in the world and potentially abandons almost 400 million users. In this particular case, Google has proved that a big multinational company can really stick to its ethics policy. Having its founders still aboard directing the company, Google has every chance of reflecting its core values and beliefs in its every action in the future. And, if Google continues to prosper, it will prove that there is no inherent conflict between making money and acting in a sustainable and humane way.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-995" speaker_id="96978" name="Nuno MELO" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="18-03-1966" birth_place="Joane" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">There have been recurring violations of human rights in China, and we cannot omit to condemn them. The fact that the EU is one of China’s main economic partners increases our responsibility to condemn all actions that violate the rights of any citizen, especially those who defend freedom of expression and human rights in this country. It is crucial that the People’s Republic of China respects and honours the commitments it made before the Human Rights Council.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-080" speaker_id="96652" name="Alajos MÉSZÁROS" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="18-06-1952" birth_place="Bratislava" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="sk">The larger a country is geographically, and the more independent it is economically, the more difficult it is to demand the observance of human rights by this country. I find it unacceptable that in its relations with China, the European Union keeps putting economic interests first. At almost every meeting at higher diplomatic levels, all we are able to do is to give a shy reminder of the issue of violations of human rights in this country. In Europe, unfortunately, we have had plenty of negative experiences with the practices of Communist regimes with respect to suppression of human rights. I am therefore convinced that the real number of violations of human rights is much higher than our information leads us to believe. For this reason, there is an urgent need for us to be able to make China respect human rights even at the cost of economic and political sacrifice. Otherwise, the developments in China may have an unfavourable impact on the overall developments in the political situation in Asia with subsequent impacts on the overall global economy and politics.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-081" speaker_id="96783" name="Wojciech Michał OLEJNICZAK" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Poland" birth_date="10-04-1974" birth_place="Łowicz" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="en">I voted in favour of the resolution condemning violations of human rights, because we must not tolerate or consent to their being broken, either as people or as citizens. Conduct which is harmful to people, their freedom and rights, which were defined many years ago, is contrary to the foundations on which Western democracies are built. The dialogue which was begun between the European Union and China in 2000 has not brought the expected effects. We should, therefore, ask ourselves if we have done everything we could have done, and if the answer is ‘no’, we should apply the provisions of resolutions on the effectiveness of economic cooperation. Human rights should become the basis for dialogue between the Union and China, and the interests of people should stand above economic interests.</p>
      <p sl="en">The arrest and sentencing of peace campaigner and human rights activist Liu Xiaobo, who has called for greater democracy in China, is a clear signal that our current measures are not effective. Therefore, it is worth taking other steps, apart from resolutions, which will make possible greater respect for what Liu Xiaobo is fighting for, as well as thousands of Chinese people and many other people around the world.</p>
      <p sl="en">Thirty years ago reforms were begun in China which showed the world that something was changing, that it may do something for the benefit of society. We expect the same today. We want, today, to have a partner which respects principles which, for us, are fundamental.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem6" title="3.3. Philippines">
    <intervention id="4-083" speaker_id="4308" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Alejo VIDAL-QUADRAS" nationality="Spain" birth_date="20-05-1945" birth_place="Barcelona" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the debate on six motions for resolution concerning the Philippines .</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-084" speaker_id="96994" name="Fiorello PROVERA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Italy" birth_date="31-03-1946" birth_place="Vigevano" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, the series of killings being carried out throughout the world for political, religious and other reasons is now sadly an everyday reality, but I am astounded by the cruelty with which 57 people were murdered whilst queuing at a political meeting to support a presidential candidate in the Philippines.</p>
      <p sl="it">This was a cold-blooded massacre carried out by an armed group in the name of a revolution of which it is difficult to make any sense. Moreover, this mass killing is not an isolated incident in this country where, in some regions, such as in the Mindanao region, armed uprisings – including those motivated by religion – have been taking place for years.</p>
      <p sl="it">Apart from duly expressing our condolences regarding these bloody events, I believe that we must offer our strong support to the Philippine Government so as to establish how Europe may be of use in resolving the serious armed conflicts and opposition which are bathing this unfortunate country in blood.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-085" speaker_id="25919" name="Martin KASTLER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Germany" birth_date="18-06-1974" birth_place="Nürnberg" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, the massacre on 23 November of last year in the Province of Maguindanao in the Philippines was a black day for human rights and a barbaric act of terrorism. Fifty seven people were killed, women were raped, people were injured – they convey a bloody message. As a journalist, it struck me, in particular, that there were 30 journalists among those killed. According to the renowned International Crisis Group, in no other case on record have more journalists ever been murdered at one time. For this reason, it is appropriate for the European Parliament to make a clear statement, as we are doing today in this draft resolution.</p>
      <p sl="de">However, as the Group of the European People’s Party (Christian Democrats), we request that the present text be toned down in three places through a split vote, because we ought to support the Philippine Government in its fight against terrorism and violence and therefore dispense with overly accusatory remarks directed at the government. Therefore, on behalf of the PPE Group, I request a separate vote on recital F. This accuses the Philippines of showing all the signs of a non-functional legal system.</p>
      <p sl="de">In paragraph 2, we would like to delete the insinuation about what are referred to as initial delays in the investigation.</p>
      <p sl="de">Finally, in paragraph 6, it is claimed that some missing persons are locked away in Philippine prisons. This, too, is currently an unproven insinuation and should, in our opinion, be deleted.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-086" speaker_id="4521" name="Charles TANNOCK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="25-09-1957" birth_place="Aldershot" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, this horrendous crime in Maguindanao is undoubtedly deserving of our strongest condemnation. It reveals the extent to which lawlessness has taken root in some parts of the Philippines.</p>
      <p sl="en">There are many reasons for this depressing development: the dispersed nature of the islands of the Philippines archipelago, the weak central government, corruption, poverty and an ongoing Islamist terrorist insurgency supported by al-Qaeda in the south.</p>
      <p sl="en">This crime, apparently politically motivated, therefore must be seen in its wider social and historical context. We should not disregard the efforts that the Philippine Government has made to develop a more democratic political culture in the past 25 years following the fall of the kleptocratic dictator Ferdinand Marcos. Nor should we underestimate the existentialist threat posed by the terrorists of Abu Sayyaf and how they are destabilising the whole of the society that makes up the Philippine state.</p>
      <p sl="en">Constructive engagement and targeted assistance offer the best chance of helping the Philippines, a country which shares our common values in many ways, in order to enable them to embed the rule of law in central and in local government.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-087" speaker_id="29579" name="Marc TARABELLA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Belgium" birth_date="11-03-1963" birth_place="Ougrée" m_state="BE">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, last November, I had the opportunity to welcome Mrs Edita Burgos, the mother of Jonas Burgos, to the European Parliament. This young Filipino was abducted by armed men in a very busy shopping centre in Manila on 28 April 2007. Since that day, neither his family nor his loved ones have had any news of him. Jonas Burgos is one of hundreds of people who have disappeared or been killed in the Philippines. Murders are committed with total impunity, and the perpetrators are very rarely brought to justice.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Looking ahead to the May 2010 elections, we are fearful of an increase in crime and of abductions of all those who are opposed to the government in power. As such, we condemn the Maguindanao massacre of 23 December last, and we hope that light will be shed on the murder and torture suffered by the Ismael Mangudadatu convoy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-088" speaker_id="96821" name="Rui TAVARES" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="29-07-1972" birth_place="Lisboa" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">Mr President, little more than two decades ago, the Philippines excited a great sense of hope around the world when they set off a democratic wave in Asia. This led us to harbour hopes for human rights in that area, and an increase in employees’ rights, students’ rights, the rights of the people and electoral and democratic normality in those countries.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Now that the world’s attention is directed elsewhere, we cannot leave the democratic situation in the Philippines to deteriorate. Over the last few years, there have been some very disturbing instances of corruption and, in particular, violence and harassment directed at the opposition during the elections.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The most disturbing event, and the subject of our resolution, was the Maguindanao massacre, the assassination of 46 people who had been following the electoral convoy of the opposition candidate Mr Mangudadatu. They were allegedly slaughtered by a group linked to the dominant clan in the province of Maguindanao, the Ampatuan clan.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Among other aspects, I would like to draw attention to the fact that 30 journalists were assassinated in this massacre. This makes it the greatest massacre of journalists in world history.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Apparently, the House itself is distracted from what we are discussing here, which is a shame, but we cannot allow the world’s distraction to let the Philippines slip into a situation where it goes from being the best example of democracy to being known as the worst, a mere two and a half decades down the line.</p>
      <p sl="pt">This massacre needs to be investigated and there needs to be a demand for President Gloria Arroyo, who belongs to the Ampatuan clan, to conduct the investigations through to their conclusion, as a matter of urgency. It is also important for the Philippines to know that Europe is alert and carefully watching developments in the country.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-089" speaker_id="96728" name="Barbara LOCHBIHLER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-05-1959" birth_place="Obergünzburg" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, the reason for this urgency is the brutal murder of 57 people, who were accompanying a politician on her way to register as a candidate in the elections for the position of provincial governor. The perpetrators belong to a local militia and some local police officers were involved.</p>
      <p sl="de">This brutal attack is an extreme example of the menacing rise in politically-motivated extrajudicial executions and the forced disappearance of people that has been going on for years without these serious crimes ever being investigated.</p>
      <p sl="de">The government has not shown any discernible will to take decisive steps to counter this development. Out of hundreds of cases, only two were investigated and not one senior official has been prosecuted in relation to these. In 2008, the UN Special Rapporteur on Extrajudicial Executions wrote that ‘These killings have eliminated civil society leaders, including human rights defenders, trade unionists and land reform advocates, intimidated a vast number of civil society actors, and narrowed the country’s political discourse.’</p>
      <p sl="de">This is the climate in which the Philippines is preparing for the elections in May. There is a danger of there being further political murders. It is therefore of the utmost urgency that the Philippine Government should take effective measures to put a stop to this.</p>
      <p sl="de">I would like to propose an oral amendment. Paragraph 6 states: ‘to release all disappeared persons who are still in captivity’. We would like to replace this with: ‘to make every effort to ensure that all who have been abducted are safely returned to their families.’</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-090" speaker_id="28279" name="Justas Vincas PALECKIS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group" nationality="Lithuania" birth_date="01-01-1942" birth_place="Samara " p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="LT">
      <p sl="lt">If a Central European citizen were asked what is happening in the Philippines, he probably would not be able to answer and would say that there is nothing about it on television, so things are probably calm there. However, political murders, clan warfare, people being buried alive, chainsaw massacres, a state of war − this is everyday life in the Philippines. Quite recently, 57 people were murdered, half of them journalists. That is the biggest ever death toll among journalists in the world. We call on the government, we demand that it immediately stop such occurrences, disband the private militias and finally put an end to impunity. This is particularly important during the upcoming elections.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-091" speaker_id="28377" name="Lidia Joanna GERINGER de OEDENBERG" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="12-09-1957" birth_place="Wrocław" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, presidential and local government elections are planned in the Philippines for 10 May. Now is the time to do everything to ensure they are fair elections. First of all, it is necessary to establish who was responsible for the murder, in November, of 57 journalists, family members and co-workers of Ismael Mangudadatu, a candidate for governor in the province of Mindanao. So far, local law enforcement agencies have not shown any determination in finding the perpetrators of this massacre. So many mistakes have been made in the investigation that it almost authorises the use of force in politics. The Philippine Government must, at last, face up to the people from the criminal world who have used the opportunity of recent election campaigns to make so many politically-motivated kidnappings and have now murdered over 100 candidates.</p>
      <p sl="pl">In addition, the Philippines should take steps to make efficient use of means available under the EU-Philippine Justice Support Programme, which has been established to strengthen the judicial system and build civil society. The elections in May will, therefore, not only be a check of the efficiency of the Philippine authorities, but also of the effectiveness of our aid instruments.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-092" speaker_id="28409" name="Raül ROMEVA i RUEDA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Spain" birth_date="12-03-1971" birth_place="Madrid" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance - Vice" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">Very briefly, I would simply like to say that we are in a new year, with a new Treaty, but with the same bad habits as before. We still miss the presence of the Council in this type of debate on urgent matters, and we also continue to miss this interinstitutional dialogue that should enable us to respond to this type of case.</p>
      <p sl="es">In the specific case of the Philippines, I must point out once again that, although this situation does not have the impact of others, such as Haiti, the fact that in the last decade, almost 1 000 people have disappeared or died means that there is a structural problem that requires structural measures.</p>
      <p sl="es">We cannot always be acting based on headlines. We need to act based on problems, and the fact that currently, the main people affected are human rights defenders and journalists means not only that we cannot pass over these situations in silence, but also that we need to act forcefully in response to them.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-093" speaker_id="28372" name="Ryszard CZARNECKI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="25-01-1963" birth_place="Londyn " m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, defence of human rights is the trademark of the European Union. I greatly regret that this trademark is not important to the Spanish Presidency, and that there are no representatives of the Council here at the moment. This is a very disturbing and downright scandalous situation. We are talking about human rights, we want to defend them, but there is no one here from the Council, and no representatives of the country which is leading the European Union for the next six months. This is, truly, an absolutely unacceptable situation.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I will be very brief, because we want to vote. The Philippines is a country with a Christian tradition going back to a culture which is, in part, European. In that country, especially, human rights should be respected, because they are often not respected in that continent. We must talk openly about this and show solidarity with all those who suffer discrimination in the Philippines. It is the role of the European Parliament to speak on this matter.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-094" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neelie Kroes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I am representing the High Commissioner and I am representing the Commission.</p>
      <p sl="en">The massacre in Maguindanao on the island of Mindanao on 23 November last year in which 57 people were killed has highlighted long-standing human rights issues in the Philippines related to the disappearance or unexplained killing of citizens and the effective impunity for the perpetrators in the past.</p>
      <p sl="en">On this occasion, the government has acted swiftly and has taken decisive action to prosecute the perpetrators. That is very welcome. It is important to break the culture of impunity about such killings and to put an end to them.</p>
      <p sl="en">The government has taken some important steps in strengthening human rights. The current administration of President Arroyo has abolished the death penalty and with ASEAN, has advocated including human rights provisions in the recently adopted ASEAN Charter.</p>
      <p sl="en">An objective still to be achieved is ending the 40-year-old conflict with Muslim rebels in Mindanao on the basis of a peace deal that is fair to all sides. There appears to be renewed progress, and hopes have risen for agreement later this year. It should be noted that the massacre in Maguindanao took place between political families – all Muslim by the way – and that, as such, it was not related to intercommunal conflicts.</p>
      <p sl="en">The EU has a well-established dialogue with the government of the Philippines where both sides discuss a wide range of issues, including human rights. We are also negotiating a PCA with the Philippines which will include important human rights commitments. We actively support the government in its efforts to improve respect for human rights.</p>
      <p sl="en">In agreement with the government, we have launched an ‘EU-Philippines Justice Assistance Mission’. This is a very timely action aimed at capacity-building for the Philippines judicial authorities, including police and military personnel, to help them investigate cases of extrajudicial killings and to prosecute those guilty of murder. We shall also put in place a monitoring system to develop confidence. EPJUST has an initial duration of 18 months and is funded under the Instrument for Stability, but can be extended. Furthermore, we have ongoing projects at local level to promote respect for human rights. These include monitoring of the implementation of international commitments, actions to support the ratification of the Rome Statute of the ICC and voter education.</p>
      <p sl="en">The EU is also helping in the Mindanao peace process for the moment, mainly through support for social services and confidence-building activities, but we stand ready to do more if the process advances.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-095" speaker_id="4308" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Alejo VIDAL-QUADRAS" nationality="Spain" birth_date="20-05-1945" birth_place="Barcelona" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed. The vote will take place next.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">I would like to remind Mrs Lochbihler to table her oral amendment at the correct time, during the vote.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem7" title="4. Announcement by the President: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem8" title="5. Calendar of part-sessions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem9" title="6. Approval of the minutes of the previous sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem10" title="7. Voting time"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="7.1. Recent attacks on religious minorities in Egypt and in Malaysia (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem12" title="7.2. Human Rights violations in China, notably the case of Liu Xiaobo (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem13" title="7.3. Philippines (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-104" speaker_id="96728" name="Barbara LOCHBIHLER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-05-1959" birth_place="Obergünzburg" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, we would like to replace the sentence in paragraph 6 which reads: ‘to release all disappeared who are still in captivity’.</p>
      <p sl="en">Instead we would like to introduce: ‘to make every effort to ensure that all who have been abducted are safety returned to their families’.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem14" title="7.4. European Strategy for the Danube Region (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem15" title="8. Explanations of vote">
    <intervention id="4-111" speaker_id="28280" name="Filip KACZMAREK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="22-11-1966" birth_place="Poznań" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, I voted in favour of the resolution on the European Strategy for the Danube Region, because I think the European Union needs such regional strategies. I am convinced that implementation of such strategies can have a very positive influence on regional development and, as a consequence, can influence the lives of the region’s residents and improve their quality of life. For surely it is the residents of the European Union who are the objective of our action – of Parliament’s and the European Union’s action. This is why I voted in favour of adopting the resolution.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-112" speaker_id="2229" name="Bernd POSSELT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="04-06-1956" birth_place="Pforzheim" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, I welcome the Danube Strategy as something that is profoundly European. It connects a founder Member of the EU, namely Germany, with the two most recent Members, Bulgaria and Romania. It also connects the next candidate country, Croatia, with a country that is striving for candidate status, namely Serbia. I am pleased that the intention is to also include the Czech Republic, Montenegro and a few others which, historically and geographically, belong to this group, although they are not directly situated on the Danube.</p>
      <p sl="de">However, I would ask that Bavaria not be neglected in all this. If it was independent, Bavaria would be the second largest state on the Danube after Romania. Bavaria has a particular interest in the Danube Strategy. I am therefore grateful and pleased that we are now pressing forward with this strategy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-113" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel HANNAN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="01-09-1971" birth_place="Lima" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group - Vice" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, we see once again how the European Union elevates appearance over substance, how it elevates motive over outcome. We have just voted through a series of resolutions condemning human rights abuses in China. What, though, is the European Union doing in the real world? We are isolating Taiwan; we have agreed in principle to sell weapons to the Communist regime in Beijing; and we are collaborating with it to create a rival to the American system of GPS, which President Chirac refers to as ‘technological imperialism’.</p>
      <p sl="en">See how hypocrisy has been elevated into a governing principle! We bleat about human rights, and then we funnel money to Hamas. We refuse to deal with the anti-Castro dissidents in Cuba, we disregard democracy within our own borders when referendums go the wrong way, but we convince ourselves that we are still the good guys because – look at the text of our resolution on human rights!</p>
      <p sl="en">We are now going to have the extraordinary spectacle of sending Baroness Ashton as our foreign representative to Iran and Cuba and these places to tell them that their democracy is inadequate, when she has never once in her entire career subjected herself to the ballot box, or invited her fellow countrymen to vote for or against her.</p>
      <p sl="en">I shall finish, if I may, by congratulating the good people of Massachusetts for taking a stand against excessive taxation and excessive government. It was the people of Massachusetts who began the revolution in order to get away from the idea that taxes could be levied without popular consent. We need such a revolution again here in Europe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-114" speaker_id="28341" name="Mirosław PIOTROWSKI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="09-01-1966" birth_place="Zielona Góra" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, I want to express my satisfaction at the adoption by the European Parliament of the resolution on attacks on Christian minorities. Members of the European Parliament must not remain silent in the face of attacks on Christian minorities around the world, because this matter concerns the foundations and roots of the nations of the European Union. For our voice to sound credible, today we should have adopted two amendments put forward by the European Conservatives and Reformists Group to distance ourselves from the ruling of the European Court of Human Rights on crosses. I regret this did not happen, because we must remember the fundamental role which Christianity has played in forming Europe’s historical and cultural identity, and promote and protect these values in the world as well as inside the European Union.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-115" speaker_id="4436" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Gianni PITTELLA" nationality="Italy" birth_date="19-11-1958" birth_place="Lauria " p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="unknown">Mr Piotrowski, I allowed you to speak even though you did not have the right to do so, because explanations of vote are admissible only on the Strategy for the Danube Region and not on emergency resolutions. However, you have spoken now; therefore, for future reference, I will state that there shall be no explanations of vote on emergency resolutions. Therefore, I will also state, for the benefit of the speakers who have registered, that explanations of vote may refer only to the European Strategy for the Danube Region.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-118" speaker_id="28372" name="Ryszard CZARNECKI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="25-01-1963" birth_place="Londyn " m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, I, too, would like to speak about the discrimination experienced by Christians in Africa and Asia, but I am going to speak, of course, about our strategy on an extremely important matter. Let us remember that the Danube is the second longest river in Europe, after the Volga. The Danube flows through 10 European states, and as many as 17 states lie within the Danube river basin. This is, of course, a question of a certain responsibility, a certain challenge, for the European Union, because, in addition, some of these countries are currently affected by the very severe crisis. I am also talking about Member States of the European Union. The European Union is showing a certain solidarity in this way. I hope it will also be like this in other cases.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-119" speaker_id="23768" name="Bogusław LIBERADZKI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="12-09-1948" birth_place="Sochaczew" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, I voted in favour of the resolution on the Danube Strategy. Why? – because it shows that the European Union is open to specific regions, to regions which have a feature in common like, for example, a long river flowing through them. I would also like to express my satisfaction that the amendments which were put forward by the European Conservatives and Reformists Group were not accepted. This has made our resolution clearer. I would like this resolution to be followed by a focus on other characteristic regions, too, including perhaps the Odra Corridor.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-994" speaker_id="96867" name="Maria da Graça CARVALHO" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Portugal" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">I welcome the European Council’s conclusions of 18-19 June 2009 in which it asks the European Commission to draw up a European strategy for the Danube Region by 2011. I am voting in favour of the motion for a resolution presented here. The Danube Region is facing several challenges, and a strategy for this region will improve connections and communications systems, preserve the environment and encourage growth, job creation and security. It is important that the Commission makes the most of the operational experience that it acquired with the strategy for the Baltic Sea, and that its strategy is based on the determination of the governments and citizens of the Member States and the regions to overcome immediate common challenges. It is also important to bring this strategy into line with the EU 2020 Strategy and the Commission report entitled ‘Regions 2020’, to tackle the major challenges that Europe is currently facing, such as globalisation, demographic trends, climate change and energy use and supply. I would also urge Parliament to develop a process of reflection on the future of the European Cohesion Policy and to devise new possible strategies for other regions in order for them to adapt to the changes and pressures of a global world.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-993" speaker_id="95281" name="Viorica DĂNCILĂ" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Romania" birth_date="16-12-1963" birth_place="Roşiori de Vede" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">I think that the importance of reinforcing a European Union strategy for the Danube Region will facilitate the EU’s external action in its immediate neighbourhood, highlighting its potential role in helping bring stability to the regions of south-eastern and eastern Europe through implementing specific projects supporting the economic and social development of these regions. The fact that Member States bordering the Danube have assumed responsibility for promoting at EU level the proposal for creating this strategy for the Danube Region confirms their ability to make a specific contribution to promoting major initiatives capable of ensuring the continuation of the European integration process.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-125" speaker_id="96859" name="Ioan ENCIU" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Romania" birth_date="14-04-1953" birth_place="Odorheiul-Secuiesc" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">I voted in favour of the European Parliament joint resolution on the Danube, proposing that a European strategy be drawn up for this region as a matter of the utmost urgency. This strategy will give a considerable boost to inter-regional cooperation and will have the following objectives: the development and modernisation of river transport on the Rhine/Meuse-Main-Danube waterway, as well as road and rail transport in the Danube Region; the development and efficient use of renewable energy resources with a view to cutting carbon emissions and increasing energy security; the protection of the environment through implementing projects intended to restore and protect the ecosystems in the region; efficient absorption of EU funds and the attraction of investments, the promotion of tourism, all of which feature in the EU 2020 strategy.</p>
      <p sl="ro">This strategy will have a beneficial impact on Romania, particularly on the country’s connections with European transport networks, the protection of the Delta’s national heritage, as well as the socio-economic development of the localities in the Danube basin and in other areas.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-126" speaker_id="96977" name="Diogo FEIO" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="06-10-1970" birth_place="Porto" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">I firmly believe that the full development of the European Union can only come about if there are adequate development policies for all EU regions which respect their differences, needs and specific features.</p>
      <p sl="pt">I consider that territorial cohesion means creating different strategies for the different regions, fostering sustainable development within a context of respect for the environment and economic exploitation of its potential.</p>
      <p sl="pt">I am aware that macro-regional strategies are aimed at promoting balanced regional development within the EU, using existing resources.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Last but not least, I recognise the strategic, territorial, environmental and cultural importance of the Danube in Central Europe. For all of these reasons, I am voting in favour of this motion for a resolution for an EU strategy for the Danube Region.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-127" speaker_id="96899" name="José Manuel FERNANDES" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="26-07-1967" birth_place="Vila Verde" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">This resolution backs a strategy for the Danube Region with a coherent, territory-based approach for this important river, and enables the sustained and integrated development of a region that stretches over 14 European countries.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The proposed strategy will allow a coordinated and integrated policy which can achieve synergetic effects, promote cohesion and foster economic growth and competitiveness, all while protecting the environment.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The objectives to be achieved and harmonised include modernising the ports, improving the navigability of the river (with freight corridors, interconnections and intermodality with the North Sea), improving the quality of the water, protecting the whole Danube Basin and, last but by no means least, protecting the ecosystems that fall within the Natura 2000 Network.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Therefore, the Commission should soon launch a broad consultation process with all countries along the Danube so that the strategy in question is set out by the end of this year and is brought into line with the next multiannual financial framework.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-128" speaker_id="96706" name="João FERREIRA" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="20-11-1978" birth_place="Lisboa" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">We agree with the creation of a strategy for the Danube Region, based on an earlier consultation and cooperation between the countries and regions that are located along its course. Such a strategy will promote economic and social cohesion in those regions and promote territorial cohesion without jeopardising any of them. The strategy calls for improvements to the ecological status of the Danube, along with the development of a comprehensive plan for conserving and restoring the natural stocks.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Furthermore, it proves to be a positive strategy in the proposal for improving the Danube’s multicultural environment, cultural dialogue and protecting its cultural and historical heritage. As stated in the report, we believe that implementation of this strategy must not impinge on the responsibilities of regional and local government, being based instead on cooperation between the countries and areas within this region.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-992" speaker_id="96795" name="Jacek Olgierd KURSKI" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Poland" birth_date="22-02-1966" birth_place="Gdańsk" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="en">The strategy for the Danube Region which we have prepared, and which we have voted on today, makes it possible to promote regional and cross-border cooperation. The Danube river basin unites as many as 10 European countries at present – Germany, Austria, Slovakia, Hungary, Croatia, Serbia, Bulgaria, Romania, Moldova and Ukraine, of which most are Member States of the European Union or countries aspiring to become Member States. For this reason, the Danube Region is a significant factor, bringing together different programmes which are part of EU cohesion policy, as well as programmes for candidate countries and countries included in the European Neighbourhood Policy. What we have adopted today is a certain outline plan of support for the Danube river basin area, but whether the programme remains on paper or the model is filled out with specific content depends on whether additional means are found which will not affect, or will not reduce, the pool designated for the cohesion policy in individual countries. I hope that a cohesive strategy for the Danube Region will contribute to a rise in prosperity and sustainable and lasting development, and will generate new jobs and security in the region.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-129" speaker_id="96823" name="Petru Constantin LUHAN" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Romania" birth_date="19-03-1977" birth_place="Jud. Suceava" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">I voted in favour of drawing up a development strategy for the Danube, which will allow us to ask the Commission to draft this document as soon as possible, taking into account specific consultations with experts in the field and in the relevant regions, while identifying the financial resources available and including non-EU countries. This strategy must focus on aspects relating to environmental protection and water quality, economic potential and Trans-European transport networks. The Resolution on the European Strategy for the Danube Region emphasises the role and importance of broad consultation with local actors, which the European Commission must organise so that citizens’ interests can be represented as faithfully as possible.</p>
      <p sl="ro">Furthermore, the Resolution states that any strategy relating to macro-regions must be incorporated into the cohesion policy, which is the coordinating policy at European Union level. In addition, an analysis will need to be carried out on the added value created by this strategy in terms of European territorial cohesion. I think it is necessary to correlate the TEN-T (Trans-European Network of Transport) strategy, where the Danube comes under point 18, with the new territorial and economic development strategy, so that development takes place in a cohesive manner.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-130" speaker_id="96978" name="Nuno MELO" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="18-03-1966" birth_place="Joane" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">Given the strategic importance of the Danube Region due to its location, closer relations between all countries in this region are crucial, particularly for those that do not yet belong to the EU. This will aid integration in case of future EU enlargement. Thus, the implementation of all the recommendations approved in this motion for a resolution is crucial if there is to be a proposed EU strategy for the Danube Region by the end of 2010.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-131" speaker_id="28255" name="Andreas MÖLZER" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Austria" birth_date="02-12-1952" birth_place="Leoben" p_group="Non" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="de">The strategy for the Danube Region represents a reasonable model for coordinating EU measures for this contiguous region. In addition to issues that relate to the river itself, such as improving the water quality and the ecological situation, the programme that the Commission is to draw up could also result in economic and administration-related synergies. The report that has been tabled put forward some good proposals in this regard and I therefore voted in favour of it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-132" speaker_id="96783" name="Wojciech Michał OLEJNICZAK" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Poland" birth_date="10-04-1974" birth_place="Łowicz" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="en">I endorsed the resolution on a European Strategy for the Danube Region. Territorial cohesion is listed in the Treaty of Lisbon as one of the European Union’s priorities. Operation of the Strategy for the Danube Region concerns many areas of support, such as social policy, culture and education, environmental protection, infrastructure and lasting economic development. The very fact of the great impact of the strategy and its solutions in these areas proves that regional strategies should be established and implemented. The Danube Region needs a strategy, and needs support and our action, because this matter concerns many European countries. Six of them are EU Member States, and the rest are potential candidates. The influence of the region is also important for other countries which are not directly associated with it.</p>
      <p sl="en">The idea of establishing functional regions – macro-regions – began with the Baltic Sea Region Strategy. The Danube Strategy, as with other macro-regional strategies planned by the EU, has the main objective of strengthening integration by cooperation at regional and local level. It is extremely important that governments, local governments, non-governmental organisations and citizens work together with the European Union on the development and realisation of solutions which are adopted, because, together with us, they make up the European Union.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-133" speaker_id="96778" name="Artur ZASADA" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Poland" birth_date="05-06-1969" birth_place="Zielona Góra" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="en">Support should be given to every EU initiative which aims to coordinate and strengthen regional initiatives and which contributes to increased economic cooperation, improved transport infrastructure and better environmental protection. The Strategy for the Danube Region confirms the growth in significance of the macro-regional approach to European Union regional policy. Thanks to the document which has been adopted today, relations will be strengthened between old, new and possible future EU Member States, on the one hand, and Central Europe and the Black Sea Region, on the other. I believe that in the not-too-distant future, similar approval will be given to the concept of a corridor based on the Odra line. It would link the Baltic Sea with the Adriatic and would run from Sweden through Poland, the Czech Republic, Slovakia and Hungary to Croatia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-134" speaker_id="4436" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Gianni PITTELLA" nationality="Italy" birth_date="19-11-1958" birth_place="Lauria " p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="unknown">That is not possible, Mr Zasada. I have already explained that explanations of vote on emergency resolutions are not possible. Explanations of vote may refer only to the European Strategy for the Danube Region. I am sorry, but this was not my decision.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem16" title="9. Corrections to votes and voting intentions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem17" title="10. Implementing measures (Rule 88): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem18" title="11. Decisions concerning certain documents: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem19" title="12. Written declarations included in the register (Rule 123): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem20" title="13. Forwarding of texts adopted during the sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem21" title="14. Dates of forthcoming sittings: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem22" title="15. Adjournment of the session"/>
</text>
