<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20120521.EN" lang="en" date="2012-05-21" place="Strasbourg" edition="OJ edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Resumption of the session">
    <intervention id="1-004-000" speaker_id="1911" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Martin SCHULZ" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-12-1955" birth_place="Hehlrath" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="unknown">I declare resumed the session of the European Parliament adjourned on Thursday, 10 May 2012.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Approval of the minutes of the previous sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Composition of Parliament: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Statement by the President">
    <intervention id="1-008-000" speaker_id="1911" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Martin SCHULZ" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-12-1955" birth_place="Hehlrath" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="unknown">Ladies and gentlemen, before I make any further announcements, I should be grateful for your attention on two matters.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">We have witnessed a violent crime against a school in Italy. The school is named after Francesca Morvillo Falcone, the widow of the former Judge Falcone, both of whom were themselves victims of a cowardly murderous attack. Two girls at this school have also now fallen victim to an attack, the details of which are still unclear. Melissa, a young girl 16 years of age, was killed. Another girl, Veronica, is fighting for her life as we speak. Many other young girls were injured, some seriously, the victims of a bombing. The background details of the attack are not yet known.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Ladies and gentlemen, what I do know, however, is that at more or less every session in recent months, I have been in the difficult position of having to report on the killing of children and young people. For a very long time, there has, without doubt, been an unwritten rule – even among the most base criminals – that the killing of children must be avoided, that one should not kill children and young people. It was a red line, and most people did not cross it. We are finding, however, that increasingly, there are cases in which this red line is being crossed, in which out of ideological, religious or even criminal blindness, confusion or fanaticism, children or young people are actively killed or their deaths accepted. I believe I speak on behalf of all of us when I say that we have nothing but contempt for such people who perpetrate acts of this kind.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
      <p sl="unknown">Our thoughts therefore go out to the families and friends of Melissa, the girl who was killed. We are hoping for the best for Veronica, who is fighting for her life, and our thoughts are with the pupils, the parents and the teachers at the school who are living through such dark times.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">At the same time, I would also like to mention that in the past few hours, we have been shaken by the tragic events in Emilia Romagna. Once again, Italy has been stricken by a serious earthquake. The Emilia Romagna region is badly affected, and particularly the comune of Finale Emilia. According to the latest figures, seven people have lost their lives, many more are seriously injured and more than 3 000 people are homeless. We would like to express our solidarity and our sympathy with these people too.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">However, I should also like to address a few words to the Italian people. Anyone who has seen the images of solidarity in the past few days – both in Emilia Romagna and with the victims in Brindisi – can only be impressed by the Italian people. There are times when a people come together in a difficult situation, such as that which Italy is facing now. On behalf of the European Parliament, I would like to express my greatest admiration for the Italian people for the national solidarity they are demonstrating in these difficult times.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. Announcement by the President: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Composition of committees and delegations: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Corrigendum (Rule 216): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem8" title="8. Signature of acts adopted under the ordinary legislative procedure: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem9" title="9. Oral questions (submission): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem10" title="10. Petitions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="11. Lapsed written declarations: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem12" title="12. Action taken on Parliament’s positions and resolutions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem13" title="13. Order of business">
    <intervention id="1-018-000" speaker_id="1911" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Martin SCHULZ" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-12-1955" birth_place="Hehlrath" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="unknown">The final draft agenda, as drawn up pursuant to Rule 137 of the Rules of Procedure by the Conference of Presidents at its meeting of Wednesday, 16 May, has been distributed. The following changes have been proposed:</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Monday: no amendments.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Tuesday and Thursday: The groups have agreed to bring forward the oral question on the trade agreement with Colombia and Peru from Thursday to Tuesday afternoon and to defer the report by Mr Kazak on macro-financial assistance to third countries from Tuesday afternoon to Thursday.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Wednesday: no amendments.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-019-000" speaker_id="1186" name="Astrid LULLING" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Luxembourg" birth_date="11-06-1929" birth_place="Schifflange" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="LU">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, I am a little surprised to see what Parliament’s priorities are after hearing the order of business for this week.</p>
      <p sl="fr">We had asked for permission to submit an oral question on the situation in the dairy sector. It has not been retained while we have kept a debate on homophobia yet again. We have a human rights charter in the Treaty and discrimination of any kind is not allowed.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I would therefore like to know, Mr President, why we are not discussing the priorities that concern our economy. We want growth, but instead of dealing with agriculture, we are dealing with homophobia.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-020-000" speaker_id="1911" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Martin SCHULZ" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-12-1955" birth_place="Hehlrath" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="unknown">Ms Lulling, as you know, the agenda is determined by the wise decisions made by the group chairs. I will pass on to those concerned the fact that you favour dairy production over homophobia, and I hope they will be understanding.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-021-000" speaker_id="33775" name="Jean-Pierre AUDY" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="France" birth_date="12-06-1952" birth_place="Tulle" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, the Heads of State or Government are meeting in an informal Council. It was customary for the President of the Council to come and report on the Councils, even when they were informal. However, I believe you will take the floor at 19.00 – I also hope that they will let you stay for dinner so that the President of Parliament can stay at the Council – but has the President of the Council been invited? How can we explain why he is not coming to report on the Council, even though it is informal?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-022-000" speaker_id="1911" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Martin SCHULZ" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-12-1955" birth_place="Hehlrath" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="unknown">Mr Audy, you have rather wrong-footed me. I will make enquiries and let you know why Mr Van Rompuy is not coming. In principle, however, you are right. Mr Van Rompuy ought, in fact, to be here. Mr Swoboda, do you know?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-023-000" speaker_id="2295" name="Hannes SWOBODA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Austria" birth_date="10-11-1946" birth_place="Bad Deutsch Altenburg" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament - Vice" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, I know from an earlier occasion that Mr Van Rompuy declines to come beforehand because he feels he has nothing to say at that time – since he does, after all, have to ask the Heads of Government first. However, I absolutely agree with Mr Audy, because looking at it the other way round, it might be useful for Mr Van Rompuy to find out from us what he should say there or how he can support the President in his address. Since the President is to put across Parliament’s opinion, it would be a very good idea for Mr Van Rompuy to hear this opinion first. I believe, Mr President, it really would be a good idea to ask Mr Van Rompuy more often. Since such decisive consultations now take place in the Council, it would be good if Mr Van Rompuy were also to attend Parliament more often.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-024-000" speaker_id="1911" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Martin SCHULZ" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-12-1955" birth_place="Hehlrath" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="unknown">I will pass that on and present Parliament’s position in the necessary form by the time of the family photo at the latest.</p>
      <a text="(The order of business was thus established)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem14" title="14. Internal market scoreboard (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-026-000" speaker_id="1911" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Martin SCHULZ" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-12-1955" birth_place="Hehlrath" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report by Simon Busuttil, on behalf of the Committee on the Internal Market and Consumer Protection, on the internal market scoreboard (2011/2155(INI)) (A7-0153/2012).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-027-000" speaker_id="28120" name="Simon BUSUTTIL" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur" nationality="Malta" birth_date="21-03-1969" birth_place="Attard" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="MT">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, lately, there has been a lot of talk about growth, and how to kick-start Europe’s economies and get them out of their dismal state. But we need to go beyond slogans and spell out how growth can be achieved.</p>
      <p sl="en">In my report on the internal market scoreboard, which I am presenting here today, I want to transmit a simple but important message. If we really want to achieve growth, let us truly deliver the internal market to citizens, because it is the single most important European investment for growth. To do this, we need to fix what is not working. Where are we failing to deliver? The Commission’s internal market scoreboard shows us that a number of Member States’ efforts to transpose EU single market legislation have been found wanting. Unless Member States step up their efforts to make sure that EU legislation is correctly transposed and fully implemented, there can be no internal market.</p>
      <p sl="en">Not all is gloom and doom, of course. Some Member States have shown consistent commitment to the internal market. I am happy to see that my own Member State, Malta, once again has the best record amongst Member States for transposing most EU laws on time. Other Member States, such as Estonia, have shown very positive results on all counts in the ‘internal market health check’.</p>
      <p sl="en">These positive results do not form an exception to the rule; rather, they show that, if there is political will, other Member States can perform well too. Unless more is done to ensure EU legislation is transposed and implemented correctly in the shortest time possible, however, our citizens and enterprises will not be able to reap the benefits of the internal market. Member States therefore need more ambitious targets, and need to stick to their commitments.</p>
      <p sl="en">For its part, the Commission needs to continue to fulfil its role as the EU’s executive with more vigour. Breaches of EU law must be pursued more swiftly by infringement proceedings. To that end, I am also putting forward, by means of an amendment, a proposal to establish fast-track infringement proceedings through an internal market prosecutor with sufficient independence to act objectively on infringements and institute infringement proceedings free from political pressure.</p>
      <p sl="en">Building the regulatory framework of the internal market is not, however, the only step towards delivering the internal market for our citizens. That is why my report also focuses on the importance of bringing the internal market directly to our citizens and enterprises. The work of the established network of Commission tools is crucial here, and the success stories of services such as SOLVIT need to be followed up with a commitment to further strengthen these problem-solving services. For citizens are still faced with a complex, and often impersonal, network of services when they have a complaint to make. This makes finding the solution to their problem a problem in itself.</p>
      <p sl="en">My report therefore calls for further coordination among the Commission’s network of services and stresses the importance of the Your Europe portal as the single online gateway for all citizens’ problems. But we also need to establish ‘live’ points of contact, for example, by having case officers in the Commission’s representative offices in EU capitals to work directly on citizens’ complaints. Lately, we have been asking our citizens to make a lot of sacrifices to ensure that our economies survive the current climate, but we do have the internal market, which is the best way of delivering growth and the economic prosperity that our citizens expect of us.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-028-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Michel Barnier" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, honourable Members, firstly, I would like to thank Mr Busuttil for the work that he has done personally on this report, with the support and understanding of all the members of the Committee on the Internal Market and Consumer Protection (IMCO) – I am referring to Malcolm Harbour and the coordinator, whom I would also like to thank.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Ladies and gentlemen, we are at a serious time of crisis – the financial crisis which has not ended, and the economic crisis which has many human, social and economic consequences. In this time of crisis, as we can clearly see, Mr President, many citizens are suffering and are affected by unemployment. Many are angry and they are expressing that anger, and the internal market that we are talking about in Mr Busuttil’s report finds itself in a rather paradoxical situation whereby it could, if we are not careful, become the first victim of this anger, of the return to nationalism and, at times, nationalist reflexes, the first victim of protectionism. At the same time, the internal market, the single market, is our best chance, our main asset for getting out of the crisis, if it can function more smoothly. That is why what we have done, with Parliament’s support, since the Monti report, since the Grech report – this act for the single market, an integral part of which is governance, these 50 proposals and soon, Mr President, a dozen new proposals to restart the competitive social market economy – must, in my view, form part of the European growth strategy that the Heads of State or Government will debate this week.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I think, and I have thought for a long time, that the sound management of public finances, on the one hand, and growth, on the other – in particular, growth with the internal market – are not only compatible but must be managed together.</p>
      <p sl="fr">That is why I am pleased that Mr Busuttil has emphasised how much potential the internal market has for growth. We believe that if it were to work better in terms of mobility, exports, trade, investment, social entrepreneurship, services and e -commerce, we could seek out two, three or four extra growth points within our internal market ourselves.</p>
      <p sl="fr">That is what internal market governance is really about: improving the functioning of this space, which is home to 500 million citizens and consumers and 22 million companies, the vast majority of which are small and medium-sized enterprises. As long as they want to participate in this internal market, these citizens and these small and medium-sized enterprises need more efficient tools closer to home. That is what we want to do with SOLVIT, with the Your Europe portal, with EU Pilot, with the Internal Market Information system (IMI), too, and the European Consumer Centres.</p>
      <p sl="fr">This governance work starts with the scoreboard, that is, the snapshot of what works and what does not, this scoreboard that we produce with the Commission twice a year. This scoreboard gives us an accurate view of the transposition and implementation of internal market legislation in each Member State. It needs to work more efficiently, with figures that more or less speak for themselves, figures that are an incentive for Member States to keep up their efforts. The Busuttil report highlights this too.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Honourable Members, this internal market scoreboard is not the only string to our bow; it is not the only tool that we have when it comes to following internal market rules for European citizens.</p>
      <p sl="fr">This crisis that I mentioned just a moment ago is challenging us to learn from certain deficiencies in each of our Member States and to find a way to make new efforts.</p>
      <p sl="fr">That is how committed we are. We are striving for transparency and greater cooperation with you in Parliament and with the Member States in order to review the governance of the single market year on year. We did this for the first time on 27 February.</p>
      <p sl="fr">This first review paves the way for a communication that we will publish during the next European Council in June – since the Council had invited us anyway – on possible ways of enhancing the proper implementation of internal market legislation.</p>
      <p sl="fr">For me, two main aspects form the outline of this communication: the implementation of this legislation and growth. We, Parliament and the Commission, cannot draw up new rules if we are not concerned about them being properly implemented on the ground. Legislation which is not implemented is not only useless, it is often counterproductive. It creates imbalances between one country and its neighbours, who themselves are able to implement it correctly. It penalises growth and job creation by limiting opportunities for citizens and companies. That is why we proposed, in the framework of the Single Market Act, to lower the ‘allowable’ deficit in the transposition of those rules in the Member States from 1% to 0.5%. I am pleased that Mr Busuttil has echoed this proposal. We cannot content ourselves with an average European transposition deficit of 1.2% and even a figure of 1.7% in one Member State.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The Commission is currently leading a number of steps, together with the Member States, to improve and rationalise the implementation of internal market legislation. That is also why, honourable Members, I have visited each of the Member States’ capital cities – as I promised to do before Parliament – to meet with the national officials responsible for all internal market legislation (the Services Directive, the Professional Qualifications Directive, the Public Procurement Directive, the e -Commerce Directive, etc.) in order to have direct contact with them. We have therefore set up a task force of 700 officials who are responsible for this body of legislation within the different Member States in order to work more confidently and efficiently.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I will continue this tour of the capital cities by now going beyond capitals and into each region, since, in economic terms, there are companies, trade unions, non-governmental organisations, local authorities and actors in each region that are important for the single market. I will report on the first conclusions from this tour of capital cities and countries in my communication in June.</p>
      <p sl="fr">To conclude, we think that these tools for the internal market, these assistance and information instruments, must truly benefit citizens and companies. We have a certain number of tools that have been developed to offer greater transparency and clarity in terms of information. However, some of these tools have been developed in a slightly disorganised way. Today, we must therefore put things back on track together and make them more effective.</p>
      <p sl="fr">We shall continue to develop the Your Europe portal with a guide for citizens and companies on how to use Europe. Like you, I would also particularly like to improve in each of the Member States the functioning of SOLVIT, an online problem solving tool and a European network of national administrations which, in my view, is a priority.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Ladies and gentlemen, we will celebrate the 20th anniversary of the single market this year. It had already been said that this anniversary should not be nostalgic or melancholic, especially at the moment. It should be dynamic and proactive for the growth that citizens expect, with concrete benefits for their daily lives. That is also the spirit of this pact for better governance of the single market, which we are calling on Member States to provide.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Everyone has their part to play – governments, Parliament, the Council and, of course, the Commission – and I insist we must make this 20th anniversary the time for a new dynamic, a new boost for the single market. That is why I also hope that we can talk about this transparently and sincerely, not only among ourselves, but also with the actors in each of our countries, whom I mentioned a moment ago. That will be the spirit of this single market week, when we will again take up the idea of the forum that we successfully put in place in Kraków on your initiative, but by developing it in each of the Member States, during the week of 15 to 20 October 2012, over the course of which we will solemnly mark the 20th anniversary of the single market in Parliament, but we will also debate what is going well and what is not going well in each of the Member States. How can we remove some of the obstacles? How can we avoid fragmentation? How can we together quickly implement these 50 proposals that we have cited in the Single Market Act? How can we draw up new proposals based on those you will draw up yourselves?</p>
      <p sl="fr">As you can see, we have a great deal of work to do on the single market at this time. That will be my priority as far as I am concerned, along with you, and that is also what the citizens expect because there is currently a great demand to restore employment, competitiveness and growth, with all the risks I mentioned earlier about returning to nationalism or protectionism.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-030-000" speaker_id="28223" name="Andreas SCHWAB" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group" nationality="Germany" birth_date="09-04-1973" birth_place="Rottweil" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I think that all of us here are agreed that, as the Commissioner has just said, we must not allow the internal market to become the first victim of the crisis; on the contrary, 20 years after the creation of this single market, we must instead do all we can to ensure that this internal market genuinely abides by the uniform rules that all of us here purport to be working to achieve. I would therefore like to express my great thanks to Mr Busuttil for his work on this report in the Committee on the Internal Market and Consumer Protection, because in principle, the internal market scoreboard provides the European Parliament with a consistent annual barometer which shows the status of the internal market.</p>
      <p sl="de">However, ladies and gentlemen, 20 years after the introduction of the single European market, we must take this opportunity, and the opportunity presented by the festivities that will take place at the end of the year, to ask what has worked well in these 20 years and what could potentially be improved. I feel that Mr Busuttil’s report on the internal market scoreboard shows very clearly where the internal market still has shortcomings.</p>
      <p sl="de">In general terms, there is a lack of transparency. There are, in principle, two problems with the transposition of legislation relevant to the internal market. Firstly, there is the failure to transpose the legislation – and in this regard, we have just had mention once again of our nice target of 1%, which is met by only a very few of Europe’s Member States. I believe, however, that this figure conceals how poorly some Member States are implementing the internal market and its acquis , because there is a second problem, which is not the failure to transpose European law, but the fact that European law is being transposed incorrectly or is not being adequately implemented.</p>
      <p sl="de">I believe – and I am firmly convinced of this – that we simply need greater transparency here. It does not help when the Legal Service of the European Commission tells us that infringement proceedings must take place behind closed doors. We need greater openness, firstly, as regards what is going wrong in the individual Member States, in what way things are not being transposed correctly, and secondly, as to why the Member States do not remedy this promptly when the European Commission asks them to do so. I therefore very much welcome Mr Busuttil’s suggestion of creating a category for fast-track proceedings.</p>
      <p sl="de">Secondly, I know from my eight years in the European Parliament that in the case of many directives and regulations, but particularly in the case of directives, the Members of Parliament and even the Commission often do not know how earlier directives were transposed into national law. The European Parliament has frequently called in the past for a correlation table to be obtained from the Member States when new legislation is passed. I believe we should try to make this a reality by taking the 2004 acquis , in which we have correlation tables for all the new Member States as at 2004, as a basis for also drawing up a correlation table as at 2004 for the older Member States, possibly financed from our own resources, because this could shed more light on things.</p>
      <p sl="de">I feel that this debate on internal market governance is only just beginning, and I am therefore pleased to be playing an active part in the debate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-031-000" speaker_id="96975" name="António Fernando CORREIA DE CAMPOS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="14-12-1942" birth_place="Viseu" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">Madam President, Commissioner Barnier, I would congratulate the rapporteur in general terms on his excellent report. A fully operational internal market will ensure more jobs and more trade, will enable consumers to be better informed and to have access to more varied, better quality and more reliable goods and services, and will strengthen small and medium-sized enterprises and better prepare them to confront globalisation.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The Member States play a key role in this, not just in terms of producing legislation, which has to be appropriate, innovative and inventive, but also during the stage of transposition to domestic legal systems. That is where the problems arise. The Member States sometimes consider the transposition deadline to be far longer than the stipulated two years, which is a major spanner in the works for this market of 500 million people and makes the entry into force of rules governing it impractical. Other Member States transpose directives incorrectly or insufficiently, causing enormous problems with interpreting rules and applying them to the European market.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The 2011 communication on governance of the internal market compiles the life cycle of governance in a single document. The holistic approach Parliament has been advocating for a long time, particularly in the Grech report, now enables us to have a more complete and wide-ranging vision of the obstacles to the internal market being fully operational.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Resistance from Member States, inertia and, at times, weak commitment to proper transposition should be actively combated by the European Commission, by Parliament and, let us not forget, by active scrutiny from the national parliaments.</p>
      <p sl="pt">SOLVIT, which has a key role in extra-judicial resolution of the problems which arise for members of the public and companies as a result of the internal market not working properly, should be given, as soon as possible, a legal basis that enables its full potential to be exploited and the best possible response to be given to the challenges. It should also complement the Commission’s work on infringement proceedings.</p>
      <p sl="pt">From now on, the annual governance report and the Single Market Forum – which was initially suggested by my colleague, Mr Grech, and whose first meeting in Kraków in October 2011 was a great success – should guide the development of the internal market. This forum, or – as Commissioner Barnier has just called it – Single Market Week, which we hope will take place regularly, is enormously important in evaluating the progress with, and obstacles to, the development of the internal market. This is because, as well as giving us information, the governance report brings together in the same place various actors, legislators, consumers, business owners and other interested parties who will thereby be able to audit the internal market’s performance and to have a better perception of the rights and developments in this area.</p>
      <p sl="pt">I shall conclude by taking the opportunity to express some surprise at a proposal by the rapporteur from the day before the vote in committee, following a fruitful debate lasting more than six months. This proposal advocated the creation of a body independent of the Commission responsible for internal market infringement proceedings and with the authority to launch infringement proceedings following approval by the Commission: a Single Market Prosecutor.</p>
      <p sl="pt">This is a hugely complex idea, requiring an in-depth debate that has not taken place and clarification of the legal nature that this body would be given, its intrinsic powers and its modus operandi . We regret that this complex proposal emerged so late, making debate impossible; under the circumstances, we are not very receptive.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-032-000" speaker_id="28243" name="Jorgo CHATZIMARKAKIS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group" nationality="Germany" birth_date="21-04-1966" birth_place="Duisburg" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, Commissioner, Mr Busuttil, ladies and gentlemen, on behalf of the Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe, I warmly welcome this own-initiative report by Mr Busuttil. It is further proof of how important it is that Parliament sets the agenda on important matters. Thank you, then, Mr Busuttil, for this very balanced report.</p>
      <p sl="de">The subject is more relevant than ever, for alongside the things that we imagined would be the engine of European integration when the internal market was established 20 years ago, we can also see that there are imbalances in the internal market. The imbalances where the balance of payments is concerned are also one reason why the euro area has run into such difficulty. The single European market as a whole is also at risk of losing its legitimacy, its role as an engine, if we do not devote particular attention to what has happened now, on its 20th anniversary.</p>
      <p sl="de">The internal market scoreboard could be a useful instrument for indicating where things are going wrong at a very early stage, as a kind of early warning system. It would be a significant first step towards economic policy that is at last coordinated. That is why I also welcome the European Commission’s plans to publish this internal market scoreboard annually. We need to square the circle here. On the one hand, the economies that have nursed their labour markets back to health by making appropriate reforms – those that are more prompt with transposition – must naturally not be punished for their achievement. On the other hand, however, even the best in class will be affected if its neighbour gets into excessive debt in order to buy its products.</p>
      <p sl="de">As an initial step, it would be sufficient for the EU’s internal market regulations to finally be transposed in a more timely manner. In reality, what we need here are realistic transposition and implementation targets – as this report also underlines. Then there is the varying speed of transposition. In May 2011, the Member States took, on average, 5.5 months longer than the transposition deadline to transpose EU directives; today, the figure is nearly 8 months. This time period needs to be reduced, for the sake of equal opportunities alone. In short, the Member States must meet their obligations better and must demonstrate greater commitment to and make greater efforts towards implementing European legal provisions.</p>
      <p sl="de">At the same time, it can be seen that 20 years of the internal market have resulted in a drastic increase in the differences between the competitiveness of the national economies in the European Union. There has been a radical shift in the balance of payments between the strongest economies and what are now the weakest economies, in favour of the strongest. The low interest rate policy conducted since the launch of the euro has reinforced this trend, acting rather like an accelerant.</p>
      <p sl="de">We Europeans have trusted in the healing powers of the internal market, while ignoring the fact that competitiveness has not necessarily improved across the board as a result of this internal market policy. Commissioner Barnier, we need to take action to counter this. The scoreboard provides one way of doing so. The 20th anniversary of the single European market also gives us an opportunity to look into drawing up a plan for more equal balances of payments at national level, and possibly even at regional level in a further step, alongside the completion of the internal market. Only then will we achieve overall economic equilibrium in even the marginal regions of Europe, and particularly in the southern parts of the euro area.</p>
      <p sl="de">Europe’s sovereign debt crisis shows that the surpluses in the north and the deficits in the south will have a blocking effect on each other unless we can resolve this problem in the medium term. I would therefore urge Europe’s economists to give us new theories that reconcile the internal market with reciprocal balance. The internal market scoreboard could provide a decisive starting point for this, but it must not be allowed to become a paper tiger. Let us use the internal market week as an opportunity to think about these things. Let us also use the 20th anniversary of the internal market as a chance to make all of us in Europe – not just the strong countries of the north, but everyone as a whole – fit for the future.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-033-000" speaker_id="96956" name="Julie GIRLING" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ECR Group" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="21-12-1956" birth_place="London" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, my group welcomes this report. As everybody knows, we do not always have enthusiastic support for proposals in this Chamber, but this is one area in which we can pledge more than enthusiasm. We are positively excited about the idea of being able to get to the completion of the single market.</p>
      <p sl="en">Businesses and consumers are, of course, the beneficiaries of a fully functioning and operative single market, most particularly so in this time of economic challenge. Whilst we are all looking for markets outside Europe – looking at the challenges of export – we must not neglect the challenges and the opportunities of the internal market.</p>
      <p sl="en">Of course, delivering a single market for citizens and business does not stop at the creation of good legislation. There must also be adequate implementation as well as cross-border synergy between various national administrations. Without this, and without this implementation, citizens will not be able to enjoy the benefits of the single market.</p>
      <p sl="en">My group supports the efforts of the Commission and, most particularly, Mr Barnier, in the field of detailed reporting on progress with transposition in the Member States. We welcome the rapporteur’s call for more determination in the enforcement of single-market legislation and clearer reporting on infringement proceedings being taken. ‘Name and shame’ is often an ugly tool in politics, but it is often a very useful one – as is praising those who do well.</p>
      <p sl="en">We call on the Commission to establish the Single Market Act as a rolling programme to be continually reviewed and updated in order to ensure completion of the market. This should include prioritisation of measures to complete the digital single market, including investment in high-speed Internet and cross-border payments. We also call on national administrations to sharpen up their thinking and their action. It is important for single-market transposition to be treated with urgency and transparency, so that, as we celebrate this auspicious anniversary, we can truly see the single market as the jewel in Europe’s crown.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-034-000" speaker_id="96654" name="Jaroslav PAŠKA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the EFD Group" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="20-06-1954" birth_place="Banská Štiavnica" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group - Vice" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="sk">Madam President, this year marks the 20th anniversary of the single market as one of the most important instruments for promoting economic growth in the European Union. I agree with the opinion of the author of this report, Mr Busuttil, that ensuring the benefits of the single market for citizens and businesses will not end with the adoption of this legislation. I do believe, however, that besides improving mechanisms for surveillance over the transposition of directives and assistance for businesses in promoting their rights to enjoy the benefits of the single market through support mechanisms such as the SOLVIT website, the Your Europe portal, Enterprise Europe Network, European Consumer Centres or the European employment service, we should also look at the work of certifying bodies, which open up the way to the common market for each product. In my country, the State Veterinary and Food Administration provides an almost constant stream of public information about revelations regarding food products that have found their way into the sales network and which fail to meet the required level of quality and food security. You all probably remember the dioxin contaminated eggs, pork and poultry meat, which appeared last year in the northern regions of Germany. Recently, we also learned that a company in Poland had re-packaged salt for spreading on roads in small packages and sold it as a cooking salt. In this way, road salt got into bread, meat products and canned fish. A consignment of chicken from the land of the Gallic cockerel, which came onto the market in Slovakia, was nothing short of a scandal. The French poultry contained offal that should not have been in the pack, there were small, broken bones, and the gall bladder had been disgorged throughout the product. There was a similar situation with packets of flakes which caused vomiting. Such products, which have no place in a common market, are appearing with increasing frequency. I therefore believe that as part of the improvement of the single market, we should also pay attention, in the interest of our consumers, to the improvement of oversight mechanisms when introducing products onto our common market.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-035-000" speaker_id="109649" name="Mikael GUSTAFSSON" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group" nationality="Sweden" birth_date="06-03-1966" birth_place="Dragsfjärd" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="SE">
      <p sl="sv">Madam President, I do not intend to join in the chorus of praise for the internal market. Instead, I will be focusing on its failings. Currently, the EU’s neoliberal economic policy, the European Monetary Union (EMU), and the internal market are, in principle, putting the free movement of goods before the interests of citizens. As a result, a new Europe has been created, one which is characterised by mass unemployment, poverty and a growing class divide. At the same time, there have been cutbacks in measures to improve the environment and increase equality.</p>
      <p sl="sv">The report refers to the Kraków Declaration where the internal market is described as ‘the most powerful tool for putting Europe back on the path to sustainable growth’. The internal market cannot itself establish sustainable growth or create more jobs. That would be impossible. To achieve this, we need a completely new economic policy which is green and wide-ranging, allows for investment in the public sector, and puts people before the system.</p>
      <p sl="sv">Paragraph 33 states that the EU must offer direct human contact with ‘citizens and consumers via the Commission’s representative offices’. This is an excellent idea. We should be actively inviting citizens to visit the representative offices in their thousands, so that they can say what they think about the internal market and the current austerity policy, which has ruined millions of people’s lives and destroyed their future prospects.</p>
      <p sl="sv">The basic principle and objective of the internal market should be the welfare of people and the environment. It should not be promoting the interests of large companies as it currently does. In addition, the internal market has erected high barriers, which are carefully monitored, between itself and the rest of the world. The internal market scoreboard says nothing about the thousands of poor people from countries in the south who were hoping for a better future in Europe, but who drowned when their boats sank in the Mediterranean.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-036-000" speaker_id="96981" name="Franz OBERMAYR" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Austria" birth_date="25-05-1952" p_group="Non" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, the internal market with its four fundamental freedoms has now existed for 20 years, and it has undoubtedly benefited Europe’s citizens. To exploit its full potential, problems need to be identified and resolved as close to citizens as possible. Agencies such as SOLVIT are an important instrument in this regard. The people who work there are quick and efficient. Unfortunately, they are often understaffed, and here it would be better to invest in personnel rather than setting up another ineffectual EU agency, the benefits of which EU citizens find not very convincing.</p>
      <p sl="de">While the internal market can certainly do a lot, it cannot be the ultimate answer to the economic crisis – especially not if the limits of the internal market are ignored. For example, bogus self-employed workers from the East in the building trade, who are kept more or less as wage slaves in Austria and Germany. The Frankfurter Allgemeine newspaper calls Frankfurt the capital of Bulgarian industry. According to tax investigators, around 10 000 to 17 000 bogus self-employed people are currently working in Frankfurt. The number of unreported cases is likely to be much higher. This undoubtedly has great advantages for the building companies. They would have to pay a domestic worker around EUR 35 per hour, whereas the bogus self-employed generally come in at a reasonable EUR 10. That surely is not what the internal market is there for; in this case, the fundamental freedoms are being exploited to the detriment of both domestic companies and workers.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-037-000" speaker_id="96757" name="Raffaele BALDASSARRE" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Italy" birth_date="23-09-1956" birth_place="Lecce" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="it">Madam President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, I fully agree with the priorities and the points Mr Busuttil has stressed in his report. I hope this House will adopt the report by an overwhelming majority so as to further enhance the operation of the single market, which is an absolutely vital part of the policies for EU development.</p>
      <p sl="it">That would send out a strong signal to the individual Member States. The latest results from the internal market scoreboard have shown how Member States are increasingly failing to deliver on the transposition of European legislation. That is why I agree with my fellow Member that we need to increase the power and flexibility of infringement proceedings, while rethinking the role SOLVIT should play as an alternative to seeking legal redress.</p>
      <p sl="it">In that respect, I share his reservations about the danger that we might run into problems with the principle of subsidiarity if the legal basis for SOLVIT is over-formalised. I therefore think the Commission needs to examine all kinds of solutions very carefully so as to make the portal more operational without running the risk of getting bogged down in legal technicalities.</p>
      <p sl="it">Lastly, we must bear in mind the fact that the Treaty of Lisbon has redefined Parliament’s role considerably by giving it substantial powers to structure and review EU legislation. In that regard, the conclusions of the scoreboard need to be properly examined within this Parliament’s regular dialogue with the national parliaments, with a view to a more fruitful collaboration with the national authorities.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-038-000" speaker_id="1907" name="Barbara WEILER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="17-09-1946" birth_place="Düsseldorf" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, in the past week, I had the honour of speaking about the 20th anniversary of the completion of the internal market at a Franco-German partnership celebration. It was interesting to see how the guests reacted to this. They took it all for granted, and indeed it is good that citizens consider this something that goes without saying. The four fundamental freedoms are the core of the European Union, and I hope that we, as Parliament, will fight all joint attempts to erect new barriers and new borders, such as when the German Government and the former French Government attempted to erect new barriers, because the freedom of movement of our citizens is at least as important to us as the freedom of movement of capital or goods.</p>
      <p sl="de">In my view, Mr Busuttil has presented a good and helpful report. The internal market scoreboard, SOLVIT and other instruments are useful for establishing whether the governments really want European laws and whether the deficits are actually being reduced, as the Council has in fact agreed. We want the internal market to be simplified for consumers. We want SMEs to have easier access and we want all our citizens to profit from it.</p>
      <p sl="de">Interestingly, transposition is not always related to the size of the country. As has already been mentioned, Malta comes out best; Belgium, unfortunately, has not done so well. Mr Busuttil, your motion is also interesting and I have great sympathy for you, but I must point out that there are a few other demands in your report that already incorporate this, such as Article 18 on transparency, or Article 24, in which we call for correlation tables, or even Article 21, which suggests that the European Court of Justice could work more quickly. So perhaps we should work on this first.</p>
      <p sl="de">On behalf of the Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament, I should like to highlight four further aspects. Firstly, the transposition must be correct; that is, it does not have to be gold-plated, but it must not be lax and inadequate. Mr Chatzimarkakis, if I may have your ear for a moment: the two liberal camps in the national German Government are currently dabbling with the Payment Services Directive, and from what I have heard, initial reports are not encouraging.</p>
      <p sl="de">Now for my second point, which is that the internal market is also a way of overcoming the crisis, creates jobs and contributes to growth.</p>
      <p sl="de">Thirdly, we consider the procedures for the social protection of workers to be too cumbersome, because as far as we are concerned – and this is my only criticism, Commissioner Barnier – social cohesion is dealt with too briefly in this report. We will insist on this, because we have a long tradition of social cohesion.</p>
      <p sl="de">Finally, I would like to quote your former colleague, Jacques Delors, who said that the internal market works according to three principles: competition which stimulates, cooperation which strengthens and solidarity which unites.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-039-000" speaker_id="111589" name="Inês Cristina ZUBER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="11-03-1980" birth_place="Évora" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">Madam President, this report makes very interesting comments. For example, it says that the success of the internal market is a key driver of increased competitiveness and growth, and one of the best means of resolving the economic crisis. These may be interesting comments, but they are solely and exclusively in the interests of big business and the financial sector.</p>
      <p sl="pt">These comments certainly did not take into account the economic and social development of the outlying countries and their peoples. That is because it is those countries that are, in this time of crisis, experiencing the greatest difficulties resulting from their economic weakening, to which – surprise, surprise – the construction of the internal market has contributed greatly.</p>
      <p sl="pt">For the more economically vulnerable countries, the internal market – otherwise known as policies that liberalise, privatise and deregulate the economy – has meant that their productive capacity has been destroyed, their exports have declined, and their imports in sectors like energy and food have risen, leaving them extremely dependent on foreign countries.</p>
      <p sl="pt">What have the consequences of the internal market been for countries like mine, Portugal? Increasing numbers of companies going out of business, particularly small and medium-sized enterprises; the destruction of thousands of jobs; increased levels of poverty, exclusion and inequality; the loss of workers’ rights and the spread of precarious labour relations; the privatisation of the energy and transport sectors, of the postal service, and of banking and insurance; and the liberalisation of essential public services.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The truth is that, from the point of view of the internal market, people are not free to have social rights and a dignified life. From the point of view of the internal market and its advocates, there is only the free movement of goods and capital. The workers in the various countries of Europe have been fighting bravely for their freedoms, and their social and economic rights, and have been demanding a change of course away from the current policies.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-040-000" speaker_id="102886" name="Ildikó GÁLL-PELCZ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="02-05-1962" birth_place="Szikszó" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="hu">Madam President, allow me first of all to thank the rapporteur, Mr Busuttil, for this excellent report, and not just as a mere gesture of formality, but because I find that this is a very timely and very useful report, as it stresses the importance of a tool that gives us increased accuracy and transparency when dealing with the instruments of the internal market and with the host of tasks that lie ahead of us.</p>
      <p sl="hu">I agree with those Members who argue that despite its long history and great many benefits, the internal market, unfortunately, still functions imperfectly. Our ultimate goal is precisely to ensure that this market provides all European citizens with an increasing number of benefits in which every single participant can have a share.</p>
      <p sl="hu">Although the results of the chart included in the report tabled before us show a positive trend, which is a very important step, this should by no means lead us to complacency. In fact, it is high time that we investigate more thoroughly in what areas we still need to make headway and undertake further efforts. This is where the report helps us, while also pointing out that positive overall indicators must not be used to obscure the details, including any problems that remain to this day.</p>
      <p sl="hu">To mention just one of these, there is the matter of public procurement, which accounts for about 15-20% of Europe’s GDP. If we are able to open up these markets fully and apply European legislation to them appropriately, governments could make considerable savings in the future. We must see clearly that Europe can only become more competitive if, in addition to following strict budgetary policies, it also pays sufficient attention to generating economic growth.</p>
      <p sl="hu">Moreover, I would like to stress that it is very important to reinforce SOLVIT, which was, in part, initiated by the Commission. It is vital for us to realise the extent of our deficit in transposing legislation. However, this in itself is not enough. We also need to reinforce one-stop-shop administration and create additional information portals and better coordination mechanisms, and it is imperative that we eliminate overlapping instruments. Our task is therefore to enforce legislation, and do so in such a way as to meet citizens’ expectations concerning employment opportunities, growth and security.</p>
      <p sl="hu">I am convinced that we need these scoreboards not simply to serve as checklists in which to mark tasks as completed, but also to help us understand precisely where we are at any given moment. I congratulate the Member States on their progress so far and, just as the rapporteur did, encourage them to seek closer coordination and to increase transparency further.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-041-000" speaker_id="96915" name="Sergio Gaetano COFFERATI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Italy" birth_date="30-01-1948" birth_place="Sesto ed Uniti " p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="it">Madam President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, we are all convinced that the internal market is vitally important to European integration, and over the last 20 years, it has become one of the identifying features of the Union. We are also convinced that the internal market has the potential to make a major contribution to growth in each individual country and in the Union as a whole. For these reasons, and precisely because we agree on this matter, we have to be very careful about certain aspects that, not surprisingly, have already been mentioned in today’s debate.</p>
      <p sl="it">In my view, the first of these aspects is that the real enemy of the internal market today is the crisis. The crisis is calling the value of the internal market into question for many people, and it is eroding the potential added value that the internal market represents. As a result, it has been widely said, including in this Chamber, that we have to focus on growth as our top priority, because without growth our work – our work on the internal market – is clearly made more difficult.</p>
      <p sl="it">The crisis enveloping our countries is, in fact, having a further adverse effect: it is giving some countries an unfounded excuse to implement incorrectly what Parliament, the Commission and the Council decide.</p>
      <p sl="it">As has already been pointed out, we are faced with two problems. The first concerns the Member States’ transposition backlogs, which cannot be attributed to the complexity of the legislation but are often due to poor political decision making. The second concerns the changes or errors made in transposition. All too often, the transposed version departs either from the text itself or from its intentions. The difference can be quite substantial in some chapters: the average values are recorded – rightly so – but the breakdown of where the largest deviations lie gives one the feeling that sometimes Europe tries to use the resources at its disposal rather too artfully. Consequently, the instruments needed to give substance to the internal market ought be revised and strengthened.</p>
      <p sl="it">Some people have talked about imposing sanctions where decisions are implemented incorrectly or late; personally, I would also like to emphasise the importance of SOLVIT. I realise that finding the right legal basis for it is tricky, but an instrument that has proved its worth cannot be left in the state it is currently in.</p>
      <p sl="it">I would now like to make a last point to the rapporteur: given that we are facing difficulties at the moment on account of the crisis and external circumstances, I do not understand why the idea of an internal market prosecutor has been floated. This would be a third party who would make us embark on lengthy discussions at a time when we need instead to make quick decisions with as much consensus as possible. That kind of consensus used to exist, but this proposal is liable to call it into question.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-042-000" speaker_id="97016" name="Angelika WERTHMANN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Austria" birth_date="07-11-1963" birth_place="Schwarzach" p_group="Non" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, the effects of the economic crisis are currently being felt throughout the European Union. If we are to get back onto the road to growth, we need to focus on the internal market – the most important instrument.</p>
      <p sl="de">It should be an internal market for citizens and companies at the same time. Synergies between the national authorities are therefore to be supported, and these should demonstrate more commitment in order that legal provisions are transposed properly and within deadline. The Member States must meet their obligations, and transparency and efficiency are urgently necessary.</p>
      <p sl="de">The advantage needs to be clearly conveyed to citizens and companies. SOLVIT makes a contribution to this. I am very grateful to Mr Busuttil for this extremely good report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-043-000" speaker_id="28223" name="Andreas SCHWAB" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="09-04-1973" birth_place="Rottweil" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, ladies and gentlemen, I have been somewhat surprised by some of the opinions expressed in this debate; for example, when Mr Gustafsson, on the left, who I regret to say is no longer here, said that the internal market had driven people into poverty and only served the interests of big business. The only thing I can say to that is that he should come to my constituency. In my constituency, there are hardly any big companies. My constituency lives off of this internal market and has a great many small and medium-sized enterprises that profit from this internal market. They would not have anywhere near the same sales opportunities in a world without the internal market. That is why I can say that, where my constituency is concerned, this opinion is grossly incorrect.</p>
      <p sl="de">Secondly, Ms Weiler mentioned in the debate that in her view, the transposition of the Payment Services Directive was also somewhat lagging in Germany. All I can say to you, Ms Weiler, is that we will do all we can – whoever is in government in Germany – to ensure that the directives passed in this House – with the democratic participation of the European colegislator, of the Council and thus of a federal German minister – are also transposed in Germany as they should be.</p>
      <p sl="de">Finally, may I come back to one point that has not received much attention in this debate so far, but which is included in Mr Busuttil’s report. If we pass more regulations – and thankfully the Commission has made some proposals in the Single Market Act as to where the instrument of the regulation should be used for legislation in the single European market – we allow the Member States scope in their transposition, but we create uniformity in the application of the law. That seems to me to be something that we should bear in mind much more in the future if we are to succeed in reducing the transposition deficit in this internal market.</p>
      <p sl="de">Commissioner – Michel – I would therefore like to remind you once again that the Group of the European People’s Party (Christian Democrats) places particular emphasis on checking very carefully where directives should be used and where regulations should be used, in order to achieve the best results in the internal market.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-044-000" speaker_id="37312" name="Christel SCHALDEMOSE" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Denmark" birth_date="04-08-1967" birth_place="Odense" m_state="DK">
      <p sl="da">Madam President, when I was young 20 years ago, I was not actually that keen on the introduction of the internal market. I thought it would only benefit capital and not be of much benefit to the people, to citizens. Fortunately, however, I have changed my mind about the internal market since then. I have seen it in action, and I have to say that today, the internal market has become the engine of EU cooperation. The internal market has contributed to growth, to jobs and to prosperity for the EU’s citizens.</p>
      <p sl="da">It is important that this continues in the future. That is why we have to ensure that the internal market functions even better in the future. That requires us to do more than we are doing at present, however. In fact, I am a bit annoyed that the Council is not here to listen to the debate, because one of the things that I feel is important is that the Member States realise that they have a huge responsibility to ensure that the legislation made in the internal market is correctly transposed.</p>
      <p sl="da">As Mr Busuttil said, it appears that there are countries that are doing this really well. If all the EU Member States were like Malta, we would have a pretty well functioning internal market. As far as I can see, then, it is largely about whether the Member States have the will to do it. That is what we need to improve.</p>
      <p sl="da">We have to do it better, because if we do not do it better, then we will lose our citizens’ and our businesses’ support for the internal market. We are already making a mockery of our farmers, who are complying with the requirements by having built new housing for their egg-laying hens. We are making a mockery of them because at the same time, we in effect allow eggs to be sold on the internal market that come from hens housed in accommodation that does not comply with the requirements. We are also creating distrust among consumers, who are finding that they cannot be confident that the products they buy on the internal market are safe and healthy because there are Member States that are not ensuring effective market surveillance. We are also creating legitimate dissatisfaction among workers, who find that they are being forced out of their jobs because the authorities are not capable of ensuring fair competition.</p>
      <p sl="da">We can do better, if we want to do better. In my opinion, the scoreboard is a really good example of this. It is a tool that shows us where the problems lie and what we can do about them. I also agree with Mr Busuttil’s idea of creating fast-track proceedings to deal with those cases in which Member States are not properly adhering to the rules. Getting EU legislation transposed should not take a long time. It is not being done quickly enough at the moment. There are other things that can be done, too. As the Commissioner said, there is the task force that travels around the capitals of the Member States and helps countries improve their transposition of EU legislation.</p>
      <p sl="da">I would therefore like to express my thanks for a good report and for the work that has been done. We can do better, and I think it is important that we use the 20th anniversary to show our citizens that the internal market is there for them, not the other way round.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-045-000" speaker_id="96686" name="Mitro REPO" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Finland" birth_date="03-09-1958" birth_place="Heksinki" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="FI">
      <p sl="fi">Madam President, peace and the goal of social justice have formed the basis of EU thinking from the start, and all of this can only be realised if the EU allows its internal market to function.</p>
      <p sl="fi">The European Union has endless opportunities, but there is also the danger that we will ourselves destroy those opportunities. In this respect, Mr Busuttil’s report adopts an opinion on a very important issue: the implementation of legislation. Member States continue to fail to implement jointly agreed directives and regulations within the agreed deadlines. This is particularly the case with matters relating to taxation and the environment.</p>
      <p sl="fi">It is worth noting that it is not just the citizens of any given Member State that will suffer if legislation is not implemented: the other Member States operating within the EU’s internal market will also suffer. If our objective is to promote unity and economic growth in the EU and the functioning of its internal market, we should put the provisions of directives and regulations into practice more quickly than is the case now. If Member States are not willing to implement, for example, legislative acts on the environment, how does the EU intend to achieve, say, the goals of the Europe 2020 strategy as regards resource and energy efficiency in Europe?</p>
      <p sl="fi">Legislation that is implemented unsatisfactorily weakens the credibility of the EU, competitiveness and, above all, the rights of citizens. We should also ask ourselves how we can ask the public to believe in and, furthermore, commit to an internal market for the EU, if Member States and policy makers in the various Member States do not care to.</p>
      <p sl="fi">The EU uses legislation to aspire, for example, to a better operating environment for consumers and SMEs. A better operating environment will be difficult to achieve, however, without reform and common legislation. For this reason, we need to be prepared, if necessary, to intervene in some way in the activities of Member States that are reluctant to obey the rules that we have agreed on together.</p>
      <p sl="fi">If we do not intervene in the activities of Member States who flout the rules, the future of the internal market will be fragmentation, not unity. Moreover, this is the issue with the crisis that is now affecting Europe. It is a matter of morals and ethics: about whether all the Member States, from the largest to the smallest, are actually prepared to commit to decisions made jointly.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-046-000" speaker_id="39721" name="Theodor Dumitru STOLOJAN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="24-10-1943" birth_place="Târgovişte" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">Madam President, I, too, would like to congratulate my colleague, Mr Busuttil, for this own-initiative report.</p>
      <p sl="ro">The single market is a topic where it is agreed, among all Member States without exception, that it is beneficial to the European Union in terms of restoring economic growth and creating jobs. However, the first condition ensuring the single market’s smooth operation is for all Member States to transpose European regulations into national legislation. On this point, unfortunately, although progress has been made, we still have Member States delaying this transposition.</p>
      <p sl="ro">The second condition is to have a high-quality process for transposing European regulations into national legislation. On this score, I must point out that we come up against the first obstacle even when drafting European legislation.</p>
      <p sl="ro">Any time we enter into tripartite negotiations involving the European Parliament, Council and the Commission, we encounter resistance from some Member States in agreeing to produce correlation tables between the provisions of the European regulations and the provisions of the national legislation into which these regulations are being transposed. These correlation tables mark the first step towards proficient monitoring of the way in which quality is observed in the transposition process. This is why I think we should have a rule stating that any European legislation must be accompanied by the production of these correlation tables in Member States.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-047-000" speaker_id="96925" name="Sylvana RAPTI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Greece" birth_date="10-11-1958" birth_place="Kerkyra" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="el">Madam President, my thanks to Simon Busuttil for a job very well done. I had prepared a different speech but, unfortunately, I have to say something else, having noticed the amendment that completely changed the spirit of the report. In Greece, there is a very well-known song, which says, ‘what starts well ends in tears’. I remembered that song, because the report started well and was widely accepted, having been passed unanimously in committee, but it will not end well, because the internal market – and especially the scoreboard – concerns people, not numbers. It concerns European citizens, in a time of crisis no less.</p>
      <p sl="el">When the European Parliament debates, considers and legislates, it does so for European citizens and it considers and legislates in vivo , not in vitro , because we are interested in life itself. As far as the scoreboard is concerned, we know that it maps how well each Member States has transposed European legislation and how well it is being applied in its territory. We all know that there are Member States in arrears. We all agree that those Member States must accept reprimands and, possibly, suffer penalties. However, what we must consider, before imposing a penalty, is why those Member States are in arrears and what exactly is to blame. The fact that half the cases pending have to do with taxation and the environment speaks volumes, because we are currently debating economic and monetary union and because it is clear that, when these two are not in step, we have problems and crisis in Europe and the euro comes under threat. So this amendment has been tabled calling, no more and no less, for us to appoint a prosecutor and establish another elected body to impose penalties in order to bring the Member States to their senses. I fear that, if we take that route, Europe will not progress and the internal market will become unattractive. Please can we think very seriously about the question of incentives and penalties, because they reflect perceptions. We socialists and democrats are in favour of incentives and trust that the Group of the European People’s Party (Christian Democrats) are not only in favour of penalties.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-048-000" speaker_id="4538" name="Malcolm HARBOUR" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="19-02-1947" birth_place="Woking" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I am very pleased to be here – rather later than I expected, and thank you very much for including me in the speakers’ list. I was sorry to miss Simon Busuttil’s presentation of his report and your response, Commissioner, but I would just say that, as Chair of the committee, I am pleased that so many colleagues are here to support you. We do not all agree on everything, as Ms Rapti indicated, but nevertheless, I think the detailed analysis of the issues in this report is an indication of the depth of knowledge and engagement that my committee has for single market issues. I know you will take it seriously, as I am sure you have already said at the beginning.</p>
      <p sl="en">Unfortunately, because I was not here to hear everybody else’s speeches, I do not know whether I will be duplicating what people have already said. But in my remarks, I just want to concentrate on two particular aspects.</p>
      <p sl="en">I will come back in a moment to refer to the question of infringements which Ms Rapti raised, but first I want to highlight how our monitoring of the effectiveness and impact of the single market can evolve, namely, by understanding the level of lost opportunities that still exist.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am reminded of a phrase that was used by one of your distinguished predecessors, Mr Bolkestein, in one of his reports on the single market, which we received annually – and I have been around long enough in the single market to have done a report on that – where he described the single market as a Ferrari motoring along in second gear. At the time, I said that it was not necessarily a Ferrari that we wanted, because what we want is not top speed but solidity, reliability and accessibility to everybody; but I think the point was, nevertheless, well made. The problem that we have, colleagues, is that we do not know how many lost opportunities are still out there in the single market, where businesses have tried to sell goods or services in a country (which they are legally entitled to do) and are still frustrated by existing barriers – many of which should have been cast away by the Services Directive and the goods package – so they go off and go to another market, or they take another product.</p>
      <p sl="en">We can never calculate those lost opportunities, but I think the question about attitudes of business to the single market, knowledge of instruments like SOLVIT and the point of single contact, are clear indicators of loss of potential. In this report, there is just a short paragraph (but a significant one) where we ask the Commission to include the findings of the Eurobarometer surveys in the annual governance check-up. What I particularly want to ask the Commissioner is whether, in the annual Eurobarometer surveys that are linked into the governance framework for the internal market, we should be including awareness measures about the extent to which companies and individuals know about their rights, SOLVIT and the points of single contact – because if we do not do that, we will have no indication about how the Member States and the Commission are promoting [the single market] together. Similarly, my colleagues have called for the Your Europe platform to be incorporated too so we can have a single powerful brand name and citizens and businesses will know where to go to get information. That is my first point.</p>
      <p sl="en">On the second point, about infringements, I think the core idea that was in the report about fast-track procedures stands. It may well be that ideas about an independent infringement assessment are at too much of an early stage but, to be fair to Mr Busuttil’s amendment, it only says ‘potentially considered’. However, it seems to me that, if people cannot sell a product or a service because of a government not implementing legislation, we have to deal with that quickly. Justice delayed is justice denied.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-050-000" speaker_id="39916" name="Zofija MAZEJ KUKOVIČ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovenia" birth_date="14-05-1955" birth_place="Črna" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="SI">
      <p sl="sl">Madam President, Mr Busuttil’s report is certainly very much welcome at a time when we are celebrating the 20th anniversary of the internal market and facing this serious crisis. At the end of the day, we need to realise that we should compete less with each other within Europe and focus more on competing with other global competitors, such as the BRIC countries.</p>
      <p sl="sl">I therefore welcome all these initiatives and the only thing I would like to be given greater emphasis is the strong need for communication, because you have portals everywhere, in every country, but there is too little communication taking place on these portals, even between people whose responsibility it is to communicate. There is very little in the way of advance communication, including oral communication, which is why the percentage of small and medium-sized enterprises that actually know about this is very small, while the others are practically excluded.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-051-000" speaker_id="96814" name="Elena BĂSESCU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="24-04-1980" birth_place="Constanţa" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">Madam President, the single market plays a vital role in Europe’s recovery from economic stagnation. In this context, I would like to stress how important it is to transpose European directives in good time and implement them correctly. This is why I think that it is vital for Member States to be constantly monitored.</p>
      <p sl="ro">This will help create a framework for tighter regulation of the internal market. Both businesses and citizens will be able to benefit from an enhanced single market. The latest internal market scoreboard indicates that only a small number of Member States have fulfilled their transposition targets.</p>
      <p sl="ro">Unfortunately, Romania has failed to meet its target of 1%, although it recorded good results in March. Our country needs to step up its efforts in transposing EU regulations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-052-000" speaker_id="96749" name="Andrew Henry William BRONS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="16-06-1947" birth_place="London" p_group="Non" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, in the early days of what was the EC, the words ‘free trade’ rather than ‘single market’ were used. The word ‘free’ is, of course, an emotively favourable word that gave the idea an attraction, but misled many about its reality. The freedom enjoyed by this traded good is paid for by that person’s job, or the other firm’s factory. This person’s free movement is that person’s lost job.</p>
      <p sl="en">The rapporteur refers to the alleged need for Member States to transpose and implement the laws of their EU masters. He calls upon the Commission to pursue swiftly infringement proceedings against countries that have failed to remove minor impediments to a single market. He calls rather ominously for greater monitoring of Member States by the Commission.</p>
      <p sl="en">Back in 1973, when the UK joined, many of us warned of the Orwellian double-think that lay behind nice words like ‘free’ and ‘freedom’. We can now hear the chilling and repressive reality falling from the lips of the Eurocrats.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-053-000" speaker_id="96776" name="Róża THUN UND HOHENSTEIN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="13-04-1954" birth_place="Kraków" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Madam President, the internal market scoreboard is an extremely important document, and all of us should use it alongside other available means to ensure that the single market is at the centre of public debate. The European Union works in the citizens’ interests when we transpose EU law well, so the numerical targets must be met here. Transposition of legislation is something which is extremely important, so these numbers are needed, as of course are incentives and exchange of best practices – such as the Eurobarometer surveys and a single good information portal like Your Europe – so that these missed opportunities will not occur. I am pleased that the Single Market Forum I proposed in my report two years ago was so successful that this year, we are holding a Single Market Week. However, I would firstly like this project to be continued, so that a Single Market Forum or Single Market Week will be held every year, and I would like to secure still closer cooperation between Parliament and the European Commission as part of this project, because only then will the single market really be something all the citizens understand and identify with, and only then will it be at the centre of debate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-055-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Michel Barnier" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="fr">Madam President, I am grateful to each and every one of you for your speeches and your proposals. I would like to thank Andreas Schwab in particular, as Ms Girling did just a moment ago, for highlighting at the beginning of his speech that when we talk about the single market, we are talking about this source of growth.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I said – and I am also responding to Mr Cofferati here, who was talking about the crisis as the main threat to the single market – at the beginning of my own speech earlier something that is in line with the speeches you made yourselves. I will say it again: in this crisis – with the rise of protectionism and the return to nationalism – we are seeing that the market could be its first victim. For if we split up European economic activity again under the impetus of national or indeed nationalist reflexes and protectionism, it is clear that the single market will not be able to withstand it.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Yet, at the same time, in order to get out of this crisis, I agree that this large internal market, with more freedom and less separation, is our best chance. It is our best chance for restoring growth.</p>
      <p sl="fr">That said, in order to act effectively, in order to make the single market work properly, we must recognise where there are weaknesses, bad transpositions, sometimes mistakes, shortcomings in terms of contact or information with citizens or companies, and I agree with Malcolm Harbour, who called for such recognition – that is where the interest lies in Mr Busuttil’s report and the work that we are doing.</p>
      <p sl="fr">That is the reason for this scoreboard, for this desire for transparency that Mr Schwab recommended. I would like to tell Mr Schwab that beyond this global scoreboard, which mentions all the single market texts, we must indeed go further and examine how it functions, text by text. That is what I am going to do, for example, with one of the main documents on the single market, which is not working well, and it has only been in place for three years. I am talking about the Services Directive, which covers 40% of the European economy, as all the other services sectors are covered by other European texts. We must examine text by text, brick by brick, how each of the directives is evaluated within the overall framework of the scoreboard.</p>
      <p sl="fr">With this scoreboard we have, as Ms Schaldemose and Ms Băsescu said, an opportunity to send out regular early warnings, to point the finger, to separate good or bad points from time to time, but also to help Member States, to practise what Róża Thun mentioned as an exchange of good practices.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I would also like to say to Mr Stolojan and Mr Schwab that it is important to me, as it is to them, that we have correlation tables, that Member States provide these correlation tables for all the texts, all the directives and that we are able publish them, where appropriate.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Mr Repo mentioned infringement proceedings. I have decided to use these infringement proceedings – as I have already done – to force Member States to do what they must, but I want, above all else, to rule out any possible contracts or incentives. We have already improved things, Mr Repo. I want to say this to be objective. For example, thanks to EU Pilot proceedings, we have substantially reduced the number of infringement proceedings.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I would now also like to reduce the length of infringement proceedings. Among the tools that we need to bring the single market together, to bring Brussels closer to citizens and companies, we have SOLVIT, this tool that I firmly believe in. I have worked a great deal for two years in each Member State so that SOLVIT could have – as Mr Correia de Campos and Mr Obermayr wanted – the legal and technical resources it needed as well as the necessary staff, and I am continuing in this work with a great deal of vigilance.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Many of you, like Mr Busuttil, but also Ms Weiler and Ms Rapti, mentioned this new idea – Mr Busuttil – of a prosecutor.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The Commission has certain reservations about this idea quite simply – I believe that Mr Busuttil will understand this – because we believe institutionally, within the framework of the Treaties, that we are the Guardian of the Treaties and that duplications or reduplications in terms of function or responsibility should be avoided. However, you have a right, as it is your role as legislator, to ask the Commission to do its work. That is the aim of this report, the aim of other tools we have.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I think that Parliament has a role of political oversight within all these tasks, and I believe that it is through dialogue between our institution and yours, with the support of the Council, that we can improve the implementation of these tools. Now I think, Mr Busuttil, that we must strengthen the role of the Commission and its work with a view to the proper transposition of all these texts. I will propose working on certain ideas such as determining the legislation or sectors that are a priority in terms of the internal market, where we could, after identifying the most efficient priority sectors for growth and competitiveness, have a strengthened partnership with the Member States and, in some cases, achieve zero tolerance. This is, moreover, the objective that you undoubtedly had in mind with your amendment, Mr Busuttil.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I would like to remind you that we could suggest that this exercise regarding the proper implementation of the market falls within the framework of a binding and more comprehensive exercise, that is the European Semester, so as not to content ourselves in this semester with assessing performances or budgetary recommendations, but also competitiveness and growth. I have already discussed this with my colleague, Olli Rehn.</p>
      <p sl="fr">We must do our work, but we must also make an effort to open dialogue with citizens and with small and medium-sized enterprises. I would like to tell Ms Mazej Kukovič that that is indeed the idea behind this internal market week, which comes after the success of the internal market forum, which your colleague, Róża Thun, set up and in which many of you participated.</p>
      <p sl="fr">We will try to use all the new means of communication, particularly online and social networks, to get as close to people as possible. I will, as Mr Harbour and Mr Schwab have advised me, along with my colleague, Mr Tajani, specifically bear small and medium-sized enterprises in mind in the dialogue, using the Internet to directly bring them the content of everything we have been doing with you for several years, and at this very moment, to facilitate their work. Reconciling citizens and small and medium-sized enterprises with the internal market is precisely what we want to do, and it is also one of the points that Mr Baldassarre mentioned while urging us not to forget about national parliaments. I completely agree.</p>
      <p sl="fr">When we talk about freedom and the circulation of goods – I am responding to Mr Paška here – we are actually talking about the security of goods as well, Mr Paška, of those that enter the internal market and which must respect standards, particularly in terms of security, and of those circulating within the market. It is a subject which my colleague, John Dalli, is, of course, responsible for and which he is following closely.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Within this large single market, there is – as Ms Gáll-Pelcz rightly mentioned – a part of the economy which depends on public procurement: 15 to 17%. I think that respect for these texts in terms of public procurement and also the progress we can make, particularly with electronic public procurement, can lead to extremely significant, beneficial savings.</p>
      <p sl="fr">The other day, several of you were there at the workshop we held in Parliament in Brussels with Mr Tarabella and Mr Arias Echeverría on e -procurement. We had demonstrations which showed that if we manage, together, through our texts, to systematise, to generally develop public e -procurement, we could make savings with all the local authorities of close to EUR 100 billion per year, thanks to this digitisation and this generalisation.</p>
      <p sl="fr">That is the concrete progress that has been made in the Single Market Act. I share the opinion of Mr Schwab because we must be objective with the single market and the interest that it represents for small and medium-sized enterprises. The work that we want to do in all our texts, as I have just said, is to speed things up where accounting standards, very small enterprises, public procurement are concerned through simplification, activity and investment in small and medium-sized enterprises.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I would like to tell Mr Gustafsson and Ms Zuber that the single market does not mean all European policies. What is the single market? It is the foundation. It is the base on which we build public or private policies. However, of course, if the foundation is not broken, if the foundation is solid, anything that we build upon it, in terms of public or private initiatives, will be more efficient. This is precisely how we are working with policies for green growth, such as those mentioned by Mr Gustafsson in the framework of the Europe 2020 strategy. This is how we have worked with the 12 levers that form the Single Market Act and that demonstrate the balance we are hoping for. These levers embrace the foundations of the competitive social market economy – I personally wanted this and many of you encouraged me – in three, or rather, four words: economy, social, market, competitive. You will find this balance in the 12 levers which we will retain within the framework of the Single Market Act II that we are preparing for the end of the summer.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I would like to say, along with Ms Gáll-Pelcz, that I do find Mr Busuttil’s report effective, to use her words. I think that we must – as Mr Schwab always wanted, so that we can be even more effective, because we can be, and I am undertaking this screening work with that in mind – look at whether we should use the regulation rather than the directive, as I wanted to do. I am also undertaking similar work in the field of financial markets, and in the field of the Single Market Act and the internal market.</p>
      <p sl="fr">It is in this spirit that we are preparing the Single Market Act with Ms Schaldemose and the Council, which has a very important role to play as colegislator. That is also why I want us, in Parliament, the Council and the Commission, to be able to find a way to deliver, to act on the 40 texts which are in this brochure and which have now been on your table for several months.</p>
      <p sl="fr">It is time to take action by going further, as we are going to do, by removing the obstacles that Mr Harbour mentioned. These obstacles to the internal market amount to missed opportunities for growth and employment. Frankly, I believe that we do not have the right, in times of crisis such as we are currently experiencing, to waste opportunities.</p>
      <p sl="fr">That is why we must have the right tool, as Mr Busuttil recommended, to implement, with the Member States, all the internal market texts as they have already been proposed and adopted, and also to go further, sector by sector, company by company, as we proposed in the Single Market Act, to make this single market work better.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Ladies and gentlemen, I am convinced that that is where the first, the closest source of growth, competitiveness and employment lies, and we must go looking for it where it is.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-056-000" speaker_id="28120" name="Simon BUSUTTIL" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur" nationality="Malta" birth_date="21-03-1969" birth_place="Attard" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="MT">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, let me start by thanking Commissioner Barnier and all those colleagues who have spoken in this very interesting debate – all those who have, almost unconditionally, supported my report, as well as those who have expressed some reservations, in particular, about the amendment that is to be presented. I will come back to that in a moment.</p>
      <p sl="en">At the very beginning of this debate, Commissioner Barnier said we are facing a paradox: on the one hand, we all – or almost all of us – understand the potential of the internal market; on the other hand, we know that the internal market often ends up as the first victim of a protectionist tendency when things are going badly. This is, indeed, a paradox and it is the hurdle that we need to overcome.</p>
      <p sl="en">In my report, I mention three ways of overcoming this paradox. The first is through transposition. We need to transpose internal market legislation on time and correctly. If we do not do that, we have a problem. Secondly, we need to implement laws effectively. If we do not implement laws, it is no use having them in the first place. Thirdly, we need to provide citizens and enterprises with the tools to find remedies when things go wrong.</p>
      <p sl="en">Some colleagues have mentioned their reservations on the amendment that is to be presented. Let me quickly go through it in order to put their minds at rest. The amendment reads as follows: ‘calls on the Commission to put in place a fast-track infringement procedure and to consider’ – I emphasise ‘consider’ – ‘establishing an independent body within the Commission responsible for prosecuting cases of internal market infringements and pursuing infringement proceedings after obtaining the approval of the College of Commissioners’.</p>
      <p sl="en">This amendment seeks to develop the concept of fast-track infringement proceedings. We want to give concrete meaning to this proposal. It would free the Commission from the undue political pressure that we all know it often faces when it tries to negotiate better implementation, or better transposition, with Member States at the initial stages of infringement proceedings – often with the result that the infringement proceedings are delayed for too long. So this is not about sanctions – as Ms Rapti understood it to be – but rather about depoliticising the process and making it quicker. It is certainly not ominous: it is about making the internal market work.</p>
      <p sl="en">As to the timing and the question ‘why now?’ – now is the right time because, if we do not act now, we really have lost the plot.</p>
      <p sl="en">In conclusion, I agree with all those colleagues who say that Europe’s major strength is the internal market. The question is how to ensure that we make the internal market work for all of us. I believe that we should seize the opportunity of the 20th anniversary of the internal market to muster the political will to address the remaining weaknesses of the market, in order to achieve a truly single internal market that can deliver the growth and economic prosperity that all our citizens want.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-057-000" speaker_id="39317" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Anni PODIMATA" nationality="Greece" birth_date="08-10-1962" birth_place="Athina" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place tomorrow, Tuesday, 22 May 2012, at 12.00.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 149)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-058-000" speaker_id="28275" name="Małgorzata HANDZLIK" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Poland" birth_date="01-01-1965" birth_place="Bielsko-Biała" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Internal market scoreboard, Simon Busuttil, A7-0153/2012 . The citizens, which means consumers and business people, are a key component of the internal market, and it is these citizens we should especially bear in mind when drafting legislation or making information available. However, they often have problems finding the right information and do not know what opportunities the internal market does in fact offer them. This is often caused by information being provided in the wrong way. I do appreciate the work of the Commission in this respect, but the number of portals offering information is often so overwhelming that the citizens get confused and, as a result, do not find the information they need. This is why it is so important to coordinate information tools. I have already pointed out the problem with efficient provision of information about the single market on numerous occasions. When it comes to the Services Directive, for example, the Points of Single Contact were supposed to improve the situation, but as it turns out, they are not fully operational. The Member States should implement EU legislation in a way which makes the laws we adopt in Parliament useful to the people these laws are intended to benefit – the citizens. The internal market scoreboard is a good tool for motivating the Member States to transpose legislation efficiently. Unfortunately, the latest scoreboard has shown that the trend in terms of implementation of legislation is negative in comparison with previous years. We should therefore send a clear signal to the Member States that the potential of the internal market can only be fully achieved with real commitment on their part.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem15" title="15. Visa-free travel to Canada for all EU citizens and the EU-Canada Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-060-000" speaker_id="39317" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Anni PODIMATA" nationality="Greece" birth_date="08-10-1962" birth_place="Athina" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the Commission statement on visa-free travel to Canada for all EU citizens and the EU-Canada Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-061-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Cecilia Malmström" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the issue of visa non-reciprocity continues to be a significant irritant in EU-Canada relations. Canada continues, as you know, to maintain the visa requirement for the citizens of Bulgaria and Romania, and also reintroduced it for Czech citizens over two years ago. This is an issue we have raised numerous times in the course of the contacts we have with Canada, on every relevant occasion and at all levels, in order to try to find a solution in partnership with the Member States affected.</p>
      <p sl="en">The EU is the number one source region for asylum applications in Canada. This is, of course, a serious concern, and we know it could have potential negative effects on the successful conclusion and ratification of several important agreements with Canada, such as the Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement (CETA) and the Strategic Partnership Agreement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Visa-free travel between the EU and Canada does not fall within the scope of the CETA negotiations, and CETA has not been directly used as a way of putting pressure on Canada. However, the EU negotiators have repeatedly, in the margins of the negotiations, made it clear to their Canadian counterparts that this issue is important for the EU, and decisive for the Member States concerned. It has been pointed out to the Canadian negotiators that such measures are in contradiction with the spirit of an agreement like the CETA, which tries to bring the EU and Canada more closely together.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission welcomes the draft asylum reform proposed in Canada. Once this is adopted and in force, it should act as a deterrent to unfounded applications and lead Canada to lift the visa requirement for Czech citizens. We are ready to explore with Canada, in close cooperation with the Member States concerned, possible additional measures to help reduce unfounded asylum applications, and we plan to set up a joint working group on this issue. In the case of Romania and Bulgaria, full accession to the Schengen area will be an important factor with regard to Canada’s position on visas. The Commission will shortly present its seventh visa reciprocity report. This will include the Canadian issue and will set out the future approach.</p>
      <p sl="en">Our previous report, in 2010, concluded that the EU was ‘confronted with the limits’ of the existing reciprocity mechanism. In the ongoing negotiations on the amendment of Regulation No 539/2001, the Commission fully supports improvements to the reciprocity mechanism to ensure solidarity among the Member States, provided that these are legally and institutionally sound and do not conflict with the Commission’s right of initiative.</p>
      <p sl="en">A better reciprocity mechanism should enable the EU to exert quicker and more sustained influence over relevant third countries. All existing countries would be re-examined by the Commission under this new, more efficient mechanism. The Commission hopes that the legislative negotiations on all aspects of the proposal will proceed quickly, allowing agreement to be reached in the course of the Danish Presidency.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-062-000" speaker_id="33982" name="Marian-Jean MARINESCU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group" nationality="Romania" birth_date="11-08-1952" birth_place="Râmnicu Vâlcea" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">Madam President, relations between the European Union and Canada enjoy a special status. However, citizens of three Member States still require a visa to enter Canada. This situation undermines the common European visa policy, which is based on reciprocity and is intended to ensure equal treatment for all EU citizens.</p>
      <p sl="ro">Member States participate on an equal footing in the Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement with Canada. This agreement is crucial to the future of EU-Canada economic relations and will set out the future legal framework for developing these relations. As part of this agreement, Canada treats all Member States equally. However, when it comes to granting entry visas into Canada or equal treatment on the subject of waiving visas, Canada is not as consistent in its actions. Double standards are being applied and criteria are being used which are not sufficiently clear and transparent.</p>
      <p sl="ro">The new legislation on the Canadian asylum system discourages asylum applications from EU countries. This is yet another argument confirming that maintaining the visa requirements for the three Member States is unjustified. The Commission will soon ask Parliament, during this year, to give its assent to the Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement with Canada. Failure to apply equal treatment to all EU citizens when it comes to visa-free travel to Canada raises clear reservations with regard to the vote, and it is not out of the question that it will end up in the undesirable situation of the European Parliament withholding its assent. I should remind you that the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs recently voted in favour of an automatic procedure for applying the reciprocity clause to third countries which maintain visa requirements for EU citizens.</p>
      <p sl="ro">The Commission is obliged to find a solution to the current situation where visas are imposed on Romanian, Bulgarian and Czech citizens. I call on the Commission to support, as a priority, during the negotiations on the comprehensive economic agreement, the waiving of visas for all EU citizens. The Commission has a duty to ensure that all EU citizens enjoy equal treatment.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-063-000" speaker_id="96859" name="Ioan ENCIU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group" nationality="Romania" birth_date="14-04-1953" birth_place="Odorheiul-Secuiesc" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">Madam President, the CETA agreement, which is currently being negotiated, marks progress in trade and economic relations between the European Union and Canada. However, it also symbolises a major paradox and serious contradiction on the part of the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="ro">This agreement will allow goods and services produced in Romania, Bulgaria and the Czech Republic to move freely in Canada, and yet the citizens of these states do not enjoy the same right. In other words, goods produced in Romania, Bulgaria or the Czech Republic are, unfortunately, more important than the actual citizens of these Member States. This is an anomaly and act of discrimination which cannot be accepted, also highlighting the European Commission’s inability to guarantee equal rights for EU citizens. The European Parliament must constantly remind the Commission and Council that any lack of solidarity between Member States means that the European Union cannot function under ideal conditions.</p>
      <p sl="ro">At the same time, we can also say that the spirit of good cooperation is lacking from Canada. While, in the case of the Czech Republic, the reason given has discriminatory tones against an ethnic group, when it comes to Romania, Canada is keeping the refusal rate artificially high to justify these citizens not being included in the visa waiver programme. This is affecting numerous Romanian citizens, and I would like to mention here just those who have agreed to have their names made public: Maria Dalcu, Cosmin Drăgoi or Nicolae Ion. They have submitted complaints to us about the unjustified way in which Canadian consulates have turned down their visa applications. There are far more cases than this, which makes me even question the good faith of the Canadian authorities involved.</p>
      <p sl="ro">There are also definitely positive messages coming from the Canadian authorities which I have had the opportunity to meet as part of several official delegations. During the most recent visit to Ottawa, early this month, we received assurances both from the Federal Minister for emigration and from members of the Federal Parliament that the visa issue would be resolved once the new immigration law is adopted in June. However, tangible progress is extremely slow. Even if the new law comes into force, it is not clear when and if visas will be waived for citizens from Romania, Bulgaria and the Czech Republic, as other conditions may be used to continue blocking visa-free entry to Canada for citizens from these three countries.</p>
      <p sl="ro">I wish to stress once again that the visa issue must not be sidelined by either Canada or the European Commission, but needs to be a priority on the bilateral relations agenda. As I have already said, goods and services cannot be more important than actual citizens. As representatives of these European citizens, it is our role to ensure that their rights take precedence over any other economic considerations. This is why I wish to end by saying loud and clear that ratification of the CETA agreement may also depend on the progress made on lifting visa requirements for Romanian, Bulgarian and Czech citizens.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-064-000" speaker_id="34234" name="Antonyia PARVANOVA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group" nationality="Bulgaria" birth_date="26-04-1962" birth_place="Dobrich" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe - Vice" m_state="BG">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, I warmly welcome today’s debate, which is jointly addressing the issues of visa-free travel for all EU citizens and the EU-Canada economic and trade agreement, and I would like to start by congratulating the colleagues who have taken this initiative.</p>
      <p sl="de">Not only are we addressing an issue which is of key interest and which directly affects European citizens from Bulgaria, Romania and the Czech Republic, but we are also touching on the values of our Union and the principles on which we would like the Commission to stand firm as part of its negotiating mandate.</p>
      <p sl="de">I am confident that the Commission will continue negotiating a comprehensive economic and trade agreement with the Canadian authorities, taking due account of our international commitments when it comes to trade and economic exchanges, as well as our rules and priorities for our own single market and our consumers.</p>
      <p sl="de">The Commission, as Guardian of the Treaties, and representing the interests of the Union in this negotiation, has a duty to make sure our economic and market rules are respected and upheld in any international agreement that is concluded.</p>
      <p sl="de">But let us not forget that our Union is not only about trade and economic exchange or about the free movement of goods and capital. It is also and mainly about people – about the citizens of Europe – and I hope that the Commission will put the core principle of European citizenship on the same level as our economic interests.</p>
      <p sl="de">We should not forget, either, the existing common EU visa policy. Together with MEPs from Romania and the Czech Republic, I have already sent a letter to Prime Minister Harper expressing our hope that by the date of completion of negotiations for either or both of the bilateral agreement and the comprehensive economic and trade agreement, scheduled for the first quarter of next year, the visa situation for Romanian, Czech and Bulgarian citizens will be resolved.</p>
      <p sl="de">Looking at the situation today, we still have reason to be concerned. As you know, any future EU-Canada economic and trade agreement will have to be approved by this House, and we have made clear to Prime Minister Harper that we are not ready to compromise on the principle of equal treatment for all European citizens.</p>
      <p sl="de">We are also aware that other points in the negotiations might be problematic, notably with regard to trade, preferential markets or energy and the environment, for example. We are not denying, or forgetting about, these crucial issues but are simply asking for a fair and comprehensive negotiating strategy on the Commission’s part – one which takes into consideration the concerns and warnings voiced by the European Parliament.</p>
      <p sl="de">So let us be clear and consistent and let us not conclude an agreement which would imply different levels of rights for European citizens according to whether they come from France, the UK or Germany, or from Bulgaria, Romania or the Czech Republic, for example.</p>
      <p sl="de">As an elected Member of the European Parliament who comes from Bulgaria, I do not ask for any exemption or special consideration. I am simply standing up for equal treatment for all European citizens, regardless of their Member State of origin.</p>
      <p sl="de">Finally, I would be grateful if the Commission could clarify whether this principle will indeed become a ‘red line’ for the EU when it is concluding negotiations with the Canadian authorities.</p>
      <p sl="de">Could you, Commissioner, also inform us about your cooperation with Commissioner De Gucht on this matter, as we believe it is crucial that both citizens’ rights and trade considerations should be pursued on the same path, towards, we hope, a successful outcome?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-066-000" speaker_id="96912" name="David CAMPBELL BANNERMAN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ECR Group" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="28-05-1960" birth_place="Bombay " p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I am alarmed at the tendency of the European Union to trespass into areas of national sovereignty where it does not belong; this is another example of that trend. It is the rightful business of the Canadian Government – and not us – to decide who it lets into its country, and why.</p>
      <p sl="en">Canada is not discriminating against us Europeans: it introduced similar restrictions for Mexicans, even though Mexico is in the North American Free Trade Agreement. Canada has successfully lifted the requirement for temporary visas where conditions are met. It has done so for Estonia, Latvia, Poland, Slovakia, Lithuania and Hungary.</p>
      <p sl="en">There seems to be serious confusion in the Commission’s stance in two regards.</p>
      <p sl="en">Firstly, there is confusion as to whether such visa matters belong in free trade agreements. They do not; just as ‘Mode 4’ worker access is not appropriate in the draft EU/India free trade agreement, so traveller visa matters do not belong in this Canadian free trade agreement. Border issues like this are a matter for Member States.</p>
      <p sl="en">The second point of confusion is about the European Union being a country. Yes, it aspires to be a country, but it is not one yet. So it is not the business of this place to force Canada to treat every EU nation equally, as if we were one country. That is a matter for individual nation states working through their own embassies.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Canadians have laid down fair and reasonable criteria, including low immigration violation rates, low asylum claims, high integrity of travel documents and good cooperation on removals. Those are reasonable terms.</p>
      <p sl="en">If this principle is breached, however, every EU Member State can expect the EU to start dictating all its border matters, and many EU Member States may well dislike losing control of their own borders to EU diktats. France and Spain have suspended Schengen on occasion, as has Spain this month, and the Dutch have tried to block Bulgaria and Romania. So in conclusion, Mr President, this is a line in the sand; a legal and political border that the EU must not cross.</p>
      <a text="(The speaker agreed to take a blue-card question under Rule 149(8))"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-067-000" speaker_id="34234" name="Antonyia PARVANOVA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Bulgaria" birth_date="26-04-1962" birth_place="Dobrich" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe - Vice" m_state="BG">
      <p sl="en">Blue-card question. – Mr President, I would like to put a question to Mr Campbell Bannerman. In explicitly mentioning Mexico as an example, does he see any similarities between Bulgaria, Romania and Mexico and, if so, could he mention some of them? Or does he see that Bulgaria and Romania actually have more similarities with the rest of the European Union?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-068-000" speaker_id="96912" name="David CAMPBELL BANNERMAN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="28-05-1960" birth_place="Bombay " p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Blue-card answer. – Ms Parvanova, I think the point you are missing is that they are all nation states. The objection I have is to pretending that the EU is one country and saying that we are trying to force equality on Canada as if the EU were one country. By all means let the national embassies argue with the Canadian authorities and do it for themselves, but I do not think the EU should be acting this way, and certainly not within free trade agreements. I am on the Committee on International Trade, and too much leeway is being given to items which are not to do with trade and jobs. Europe desperately needs trade and jobs at this point.</p>
      <a text="(The speaker agreed to take a blue-card question under Rule 149(8))"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-069-000" speaker_id="96859" name="Ioan ENCIU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="14-04-1953" birth_place="Odorheiul-Secuiesc" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">Blue-card question. – I would like to ask our colleague the following: in this case, why does Canada not sign a trade agreement with each Member State separately?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-070-000" speaker_id="96912" name="David CAMPBELL BANNERMAN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="28-05-1960" birth_place="Bombay " p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Blue-card answer. – The answer is that, as part of being a member of the European Union, every member country, such as Britain, has to hand over the negotiation of free trade agreements to the EU. I personally think that Britain should be outside the European Union and negotiate its own free trade agreements, as do Norway and Switzerland – and we would get a better result. That is the reason that is driving it. I am in favour of trade and of helping Europe get better jobs – I think we all are here – but I think there are better ways of doing it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-071-000" speaker_id="28497" name="Gerard BATTEN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the EFD Group" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="27-03-1954" birth_place="London" p_group="Europe of Freedom and Direct Democracy Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the Czech Republic, Bulgaria and Romania are threatening the EU-Canada trade agreement unless Canada lifts its visa requirement for visitors from those three countries. Canadians do not need visas to visit EU countries, whereas Canada has imposed visa restrictions on these three EU Member States. This is because of a previous influx of people from those countries who outstayed their welcome.</p>
      <p sl="en">Canada takes the quite reasonable view that not all EU countries are the same, and that some pose a particular risk when it comes to unwanted visitors and guests. The Canadians want to pick and choose who they admit and who they do not. However, this realistic view of the world falls foul of the EU ideological view that the EU is, in fact, one country, and to discriminate against one of its regions is not permissible.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Canadian Government already has a very generous system of allowing visa-free entry for 24 EU Member States, but perhaps it has looked at my constituency, London, and seen what a completely unrestricted open-door immigration policy actually delivers. They will not get the visitors and migrants they want – the decent, hard-working and law-abiding – they will also get the down-and-outs, the deadbeats and the criminals. In Marble Arch, the very centre of London, we now have migrants living on the street, with all the unpleasant social and sanitary consequences that involves, which I will leave to your imagination.</p>
      <p sl="en">This is what indiscriminate, visa-free travel can deliver. The Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement put in jeopardy by Canada’s reluctance to open its doors to allcomers is reputedly worth a potential USD 12 billion per annum, and would boost two-way trade by 20%.</p>
      <p sl="en">What does the world need now? Does it desperately need increased trade? Does it desperately need increased economic activity, jobs and increased prosperity? I think we would all agree that it does. Does it desperately need even more uncontrolled and unlimited migration? Most rational people would think that it does not. Let the Canadians choose who they want to let into their country, and on what terms. Let Canada and Europe get on with increasing the trade between them that can help us all out of the dire economic situation that we find ourselves in.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-072-000" speaker_id="96852" name="Cornelia ERNST" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group" nationality="Germany" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, firstly, either there are uniform EU visa rules and a binding reciprocity mechanism for all Member States, in which case the Commission – as Guardian of the Treaties – must fight hard for these to be implemented, or there are not, in which case the Commission has already been tolerating a two-tier system for EU citizens for many years, and my group considers that absolutely unacceptable. We demand that the Commission resolves this problem without delay and prior to concluding the agreement with Canada. Otherwise, the reciprocity mechanism must apply. That is my first point.</p>
      <p sl="de">At the same time, however, we have to take ourselves seriously, which leads me to ask whether the new visa regulation will at least strengthen the reciprocity mechanism? Is that the case? Can we in fact prevent such practices as have occurred in relation to Canada from occurring again in future? The only thing I can say to that is: by no means. What has emerged, however, is that visa policy continues to be used as a means of exerting pressure against migration.</p>
      <p sl="de">As my third point, can we please talk for once about the population group that is often meant when we talk about the Czech Republic, Bulgaria and Romania. It is the Roma. Many Roma have gone to Canada, and the Czech Republic argues that Canada is itself to blame for this because Canada has for years created incentives for high levels of immigration through its generous and tolerant asylum policy. That is Canada’s argument, and they are doing nothing to counter this. On the contrary, they go so far as to support it by saying: well, how is it that EU citizens are even able to go to third countries and claim asylum? Indeed, why is that? It is because the Roma have miserable living conditions in the EU – a situation of which we have been aware for many years, in which they are so discriminated against and excluded that it is no wonder that people are going to countries such as Canada. To me, this issue is also a kind of Lex Roma ; and to that extent, if we really want to do something about it, if we want to prevent emigration, then we have to improve conditions at home. That is what we should be looking at.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-073-000" speaker_id="28255" name="Andreas MÖLZER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Austria" birth_date="02-12-1952" birth_place="Leoben" p_group="Non" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, in the context of the EU-Canada trade agreement, visa facilitation is undoubtedly one more step in the intensification of a long-standing relationship that has been defined by common roots and values. Even though, in Canada’s case, we can undoubtedly count on high standards of security, the visa scandals of the past years and the far too frequent confusion of visa freedom with freedom of establishment – as is clear from the 700% increase in Serbian asylum applications, for example – should serve as a warning.</p>
      <p sl="de">While one side has even resolved to have its own visa warning files, the other – as we know – has announced cost-cutting measures. However, it is precisely in sensitive sovereign areas such as the issuance of visas that privatisation can open the door to manipulation. After all, in 2004, 2008 and 2010, there were innumerable cases of visa fraud as a result of local corruption. As far as I am concerned, the EU should exhibit particular sensitivity in these areas and pay heed to ensuring the highest possible level of security.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-074-000" speaker_id="28120" name="Simon BUSUTTIL" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Malta" birth_date="21-03-1969" birth_place="Attard" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="MT">
      <p sl="mt">Mr President, this is not the first time that we are experiencing a situation of this sort. Third country nationals, such as those hailing from Canada, can enter any European Union country without a visa, whilst a number of European Union citizens still require a visa in order to enter the very same countries. The issue here, therefore, is the lack of reciprocity between countries, and not whether the European Union is a single country, as some colleagues have reiterated.</p>
      <p sl="mt">Today’s case concerns Canada and the citizens of the Czech Republic, Bulgaria and Romania. Yet we have already witnessed the same scene with regard to the United States, and a similar situation is taking place in countries such as Brazil, which is still dragging its feet on the issue of lifting the visa requirement for certain countries, amongst which are Malta, Lithuania and Latvia.</p>
      <p sl="mt">As has already been mentioned, the European Union is currently negotiating an Economic and Trade Agreement with Canada. At the same time, Canada persists in acting in a discriminatory manner against the citizens of Bulgaria, Romania and the Czech Republic. The Commission has to make it clear that this is unacceptable. In the event of third countries demonstrating a lack of goodwill, the European Union should be able to re-introduce the visa requirement obligation on the countries in question as a last resort. In fact, we have just taken a vote on the issue a few weeks ago within the LIBE Committee, where we adopted the concept of a suspension mechanism. Naturally, for their part, the Member States must show solidarity with the countries that are being discriminated against and lend their support to the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="mt">To conclude, I believe that if we, for one, are not capable of taking both our citizens and foreign policy seriously, then we cannot expect third countries to treat us like a united group. On the other hand, the more we put up a united front, the better the chance of convincing them to respect a level playing field on the visa issue. This is why the Commission should act without delay with regard to this case and all the other pending cases involving a lack of visa reciprocity.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-075-000" speaker_id="36281" name="Silvia-Adriana ȚICĂU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="14-11-1970" birth_place="Galaţi" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">Mr President, there are numerous bilateral science and technology agreements between Canada and the European Union Member States involving government institutions, university research centres, private foundations and the private sector. At the same time, the European Union and Canada must step up their cooperation on electronic communications and information technology.</p>
      <p sl="ro">I should point out that, in the transport sector, the European Parliament has approved the conclusion of three agreements between the European Union and Canada: an air transport framework agreement, a civil aviation safety agreement and a Passenger Name Record agreement, with all these agreements being regarded as model agreements for each category individually.</p>
      <p sl="ro">These agreements facilitate the task of creating a single market for air transport between the European Union and Canada where investment could flow freely and where European and Canadian airlines would be able to provide air services without any kind of restrictions, including in the domestic markets of both parties.</p>
      <p sl="ro">The air transport framework agreement includes a gradual phasing in of traffic rights and investment opportunities, as well as far-reaching cooperation on a number of issues, including safety, security, social matters, consumer interests, the environment, air traffic management, State aid and competition.</p>
      <p sl="ro">All these bilateral agreements and, in particular, a comprehensive economic and trade agreement between the European Union and Canada are based on a spirit of trust and cooperation between parties. However, the same spirit of trust and cooperation must also be evident when it comes to providing a regime allowing visa-free travel to Canada for all European Union citizens.</p>
      <p sl="ro">We call for Romanian, Bulgarian and Czech citizens to enjoy the visa-free travel regime to Canada as of this year. We call for a comprehensive economic and trade agreement between the European Union and Canada to be signed only on the proviso that all European Union citizens, which also means Romanian, Bulgarian and Czech citizens, will enjoy the visa-free travel regime to Canada without any discrimination.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-076-000" speaker_id="96802" name="Jacek WŁOSOWICZ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="25-01-1966" birth_place="Skalbmierz" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">Mr President, last December saw the passing of 10 years since the meeting held in Ottawa between the then President-in-Office of the Council, Anders Fogh Rasmussen, and Canadian Prime Minister, Jean Chrétien. At the time, they declared joint action to strengthen ties between the European Union and Canada. Much has happened in the international arena since then. The treaty which forms the basis of the European Union has undergone two major transformations. During this time, the euro has become the common currency of many of Europe’s countries. There has also been the greatest enlargement of the European Union in its history.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The values shared by the citizens of the European Union and Canada have strengthened and fortified the foundations of mutual cooperation, and the scope of that cooperation has extended much further than was foreseen in the initial plan. Plans have emerged in the fields of property rights, competition law and government procurement. It has not been possible to regulate all the new areas in this time but, as can be seen, further work is under way in order to ensure full implementation of the agreements which do already exist. I think, therefore, that there is a need for a breath of fresh air and – as I see it – for essential steps to be taken to develop economic relations between the European Union and Canada in the 21st century. Therefore, I welcome the progress being made in ongoing work in this area – the area of visa-free travel on an equal basis for the citizens of all the European Union’s Member States.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I do, of course, remember that not all the Union’s citizens are being treated equally. The explanations being offered by the Canadians make it look as if they are just dragging their feet instead of making a definitive decision. We Poles are experiencing similar treatment in our contacts with Canada’s neighbour, the United States. Although we are treated at the American border as European Union citizens, we are unfortunately treated as second-class European Union citizens. I think the economic and trade agreement being negotiated between the EU and Canada must not just contain measures on economic matters, but must also include measures which regulate civil matters. If we allow citizens from different EU Member States to be treated unequally, we are admitting that the common foreign policy, which also covers visa matters, does not in fact exist, in which case we would do better to stop spending large sums of money on it. Furthermore, it should also be remembered that what we are asking for – the ability to enter Canada without a visa – will only give EU citizens the same rights as those held by Canadian citizens, because after all, Canadians already enjoy visa-free travel to the EU.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-077-000" speaker_id="96858" name="Marie-Christine VERGIAT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="France" birth_date="23-09-1956" birth_place="Roanne" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="fr">Mr President, I will speak – I hope that you do not mind, Ms Malmström – only about the Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement (CETA) between Canada and the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="fr">I fear that this agreement will meet the same fate as the Anti-Counterfeiting Trade Agreement (ACTA). The least we can say is that these negotiations on the Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement lack transparency. These negotiations began in 2009 and we are in the 12th round of negotiations. However, we cannot say that we are very well informed about the content of these negotiations. The Commission’s own website is blocked at the ninth round. It includes no real information and the most relevant information we have comes from Canada. What is worse, Parliament’s point of view hardly seems to have been taken into account from one resolution to the next.</p>
      <p sl="fr">This agreement is the most ambitious agreement ever negotiated with Canada, indeed with any other state in the world. It is based on a so-called negative list approach for the liberalisation of services. Yet most public services do not seem to have been excluded from the negotiations. What will happen to services for health, education, electricity, telecommunications, drinking water and even culture, if only the economic and trade approach prevails on either side of the Atlantic? Only the interests of large public companies which want to win new market shares at the expense of the general interest, of the public interest of our communities, seem to have been taken into account. This vision of the world has, however, already caused quite enough damage for us to stop this headlong flight. Yet nothing is being done. The points of view of the experts responsible for assessing the impact of these agreements seem to be diverse to say the least. Some talk of creating 80 000 jobs in Canada, while others talk about cutting 30 to 150 000 jobs. A study of this kind does not seem to have been published for the European Union, and that is certainly a shame. The impact of this agreement could also have serious consequences for the local authorities and their public procurement, which, basically, seem to have been pushed aside.</p>
      <p sl="fr">Could we have an accurate assessment of this agreement and equally accurate impact studies on its consequences? ACTA should serve as a lesson for us; it does not and I regret that.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-078-000" speaker_id="97968" name="Andrey KOVATCHEV" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Bulgaria" birth_date="13-12-1967" birth_place="Sofia" m_state="BG">
      <p sl="bg">Mr President, Ms Malmström, ladies and gentlemen, the European Union’s common foreign trade policy must prove that Europe has a strong voice in the world and that European institutions are able to defend the interests of all European Union citizens, as opposed to what my colleague from the UK clearly does not want, namely, to have such a strong European Union. I am sorry that he is no longer here in the Chamber.</p>
      <p sl="bg">I am in favour of deepening European integration further, resulting in a more effective, strong common supranational foreign policy, foreign trade policy and security policy. Any country that does not want such integration is free and has a sovereign right to leave the European Union, but it is wrong to constantly reject the desire of the other countries wanting such integration.</p>
      <p sl="bg">Returning to the subject, Canada is an important ally and economic partner of ours. The Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement desired by both sides, which is currently under negotiation, is intended to provide an essential tool for facilitating trade between the partners in their mutual interest.</p>
      <p sl="bg">However, the existing visa restrictions on citizens from Bulgaria, the Czech Republic and Romania when travelling to Canada must be dropped. During the negotiations, European institutions must make this task their priority, which will help genuinely facilitate and liberalise trade relations between the European Union and Canada.</p>
      <p sl="bg">The aim of the trade agreement is to liberalise the trade in services, mainly in the travel and transport sectors, with its text having to contain measures aimed at eliminating the barriers impeding access to this services market. The requirements to have a visa are precisely such a barrier.</p>
      <p sl="bg">I think, Commissioner, that there is a direct link between the trade agreement and visa regime, and these barriers need to be lifted. Thank you, Commissioner, for your position. I expect the Commission to continue to ask our Canadian partners this question in the remaining rounds of negotiations, particularly in light of the forthcoming changes to Canadian migration legislation, of guaranteeing the principle of reciprocity and, of course, of the trade agreement being debated.</p>
      <p sl="bg">Visa-free travel to Canada for all European Union citizens is a key condition, the fulfilment of which will also genuinely facilitate trade between the European Union and Canada. I also share the view of my colleagues who stated previously that there is a risk that this agreement will not be ratified in our Parliament unless these conditions are met.</p>
      <p sl="bg">Ensuring visa-free travel and guaranteeing reciprocity for all European Union citizens must be a priority for European institutions in their relations, especially with our strategic partners such as the United States, Canada and Australia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-079-000" speaker_id="97009" name="Kriton ARSENIS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Greece" birth_date="03-08-1977" birth_place="Thessaloniki" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I heard and I share the concerns of colleagues on the visa issue, and I would also like to draw attention to another possible problem regarding this agreement.</p>
      <p sl="en">For the first time since the Lisbon Treaty allowed us to do so, we have concluded EU agreements on investment issues. It seems that the proposal will include provision for investor-State dispute settlement. This will mean that not only States but also individual investors can sue EU States over what they regard as obstacles to their investments. This might seriously reduce our powers here in this House, and also in the national parliaments, to regulate on environment-related, social and labour issues.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is proposed to maximise economic profit and benefits, but our own EU assessment – the economic, social and environmental assessment – says there is no solid evidence to suggest that investor-State dispute settlement will maximise economic benefit in CETA beyond simply serving as one form of enforcement mechanism, just as State-State settlement is also an enforcement mechanism. It goes on to say that a well-crafted State-State dispute settlement mechanism might be a more appropriate enforcement mechanism in CETA. So our own assessment says we should move in another direction.</p>
      <p sl="en">The idea of an investor-State settlement mechanism was introduced in the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) because Mexico’s courts were considered to be corrupt, but in the end the mechanism was used mainly against Canada. Twenty-eight cases have been taken against Canada under NAFTA, and out of them eight have been concluded officially. Four have been lost – 50% have been lost.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to mention very briefly the case of Ethyl Corp versus Canada. Canada decided to ban, for health reasons, a gasoline additive, and the Ethyl company took Canada to the NAFTA tribunal. It made Canada pay CAD 16 million in compensation, apologise and withdraw the ban. I believe that this is not the kind of regulation we can accept in this agreement.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-080-000" speaker_id="96848" name="Mariya GABRIEL" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Bulgaria" birth_date="20-05-1979" birth_place="Gotse Delchev" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) - Vice" m_state="BG">
      <p sl="bg">Mr President, Commissioner, back on 9 June 2010, members of the European Parliament and I tabled a question to the European Commission regarding Bulgarian, Romanian and Czech citizens requiring visas for Canada.</p>
      <p sl="bg">Before this, during the last summit between the European Union and Canada, a commitment was made to remove the remaining barriers preventing a visa-free travel regime from being achieved for all European Union citizens. Almost two years have passed since then, but the visa regime is still in place, restricting the free movement of citizens from these countries.</p>
      <p sl="bg">According to the European Parliament, there is only one category of citizens within the European Union, and there is definitely no ‘second-class’ category.</p>
      <p sl="bg">The Commission’s negotiations with Canada on the Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement will define the future legal framework for economic relations between the European Union and Canada.</p>
      <p sl="bg">A key aspect of economic and trade agreements is the extent to which they facilitate travel for trade partners. However, at present, this aspect is not being applied to its full extent as Canada requires visas for citizens from Romania, the Czech Republic and Bulgaria. It is therefore important for such an agreement to be reached based on visa reciprocity.</p>
      <p sl="bg">Introducing visa-free travel for citizens of all European Union Member States has to be a priority for the remainder of the negotiations. A visa waiver will help establish close ties benefiting both Canada and the European Union as an inseparable whole.</p>
      <p sl="bg">Fairness needs to be achieved because, unfortunately, we are witnessing unilateral fairness: Canadian citizens can travel freely in all 27 Member States, whereas, at the same time, some fully-fledged Member States of the European Union are subject to a restriction.</p>
      <p sl="bg">I firmly believe that waiving visa requirements will help strengthen cooperation in business and trade, encourage cultural and scientific exchanges and will allow stronger ties between Canada and Europe.</p>
      <p sl="bg">Canada is a partner of the EU in many areas, which means that we must be committed together to removing the barriers which hinder us from achieving our common goal of creating an area of free movement. Achieving this common goal of ours involves removing restrictions and strengthening the principle of reciprocity, which are two elements that can be greatly beneficial to both Canadian and European citizens with whom we are ultimately travelling in the same boat thanks to this agreement.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-081-000" speaker_id="96715" name="Pavel POC" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Czechia" birth_date="26-05-1964" birth_place="Havlíčkův Brod" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="CZ">
      <p sl="cs">Mr President, the Charter of Fundamental Rights and Freedoms establishes the indivisible and universal values of human dignity, freedom, equality and solidarity as cornerstones of the EU. Chapter III of the Charter talks about equality before the law and the banning of discrimination. The European treaties talk of European citizenship. The European Commission likes to be called the Guardian of the Treaties, but it should rather play a much more active role in trying to secure equal access for all European citizens to the fundamental principles of the European treaties and not create ‘second class’ citizens through its inactivity.</p>
      <p sl="cs">In July 2009, Canada imposed a unilateral visa requirement on citizens of the Czech Republic, without any reciprocal measures to date from the EU. The ostensible reason for imposing the visa requirement was the large number of asylum applicants from the Czech Republic. Of course, in view of the fact that other Member States later began ‘supplying’ Canada with large numbers of asylum seekers with no measures whatsoever from the Canadian side, I cannot overlook the Commission’s hesitant and unproductive approach to this matter so far. Is there perhaps some truth in the rumours of a deliberate, informal agreement between the Commissioner and her Canadian counterpart, aimed at avoiding other Member States suffering the same discrimination as my own country? Has the Commission perhaps simply tossed one group of EU citizens overboard? I do not know, and I hope this is not the case. Either way, I hope the Commission will finally heed all of the calls and endeavour to end the visa requirements for some European citizens travelling to Canada.</p>
      <p sl="cs">On 18 October 2011, Ms Parvanova, Mr Bodu and I sent Canadian Premier Harper a personal letter, warning him that a political link might be made between the unilateral imposition of the visa requirement and the Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement (CETA). The letter still remains unanswered. Unless this situation is rapidly resolved, I would not be surprised if there were difficulties over the CETA ratification, and not only in the Czech Parliament.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-082-000" speaker_id="28397" name="Agustín DÍAZ DE MERA GARCÍA CONSUEGRA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Spain" birth_date="27-09-1947" birth_place="Daimiel " p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, this afternoon’s debate is neither new, nor is the issue limited to Romania, the Czech Republic and Bulgaria; it affects all Member States.</p>
      <p sl="es">These are the three affected countries today, but this could happen to any other on other occasions. This House, in fact, in its Declaration of 8 March 2011, has already asked the Commission to establish a new mechanism that will guarantee complete reciprocity for all Member States, ensuring that if a third country fails to reciprocate the visa regime, all Member States would enforce obligatory visa requirements for the citizens of that country.</p>
      <p sl="es">The principles of reciprocity and solidarity should guide the Union’s policy on visas, whilst also respecting, as is the case here, other debates on the Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement between the European Union and Canada. Only this way will we achieve a visa policy that is robust, rigorous, credible, supportive and unified.</p>
      <p sl="es">In the same manner, I am also aware of the importance of the Union’s foreign relationships, as well as those of the individual Member States; and for that reason, there is a need to find the balance between respect for the principles of reciprocity and solidarity and European trade relationships.</p>
      <p sl="es">This issue, as you are aware, has been debated for almost a year within the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs, via a proposal for the modification of Council Regulation (EC) No 539/2001. This would lead to the establishment of a list of the third countries whose citizens require visas to cross borders and a list of third countries whose citizens are exempt from this requirement. I am the rapporteur for this legislative initiative.</p>
      <p sl="es">The exact objective of this proposal is to provide the Union with an effective and realistic mechanism to resolve conflicts such as those currently being experienced by Romanian, Czech and Bulgarian citizens with Canada. We began the trialogue negotiation stage with the Council a week ago, but I have a strong mandate when it comes to reciprocity.</p>
      <p sl="es">The Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs (LIBE) is committed and calls for reciprocity. The stances of the three institutions and the Parliament are currently being aligned, but we are all aware of the urgency and the need to reach an agreement that satisfies the interests of all those concerned. Commissioner, I do not believe we can reach this agreement under the Danish Presidency.</p>
      <p sl="es">You are already aware that Parliament only says ‘yes’ or ‘no’ to an international agreement. I will say ‘no’ and will recommend that my political group says ‘no’ if Canada does not absolve the Czechs, Bulgarians and Romanians from the obligation, prior to the vote.</p>
      <p sl="es">Mr President, Mr Enciu makes a very solid and impeccable argument.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-083-000" speaker_id="39722" name="Sebastian Valentin BODU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="07-12-1970" birth_place="Constanţa" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">Mr President, today’s debate is a ‘semi-final’ in a contest, culminating in a final involving visas being waived for Romanian, Czech and Bulgarian citizens, which have been imposed by the Canadian authorities for the same old reason: the high rate of asylum applications from some East European citizens, especially from those belonging to certain minorities, once they have arrived in Canada with a tourist visa.</p>
      <p sl="ro">As a member of the EU-Canada interparliamentary delegation, I have used every opportunity I have had, including sending letters to the Canadian authorities, to support the need to amend the asylum procedure for European citizens to eliminate the constant abuse of this procedure.</p>
      <p sl="ro">A few months ago, Canada finally adopted new immigration legislation, which, in the case of citizens from democratic states, has resulted in a reduction in the period for settling asylum applications from several years to several weeks. I hoped that, once the problem of illegal asylum seekers had been cleared up, Canada would drop visas, as there were no longer any reasons for keeping them. Unfortunately, however, I regret to note that Canadian officials have not changed their tune at all on this issue, which means that the last chance to change this attitude lies in the call for European solidarity.</p>
      <p sl="ro">During the second half of this year, the long-negotiated EU-Canada free trade agreement will be submitted to Parliament for approval. This agreement does not currently feature any visa waiver provision. In the context of this debate, I myself and other colleagues who have submitted questions to the Commission want to send a strong message both to the European negotiators, so that they regard the visa problem as a priority, and also to the Canadian Government, so that the European Parliament is not put in the position of rejecting the free trade agreement for the reason that there is no regime allowing the free movement of persons.</p>
      <p sl="ro">As is well known, the European Parliament is highly sensitive to issues arising from human rights, as has been demonstrated on a huge number of occasions, to the surprise of many. Indeed, in the case of a free trade agreement, we obviously cannot talk about free movement of goods, capital and services while not having the free movement of persons.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-085-000" speaker_id="96654" name="Jaroslav PAŠKA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="20-06-1954" birth_place="Banská Štiavnica" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group - Vice" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="sk">Mr President, I believe we all have an interest in having the best possible relations with Canada, which we consider to be a mature, civilised and democratic country. I also firmly believe that we all respect the rights of the Canadian administration to determine their own conditions for the entry of persons from other countries arriving on its territory.</p>
      <p sl="sk">On the other hand, it should be noted that the agreement on economic and trade cooperation, the aim of which is to regulate cooperation between Canada and the European Union, will also apply to the Czech Republic, Romania and Bulgaria, and any of these countries will be able to oppose the conclusion of an agreement if they feel discriminated against as a result of Canada’s approach to their citizens. I would therefore like to believe that the forthcoming reform of the Canadian asylum laws will remove the concerns of Canadians regarding the abuse of their social system by citizens of certain European countries and will pave the way for visa-free travel for all EU citizens to Canada.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-086-000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán KELLY" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Ireland" birth_date="26-04-1952" birth_place="Killarney" m_state="IE">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I, too, am a member of the EP Delegation for Relations with Canada. I find the experience rewarding, and I find the Canadians upfront and honourable. For that reason, it is a pity that we have this logjam, which we must work our way through.</p>
      <p sl="en">For that reason, I would be loath to use what I would regard as the ‘nuclear option’ of withdrawing visa-free travel for Canadians at this point in time. That is something we should hold as a bargaining tool. I think that, with our shared history and culture, we should be able to get through this difficulty and come to an understanding so all 27 Member States would have the same rights with regard to travel to Canada.</p>
      <p sl="en">Also, I think that the trade agreement is of paramount importance and, particularly at a time of recession, we do need to work at ensuring that we have every opportunity to grow our economy. Certainly, having a country like Canada in a position to have a free trade agreement with us offers huge opportunities for us. So I think the message here is that we should negotiate and come to an agreement with people who share a history, a culture and democratic principles with us.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-087-000" speaker_id="96981" name="Franz OBERMAYR" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Austria" birth_date="25-05-1952" p_group="Non" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, in principle, a Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement with Canada is to be thoroughly welcomed. I will come back to the restriction of visa freedom in a moment. However, it should be up to each sovereign state to decide for itself who shall benefit from travel facilitation. Accordingly, Romania and Bulgaria are likewise free to decide whether they want to make it easier or more difficult for particular countries’ citizens to get into their countries.</p>
      <p sl="de">I also consider Canada’s asylum policy – which makes a clear distinction between applicants from democratic and undemocratic countries – to be a sensible one. By its very definition, an asylum seeker can only be someone who comes from a country in which he or she is persecuted, which can hardly apply in the case of democratic EU countries. The EU should rather learn from the example of Canada’s asylum policy. Canada was and remains a fundamentally generous country when it comes to immigration. However, if you have had negative experiences of so-called tourists who then disappear, people who exploit your hospitality and confuse it with freedom of establishment, then I can quite understand why even Canada has concerns about this kind of immigration.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-089-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Cecilia Malmström" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to thank all the Members for this very important debate. Canada is a country with which we have a special relationship. It is a friend and an ally on many issues, and it is in both Canada’s interest and our interest that we try to deepen the relationship in all possible ways. That is why this visa issue is so frustrating, and I share your frustration here.</p>
      <p sl="en">Of course the Commission is doing everything it can to make sure that there will be full visa freedom between Canada and the EU, in both directions. I have, on numerous occasions, raised this issue with the Canadian authorities, indeed with the Minister himself, and so have my colleagues in the Commission and many of the Commission’s officials. We hope that the issue between Romania and Bulgaria, on the one hand, and Canada, on the other, can be solved very soon when Romania and Bulgaria enter the Schengen cooperation system. Meanwhile, the immigration bill should enter into force by the end of this year, so there should be a possibility of breaking the deadlock.</p>
      <p sl="en">This is an issue we are following very, very closely and we have made clear to our Canadian counterparts that visa reciprocity is a key issue for us in the Commission, for Member States, for the European Parliament and for our citizens. We have also made clear that it may influence the ratification of the CETA process. However, this is not part of the formal negotiating mandate.</p>
      <p sl="en">I think the message from this plenary has been very clearly heard, and we will continue on the Commission side to push this issue. It will also be part of the discussion on a new EU-Canada framework agreement, and we will set up a working group with the countries concerned, the Commission and the Canadian authorities. I am confident we can achieve a solution to this problem, and I hope we will do so very soon.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-090-000" speaker_id="23820" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="László SURJÁN" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="07-09-1941" birth_place="Kolozsvár" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 149)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091-000" speaker_id="23840" name="Richard FALBR" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Czechia" birth_date="29-09-1940" birth_place="Chester" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="CZ">
      <p sl="cs">When I hear the continuing lamentations on the theme of how Canada is treating the citizens of three EU countries – that is to say, Bulgaria, the Czech Republic and Romania – as second class citizens, I cannot help thinking that we are barking up the wrong tree. These three countries should put their own house in order, so that there is no mass exodus of minorities who, due to the social policies implemented in these three countries, find themselves living under intolerable conditions and with no prospect of a solution.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091-250" speaker_id="111027" name="Svetoslav Hristov MALINOV" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Bulgaria" birth_date="19-01-1968" birth_place="Dupnitsa" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="BG">
      <p sl="bg">There is something deeply symbolic in that the reason for holding a debate on waiving Canadian visa requirements for Bulgarians, Romanians and Czechs turns out to be the forthcoming trade agreement between Canada and the European Union. Trade agreements always seek mutual benefit and are as pragmatic as possible. This is why discussing principles and values during trade negotiations is often regarded as a sign of bad taste. I call for us to drop the good manners and ask our Canadian partners the following: Do you think that there are first and second class Europeans? How else can we explain your deliberate refusal to treat all European citizens equally?</p>
      <p sl="bg">The European Union has always prided itself in being a ‘Union of values’. Member States’ equality under the Treaties is declared in Article 3 of the Lisbon Treaty. This point needs to be defended because the contempt it is being shown touches the EU’s very foundations. We have sufficient mechanisms available to request that the principle of visa reciprocity be applied to Canada. Ensuring visa-free travel for all European citizens is a priority for all European institutions. Canada must lift its visa restrictions on Bulgaria, Romania and the Czech Republic. I call on MEPs not to forget this when the trade agreement between the EU and Canada returns to this Chamber for our approval.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091-500" speaker_id="28352" name="Zuzana ROITHOVÁ" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Czechia" birth_date="30-01-1953" birth_place="Praha" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="CZ">
      <p sl="cs">I welcome the debate on visa reciprocity with Canada in connection with the negotiated trade agreement between the EU and Canada, but the fact that I and others had to submit an oral question in order for this to happen came as an unpleasant surprise. I am still taken aback by the attitude of the European Commission, which is doing what suits the Canadians, and effectively failing to prevent discrimination against the countries concerned. The European Parliament warned of the danger that international agreements with Canada would not be approved two years ago in a written declaration which I initiated. This is not an empty warning, as the Czech Parliament has already blocked an aviation agreement on account of this situation. Czech MPs are planning to block the trade agreement for the duration of the visa non-reciprocity, which celebrated its third anniversary in July. I do not consider it effective to set up a working party to look at the large increase in unfounded asylum applications, since the core of the problem lies in Canadian asylum law, and not in the EU Member States. Moreover, a working party was set up between Canada and the Czech Republic in 2009, with the participation of the Commission, and it brought no progress. I call on the Commission to support the amendment proposed by myself and other MEPs for a regulation on the visa obligations of third countries as a way of putting effective, visible and firm pressure on Canada, failing which the EU will threaten future complications in Europe-Canada relations.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem16" title="16. One-minute speeches (Rule 150)">
    <intervention id="1-093-000" speaker_id="23820" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="László SURJÁN" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="07-09-1941" birth_place="Kolozsvár" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the one-minute speeches on matters of political importance.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-094-000" speaker_id="26851" name="Nikolaos CHOUNTIS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Greece" birth_date="17-09-1953" birth_place="Lagadia Arkadias" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, my country, Greece, is in the run-up to elections. The President of the European Parliament visited Greece two days ago. During his meeting with the President of the Republic, the President of the Hellenic Republic received a telephone call from Ms Merkel, who suggested that a referendum be held alongside the elections, asking the Greek people if they would accept the measures set out in the Memorandum and if they would want to leave the euro. Mr Schulz witnessed the anger and round condemnation of such intervention by all the political forces. One would therefore expect that, instead of publicising positions which the Greek people have already rejected, he would, on the contrary, opt to do his duty and make a democratic statement stressing that the Greek people should be left in peace to make a democratic decision. He did not do so. This sort of conduct and interference damage the cohesion of the European Union and damage democracy, not only in Greece, but also in the European Union. I trust that the President of the European Parliament will make a position statement on this question of democracy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-095-000" speaker_id="23746" name="Vytautas LANDSBERGIS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Lithuania" birth_date="18-10-1932" birth_place="Kaunas" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="LT">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, colleagues, recently we all witnessed the doubtful management and misconduct of our parliamentary work when a document duly adopted by plenary was later partly cancelled in a discussion of the Conference of Presidents.</p>
      <p sl="en">This happened with the resolution on EU-Azerbaijan negotiations. No parliamentary rule states that, once adopted, a document can afterwards be changed in substance by another Member of Parliament.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deletion of the relevant part of the text was announced as having been made allegedly in accordance with Rule 216, which refers to something different, namely, to possible corrigenda to literal or linguistic errata when discovered in a text after the vote.</p>
      <p sl="en">As this was not the case, the corrigendum – as distributed in a breach of due procedure – looks unlawful when the resolution in the form in which Parliament voted on it was lawful and legitimate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-096-000" speaker_id="96918" name="Derek VAUGHAN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="02-05-1961" birth_place="Merthyr" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I speak to welcome the Connecting Europe Fund, which is proposed for the new financial framework post-2013. Right across Europe, there are still many large infrastructure projects that are needed to boost economic growth. This investment is, of course, needed now more than ever.</p>
      <p sl="en">Indeed, in my own country – Wales – transport infrastructure is still needed, for example, electrification of the railway between London and West Wales, which is so vital for our economy. The UK Government proposes to fund that electrification only as far as Cardiff. I would urge them to fund it at least as far west as Swansea because of its importance to the West Wales economy. But if they are refusing to do that, they should work with others, including the Welsh Government, to ensure that the project goes ahead. They should put in place a Plan B, which should include bidding for Connecting Europe funds when they become available.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-097-000" speaker_id="96922" name="Izaskun BILBAO BARANDICA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Spain" birth_date="27-03-1961" birth_place="Bermeo" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, on 9 May, the organisation, Eurobask, from the Basque Country, decided to approve a manifesto in which we pro-Europe Basques renewed our commitment to the European project.</p>
      <p sl="es">We need a Europe that places its citizens at the heart of the integration project rather than the markets; one that stands up for an alternative to managing globalisation, leading multilateral bodies that are able to regulate the financial market.</p>
      <p sl="es">We want a European economic government that returns the financial system to its conventional mission of supporting the efficacy of the productive economy as a creator of social well-being. To achieve this, a combination of a reduction of the debt and an increase in competitiveness with a maximum investment in research, development and innovation is required, with the specific goal of a low carbon and renewable energy-based economy.</p>
      <p sl="es">We need to free ourselves from dependency, speed up growth and job creation, and establish new unified tools; more dialogue, greater common foreign policy and answer a wholehearted ‘no’ to discourse that criminalises minorities and immigration: we need all human beings to have equal rights in the face of cutbacks for ethnic minorities.</p>
      <p sl="es">In short, a new Europe that is once again a benchmark for education and a social model; a useful and just Union in which to live.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-098-000" speaker_id="111823" name="Nikos CHRYSOGELOS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Greece" birth_date="13-05-1959" birth_place="Athina" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, in order to address the budgetary crisis in Greece, measures are being taken that are provoking reaction from society whereas, on the contrary, a more balanced policy – from a social perspective – could be promoted. I would like to quote an example which is completely missing from the new Economic Adjustment Programme for Greece. I refer to the country’s dependence on imported oil fossil fuels. Greece, like other countries presently in deep recession, is totally dependent on oil imports; however, these put a heavy burden on their economy and significantly increase their balance of trade deficit. The annual cost of imported oil used solely to run power plants on the non-interconnected islands exceeds EUR 300 million. The programme should therefore place greater emphasis on energy efficiency and on the efficient use of natural resources, because this could improve the country’s finances and create jobs, thereby reviving the economy. I therefore think that one of the changes needed to the programme should be such a policy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-099-000" speaker_id="38610" name="Slavi BINEV" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Bulgaria" birth_date="10-12-1965" birth_place="Sofia" p_group="Non" m_state="BG">
      <p sl="bg">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, my immunity is being violated. I am being subjected to political persecution, but the media in Bulgaria remain tight-lipped. The reason is that I am telling the truth.</p>
      <p sl="bg">Following a meeting between supporters of ‘GORD’, the political union I created, the police arrested our followers, and the others and I were treated like criminals. Why? Because of the support for ‘GORD’.</p>
      <p sl="bg">Bulgarian celebrities who have supported ‘GORD’ are being bullied and humiliated because they oppose the government. The prime minister is personally responsible for the acts of repression against us, but he is spineless and others are doing his dirty work. Europe is ignoring my warnings, which is encouraging the dictator Borisov.</p>
      <p sl="bg">The government is abducting people and mocking its opponents. There is no democracy. I am afraid that the European institutions’ lack of action may cost both the good name and the lives of my followers, my relatives and even me.</p>
      <p sl="bg">I call on a united Europe and the leaders of the European parties to take prompt action and adopt a clear stance. If respectable people are confirming that they are being oppressed by those in power because they support me, will you intervene, or will my supporters and I need to seek political asylum?</p>
      <p sl="bg">If Brussels does not protect us from the dictator, to whom should we turn – Moscow, Washington, even Beijing perhaps? This is what the situation is like in Bulgaria.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-100-000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán KELLY" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Ireland" birth_date="26-04-1952" birth_place="Killarney" m_state="IE">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the Fiscal Stability Treaty will be put to the vote in Ireland in a referendum on 31 May, but I want to take this opportunity to denounce the undemocratic nature of the debate.</p>
      <p sl="en">There is a severe distortion of the democratic process following the McKenna judgment, which stipulates that the ‘yes’ and ‘no’ sides of any referendum campaign must be given equal weight in terms of air time during the campaign. This creates a perverse incentive for all sorts of shady interests to campaign against any referendum, often on spurious grounds. Added to this is the absurdly undemocratic nature of allowing vested interests with no democratic mandate – such as Declan Ganley, a failed European Parliament candidate in 2009 – a disproportionate platform on the national airwaves.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tonight, Mr Ganley will be given a similar platform, along with the Deputy Prime Minister, an Tánaiste Eamon Gilmore, on the popular current affairs programme, ‘The Frontline’. Mr Ganley, alongside the Russian economist, Konstantin Gurdgiev, has set up an asset management company in Switzerland called St Columbanus AG. This company would clearly stand to benefit from any financial instability in Ireland caused by a ‘no’ vote. As it states on its own website: ‘The firm provides a safe haven for assets in the midst of the continuing global financial crisis, a service that appears increasingly important in the current European context of fragile peripheral economies, and an unstable eurozone banking sector’.</p>
      <p sl="en">I think giving this platform to Mr Ganley is totally undemocratic, particularly when you consider that 11 of the 12 Irish MEPs who are in favour of the referendum are virtually ignored.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-101-000" speaker_id="39319" name="Maria Eleni KOPPA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Greece" birth_date="01-03-1963" birth_place="Athina" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, the elections on 17 June will be the most important post-war elections for Greece. Voters will be asked to choose if they want a responsible government that can get the country out of the crisis or if they prefer to take the route of populism and facile promises. Within such a crucial framework, with such extreme dilemmas, interventions from outside have a negative effect and ignite reactions even in those willing to listen. The most recent example is Ms Merkel’s proposal to the Greek political leadership that a referendum be held on the question ‘yes or no to the euro’ on the same day as the elections. This is a view that is in the wrong place at the wrong time, because an interim government cannot propose a referendum, because only Parliament, which has been dissolved in the run-up to the elections, can make such a decision and, finally, because referenda are not held just because certain partners demand one. When the PASOK Government proposed a referendum with a very specific question a few months ago, it provoked international reaction, spearheaded by Ms Merkel. Any such intervention is absolutely counter-productive at this moment in time. We call on the Commission and the Council to refrain from taking any action that creates an impression of interference in the internal affairs of a sovereign state. Greece needs a unified voice of support from the Commission, not suggestions and threats.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-102-000" speaker_id="97018" name="Theodoros SKYLAKAKIS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Greece" birth_date="18-10-1959" birth_place="Athina" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, there has been a great deal of talk recently about Greece’s leaving the euro. There is even talk about it leaving the European Union. Unfortunately, there is a great deal of talk by a great many people and there is a risk that they will provoke a crisis before we even get to the June elections. They talk with total disregard for the economic, social and geopolitical consequences of such a move.</p>
      <p sl="el">I think it would be better not to divide Greeks into two factions, depending on whether they vote for or against Europe. We need to realise that this is basically a vote in reaction to the political system that has brought Greece to this tragic pass. We must try and help the productive side of Greece, which deserves a better fate than has been reserved for it to date. Management of the really productive side of Greece has been problematic over the past two years. Unemployment has mainly hit the private sector and the European side is not without responsibility for that.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-103-000" speaker_id="99416" name="Nikolaos SALAVRAKOS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Greece" birth_date="15-02-1946" birth_place="Kalamata" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, European leaders are being called on to strike a balance between austerity and growth in their economies, both under the pressure of election results in France and Greece and under the worried eye of the markets. Strict austerity measures are still forcing people out of work and causing widespread problems of social cohesion throughout the European Union. The results of local and national elections throughout Europe, such as those being held in Italy, Germany and France, reflect a widespread reaction to the policy of strict austerity. One thing is certain: the German model of fiscal prudence and direct economic growth needs to be relaxed so that European societies can regain their balance and maintain their cohesion, which is under threat. The currency is also under threat. We must not push European citizens beyond what they can tolerate. We need to consider the possibility, based on the principle of European solidarity, of a more realistic solution that includes a Eurobond issue, a stronger European Central Bank and quantitative easing.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-104-000" speaker_id="28514" name="Kyriacos TRIANTAPHYLLIDES" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Cyprus" birth_date="03-09-1944" birth_place="Palaihori" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="CY">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, I welcome the conclusions of the Foreign Affairs Council held on 14 May 2012 on the Middle East peace process, in which the European Union reaffirms its commitment to a two-state solution and expresses concern that this solution is being undermined by settlement construction and the demolition of houses and other infrastructure in Area C. At the same time, diplomats in the area have reported that at least 62 infrastructure projects, including water cisterns and sanitation systems funded by the European Union and its Member States, were demolished by Israel in 2011, in addition to the hundreds of houses and arable and livestock holdings. Over the last ten years, Israeli occupying forces have destroyed EU-funded projects worth EUR 50 million. At present, the Israeli authorities have issued demolition orders for 110 infrastructure projects which are in danger of being reduced to rubble at any moment. This infrastructure and those projects that have already been destroyed were built at the expense of European taxpayers. Will the Council and the Commission say what action they intend to take to protect projects built with European taxpayers’ money?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-105-000" speaker_id="96987" name="Ricardo CORTÉS LASTRA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Spain" birth_date="23-09-1969" birth_place="Castro Urdiales" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, there are growing numbers of cases of what are known as stolen babies in Spain, or as they prefer to call them, appropriated children: between 200 000 and 300 000 babies between the 40s and the early 90s.</p>
      <p sl="es">These were genuine plots, involving religious people, doctors and civil servants. Initially, the plots were ideological in nature, where children of political prisoners and republican women were stolen to be given to conservative families. The motives behind these plots soon became purely financial in nature, as stated by Fernando Tena, a sociologist and expert in this historical phenomenon.</p>
      <p sl="es">They assumed they had the moral authority to steal babies from mothers with no means of support and give them to traditional families. This has begun to be brought to light in the last year or so, thanks to the tireless work of the stolen children associations, to whom I would like to express my utmost respect and whom I encourage to continue with their work.</p>
      <p sl="es">I call on the Spanish Government to ensure that justice is done in each case, and on the European Union to continue its efforts to fight slavery and people trafficking.</p>
      <p sl="es">I end with a phrase, Mr President: time is of the essence. There are many fathers and mothers who are not going to have the opportunity to find their children.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-106-000" speaker_id="96749" name="Andrew Henry William BRONS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="16-06-1947" birth_place="London" p_group="Non" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, trying to rescue a country from debt by driving its population into austerity and unemployment is not so different in principle from the 19th century British policy of locking up the indebted in debtors’ prisons.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, borrowing yet more to increase aggregate demand is hardly going to reduce debt. Quantitative easing will increase aggregate demand without increasing debt but, if not matched by increased production, it does tend to be inflationary. We must work from the principle that what is physically possible must be financially possible. If we have infrastructure work that needs to be carried out, and building workers who are unemployed, the latter must be employed to carry out the former.</p>
      <p sl="en">Can inflation be avoided? Yes, if full payment for the work is delayed until the project is complete, is in use and has added to our stock of goods and services. Created money is not inflationary if it is matched, in quantity and in time, by an increase in goods and services.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-107-000" speaker_id="110984" name="Joseph CUSCHIERI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Malta" birth_date="20-02-1968" birth_place="Attard" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="MT">
      <p sl="mt">Mr President, on 1 May, Labour Day was commemorated around Europe. This day serves to remind us of the social and economic achievements of workers. The economic crisis has eroded these achievements. They have come under attack by governments devoid of a social soul, which insist on imposing austerity measures and fiscal discipline whilst ignoring the overwhelming problems and difficulties that this is causing the workers and their families. The economic and financial crisis has become a social crisis. We need to listen to what our workers have to say more than ever before and we have to give them a voice. European workers want greater work opportunities, an increase in investment, and measures that stimulate employment, especially for our youth. This is their right. The unemployment rate in Europe is the highest it has ever been in the past fifteen years, with more than 24 million people unemployed. Austerity measures and fiscal discipline imposed by the European Council are not the solution to unemployment. This is why I endorse the European Parliament proposal, and will seek to promote it. It is a European pledge to our youth that guarantees the right of each and every young person in the European Union to a job, apprenticeship, additional training, or a combination of work and training following a four month unemployment period. In the European political, social and economic contest that we are living through today, this guarantee can be secured through funding from the European Social Fund.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-108-000" speaker_id="113487" name="Alda SOUSA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="04-08-1953" birth_place="Porto" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">Mr President, on 17 June, the Greek people go to the polls to choose their future, their life. Europe is built on this freedom. As such, Jean-Claude Trichet’s statements at the G8 meeting are unacceptable. In effect, the former President of the European Central Bank suggested that a people could lose the right to vote; that a democratically elected government, but one that rejects austerity, could be replaced by a coterie of Commissioners from Brussels.</p>
      <p sl="pt">The blackmail of the fiscal compact is also unacceptable. We consider Europe to be democracy; solidarity between peoples. It is not, and nor can it be, the enforced impoverishment of those peoples. That is why I am asking you, my fellow Members, are you prepared to accept this colonial regime?</p>
      <p sl="pt">On behalf of the people of Europe, I am sure that your response will be pro-democracy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-109-000" speaker_id="96845" name="Corneliu VADIM TUDOR" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="28-11-1949" birth_place="Bucureşti" p_group="Non" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">Mr President, there are terrible, shocking situations occurring around the world day and night. The dogs of violence have been unleashed and can no longer be stopped by anyone. The most vulnerable victims are people without any kind of protection. Take, for example, the case of a young Romanian, 38-year-old Virgil Cristian Pop. Locked up in a prison in Lecce, Italy, he was held in solitary confinement for six months where he was brutally beaten, after which he went on hunger strike. Unfortunately, no one believed him and he was completely ignored. Then, the poor chap died after not eating for 50 days.</p>
      <p sl="ro">The same lack of humanity is also demonstrated by the forces of repression which dish out beatings to environmental, anti-globalisation or anti-armament protesters, or to sports fans. Nearly every day we witness outrageous scenes. There are some assault units made up of police and other law enforcement officers, equipped as if they were from another planet, trampling on women and men, young and old, who carry no weapons other than a flower at the most. Yet, these gorillas and their political masters call this democracy and keeping public order. However, throughout history it has been the people who have always been right, not the slaves of these overlords acting like some ‘kapos ’ in a trance. Unfortunately, Hitler and Stalin have not died, but have only been reincarnated.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-110-000" speaker_id="97050" name="Antigoni PAPADOPOULOU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Cyprus" birth_date="08-07-1954" birth_place="Morfou" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="CY">
      <p sl="el">Mr President, free and democratic elections in France, Finland, the Netherlands and Greece have illustrated the increasing protest of citizens against strict austerity and the failed recipes of structural reform and strict fiscal prudence applied to date at European level. The new wind of change in France and elsewhere is reviving the hope that this will, at long last, mark the end of neoliberal policies and that Europe will return to a philosophy of growth, employment and real social solidarity. I trust that, on 17 June, Greece will acquire a government and will remain in the euro, because if it were to leave, that would cause a negative chain reaction in the countries in southern Europe and in the euro area and would impact on the systemic stability of the European financial system. Undisguised blackmail of the Greek people on the part of Ms Merkel and other high-ranking officials is, at best, unacceptable and unnecessary.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-111-000" speaker_id="96706" name="João FERREIRA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="20-11-1978" birth_place="Lisboa" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="pt">Mr President, in Portugal, recent weeks have seen yet another step backwards for society and civilisation. Sponsored by the European Union and the International Monetary Fund, the national parties have signed off on – are accepting, advocating and implementing – a veritable pact of aggression against the country and its people.</p>
      <p sl="pt">Changes to labour legislation are an attack on the historic achievements of the workers and yet another savage blow to an already weakened democracy. They facilitate redundancies, curtail compensation, cut overtime and rest days, reduce days off and abolish public holidays; that is, they impose forced and unpaid labour, and attempt to universalise precarious contracts and dismantle collective bargaining.</p>
      <p sl="pt">In this way, the Portuguese workers will be extorted of yet more millions of euro. They also promote the destruction of more jobs – which could exceed 90 000 – at a time when unemployment is already at historic highs.</p>
      <p sl="pt">It is not too late to change course. Now is the time! That will be the message once again when the streets of Lisbon are filled once more next Saturday.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-112-000" speaker_id="23820" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="László SURJÁN" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="07-09-1941" birth_place="Kolozsvár" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="unknown">The item is hereby closed.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem17" title="17. European Union’s internal security strategy (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-114-000" speaker_id="23820" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="László SURJÁN" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="07-09-1941" birth_place="Kolozsvár" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report by Rita Borsellino, on behalf of the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs, on the European Union’s internal security strategy (2010/2308(INI)) (A7-0143/2012).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-115-000" speaker_id="96916" name="Rita BORSELLINO" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur" nationality="Italy" birth_date="02-06-1945" birth_place="Palermo" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="it">Mr President, Commissioner, ladies and gentlemen, it is an emotional moment for me as I come to present my own-initiative report on the European Union’s internal security strategy. It is, in fact, 20 years ago this week – on 23 May to be precise – that Judge Giovanni Falcone, his wife and his police escort were murdered.</p>
      <p sl="it">I would like to dedicate the adoption of this report to all the victims of mafias, organised crime and terrorism, and, in particular, to Melissa Bassi, the young victim of last Saturday’s attack on a school in Brindisi, in which six other girls were also wounded. The motive for the attack is still unknown, but it clearly comes within the context of growing tension and lack of security caused by the crisis, which organisations or individuals may be tempted to exploit for violently subversive ends. My thoughts also go out to the victims of the earthquake in Emilia Romagna, because natural disasters also come within the Union’s internal security remit.</p>
      <p sl="it">The text that we will vote on tomorrow highlights the importance of having a consistent security strategy for the Union, and in that respect I would like to thank the Commission for the major effort it has made in drafting this strategy.</p>
      <p sl="it">As is repeatedly shown in the report, security must always be pursued in accordance with the rule of law and people’s fundamental rights, which form an integral and inseparable part of this strategy. That is also why the role of the EU institutions in defining and implementing the strategy is of particular importance, especially in the post-Lisbon context.</p>
      <p sl="it">The European Parliament also needs to play an appropriate role in this context, both in setting priorities for the strategy and during the evaluation stage. This role derives from the fully-fledged legislative powers that Parliament has acquired in matters of security. It is also essential for ensuring proper democratic control, which the European Parliament should exercise alongside the national parliaments. That is why we will undertake to establish regular links between the European Parliament and the national parliaments, so as to create a parliamentary political round associated with the Commission’s annual report on this subject and ending with an annual parliamentary report on the implementation status of the internal security strategy.</p>
      <p sl="it">We believe the Union needs to have a clear idea of the extent of the threats to internal security, which it currently does not have. We therefore call on Europol, with the support of the other EU institutions and agencies, to conduct a global analysis of the threats facing the Union, on the basis of a more transparent and robust methodology and relying on information contributed by the Member States.</p>
      <p sl="it">In relation to the five key objectives identified by the Commission, we are of the opinion that they are not exhaustive and that the order of priorities could probably have been better structured. The fight against terrorism, organised crime and mafias is, and must remain, a key priority within the internal security strategy. The Union must know not only how to react to whatever happens in Europe, but also how to prevent and interpret it. That has been shown by the events in Utøya and now again in Brindisi. We need to be able to recognise the early signs of violent radicalisation, barbarisation of the social milieu and violent extremism.</p>
      <p sl="it">Judicial cooperation is the main element lacking in the security strategy outlined by the Commission, and this gap needs to be filled. Joint action by judicial systems across Europe is crucial if we are to clamp down on crime and terrorism; strengthening such action must be prioritised, as must fighting corruption and combating environmental, economic and corporate crime.</p>
      <p sl="it">While we agree with the emphasis placed on fighting cybercrime, the Commission’s decision to include the protection of intellectual property rights among our security priorities hardly seems justified. As the issue of the Anti-Counterfeiting Trade Agreement shows, this topic is not just a security matter but is highly complex and involves people’s rights, and therefore it requires a more thorough debate.</p>
      <p sl="it">I would like to finish by thanking all the shadow rapporteurs who played a part in drafting this report, as well as the staff of the political groups and my personal assistant.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-117-000" speaker_id="96654" name="Jaroslav PAŠKA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="20-06-1954" birth_place="Banská Štiavnica" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group - Vice" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="sk">Mr President, the internal security of the European Union is being attacked by numerous threats which are, due to our policy of open borders, quickly spreading throughout Europe. Perhaps the greatest current internal security issue facing the European Union is increasingly sophisticated organised crime. The massive influx of economic migrants from poor countries in Asia or Africa, and also large differences in living standards in certain regions of the Union, generate exploitable potential for the organisation of illegal black market labour, prostitution and widespread defrauding of the social systems of wealthy countries. We cannot therefore ignore the link between internal security and the political and security turmoil that surrounds us, and we should therefore aim for a comprehensive European Union security policy and formulate this system in such a way that clear links between foreign influences and the domestic consequences for the security of the European Union are contained in such a system. I believe that a comprehensive approach of this nature is an essential prerequisite for a successful security policy within the European Union.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-118-000" speaker_id="96814" name="Elena BĂSESCU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="24-04-1980" birth_place="Constanţa" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">Mr President, creating an area of freedom, security and justice is one of the European Union’s main objectives. Concrete measures are needed to achieve this to ensure a greater degree of personal safety for every citizen. The Commission communication marks a first step towards this aim by identifying the five key areas and proposing specific actions. However, further efforts are required to combat organised crime and crime in general. On many occasions, an international criminal network may be behind some seemingly petty crimes, such as pick-pocketing or car theft, which affect so many ordinary people. Against this background, I support Europol becoming more involved in analysing and managing the main internal security risks, as stated in Article 6.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-120-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Cecilia Malmström" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to join Ms Borsellino in fiercely condemning this weekend’s atrocities in Brindisi. This is something that we can never defend. Whatever the causes behind this, the great symbolism that it was the school named after Ms Falcone is, of course, something that we must reflect upon. The girl came from a village that I visited only two weeks ago, to learn how the community works against the Mafia and works to confiscate the goods of organised crime. This is a barbaric act that we must all condemn.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me also thank you for your report. I think you have done excellent work. I would also like to thank the shadow rapporteurs. It really contributes to the development of the internal security strategy. We fully share your view that the internal security strategy should be a shared agenda for all the institutions and the agencies, with clear roles and responsibilities and a common goal. The security of citizens is at the heart of all our efforts.</p>
      <p sl="en">The internal security strategy provides the best platform to respond to security threats, encompassing both policy setting and operational cooperation, which is now taking shape in a cycle on serious and organised crime. In this context, we very much welcome the idea of the ‘parliamentary policy cycle’, involving the European Parliament, as well as national parliaments, in a joint debate on the state of play with regular reports from the Commission. The Commission is currently working on the second implementation report of the internal security strategy, which will be published by the end of the year.</p>
      <p sl="en">Implementing the internal security strategy is about keeping promises on the five objectives. There is no ranking between those objectives, which are fighting and preventing serious and organised crime, terrorism and cybercrime, management of our external borders, and building resilience to natural and man-made disasters.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have achieved quite a lot since the first publication: for instance, the report on confiscation of goods, the establishment of the radicalisation awareness network, the proposal on EU PNR, and the proposal to establish a cyber centre. We are also preparing, for the end of this year, reforms of Cepol, Europol and Eurojust, which would – as you call for – improve the cooperation between police agencies, but also on a national level. We will also present proposals on improving our protection against critical infrastructure and, by the end of the year, we will hold a conference gathering our experience and building on one year of the establishment of the radicalisation awareness network, with some ideas and policies presented from that network.</p>
      <p sl="en">This second report will assess the state of play of the previously promised actions, including the policy cycle, but we are also looking at the opportunities that security can offer in responding to the economic and financial crisis because, of course, this is also key in establishing an environment where people, investors and companies feel safe and secure.</p>
      <p sl="en">I believe that Ms Borsellino’s report is a very valuable milestone in Parliament’s involvement in the internal security strategy and I look forward to working with you on this matter.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-121-000" speaker_id="23820" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="László SURJÁN" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="07-09-1941" birth_place="Kolozsvár" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place on Tuesday, 22 May 2012.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 149)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-122-000" speaker_id="96707" name="Ágnes HANKISS" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="07-03-1950" birth_place="Budapest" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="hu">As shadow rapporteur for the internal security strategy, I must express my thanks to Ms Borsellino for the openness and flexibility with which she received the proposals of the Group of the European People’s Party. Our successful compromises stand as proof that if we address the issues and challenges of internal security on a professional basis and free from prejudice, we can find middle ground and rise above our political differences.</p>
      <p sl="hu">The internal security strategy is an important tool for effectively combating several forms of crime. It focuses on the fight against the various forms of international organised crime, such as mafias or ‘white-collar’ crime and money laundering, as well as on reinforcing European counter-terrorism activities.</p>
      <p sl="hu">It is crucial to develop a common threat assessment system and to better coordinate the Member State practices necessary for the effective protection of critical information infrastructure. In order to guarantee cyber security in Europe, cooperation between EU public and private sector participants as well as civilian and military actors is indispensable. The cyber security centre to be established also serves to further this goal. One of our urgent tasks is to complete the identification of European critical infrastructures. The protection of our external borders and, not least, the prevention of and response to natural and man-made disasters, also require joint action.</p>
      <p sl="hu">In order to achieve the aforementioned goals, it is unavoidable to allocate proportionate budgetary resources to them and seek to ensure that the measures included in the internal security strategy are represented appropriately in the budget for 2014-2020.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-123-000" speaker_id="96823" name="Petru Constantin LUHAN" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Romania" birth_date="19-03-1977" birth_place="Jud. Suceava" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">Internet security is currently one of the European Union’s key political priorities. The Internet obviously provides a vital infrastructure, and its disruption could result in heavy losses and risks to citizens’ safety.</p>
      <p sl="ro">This is precisely why I think that Directive 2008/114 ought to have its scope of application extended to include information and communications technologies and recognise them as a critical sector. I regard it as a matter of urgency to set up a European early warning network for critical infrastructures and include in the warning system financial services and systems in the areas of health care, food, water supply, nuclear research and industry.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem18" title="18. An EU approach to criminal law (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-125-000" speaker_id="23820" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="László SURJÁN" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="07-09-1941" birth_place="Kolozsvár" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report by Cornelis de Jong, on behalf of the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs, on an EU approach to criminal law (2010/2310 (INI)) (A7-0144/2012).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-126-000" speaker_id="96748" name="Dennis de JONG" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur" nationality="Netherlands" birth_date="22-05-1955" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="NL">
      <p sl="nl">Mr President, criminal law is not just another topic to be discussed. Criminal penalties involve curtailment of the fundamental rights of suspects and convicted criminals. You have to tread carefully in an area like this. Of course, it is justified to curtail fundamental rights in certain circumstances, but there have to be good reasons for doing so, as enshrined in international instruments of human rights and the Charter of Fundamental Rights.</p>
      <p sl="nl">By and large, there are two threats. First of all, there is us, the politicians. The media are paying more attention than in the past to striking crimes. Lawyers sometimes appear before the cameras more often than politicians, and even the Public Prosecutor and the judiciary nowadays make use of an army of advisors. Politicians tend to zero in on this by promulgating new laws that either expand the scope of criminal offences or establish new ones, or else introduce tougher punishments. If they can then also manage to convince other European politicians that such legislation should be introduced all over Europe, they believe they have provided a successful response. Things should not be that way, however.</p>
      <p sl="nl">Criminal law is not suited to recording minor successes in the short term. Before agreeing new definitions for offences or increasing punishments, you need to have thought through the consequences properly. Does this actually result in more criminals being imprisoned and re-socialised, and is public opinion still interested in these tougher punishments in the longer term, or is what we are dealing with here an occasional shock to society that could just as well have been dealt with through better enforcement of existing laws?</p>
      <p sl="nl">The second threat, sadly, comes from Brussels. We have become accustomed to making liberal use of the competences given to the EU by a series of treaties. The Treaty lists a number of crimes where minimum harmonisation is self-evident. In addition, the EU may also push through minimum harmonisation of crimes where necessary for the implementation of harmonised EU policy. This actually provides an awful lot of elbow room and the truth is I could put forward a reason to regulate at European level for each and every crime.</p>
      <p sl="nl">The same Treaty also emphasises respect for national traditions and cultural differences, which are exactly what come to the fore in relation to criminal law. The emergency brake procedure, which is a special feature of criminal law that enables a Member State to resist harmonisation that would be contrary to a fundamental principle in its constitution, is the procedural consequence of this.</p>
      <p sl="nl">There is a tension between these two elements, the generous competences and the restraint and the respect for national traditions. That is why we cannot take the same path in relation to criminal law as in other spheres: namely harmonising here and there, bit by bit, on an uncoordinated basis, without being able to cite very clear, convincing reasons for doing so.</p>
      <p sl="nl">In my report, it has now been made clear that, in the field of criminal law, the politics of symbolism is to be avoided; there must be no political hype. Before you move to harmonisation, you first have to go through an assessment framework that proves the added value of harmonisation statistically and also makes clear that there are no other less intrusive solutions available without resorting to criminal law. In addition, human rights remain a crucial factor and there needs to be constant and explicit assessment in this regard also.</p>
      <p sl="nl">It is just as important to monitor consistency and coherence. All EU bodies will have to put special measures in place in this regard, including the European Parliament. The Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs has no right of coordination, but disjointed criminal law is poor criminal law.</p>
      <p sl="nl">I would like to thank all the Members of the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs for their overwhelming support for this report. I hope that we will be able to further flesh out these rules together with the Commission and the Council in an interinstitutional working group. I am confident that, together, we will succeed in ensuring that future rules concerning criminal law will only be introduced where truly necessary and that, furthermore, such new rules will be of high quality.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-128-000" speaker_id="96761" name="Axel VOSS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="07-04-1963" birth_place="Hameln" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, I would like to start by expressing my warm thanks to Cornelis de Jong for the commitment that he has demonstrated here. He has produced a very good and very balanced report, and I am very pleased that we are making progress on the substantive issues in small steps. I have to say that I think he is right here – it is good to see that criminal law has, in fact, evolved differently in the various Member States and we therefore need different harmonisation measures, and since it is simply the strongest argument that we have for sometimes curtailing certain fundamental rights, we should therefore go about this very carefully – both in procedural matters and as regards material criminal law.</p>
      <p sl="de">That is why I believe it is worth stopping to think about whether, with this in mind, we should also develop a concept, so that we do not start with the European Investigation Order and then argue the principles afterwards, but should instead do things the other way round. I would therefore ask that we take a conceptual approach to such matters, rather than doing the final things first and the initial things, in fact, last.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-129-000" speaker_id="96736" name="Jan Philipp ALBRECHT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-12-1982" birth_place="Braunschweig" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, Commissioner Malmström, I am singing from the same hymn sheet as Mr Voss. Mr de Jong’s fine report makes it clear that we urgently need to establish once and for all a coordinated strategy for how we structure and harmonise criminal law, so that we refrain from only ever making progress in areas that serve short-term interests and instead debate a long-term, coherent system of criminal law.</p>
      <p sl="de">Maybe it would be a really good idea for you and the Commissioner for Justice, Fundamental Rights and Citizenship to sit down together and think about how we can make common progress on this, because time and again we struggle to make the link between the two perspectives clear – particularly to the Council. When it comes to the European Investigation Order and the minimum standards in criminal proceedings, we will naturally find difficulties arising time and time again as regards reconciling the views of Parliament and the Council. The Commission could undoubtedly play an important role as a mediator here. That is what I would ask you to do.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-130-000" speaker_id="28497" name="Gerard BATTEN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="27-03-1954" birth_place="London" p_group="Europe of Freedom and Direct Democracy Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, this report confirms what I have been warning my constituents in London about, and the British people generally, for some years, which is that the EU intends to create its own system of criminal law.</p>
      <p sl="en">This project is already very well advanced and very comprehensive and I have written about it in a report of my own, Freedom, Security &amp; Justice? or The Creation of a European Union Police State .</p>
      <p sl="en">We do not need an EU system of criminal law in England. We have something called the common law which has taken a thousand years to evolve. We have safeguards under the Magna Carta, the Bill of Rights and habeas corpus, which are being swept away under this new system. They are being set aside. A British citizen can now be sent off to any corner of the European Union on the strength of a piece of paper with vague accusations. They can be imprisoned for months or years. The English and Scottish courts have abdicated their duty to protect their own citizens from arbitrary arrest and imprisonment.</p>
      <p sl="en">Your system of EU criminal law would do for our liberties what the European single currency has done for your economies.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-131-000" speaker_id="2307" name="Hubert PIRKER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Austria" birth_date="03-10-1948" birth_place="Gries" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, what we are looking at here is how security can be guaranteed in the European Union in the long term. That was the case with the last report and indirectly it is, in fact, the objective here. We can ask for all the strategies we like from Commissioner Malmström, but if we do not succeed in implementing these strategies and, in parallel with this, applying criminal law across Europe, then all our initiatives and all our strategies will be useless.</p>
      <p sl="de">I am therefore in favour of us doing everything we can to harmonise criminal law across Europe, naturally taking into account national traditions, but nonetheless it must be our goal to use harmonised criminal law to implement what we have developed in the area of security in the way of initiatives, what has already been achieved in this area – from border protection, through the fight against organised crime, to cybercrime.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-132-000" speaker_id="96654" name="Jaroslav PAŠKA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="20-06-1954" birth_place="Banská Štiavnica" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group - Vice" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="sk">Madam President, I agree that the same requirements should be defined in the Maastricht and Lisbon Treaties so that we may work on the creation of a common European criminal law. However, I would like to point out that this journey will be very difficult, complicated and highly sensitive. In Europe, we have many traditions, whether social or judicial, on which law in different countries or regions has been based. An objection has already been raised by my colleague from the United Kingdom, who pointed out that law in the British Isles has a different way of addressing problems there, as they have the law of precedence, whereas in continental Europe, different rules apply. My country, for example, uses an Austro-Hungarian legal basis. I believe that Sweden and the Nordic countries use completely different rules. It therefore follows that there are some differences in the legal systems that we have to consider very sensitively. I am personally highly sceptical that we will be successful in this respect in the foreseeable future.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-134-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Cecilia Malmström" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I would like to thank the rapporteur very much for having taken the initiative to prepare a report on this issue. It links in perfectly with the communication on EU criminal policy that the Commission published last September, and I am really glad to see that this communication has achieved its goal in launching a debate inside and outside the institutions. This was our aim in the Commission: to summarise for the first time the principles guiding legislation on criminal law so as to strengthen the enforcement of EU policies under the new legal framework of the Lisbon Treaty. Mr de Jong’s report very much follows that objective, and I am really grateful for that.</p>
      <p sl="en">Clear and transparent rules on when to use European criminal law are crucial, and we fully share the view of the rapporteur that any legislation at EU level must fully respect the principles of subsidiarity and proportionality. We know – and it has been clear from the debate here – that criminal law is a sensitive area, with quite substantial differences between the different Member States. This has to be taken into account. Because of that, it is crucial that we ensure full respect of the rights guaranteed by the Charter of Fundamental Rights and the European Convention on Human Rights for all EU criminal law legislation. We need to understand each other’s systems better in order to be able to assess how we can bring them closer together where this is necessary, while respecting the different legal systems and traditions in all Member States.</p>
      <p sl="en">EU criminal law to strengthen the enforcement of EU policies is only needed in selected areas, but it can provide significant added value. We have seen this, for example, in the context of environmental crime, where two important directives were adopted in 2008 and 2009. These were the first instruments adopted on criminal law in the ordinary legislative proposal. The fruitful cooperation between the Commission and Parliament on these files has set an example for future work.</p>
      <p sl="en">We also see the importance of common EU rules when it comes to discussing proposals for criminal law measures to fight insider dealing and market manipulation. It is clear that the EU financial markets can only have investors’ confidence and trust if we send a strong signal in the form of common rules.</p>
      <p sl="en">In addition to rendering EU policies effective through the introduction of criminal law measures, the Treaty establishes ten ‘euro crimes’ that are both serious and have a cross-border dimension, justifying the need to legislate common minimum rules on definitions of offences and sanctions. Much has been achieved in relation to the latter in the post-Lisbon period, specifically with the adoption of directives on the fight against trafficking in human beings as well as the fight against sexual exploitation of children. Negotiations are being finalised regarding the Cybercrime Directive, and the newly-adopted proposal on the harmonisation of confiscation laws is about to be negotiated.</p>
      <p sl="en">All these initiatives have so far contributed to the development of Treaty provisions contributing, inter alia , to a pragmatic interpretation of the concept of common minimum rules in both areas, and they are important frames of reference for further development of criminal law at EU level.</p>
      <p sl="en">Putting in place a coherent EU criminal policy requires further reflection and discussion on many legal issues. The European Commission has just set up an expert group which will meet for the first time in June, and we will be happy to report once they have met. It will be composed of experienced academics and practitioners in the field. This expert group will be a forum to discuss the challenging and difficult questions which arise when the EU considers criminal law measures and advises on the best way forward.</p>
      <p sl="en">We fully share the approach set out in the resolution. For instance, our criminal law communication also supports the idea of simpler language to guide EU legislators when they draft criminal law provisions.</p>
      <p sl="en">So the Commission’s communication last year, and this report – which has received considerable support here – are the starting point for the shaping of a common EU criminal policy, and I look forward to working with Parliament and moving further towards a common goal: a true area of freedom, security and justice.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-135-000" speaker_id="96639" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Isabelle DURANT" nationality="Belgium" birth_date="04-09-1954" birth_place="Bruxelles" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="BE">
      <p sl="unknown">The item is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place on Tuesday, 22 May 2012.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem19" title="19. A 2020 perspective for women in Turkey (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-137-000" speaker_id="96639" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Isabelle DURANT" nationality="Belgium" birth_date="04-09-1954" birth_place="Bruxelles" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="BE">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report by Emine Bozkurt on a 2020 perspective for women in Turkey [2011/2066(INI) ] (A7-0138/2012).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-138-000" speaker_id="28171" name="Emine BOZKURT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur" nationality="Netherlands" birth_date="09-08-1967" birth_place="Zaandam" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="NL">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, it is a great pleasure to be presenting to you today my third report on the situation of women in Turkey, which presents a strategy towards 2020 and is inspired by the gender aspect of Europe 2020. In preparing my report, I spoke to various ministers, Members of Parliament, women’s NGOs and many others, such as young university students. Of all these meetings, the one that affected me the most was the meeting I had with Arzu, a woman who was staying in the shelter. Her story has helped me in evaluating the law on the protection of women from violence. I will come back to that.</p>
      <p sl="en">In my report, I have made a call for zero tolerance for violence against women. The report indicates what needs to be done about violence and stresses that, without good implementation, even the best laws cannot protect women, so I put forward suggestions to ensure that the law is strictly applied. More shelters are needed. The existing shelters should be made safer, and the personnel must be better trained. There should be vocational courses offered to women in the shelters. This is important because many of the women who have been victims of violence are housewives or, like Arzu, have lost their jobs because their ex-husbands also attacked them at their places of work. Arzu was continually beaten up by her husband even after obtaining a divorce. The law which was in effect at that time did not protect victims who were not married. It must be made clear to Turkey that the law protects women, regardless of the relationship between the victim and the perpetrator.</p>
      <p sl="en">Many positive developments are also taking place in Turkey. The Ankara Prosecutor’s Office has established a specialised bureau dealing solely with violence against women, which is very successful. We need more of these in Turkish cities and rural areas.</p>
      <p sl="en">The gender gap in primary education has been closed, but there are worries concerning the new education reform. The new system should not jeopardise the successes achieved so far concerning the schooling of girls. The percentage of women in the labour market has risen to around 30%, but more needs to be done on issues such as child care and maternity leave to further increase this ratio. Trade union activities should also be made more accessible for women.</p>
      <p sl="en">In my report, I ask for a new law on political parties and elections which would establish a temporary mandatory quota system ensuring the fair representation of women in electoral lists. In order to successfully make the necessary changes, a change in mentality is needed. Women are not only mothers or members of a family, they are individuals. This must be made crystal clear.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission is actively engaged in improving women’s rights in Turkey. Last week, during the launch of the positive agenda, Commissioner Füle once more highlighted the importance of women’s rights within the positive agenda, as well as the importance of Chapter 23 negotiations on this subject. Indeed, in order to give the EU more leverage in the area of women’s rights, Chapter 23 negotiations should be opened. I want strongly to underline the importance of the Commission and Turkey continuing to promote women’s rights in Turkey and to place women’s rights at the heart of the accession negotiations.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, I would like to thank everyone, especially the shadow rapporteurs, who have contributed to the drafting of this report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-140-000" speaker_id="96814" name="Elena BĂSESCU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="24-04-1980" birth_place="Constanţa" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">Madam President, the measures that have been adopted up to now by the Turkish authorities highlight their commitment to defending and promoting women’s rights. However, further efforts are required to implement the adopted legislation, especially in areas such as domestic violence. Setting up a specialised service within the Public Prosecutor’s Office marks a step forward to this end.</p>
      <p sl="ro">At the same time, attention needs to be focused on information and prevention measures. In this context, I welcome a special Gender Equality Commission being set up within the Ministry of Education. This proves the Turkish Government’s awareness of the need to combat the stereotypes and bring about a lasting change in mentality. Last but not least, I am pleased at the rise in the number of women in the Turkish Parliament, but I do not endorse the report’s recommendations on establishing a quota system.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-141-000" speaker_id="97050" name="Antigoni PAPADOPOULOU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Cyprus" birth_date="08-07-1954" birth_place="Morfou" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="CY">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, Turkey, as a candidate country, is obliged to abide by the acquis communautaire . It must respect human rights, including women’s rights and gender equality. It must implement legislative reforms and empower women in social, economic and political life so as to reach the objectives of Europe 2020.</p>
      <p sl="en">Turkey still has a long way to go. According to progress reports on Turkey for 2010 and 2011, Turkey needs to implement the existing legal framework in order to fight honour killings, forced marriages and violence against women, and to combat female illiteracy, discrimination, stereotypes and the very low female participation rate in the Turkish labour force and in political life.</p>
      <p sl="en">We therefore call on Turkey to implement comprehensive reforms, to fulfil the Copenhagen criteria for the sake of its own modernisation, and to establish a climate of mutual understanding and respect with all EU Member States, thus making it possible to exchange best practices on gender equality with all of those States for the benefit of its own female citizens.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-142-000" speaker_id="97017" name="Ulrike LUNACEK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Austria" birth_date="26-05-1957" birth_place="Krems a.d. Donau" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, first of all, on behalf of our Green shadow rapporteur, Marije Cornelissen, who cannot be here and who asked me to speak, let me thank the rapporteur and the other shadows in the Committee on Women’s Rights and Gender Equality for a very good report, which I think will be helpful to you, Ms Malmström, and others in the Commission in promoting women’s rights in Turkey, more than has been done up till now.</p>
      <p sl="en">Legislation in Turkey is rather good at several levels, but implementation is lacking, especially when it comes to domestic violence against women. For example, it is still a fact that two or three women are killed every day in Turkey in the domestic area by their husbands or families. More has to be done there in order to punish the person who was the perpetrator, but also family members who silently look on and do not speak out.</p>
      <p sl="en">One fact that also hinders women’s empowerment in Turkey is the low employment rate of women: only 24% of women are employed. That has been a fact for a number of years, so that is an area where more investment is needed. I find it very important to have a national action plan to combat violence against women. Other countries, for example Spain, have shown over the last few years what can be done; that is something that I hope can be achieved. Education for women is important. It has improved but not yet enough. I also think it would be important to open Chapter 23.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-143-000" speaker_id="96654" name="Jaroslav PAŠKA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="20-06-1954" birth_place="Banská Štiavnica" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group - Vice" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="sk">Madam President, I greatly welcome this report as the issue that is addressed here is indeed a very serious one. This is especially due to the fact that Turkey has applied to join the European Union and we should therefore monitor the rights and status of women in that country very carefully. The report is very clear and very concise, and notes that their legislation is more or less in order, but its application in real life is problematic. The passage where it says that spouses, friends and family members murder at least two women every day is, in my view, particularly shocking. Also, the application of laws on education and the participation of women in business or politics is highly informative. It says that the participation of women in such areas – both in real terms and in economic terms – is indeed very weak. I would like to focus on measures that we should pursue as the European Union and maybe also as community organisations. In particular, we should appeal to politicians to act as personal examples and to behave as is required of them. Then we should use the media, television and radio to promote women’s rights and to protect women more. And, of course, this appeal to social awareness would be reflected in the policy which is implemented in the regions and this is, I believe, the most important factor – to get this policy to the people and to the regions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-144-000" speaker_id="28178" name="Miroslav MIKOLÁŠIK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="11-09-1952" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="sk">Madam President, Turkey has improved its legal framework for women’s rights. However, the transposition of legislation into everyday practice is not at a satisfactory level. Violence against women therefore remains one of the most pressing problems in Turkey. I consider it shocking that during their lives, 39% of women encounter physical violence, and that every day, two to three women fall victim to their husbands, other family members or friends. The employment rate of women, which is approximately 24%, is closely related to the persisting differences between men and women in secondary and higher education. The 14 percent share of women MPs in the Turkish Parliament can also be considered to be a reflection of social reality. I welcome the report on the current situation and future prospects of women in Turkey. This report has systematically assessed the legal status and reality marked by violence against women, and also the actual participation of women in the labour market and in politics.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-146-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Cecilia Malmström" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I would like to thank the rapporteur, Ms Bozkurt, for this report. It is really good and well balanced. As is rightly emphasised, the issue of women’s rights is a major challenge on Turkey’s road to the European Union and it certainly merits a special report. The unanimous voting in the committee shows the strong support received from shadow rapporteurs and others, so thank you very much, Ms Bozkurt, for your work.</p>
      <p sl="en">As you mentioned, Commissioner Füle was in Turkey last week and he discussed women’s rights with a range of civil society representatives. Protecting women’s rights in Turkey, promoting gender equality and combating violence against women remain major challenges. The legal framework guaranteeing women’s rights and gender equality is broadly in place and has been further reinforced by the recent law to protect women and family members from violence, and the Commission agrees that this is an important step forward. But, as all of you have underlined, the legal framework is not enough: it needs to translate into political, social and economic reality for women everywhere in Turkey.</p>
      <p sl="en">Legislation needs to be implemented consistently across the country. Further training and awareness-raising on women’s rights and gender equality are needed, particularly for the police. Of course, as was also underlined in the report, serious problems remain with so-called ‘honour’ killings (which is a horrible term because there is nothing honourable in such brutality), as well as early enforced marriages and domestic violence against women.</p>
      <p sl="en">The report calls upon us in the Commission to make the issue of women’s rights central to the negotiations with Turkey, and it mentions in this respect progress on the negotiation chapter devoted to the judiciary and fundamental rights. As you know, the positive agenda in EU-Turkey relations, which was endorsed by the Council in December, includes the judiciary and fundamental rights among its main features. During his visit to Turkey, Commissioner Füle launched concrete work on this positive agenda. I am happy to report that he chaired the first meeting of the working group on judiciary and fundamental rights with Justice Minister Ergin, with the aim of fostering reforms in Turkey in this crucial area. He also had a separate meeting with the Minister on the same day to underline these issues.</p>
      <p sl="en">Commissioner Füle told the Minister that steps need to be taken to implement the new law on violence against women and to improve the real-life situation of women in Turkey as regards political representation and access to education and employment. While we need to combat violence against women as a matter of urgency, we also need to keep a focus on all the other aspects – and that is precisely what this resolution does.</p>
      <p sl="en">Madam President, honourable Members, we share the same concerns about women in Turkey. The issues mentioned here in the debate are indeed grave; some of the stories are compelling, and there is a lot to be done. Reforms need to be further accelerated.</p>
      <p sl="en">As I said, Commissioner Füle met civil society representatives and they assured him that they see the European Union as a vital source of support for their cause. We have legislation guaranteeing equality; we have standards protecting women against violence; and that is why the accession process is so important with regard to reforms on vital issues such as women’s rights, and the implementation of those reforms.</p>
      <p sl="en">We must continue to encourage the progress of reform. Our leverage and influence in Turkey will be all the more credible and all the stronger if our commitments – as outlined in 2005 when we launched the accession negotiations – remain unambiguous.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-147-000" speaker_id="96639" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Isabelle DURANT" nationality="Belgium" birth_date="04-09-1954" birth_place="Bruxelles" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="BE">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place on Tuesday, 22 May 2012.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 149)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-147-500" speaker_id="26829" name="Siiri OVIIR" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Estonia" birth_date="03-11-1947" birth_place="Tallinn" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="EE">
      <p sl="et">As an EU candidate country, Turkey is required to adhere to the Union’s values and the acquis communautaire . It is a positive development that the legislation pertaining to women’s rights has largely been enacted. Today, we are at a stage where these rights are already being implemented. It is promising that a Ministry of Family and Social Policies has been established, a Committee on Women’s Rights and Gender Equality has been created in Parliament, national action plans have been approved, etc. These are not mere words or documents: all of the ministers concerned are working together and implementing projects to enact legislation aimed at improving women’s living standards. One of the more serious problems in Turkey today is domestic violence against women. In this area, the legislation is still incomplete. It is nevertheless a positive development that social awareness in this area is continually increasing. The media, which have an invaluable role to play in changing social attitudes, have behaved responsibly. The rapporteur, Emine Bozkurt, has prepared a relevant and competent report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-148-000" speaker_id="96770" name="Joanna Katarzyna SKRZYDLEWSKA" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Poland" birth_date="17-02-1977" birth_place="Łódź" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">The Bozkurt report on a 2020 perspective for women in Turkey is extremely important because of the fact that the document raises fundamental issues such as combating violence against women, honour killings, the phenomenon of forced marriages and bringing an end to illiteracy among women. Of all the challenges confronting Turkey, preventing violence against women is one of the greatest.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I welcome the plans to increase the number of shelters for women and the setting up of telephone helplines. I would, however, like to point out that as well as increasing the number of temporary measures, it is also necessary to make intensified efforts to change the mentality of society. Running information campaigns, discussing subjects related to gender equality as part of school education and implementing a zero-tolerance policy towards violence against women, particularly in the case of honour killings and forced ‘honour’ suicides, are essential elements in the process of changing the status of women in Turkey.</p>
      <p sl="pl">I welcome the fact that gender-based disparities in primary education have been almost completely eliminated, as this will certainly contribute to ending the detrimental phenomenon of illiteracy among women. I would, however, like to appeal for greater attention to be paid to access to secondary education, where there are still significant differences between women and men.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-149-000" speaker_id="96774" name="Jarosław WAŁĘSA" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Poland" birth_date="13-09-1976" birth_place="Gdańsk" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="pl">The objective of the Europe 2020 strategy is to restore the economy to its condition before the crisis. To ensure a competitive market, it is essential that women contribute to the economy. As a European Union candidate country, Turkey is required to uphold human rights and to continue carrying out and supervising the implementation of legislative reforms. We should welcome the gradual transformation of the role of women which is taking place, but a huge amount of work needs to be done in order to make it normal for women to be active in society, the economy and politics in particular.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The greatest challenge for Turkey is to bring an end to violence against women. Data reported this year by the UN reveal that 39% of women have encountered violence at some point in their lives. Recently, however, a greater awareness of this problem has been noticeable, as is shown by the setting up of telephone helplines for victims. It is, however, essential to reorganise the system of shelters and operate a policy of zero tolerance towards violence against women. An improvement can be seen in the level of education among women, and the Ministry of Education is making efforts to eliminate sexist language and social-role stereotypes from school textbooks.</p>
      <p sl="pl">The Turkish Government has decided to tackle the very low level of employment among women, which currently stands at 30%, by implementing reforms. An example of legal changes being considered is the introduction of amendments to Turkish electoral law so that it would stipulate a mandatory minimum proportion of women in the national parliament. The proportion of female members of the Grand National Assembly of Turkey, which currently stands at 14%, would thereby be increased. These measures provide hope for an increase in the role of women in Turkish society.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-149-500" speaker_id="23894" name="Anna ZÁBORSKÁ" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="07-06-1948" birth_place="Zürich" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="sk">Of course, I also fully support the call for Turkey to do more to protect women from violence. Particular attention should be paid to mothers who are most vulnerable. However, this report is more about the ideological prejudices of the rapporteur, rather than the real problems facing Turkey. For example, it is said that for children aged 0-5 years, state-run nurseries are better than the care of a loving mother (paragraph 30). Motherhood itself is said to be a gender stereotype and Turkish journalists should be trained to keep silent about women as mothers (paragraph 66). Mothers do not even belong in textbooks (paragraph 33). In the event that parents disagree with such a method of teaching, learning alternatives should be banned (paragraph 35). Women belong in factories and the fields, because a woman tractor driver is, after all, worth more than a woman who cares for her children at home (paragraph 46). Indeed – I quote – ‘ultimately, a change in mentality is required’.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem20" title="20. Strengthening the rights of vulnerable consumers (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-151-000" speaker_id="96639" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Isabelle DURANT" nationality="Belgium" birth_date="04-09-1954" birth_place="Bruxelles" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="BE">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report by María Irigoyen Pérez on a strategy for strengthening the rights of vulnerable consumers [2011/2272(INI) ] (A7-0155/2012).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-152-000" speaker_id="105192" name="María IRIGOYEN PÉREZ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur" nationality="Spain" birth_date="01-10-1952" birth_place="Soria" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">Madam President, please allow me first to thank all my colleagues and, in particular, the shadow rapporteurs who have helped with the drafting of this report, leading to a much more robust version.</p>
      <p sl="es">We are all aware that this year is the 20th anniversary of the launch of the single market, which should be the driver of economic activity and growth in Europe, essential for exiting the crisis and achieving the Europe 2020 objectives. During the next eight years, the creation of the internal market needs to be compatible with its development, with an extensive framework of protection for consumers, with growth and rights that lead to dynamism and confidence, with transparency, the basic principle of democracy and good governance as mentioned this afternoon by Commissioner Barnier, and cooperation between the Commission and Parliament.</p>
      <p sl="es">It is now time to develop the regulatory framework for consumer protection and preparation, particularly when it comes to vulnerable consumers. We are aware that the different vulnerability situations, both endogenous and exogenous, make the adoption of an overall legislative tool difficult. This means we have to use a cross-sectional approach to deal with the vulnerability problem that takes the different needs, abilities and circumstances of consumers into account.</p>
      <p sl="es">Aware of the current deficiencies, the Commission has focused its strategy on improving information and education for consumers. Given that it is an ambitious proposal, it is not enough to protect vulnerable consumers, as their vulnerability derives precisely from their lack of assertiveness and understanding of the information they receive, the available options, or their lack of knowledge of the current systems for complaint and compensation, particularly in the case of cross-border online consumption.</p>
      <p sl="es">For those reasons, in order to resolve the deficiencies, that is, the problems, there is a need to adopt a strategy to support vulnerable consumers, and for both the Commission and the Member States to introduce specific measures into their legislation to ensure appropriate protection, which goes further than simply information, particularly in those matters where the highest number of consumer complaints occur: the financial sector, the complexity of which implies the possibility of any consumer being vulnerable.</p>
      <p sl="es">The call goes out, therefore, to the financial services to redouble their efforts to provide understandable, truthful information, filled with clear explanations, using straightforward language about the nature of the products and services on offer; to the food sector, with respect to the advertising of foods high in fat, salt and sugar, informing children and young people who are most susceptible to the advertising for these foods; to the transport sector, on which vulnerable persons often still encounter difficulties when travelling; to the energy and telecommunications sectors, where the lack of transparency in some cases leads to added complications for consumers, for example, deciding which tariff best fits their needs in the energy sector; and for access to justice, where consumers can have difficulties in accessing the existing mechanisms.</p>
      <p sl="es">The Commission and Member States, and also Mr Gallardon of the Spanish Ministry of Justice, if you will allow me to appeal to him, are therefore requested not to move backwards on rights, but to go against the flow in these difficult times, using intelligence and good governance to favour an alternative outcome to consumer disputes.</p>
      <p sl="es">Finally, I would like to mention that any one of us could become vulnerable consumers and I appreciate all the help provided by the other shadow rapporteurs in fortifying this report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-154-000" speaker_id="96814" name="Elena BĂSESCU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="24-04-1980" birth_place="Constanţa" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="ro">Madam President, I think that an increased level of protection is required for every category of consumer, while additional attention ought to be paid to vulnerable consumers. EU policy focuses on protecting and promoting consumers’ rights. This raises significant issues in terms of strengthening the single market and implementing the objectives of the Europe 2020 strategy. Therefore, I welcome a strategy guaranteeing consumers’ safety and strengthening their rights.</p>
      <p sl="ro">I should point out that Member States ought to adopt specific measures aimed at providing adequate protection. In Romania, deregulation of gas and energy prices entails establishing who the vulnerable consumers are in order to protect them from the impact of the price adjustment. Their number is estimated to be between 1.15 and 1.4 million.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-155-000" speaker_id="96718" name="Olga SEHNALOVÁ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Czechia" birth_date="25-10-1968" birth_place="Kromĕříž" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="CZ">
      <p sl="cs">Madam President, the report on a strategy for strengthening the rights of vulnerable consumers focuses on a broad range of issues where the current situation on the single market does not provide consumers with sufficient protection.</p>
      <p sl="cs">A vulnerable consumer is any citizen who does not have easy access to the information necessary for making a particular purchase, and thus for making a decision, or who simply does not understand the information that is available. Whether it is the sale of goods at presentational events, the exercise of the right to complain or the purchase of products that are sold in the single market in apparently similar packaging but sometimes with a different composition, these are all cases where the consumer is insufficiently protected due to the information gap. I therefore consider the concept of a vulnerable consumer as justified, since the consumer agenda must also address these important questions effectively.</p>
      <p sl="cs">In conclusion, I would like to thank the rapporteur, María Irigoyen Pérez, for the excellent work that has been done on this report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-156-000" speaker_id="28178" name="Miroslav MIKOLÁŠIK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="11-09-1952" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="sk">Madam President, The category of vulnerable consumers or consumers in a vulnerable situation requires special attention from the competent authorities and the development of strategies for their protection. I agree with the approach of the rapporteur, who preferred not to focus on the creation of a new definition of so-called vulnerable consumers, which could have become a double-edged sword. In my opinion, political and legal instruments should act preventatively to avoid situations where the vulnerability of consumers is frequently and intentionally abused. The improvement of the cognisance and awareness of their rights should, however, be complemented by an improvement in awareness of the safety of products and services. With regard to product safety, special information campaigns should focus on pregnant women and children. Let me also call upon the Commission to include the protection of children as one of the main priorities of the consumer agenda and analyse the effects of misleading and aggressive advertising on children and adolescents in particular, whose health regularly falls prey to such advertisements.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-157-000" speaker_id="96654" name="Jaroslav PAŠKA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="20-06-1954" birth_place="Banská Štiavnica" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group - Vice" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="sk">Madam President, first, I would like to commend this report because I truly believe that it is essential to protect children and elderly people from the risks posed by the market. In this context, I would like to focus on practical solutions that could be applied immediately. In schools throughout Europe, there are vending machines which sell sweet drinks and pastries. These vending machines are usually placed just outside canteens, and I can cite the European School in Brussels as an example of exactly such an arrangement. Perhaps we could adopt a regulation or directive that would remove such products from vending machines and replace them with fruit, for example, and this would certainly be of benefit to our children. I might also point out specific measures that we could take in relation to the certification of food, as it is necessary to make oversight more stringent and also perhaps improve those institutions that currently operate in each country and which do not always work very well. I could remind you of the dioxin affair in Germany when eggs, meat and meat products were poisoned. I could also mention the recent Polish affair where road salt, which was intended for spreading on roads, was repackaged and sold as edible salt and found its way into meat, canned fish and the like. Similar cases would therefore not arise if we had better and less shaky legislation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-159-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="John Dalli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I am very pleased to note the considerable interest that Parliament clearly attaches to consumer issues. This is evidenced in several own-initiative reports that have been very helpful to the Commission in the preparation of the Consumer Agenda – our new consumer strategy – which we are presenting tomorrow.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to thank, in particular, the rapporteur, Ms Irigoyen Pérez, and the shadow rapporteurs for their valuable work on this latest own-initiative report. Your input will contribute towards developing further actions for protecting and strengthening the rights of vulnerable consumers. The Commission wholeheartedly agrees that it is important to address the vulnerability of consumers, and this will be reflected in the Consumer Agenda.</p>
      <p sl="en">This initiative will present a coherent, strategic vision for consumer policy for the years to come, focusing on concrete measures that put consumers at the centre of the single market. Special attention will be paid to those markets also identified by the Parliament report as being particularly problematic for consumers. This includes financial services, energy, transport, telecommunications and the digital market.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would agree with Parliament’s view that it is not possible to encapsulate vulnerability in a single definition. Instead, we need to identify the various factors that can contribute to consumer vulnerability in specific markets or in particular circumstances. To this end, research and innovation have an important role to play. We are fully committed to mainstreaming the issue of vulnerability into market surveys and consumer studies, including consumer behaviour studies.</p>
      <p sl="en">As also pointed out by Parliament’s report, the concept of ‘vulnerable consumer’ has only been introduced relatively recently in European legislation. However, we already have in place provisions that safeguard the interests and rights of groups of consumers that can be considered more vulnerable in a structural sense – children, elderly people and people with disabilities.</p>
      <p sl="en">I can assure you that the Commission is constantly looking to improve these measures. I fully acknowledge that we also need to anticipate market developments and innovation to make sure that these also deliver benefits for vulnerable consumers.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me briefly outline just some of the initiatives that the Commission has already brought forward and which focus on the specific areas highlighted by the report. These initiatives include: revising the General Product Safety Directive; evaluating the implementation of the Consumer Credit Directive; looking into ways of tackling the problem of over-indebtedness; and assessing the functioning of the Unfair Commercial Practices Directive, especially in the digital and financial markets.</p>
      <p sl="en">We will also further monitor and assess the application of the rules of the Audiovisual Media Services Directive in order to strengthen their effectiveness, in particular, with regard to the protection of minors, across different audiovisual media environments. We are bringing forward a proposal on web accessibility. We have set up a Working Group across the Commission services on the exchange of best practices across Member States and long-term solutions and appropriate non-policy solutions that better target vulnerability in the area of energy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, the Commission is launching guidelines on the application of the regulation on the rights of disabled persons and persons with reduced mobility when travelling by air.</p>
      <p sl="en">If vulnerable consumers are to be properly protected, Member States, businesses and intermediaries, such as consumer NGOs, also have an important role to play. There is a need for close cooperation and the active involvement of all the main stakeholders. We must collectively remain constantly vigilant to market and societal changes that increase the risk of exclusion for certain groups or individuals.</p>
      <p sl="en">To conclude, may I say once again that I very much appreciate the valuable report that Parliament has produced, and which I know will make an important contribution to the Commission’s work.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-160-000" speaker_id="96639" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President" name="Isabelle DURANT" nationality="Belgium" birth_date="04-09-1954" birth_place="Bruxelles" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="BE">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place on Tuesday, 22 May 2012.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 149)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-160-500" speaker_id="4746" name="Sergio BERLATO" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Italy" birth_date="27-07-1959" birth_place="Vicenza" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="it">Belonging to the European Union ensures a degree of protection for consumers by establishing equal levels of safety for numerous consumer goods and by introducing measures to protect consumers’ wider interests from unfair business practices, misleading advertising and unfair contract terms. However, the general concept of ‘consumers’ subsumes a specific category, that of vulnerable consumers or consumers in vulnerable situations, who require special protection and a specific strategy on the part of the authorities. I believe that the creation of a strategy for strengthening the rights of the most vulnerable consumers may contribute not only to the social inclusion of such customers, but also to ensuring a more dynamic and competitive internal market. I agree with the rapporteur on the importance of improving consumer information, so that consumers are more aware of their rights, but I would underline the fact that practice has proven that in fact, many consumers’ vulnerability results from their lack of comprehension of the information they receive or their lack of awareness of the existing complaint and redress schemes. I would ask the Commission to consider adopting specific legislative measures to ensure appropriate protection of vulnerable consumers, going beyond mere information and in line with the Consumer Programme 2014-2020.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-161-000" speaker_id="102886" name="Ildikó GÁLL-PELCZ" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="02-05-1962" birth_place="Szikszó" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="hu">We cannot speak of effective consumer protection when consumers still feel vulnerable to companies, when the terms and conditions of contracts are incomprehensible to them, or when they can hardly hope for protection in their legal disputes.</p>
      <p sl="hu">At the same time, I believe that there can be no effective consumer protection without cooperative and consumer-friendly companies. Here, I would like to note that in order to reinforce this idea, I will soon submit a written statement for the creation of a consumer- and enterprise-friendly patent, because consumer complaints indicate that consumers still experience first hand the imbalance and complete vulnerability that characterise their position in consumer-enterprise relations when consumer interests are violated. The primary but not exclusive means of resolving this situation are legislative amendments of such extent and quality that have yet to be seen.</p>
      <p sl="hu">Last but not least, we must not forget about consumer awareness, which is the cornerstone of strong and effective consumer protection. Without awareness, there is no prevention, and without prevention there can be no protection. Thus, from the education of young people to assistance to the elderly, we must ensure that consumers know which organisations they can rely on for help in the case of a legal dispute.</p>
      <p sl="hu">The own-initiative report by Ms Pérez is exemplary, as it addresses a very sensitive and urgent topic. I would like to thank the rapporteur for her extremely timely conclusions; I will definitely vote in favour of this report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-160-750" speaker_id="96760" name="Tiziano MOTTI" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Italy" birth_date="07-02-1966" birth_place="Reggio Emilia" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="it">I would like to express my views on the motion for a European Parliament resolution on strengthening the rights of vulnerable consumers. I believe it is important to clearly define who vulnerable consumers are. On the one hand, they include persons regarded as such because of a mental, physical or psychological disability or because they are young or elderly, but on the other, we must not forget those who are in a temporary state of vulnerability due to external factors. In every case, we must always provide consumers with all the necessary means to ensure that they can make the right decisions and assert themselves. This includes providing easily accessible and understandable information about products and always explaining all the options open to the consumer, such as the existing complaint and redress schemes. Children and adolescents deserve special mention as they are often targeted by misleading and aggressive advertising, which should be more strictly controlled. I am thinking, for example, of the way foodstuffs directed at children are advertised. A final point that I would like to mention is the importance of easy access to justice for people entitled to receive redress for harm suffered.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-161-500" speaker_id="38602" name="Vladko Todorov PANAYOTOV" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Bulgaria" birth_date="07-05-1950" birth_place="Pavlikeni" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="BG">
      <p sl="en">The EU and its internal market provide the highest protection in the world to its consumers. Thanks to strict principles, the internal market has created many fair and secure opportunities for producers as well as for consumers. As the rules of the internal market are evolving along with its fast development, the concept of the vulnerable consumer and the necessity to set up special protection are assuming more and more importance in the political agenda. Indeed, in order for the internal market to stay fair and secure, it is crucial to highlight the vulnerability of some consumers and to tackle disloyal practices which aim to take advantage of this vulnerability. But types of vulnerability are various and take different shapes which can be very subtle and therefore hard for the legislator to delimitate. This report does not point out a clear definition or specific sanctions but it carefully outlines and enumerates what can be considered to be the consumer’s vulnerability. It is a big step towards a better understanding of this concept and thus a big step towards taking over this issue.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-162-000" speaker_id="96865" name="Debora SERRACCHIANI" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Italy" birth_date="10-11-1970" birth_place="Roma" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="it">All consumers are susceptible to becoming vulnerable over the course of their lives, whether as a result of endogenous causes inherent in the person and the person’s cultural, psychological and physical situation, or due to exogenous causes inherent in the objective difficulty of accessing information. Hence, there is a need for greater special protection for vulnerable consumers that takes their individual requirements into account. Disabled persons and persons with reduced mobility require particular attention, especially as regards transport, and passengers’ rights must be improved by ensuring that information and fares are transparent when a ticket is purchased.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-162-500" speaker_id="111014" name="Josef WEIDENHOLZER" is_mep="True" mode="written" nationality="Austria" birth_date="06-03-1950" birth_place="St. Florian am Inn" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="de">Achieving the highest possible level of public security is an important aim of European policy. The internal security strategy is essential for effective crime prevention, and also shows that the European institutions are capable of recognising significant potential threats and developing strategic options. However, implementing it requires constant efforts and these necessitate, above all, greater involvement of the national security authorities. Building up an effective system of internal security cannot be viewed in isolation from social developments in Europe, however. Research in the social sciences has repeatedly pointed out – most recently, for example, through the groundbreaking work of Richard Wilkinson and Kate Picket – that a high level of social security leads to a lower crime rate. An EU strategy on internal security should therefore take this basic fact into consideration and make explicit reference to it, particularly since other policy areas need to be made aware of this correlation. Current fiscal policy, for example, with its measures that always involve a reduction in social benefits, runs precisely counter to this correlation.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem21" title="21. Agenda of the next sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem22" title="22. Closure of the sitting"/>
</text>
