<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20120521.ES" lang="es" date="2012-05-21" place="Estrasburgo" edition="Edición revisada">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Reanudación del período de sesiones">
    <intervention id="1-004-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Martin SCHULZ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-12-1955" birth_place="Hehlrath" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="es">Ich erkläre die am Donnerstag, dem 10. Mai 2012, unterbrochene Sitzungsperiode für wieder aufgenommen.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Aprobación del Acta de la sesión anterior: véase el Acta"/>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Composición del Parlamento: véase el Acta"/>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Declaración de la Presidencia">
    <intervention id="1-008-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Martin SCHULZ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-12-1955" birth_place="Hehlrath" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="es">Meine Damen und Herren, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Bevor ich weitere Mitteilungen mache, möchte ich auf zwei Dinge aufmerksam machen, die ich Ihrer Aufmerksamkeit empfehle.</p>
      <p sl="es">Wir sind Zeuge eines brutalen Verbrechens gegen eine Schule in Italien geworden. Die Schule ist benannt nach Francesca Morvillo Falcone, der Witwe des früheren Richters Falcone, die beide selbst Opfer eines feigen Mordanschlages geworden sind. Nun sind an dieser Schule zwei Mädchen ebenfalls Opfer eines bisher ungeklärten Anschlags geworden: Melissa, ein junges Mädchen im Alter von 16 Jahren, wurde getötet. Ein anderes Mädchen, Veronica, kämpft in diesen Stunden ums Überleben. Viele andere junge Mädchen sind zum Teil schwer verletzt worden als Opfer eines Bombenattentats, von dem wir die Details der Hintergründe zum jetzigen Zeitpunkt nicht kennen.</p>
      <p sl="es">Aber was ich weiß, meine Damen und Herren, ist, dass ich in mehr oder minder jeder Sitzung in den letzten Monaten in der schwierigen Situation bin, dass ich hier über die Tötung von Kindern und Jugendlichen berichten muss. Es galt über einen sehr langen Zeitraum sicher die ungeschriebene Regel, noch für die niederträchtigsten Verbrecher, dass man die Tötung von Kindern vermeiden müsse, dass man Kinder und Jugendliche nicht töten solle. Das war eine rote Linie, an die sich die meisten gehalten haben. Wir stellen aber fest, dass es immer häufiger Fälle gibt, wo diese rote Linie überschritten wird, wo aus Verblendetheit, aus Verwirrtheit, aus Fanatismus ideologischer, religiöser oder auch krimineller Art entweder Kinder aktiv getötet werden, Jugendliche getötet werden oder ihr Tod billigend in Kauf genommen wird. Ich glaube, dass ich in Ihrer aller Namen spreche, wenn ich sage, dass wir für solche Menschen, die solche Taten begehen, nur Verachtung übrig haben können.</p>
      <a text="(Beifall)"/>
      <p sl="es">Wir sind deshalb in unseren Gedanken bei den Familien und bei den Freundinnen und Freunden des getöteten Mädchens Melissa. Wir drücken der um ihr Leben kämpfenden Veronica die Daumen, und wir sind in unseren Gedanken bei den Schülerinnen und Schülern, bei den Eltern, bei den Lehrern an der Schule, die so bittere Tage durchlebt.</p>
      <p sl="es">Lassen Sie mich zugleich auch sagen, dass die tragischen Ereignisse in der Emilia Romagna uns in den letzten Stunden erschüttert haben. Erneut hat ein schweres Erdbeben Italien heimgesucht. Die Emilia Romagna ist schwer getroffen, der Ort Finale Emilia in besonderer Art und Weise. Sieben Menschen haben nach den letzten Statistiken ihr Leben verloren, viele sind schwer verletzt, über 3 000 ohne Obdach. Auch diesen Menschen gilt unsere Solidarität und unsere Anteilnahme.</p>
      <p sl="es">Aber lassen Sie mich auch ein Wort an die Adresse des italienischen Volkes richten: Wer in den letzten Tagen die Bilder der Solidarität gesehen hat – sowohl in der Emilia Romagna als auch mit den Opfern in Brindisi –, kann dem italienischen Volk nur ein Kompliment machen. Es gibt Stunden, da rückt ein Volk – Italien ist in einer schweren Situation – zusammen. Ich möchte den Italienerinnen und Italienern im Namen des Europäischen Parlaments meine höchste Anerkennung zollen für die Art und Weise, in der in diesen Stunden nationale Solidarität geübt wird.</p>
      <a text="(Beifall)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. Comunicación de la Presidencia: véase el Acta"/>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Composición de las comisiones y delegaciones : véase el Acta"/>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Corrección de errores (artículo 216 del Reglamento): véase el Acta"/>
  <section id="creitem8" title="8. Firma de actos adoptados de conformidad con el procedimiento legislativo ordinario: véase el Acta"/>
  <section id="creitem9" title="9. Preguntas orales (presentación): véase el Acta"/>
  <section id="creitem10" title="10. Peticiones: véase el Acta"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="11. Declaraciones por escrito caducadas: véase el Acta"/>
  <section id="creitem12" title="12. Curso dado a las posiciones y resoluciones del Parlamento: véase el Acta"/>
  <section id="creitem13" title="13. Orden de los trabajos">
    <intervention id="1-018-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Martin SCHULZ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-12-1955" birth_place="Hehlrath" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="es">Der endgültige Entwurf der Tagesordnung dieser Tagung, wie er in der Konferenz der Präsidenten in ihrer Sitzung vom Mittwoch, dem 16. Mai, gemäß Artikel 137 der Geschäftsordnung festgelegt wurde, ist verteilt worden. Zu diesem Entwurf wurden folgende Änderungen beantragt:</p>
      <p sl="es">Montag: keine Änderungen.</p>
      <p sl="es">Dienstag und Donnerstag: Die Fraktionen sind übereingekommen, die Anfrage zur mündlichen Beantwortung zum Handelsabkommen mit Kolumbien und Peru von Donnerstag auf Dienstagnachmittag vorzuziehen und den Bericht von Herrn Kazak zu Makrofinanzhilfen an Drittländer von Dienstagnachmittag auf Donnerstag zu verschieben.</p>
      <p sl="es">Mittwoch: keine Änderungen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-019-000" speaker_id="1186" name="Astrid LULLING" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Luxembourg" birth_date="11-06-1929" birth_place="Schifflange" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="LU">
      <p sl="es">Monsieur le Président, je suis un peu étonnée de voir quelles sont les priorités de ce Parlement à la lecture de l'ordre du jour de cette semaine.</p>
      <p sl="es">Nous avions demandé l'autorisation de poser une question orale sur la situation dans le secteur laitier. Elle n'a pas été retenue alors que nous avons retenu, une fois encore, un débat sur l'homophobie. Nous avons une charte des droits de l'homme dans le traité et aucune discrimination n'est permise.</p>
      <p sl="es">Alors, je voudrais savoir, Monsieur le Président, pourquoi on ne traite pas les priorités qui concernent notre économie. On veut de la croissance, mais au lieu de s'occuper de l'agriculture, on s'occupe de l'homophobie.</p>
      <a text="(Applaudissements)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-020-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Martin SCHULZ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-12-1955" birth_place="Hehlrath" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="es">Frau Lulling, Sie wissen, dass die Tagesordnung dem weisen Ratschluss der Fraktionsvorsitzenden unterliegt. Ich werde den betreffenden Herren mitteilen, dass Sie die Milchproduktion der Homophobie vorziehen, und hoffe, dass die Herren ein Einsehen haben werden.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-021-000" speaker_id="33775" name="Jean-Pierre AUDY" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="France" birth_date="12-06-1952" birth_place="Tulle" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="es">Monsieur le Président, les chefs d'État et de gouvernement se réunissent en Conseil informel. Il était d'usage que le Président du Conseil européen vienne rendre compte des Conseils, même lorsqu'ils étaient informels. Or, vous allez prendre la parole, je crois, à 19 heures – j'espère d'ailleurs qu'ils vous garderont à dîner pour que le Président du Parlement reste au Conseil européen –, mais est-ce que le Président du Conseil européen a été invité? Qu'est-ce qui explique qu'il ne vienne pas rendre compte du Conseil, même s'il est informel?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-022-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Martin SCHULZ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-12-1955" birth_place="Hehlrath" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="es">Herr Audy, Sie erwischen mich auf dem falschen Fuß. Ich werde mich erkundigen und Ihnen mitteilen, warum Herr Van Rompuy nicht kommt. Aber im Prinzip haben Sie Recht. Eigentlich müsste Herr Van Rompuy hier sein. Herr Swoboda, wissen Sie Bescheid?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-023-000" speaker_id="2295" name="Hannes SWOBODA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Austria" birth_date="10-11-1946" birth_place="Bad Deutsch Altenburg" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament - Vice" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="es">Herr Präsident! Von einer früheren Gelegenheit weiß ich, dass Herr Van Rompuy sich weigert, vorher zu kommen, weil er meint, er hat da nichts zu sagen, weil er ja die Regierungschefs erst noch fragen muss. Ich bin aber mit dem Kollegen Audy völlig einer Meinung, denn vielleicht ist es umgekehrt sinnvoll, dass Herr Van Rompuy von uns weiß, was er dort sagen soll oder wie er den Präsidenten in seiner Rede unterstützen kann. Denn die Meinung des Parlaments wird zwar vom Herrn Präsidenten vorgetragen, aber es wäre ganz gut, Herr Van Rompuy würde auch vorher schon diese Meinung hören. Ich glaube, Herr Präsident, es wäre gut, Herrn Van Rompuy wirklich öfters zu bitten. Da jetzt so entscheidende Beratungen im Rat stattfinden, wäre es gut, Herr Van Rompuy würde öfters auch ins Parlament kommen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-024-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Martin SCHULZ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-12-1955" birth_place="Hehlrath" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="es">Ich werde das so vortragen und die Position des Parlaments zumindest bis zum Familienfoto in der notwendigen Form darlegen.</p>
      <a text="(Der Arbeitsplan ist somit angenommen.)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem14" title="14. Cuadro de indicadores del mercado interior (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-026-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Martin SCHULZ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-12-1955" birth_place="Hehlrath" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="es">Als nächster Punkt folgt der Bericht von Simon Busuttil im Namen des Ausschusses für Binnenmarkt und Verbraucherschutz über den Binnenmarktanzeiger (2011/2155(INI)) (A7-0153/2012).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-027-000" speaker_id="28120" name="Simon BUSUTTIL" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Malta" birth_date="21-03-1969" birth_place="Attard" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="MT">
      <p sl="es">rapporteur . − Mr President, lately there has been a lot of talk about growth, and how to kick-start Europe’s economies and get them out of their dismal state. But we need to go beyond slogans and spell out how growth can be achieved.</p>
      <p sl="es">In my report on the Internal Market Scoreboard, which I am presenting here today, I want to transmit a simple but important message. If we really want to achieve growth, let us truly deliver the internal market to citizens, because it is the single most important European investment for growth. To do this, we need to fix what is not working. Where are we failing to deliver? The Commission’s Internal Market Scoreboard shows us that a number of Member States’ efforts to transpose EU single market legislation have been found wanting. Unless Member States step up their efforts to make sure that EU legislation is correctly transposed and fully implemented, there can be no internal market.</p>
      <p sl="es">Not all is gloom and doom, of course. Some Member States have shown consistent commitment to the internal market. I am happy to see that my own Member State, Malta, once again has the best record amongst Member States for transposing most EU laws on time. Other Member States, such as Estonia, have shown very positive results on all counts in the ‘internal market health check’.</p>
      <p sl="es">These positive results do not form an exception to the rule; rather, they show that, if there is political will, other Member States can perform well too. Unless more is done to ensure EU legislation is transposed and implemented correctly in the shortest time possible, however, our citizens and enterprises will not be able to reap the benefits of the internal market. Member States therefore need more ambitious targets, and need to stick to their commitments.</p>
      <p sl="es">For its part, the Commission needs to continue to fulfil its role as the EU’s executive with more vigour. Breaches of EU law must be pursued more swiftly by infringement proceedings. To that end I am also putting forward, by means of an amendment, a proposal to establish fast-track infringement proceedings through an internal market prosecutor with sufficient independence to act objectively on infringements and institute infringement proceedings free from political pressure.</p>
      <p sl="es">Building the regulatory framework of the internal market is not, however, the only step towards delivering the internal market for our citizens. That is why my report also focuses on the importance of bringing the internal market directly to our citizens and enterprises. The work of the established network of Commission tools is crucial here, and the success stories of services such as SOLVIT need to be followed up with a commitment to further strengthen these problem-solving services. For citizens are still faced with a complex, and often impersonal, network of services when they have a complaint to make. This makes finding the solution to their problem a problem in itself.</p>
      <p sl="es">My report therefore calls for further coordination among the Commission’s network of services and stresses the importance of the Your Europe portal as the single online gateway for all citizens’ problems. But we also need to establish ‘live’ points of contact, for example by having case officers in the Commission’s representative offices in EU capitals to work directly on citizens’ complaints. Lately we have been asking our citizens to make a lot of sacrifices to ensure that our economies survive the current climate, but we do have the internal market, which is the best way of delivering growth and the economic prosperity that our citizens expect of us.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-028-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Michel Barnier" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="es">membre de la Commission . − Monsieur le Président, Mesdames et Messieurs les députés, mes premiers mots seront pour remercier Simon Busuttil pour le travail qu'il a personnellement accompli concernant ce rapport, avec le soutien et la compréhension de tous les membres de la commission du marché intérieur et de la protection des consommateurs – je pense à Malcolm Harbour et au coordinateur, que je remercie également.</p>
      <p sl="es">Mesdames et Messieurs, nous sommes dans un moment grave de crise – la crise financière qui n'est pas terminée, la crise économique qui a beaucoup de conséquences humaines, sociales et économiques. Dans cette période de crise, nous le voyons bien, Monsieur le Président, beaucoup de citoyens souffrent, sont touchés par le chômage. Beaucoup sont en colère et expriment cette colère, et le marché intérieur dont nous parlons avec le rapport de M. Busuttil se trouve dans cette situation assez paradoxale où il pourrait être, si nous ne prenons pas garde, la première victime de cette colère, du repli national, parfois de réflexes nationalistes, la première victime du protectionnisme. En même temps, le marché intérieur, le marché unique, c'est la première chance, le principal atout que nous avons pour sortir de cette crise, si ce marché intérieur fonctionne mieux. Voilà pourquoi, ce que nous avons fait depuis le rapport Monti, depuis le rapport de Louis Grech, avec le soutien du Parlement, – cet acte pour le marché unique, dont la gouvernance est partie intégrante, ces cinquante propositions et bientôt, Monsieur le Président, une douzaine de nouvelles propositions pour relancer l'économie sociale de marché compétitive –, doit faire partie, de mon point de vue, de l'initiative européenne de croissance dont les chefs d'État et de gouvernement vont débattre cette semaine.</p>
      <p sl="es">Je pense – et depuis longtemps – que la bonne gestion des finances publiques, d'un côté, et la croissance, de l'autre, – en particulier la croissance avec le marché intérieur – sont non seulement compatibles, mais qu'il est en outre nécessaire de les conduire ensemble.</p>
      <p sl="es">Voilà pourquoi je suis heureux que M. Busuttil ait souligné en quoi le marché intérieur est bien ce réservoir de croissance. Nous pensons que s'il fonctionne mieux en ce qui concerne la mobilité, les exportations, les échanges, l'investissement, l'entrepreneuriat social, les services, e-commerce, nous pourrions dans notre marché intérieur, en nous-mêmes, aller chercher deux, trois ou quatre points de croissance supplémentaires.</p>
      <p sl="es">C'est bien de cela qu'il s'agit avec la gouvernance du marché intérieur: faire mieux fonctionner cet espace de 500 millions de citoyens et de consommateurs et de 22 millions d'entreprises, dont une grande majorité sont des petites et moyennes entreprises. Il faut que ces citoyens et ces petites et moyennes entreprises aient des outils plus proches d'eux et plus efficaces, lorsqu'ils veulent participer à ce marché intérieur. C'est ce que nous voulons faire avec SOLVIT, avec le portail Your Europe, avec EU Pilot, avec le système IMI aussi et les Centres européens des consommateurs.</p>
      <p sl="es">Ce travail de gouvernance commence avec le tableau d'affichage, c'est-à-dire la photographie de ce qui marche et de ce qui ne marche pas bien, ce Scoreboard que nous produisons du côté de la Commission deux fois par an. Ce tableau nous donne une mesure précise de la transposition et de la mise en œuvre de la législation du marché intérieur dans chaque État membre. Il faut qu'il fonctionne plus efficacement, avec des chiffres qui soient assez éloquents et qui soient, pour les États membres, autant d'incitations à ne pas relâcher leurs efforts. C'est ce que le rapport de M. Busuttil souligne aussi.</p>
      <p sl="es">Mesdames et Messieurs, ce tableau d'affichage du marché intérieur n'est pas l'unique corde, l'unique outil, dont nous disposons lorsqu'il s'agit du suivi des règles en matière de marché intérieur pour les Européens.</p>
      <p sl="es">Cette crise que j'évoquais tout à l'heure nous appelle à tirer les leçons de certains dysfonctionnements dans chacun de nos États membres et à trouver le moyen de nouveaux efforts.</p>
      <p sl="es">Voilà en quoi nous nous sommes engagés, dans un souci de transparence et de plus grande coopération avec vous, le Parlement européen, les États membres, pour dresser chaque année le bilan de la gouvernance du marché unique. Nous avons fait ce premier exercice le 27 février dernier.</p>
      <p sl="es">Ce premier bilan ouvre la voie à une communication que nous allons publier à l'occasion du prochain Conseil européen du mois de juin – comme d'ailleurs le Conseil européen nous y avait invités – portant sur les possibilités de renforcer la bonne mise en œuvre de la législation du marché intérieur.</p>
      <p sl="es">Je retiens schématiquement deux axes pour cette communication: la mise en œuvre de cette législation et la croissance. Nous ne pouvons pas élaborer de nouvelles règles, vous et nous, sans nous soucier de leur bonne application sur le terrain. Une législation qui n'est pas appliquée n'est pas seulement inutile, elle est souvent contreproductive. Elle crée des déséquilibres entre un pays et ses voisins qui, eux, peuvent l'appliquer correctement. Elle pénalise la croissance et la création d'emplois en limitant les opportunités pour les citoyens et pour les entreprises. Voilà pourquoi nous avons proposé dans le cadre de l'Acte pour le marché unique d'abaisser le déficit "toléré" de transposition des règles dans les États membres de 1 % à 0,5 %. Je suis heureux que M. Busuttil ait fait écho à cette proposition. Nous ne pouvons pas nous satisfaire d'une moyenne européenne de 1,2 % de déficit de transposition, et même, dans un État membre, d'un chiffre de 1,7 %.</p>
      <p sl="es">La Commission mène actuellement un certain nombre de démarches, de concert avec les États membres, pour améliorer et rationaliser l'application de la législation du marché intérieur. Voilà pourquoi aussi, Mesdames et Messieurs les députés, je me suis rendu – comme je m'y étais engagé devant le Parlement – dans chacune des capitales pour rencontrer tous les fonctionnaires nationaux qui sont en charge de toutes les législations du marché intérieur – la directive sur les services, la directive sur les qualifications professionnelles, la directive sur les marchés publics, la directive sur le commerce électronique, etc. – pour avoir un contact direct avec eux. Ainsi, nous avons créé une task force de 700 fonctionnaires qui sont, au sein des différents États membres, en charge de ces législations, pour pouvoir travailler plus en confiance et plus efficacement.</p>
      <p sl="es">Je vais continuer ce tour des capitales en allant maintenant, au-delà des capitales, dans chacune des régions, puisqu'il y a dans chaque région, sur le plan de l'économie, des entreprises, des syndicats, des organisations non gouvernementales, des collectivités territoriales et des acteurs importants pour le marché unique. Je ferai état des premières conclusions de cette tournée des capitales et des pays dans ma communication du mois de juin.</p>
      <p sl="es">Pour terminer, nous pensons que ces outils pour le marché intérieur, ces instruments d'assistance et d'informations, doivent être réellement mis au service des citoyens et des entreprises. Nous avons un certain nombre d'outils qui ont été développés pour offrir plus de transparence et de clarté dans l'information. Mais certains de ces outils ont été développés de manière un peu désordonnée. Aujourd'hui, il faut donc remettre les choses ensemble et leur donner plus d'efficacité.</p>
      <p sl="es">Nous continuerons de développer le portail "l'Europe est à vous", avec un mode d'emploi de l'Europe pour les citoyens et les entreprises. Je tiens aussi particulièrement, comme vous, à améliorer, dans chacun des États membres, le fonctionnement de SOLVIT, qui est un outil de résolution en ligne des problèmes et un réseau européen d'administrations nationales, et constitue, selon moi, une priorité.</p>
      <p sl="es">Mesdames et Messieurs, nous allons célébrer cette année le vingtième anniversaire du marché unique. On avait déjà entendu dire que cet anniversaire, surtout en ce moment, ne doit pas être nostalgique ou mélancolique. Il doit être dynamique et proactif pour la croissance qu'attendent les citoyens, avec des bénéfices concrets pour leur vie quotidienne. C'est aussi l'esprit de ce pacte pour une meilleure gouvernance du marché unique auquel nous allons appeler les États membres.</p>
      <p sl="es">Chacun dans son rôle, les gouvernements, le Parlement européen, le Conseil, et bien sûr, la Commission, nous devons faire de ce vingtième anniversaire, j'insiste, le moment d'une nouvelle dynamique, d'un nouvel élan pour le marché unique. C'est pourquoi je souhaite également que, de manière transparente et sincère, nous puissions en parler, non seulement entre nous, mais aussi avec les acteurs dans chacun de nos pays, que j'ai cités tout à l'heure. Ce sera l'esprit de cette semaine du marché unique, qui reprendra l'idée du forum que nous avons réussi à mettre en place à votre initiative à Cracovie, mais en le développant dans chacun des États membres, pendant la semaine du 15 au 20 octobre prochain, au cours de laquelle nous marquerons solennellement, au Parlement européen, le vingtième anniversaire du marché unique, mais nous débattrons aussi de ce qui va bien et de ce qui ne va pas bien dans chacun des États membres. Comment éliminer certains obstacles? Comment éviter la fragmentation? Comment mettre en œuvre ensemble rapidement ces 50 propositions que nous avons reprises dans le Single Market Act ? Comment élaborer de nouvelles propositions à partir de celles que vous ferez vous-mêmes.</p>
      <p sl="es">Voilà, nous avons beaucoup de travail en ce moment sur le marché unique. Ce sera ma priorité en ce qui me concerne, avec vous, et c'est aussi ce qu'attendent les citoyens parce que la grande demande actuellement, avec tous les risques que j'évoquais tout à l'heure de repli ou de protectionnisme, c'est que l'on retrouve de l'emploi, de la compétitivité et de la croissance.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-030-000" speaker_id="28223" name="Andreas SCHWAB" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="09-04-1973" birth_place="Rottweil" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="es">im Namen der PPE-Fraktion . – Frau Präsidentin, Herr Kommissar, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen. Wir sind uns hier, glaube ich, einig, dass der Binnenmarkt, wie der Kommissar gerade ausgeführt hat, nicht zum ersten Opfer der Krise werden darf, sondern wir ganz im Gegenteil zwanzig Jahre nach Schaffung dieses einheitlichen Binnenmarkts alles daran setzen müssen, dass dieser Binnenmarkt wirklich auch den einheitlichen Regeln folgt, die wir alle hier vorgeben zu erarbeiten. Deswegen möchte ich dem Kollegen Busuttil für seine Arbeit an diesem Bericht im Ausschuss für Binnenmarkt außerordentlich danken, weil der Binnenmarktanzeiger im Prinzip immer der jährliche Barometer im Europäischen Parlament ist, an dem man ablesen kann, wo der Binnenmarkt steht.</p>
      <p sl="es">Aber, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen, zwanzig Jahre nach Einführung des europäischen Binnenmarktes müssen wir uns bei dieser Gelegenheit und auch bei den Feierlichkeiten, die wir am Jahresende haben werden, die Frage gefallen lassen, was in diesen zwanzig Jahren gelungen und was möglicherweise verbesserungsfähig ist. Ich glaube, dass der Bericht des Kollegen Busuttil zum Binnenmarktanzeiger sehr deutlich zeigt, an welchen Dingen es in diesem Binnenmarkt nach wie vor mangelt.</p>
      <p sl="es">Ganz allgemein gesprochen fehlt es an Transparenz. Es gibt im Prinzip zwei Probleme bei der Umsetzung binnenmarktrelevanter Gesetzgebung: einmal die Nichtumsetzung – und da gibt es ja die schöne Zahl, die auch gerade wieder genannt wurde, mit dem Ein-Prozent-Kriterium, das nur ganz wenige Mitgliedstaaten in Europa erfüllen. Aber ich glaube, diese Zahl täuscht darüber hinweg, wie schlecht in manchen Mitgliedstaaten der Binnenmarkt und sein Acquis wirklich angewendet werden, denn es gibt ein zweites Problem, und das ist nicht die Nichtumsetzung europäischen Rechts, sondern die falsche oder unzureichende Umsetzung europäischen Rechts.</p>
      <p sl="es">Ich glaube – und ich bin fest davon überzeugt –, wir brauchen an dieser Stelle einfach mehr Transparenz. Es hilft uns nicht weiter, wenn der Juristische Dienst der Europäischen Kommission uns mitteilt, dass die Vertragsverletzungsverfahren hinter verschlossenen Türen durchgeführt werden müssten. Wir brauchen mehr Öffentlichkeit darüber, was in den einzelnen Mitgliedstaaten zum einen falsch läuft, was an nicht korrekter Umsetzung vorliegt, und zum anderen auch darüber, warum die Mitgliedstaaten nicht zügig Abhilfe schaffen, wenn die Europäische Kommission sie dazu auffordert. Deswegen finde ich den Vorschlag des Kollegen Busuttil, eine Kategorie für sogenannte fast track procedures zu schaffen, außerordentlich positiv.</p>
      <p sl="es">Zum Zweiten kann ich aus meiner achtjährigen Erfahrung im Europäischen Parlament sagen, dass bei vielen Richtlinien und Verordnungen, vor allem aber bei Richtlinien auch die Abgeordneten und selbst die Kommission häufig nicht wissen, wie die Umsetzung von früheren Richtlinien in nationales Recht vorgenommen wurde. Das Europäische Parlament hat schon häufig verlangt, dass wir bei neuer Gesetzgebung von den Mitgliedstaaten eine Korrelationstabelle wünschen sollten. Ich glaube, beim Wunsch darf es jetzt nicht mehr bleiben, sondern wir sollten versuchen, den Acquis aus dem Jahre 2004, wo wir Korrelationstabellen von allen neuen Mitgliedstaaten mit Stand 2004 haben, zur Grundlage zu nehmen, um auch in den alten Mitgliedstaaten eine Korrelationstabelle zum Stand 2004 zu erstellen – möglicherweise mit unserer eigenen Finanzierung, weil wir damit mehr Licht ins Dunkel bringen könnten.</p>
      <p sl="es">Ich glaube, dass diese Diskussion zur Binnenmarkt-Governance erst beginnt, und deswegen freue ich mich, an dieser Diskussion aktiv teilzunehmen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-031-000" speaker_id="96975" name="António Fernando CORREIA DE CAMPOS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="14-12-1942" birth_place="Viseu" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="es">em nome do Grupo S&amp;D . – Senhora Presidente, Senhor Comissário Barnier, cumprimento o relator, em geral, sobre o trabalho apresentado. Um Mercado Interno a funcionar em pleno garante mais emprego, mais transações comerciais, permite consumidores mais esclarecidos, com acesso a uma maior variedade, qualidade e fiabilidade de bens e serviços, pequenas e médias empresas mais robustas e mais aptas a enfrentar a globalização.</p>
      <p sl="es">Para isso, o papel dos Estados-Membros é crucial, não só na fase da produção legislativa, que tem de ser adequada, inovadora, inventiva, mas também na fase da transposição para as ordens jurídicas internas. E é aqui que surgem os problemas. Os Estados-Membros, por vezes, entendem o prazo de transposição muito para além dos dois anos estipulados, o que prejudica em muito o funcionamento deste mercado de 500 milhões de cidadãos, inviabilizando a entrada em vigor de regras que o regulam. Outros Estados-Membros fazem uma transposição incorreta ou insuficiente das diretivas, o que causa enormes problemas de interpretação e de aplicação das regras no mercado europeu.</p>
      <p sl="es">A Comunicação sobre a Governança do Mercado Interno 2011 compila, num único documento, o ciclo de vida da governança. A abordagem holística há muito que era defendida pelo Parlamento, nomeadamente no relatório Grech, e permite-nos agora ter uma visão mais completa e mais abrangente dos entraves ao pleno funcionamento do Mercado Interno.</p>
      <p sl="es">As resistências dos Estados-Membros, a inércia e, por vezes, o pouco empenho na boa transposição devem ser combatidos de forma ativa pela Comissão Europeia, pelo Parlamento Europeu e por um escrutínio ativo dos parlamentos nacionais, não esqueçamos.</p>
      <p sl="es">O Solvit, que tem um papel crucial na resolução extrajudicial de problemas que se colocam a cidadãos e empresas em virtude do incorreto funcionamento do Mercado Interno, deve ser dotado, o quanto antes, de uma base jurídica que lhe permita ver explorado todo o seu potencial e dar uma resposta cabal aos desafios, sendo um complemento do trabalho da Comissão Europeia em matéria de processos de infração.</p>
      <p sl="es">O relatório anual de governação, a par do fórum do Mercado Interno, que foi sugerido inicialmente pelo meu colega Grech e coroado de sucesso na sua primeira edição, em Cracóvia, em outubro de 2011, devem balizar doravante o desenvolvimento do Mercado Interno. Este fórum ou, como agora designou o Senhor Comissário Barnier, Semana do Mercado Único, que se deseja regular, reveste-se de uma enorme importância na avaliação dos progressos e dos entraves que se verificam no desenvolvimento do Mercado Interno. Pois para além dos dados que o relatório da governança nos fornece, junta no mesmo espaço físico diversos atores, legisladores, consumidores, empresários e outras partes interessadas que poderão assim fazer uma auditoria do funcionamento do Mercado Interno e ter uma melhor perceção do que são os seus direitos e os desenvolvimentos nesta área.</p>
      <p sl="es">Aproveito, finalmente, para manifestar alguma surpresa quanto a uma proposta do relator surgida na véspera do voto em comissão, depois de um debate profícuo de mais de seis meses, proposta que defende a criação de um organismo independente da Comissão que fica responsável pelos processos de infração no Mercado Interno e competente para instaurar processos por infração após aprovação pelo Colégio dos Comissários: um Procurador do Mercado Interno.</p>
      <p sl="es">Trata-se de uma proposta de uma enorme complexidade que exige um debate aprofundado, que não existiu, e esclarecimentos quanto à natureza jurídica de que se irá revestir esta entidade, os poderes inerentes e o modus operandi . Lamentamos que esta complexa proposta tenha surgido tão tardiamente, impossibilitando o debate, pelo que a nossa recetividade, nestas circunstâncias, é escassa a este respeito.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-032-000" speaker_id="28243" name="Jorgo CHATZIMARKAKIS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="21-04-1966" birth_place="Duisburg" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="es">im Namen der ALDE-Fraktion . – Frau Präsidentin, sehr geehrter Herr Kommissar, sehr geehrter Herr Berichterstatter, sehr geehrte Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Für die ALDE-Fraktion begrüße ich diesen Initiativbericht des Kollegen Busuttil ausdrücklich. Er ist ein erneuter Beleg, wie wichtig es ist, dass das Parlament bei wichtigen Themen die Agenda vorgibt. Daher danke ich Ihnen, Herr Busuttil, für diesen sehr ausgeglichenen Bericht.</p>
      <p sl="es">Das Thema ist aktueller denn je, denn neben der Umsetzung der Dinge, die wir uns vor zwanzig Jahren, als der Binnenmarkt gegründet wurde, als Motor der europäischen Integration vorgestellt haben, sehen wir auch, dass es Ungleichgewichte im Binnenmarkt gibt. Die Ungleichgewichte, was die Leistungsbilanzen angeht, sind auch ein Grund dafür, dass die Eurozone insgesamt in eine Schieflage geraten ist. Auch der europäische Binnenmarkt insgesamt droht seine Legitimation, seine Rolle als Motor zu verlieren, wenn wir diesem Geschehen nicht jetzt, zum zwanzigjährigen Jubiläum, besondere Aufmerksamkeit widmen würden.</p>
      <p sl="es">Der Binnenmarktanzeiger, das scoreboard , könnte ein sinnvolles Instrument sein, um im Sinne eines Frühwarnsystems Fehlentwicklungen aufzuzeigen, sehr früh auf Fehlentwicklungen hinzuweisen. Es wäre ein erster großer Schritt zu einer endlich abgestimmten Wirtschaftspolitik. Ich begrüße deshalb auch die Pläne der EU-Kommission, diesen Binnenmarktanzeiger jährlich zu veröffentlichen. Hier gilt es, die Quadratur des Kreises zu lösen. Auf der einen Seite dürfen die Volkswirtschaften, die ihre Arbeitsmärkte durch entsprechende Reformen fit gemacht haben, diejenigen, die früher umsetzen, natürlich nicht für ihre Leistung bestraft werden. Auf der anderen Seite kann es aber auch den Klassenbesten nicht egal sein, wenn sich der Nachbar über Gebühr verschuldet, um dessen Produkte zu kaufen.</p>
      <p sl="es">In einem ersten Schritt würde es schon reichen, wenn endlich die EU-Binnenmarktvorschriften zügiger umgesetzt würden. Hier brauchen wir in der Tat realistische Umsetzungs- und Anwendungsziele, wie dies der Bericht auch unterstreicht. Hinzu kommt die unterschiedliche Geschwindigkeit bei der Umsetzung. Während im Mai 2011 die Mitgliedstaaten nach Ablauf der Umsetzungsfrist im Schnitt noch 5,5 Monate zur Umsetzung der EU-Richtlinien brauchten, sind es heute fast acht Monate. Diese Zeitspanne muss verringert werden, allein schon um Chancengleichheit herzustellen. Fazit: Die Mitgliedstaaten müssen ihre Verpflichtung besser erfüllen und mehr Engagement und mehr Einsatz bei der Durchsetzung europäischer Rechtsvorschriften zeigen.</p>
      <p sl="es">Gleichwohl gilt es auch festzustellen, dass zwanzig Jahre Binnenmarkt dazu geführt haben, dass die Unterschiede der volkswirtschaftlichen Wettbewerbsfähigkeit in der Europäischen Union dramatisch zugenommen haben. So hat sich die Leistungsbilanz zwischen der stärksten Volkswirtschaft und der inzwischen schwächsten Volkswirtschaft dramatisch zugunsten der stärkeren verschoben. Die Niedrigzinspolitik seit der Euro-Einführung hat diese Entwicklung, einem Brandbeschleuniger gleich, verstärkt.</p>
      <p sl="es">Wir haben als Europäer auf die Heilkräfte des Binnenmarktes gesetzt, haben aber außer Acht gelassen, dass sich die Wettbewerbsfähigkeit in der Fläche nicht unbedingt durch diese Binnenmarktpolitik verbessert hat. Hier, sehr geehrter Herr Kommissar, müssen wir gegensteuern. Das scoreboard gibt eine Möglichkeit dazu. Auch das zwanzigjährige Jubiläum des EU-Binnenmarktes gibt Anlass, sich neben der Vollendung des Binnenmarktes auch mit einem Konzept ausgeglichenerer Leistungsbilanzen auf nationaler, vielleicht sogar in einem weiteren Schritt auf regionaler Ebene zu befassen. Nur so bekommen wir auch in den Randlagen Europas, insbesondere im Süden der Eurozone, ein gesamtökonomisches Gleichgewicht.</p>
      <p sl="es">Die Staatsschuldenkrise Europas zeigt, dass der Überschuss-Norden und der Defizit- Süden sich gegenseitig blockieren, wenn wir dieses Problem nicht mittelfristig lösen. Daher mein Appell an die Ökonomen Europas: Schenkt uns neue Theorien, die den Binnenmarkt mit der gegenseitigen Balance versöhnen! Der Binnenmarktanzeiger kann dafür ein entscheidender Ausgangspunkt sein, darf aber auch nicht zum zahnlosen Tiger werden. Nutzen wir die Binnenmarktwoche, um darüber nachzudenken! Nutzen wir aber auch dieses zwanzigjährige Jubiläum des Binnenmarktes, um uns Europäer insgesamt – nicht nur die starken im Norden, sondern alle zusammen – fit für die Zukunft zu machen!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-033-000" speaker_id="96956" name="Julie GIRLING" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="21-12-1956" birth_place="London" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="es">on behalf of the ECR Group . – Madam President, my Group welcomes this report. As everybody knows, we do not always have enthusiastic support for proposals in this Chamber, but this is one area in which we can pledge more than enthusiasm. We are positively excited about the idea of being able to get to the completion of the single market.</p>
      <p sl="es">Businesses and consumers are, of course, the beneficiaries of a fully functioning and operative single market, most particularly so in this time of economic challenge. Whilst we are all looking for markets outside Europe – looking at the challenges of export – we must not neglect the challenges and the opportunities of the internal market.</p>
      <p sl="es">Of course, delivering a single market for citizens and business does not stop at the creation of good legislation. There must also be adequate implementation as well as cross-border synergy between various national administrations. Without this, and without this implementation, citizens will not be able to enjoy the benefits of the single market.</p>
      <p sl="es">My Group supports the efforts of the Commission and, most particularly, Mr Barnier, in the field of detailed reporting on progress with transposition in the Member States. We welcome the rapporteur’s call for more determination in the enforcement of single-market legislation and clearer reporting on infringement proceedings being taken. ‘Name and shame’ is often an ugly tool in politics, but it is often a very useful one – as is praising those who do well.</p>
      <p sl="es">We call on the Commission to establish the Single Market Act as a rolling programme to be continually reviewed and updated in order to ensure completion of the market. This should include prioritisation of measures to complete the digital single market, including investment in high-speed internet and cross-border payments. We also call on national administrations to sharpen up their thinking and their action. It is important for single-market transposition to be treated with urgency and transparency, so that, as we celebrate this auspicious anniversary, we can truly see the single market as the jewel in Europe’s crown.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-034-000" speaker_id="96654" name="Jaroslav PAŠKA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="20-06-1954" birth_place="Banská Štiavnica" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group - Vice" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="es">za skupinu EFD – V tomto roku si pripomíname 20. výročie vytvorenia jednotného trhu ako jedného z najvýznamnejších nástrojov podpory hospodárskeho rastu Európskej únie. Súhlasím s názorom autora predloženej správy, pána poslanca Busuttila, že zabezpečenie výhod jednotného trhu pre občanov a podniky sa nekončí prijatím právnych predpisov. Myslím si však, že popri zdokonaľovaní mechanizmov dohľadu nad transpozíciou nariadenia smerníc a pomoci podnikateľským subjektom pri presadzovaní ich práv na využívanie výhod jednotného trhu prostredníctvom podporných mechanizmov, akými sú internetová sieť Solvit, portál Vaša Európa, Európska sieť podnikov, európske spotrebiteľské centrá či Európska služba zamestnanosti, by sme sa mali pozrieť aj na prácu certifikačných inštitúcií, ktoré otvárajú jednotlivým produktom cestu na spoločný trh. Štátna veterinárna a potravinová správa mojej krajiny prakticky kontinuálne informuje verejnosť o odhaleniach potravinových produktov, ktoré sa dostali do predajnej siete a nespĺňajú požadovanú kvalitu a zdravotnú nezávadnosť. Všetci si asi spomínate na dioxínmi kontaminované vajcia, bravčové a hydinové mäso, ktoré sa objavilo v uplynulom roku v severských spolkových krajinách Nemecka. Nedávno sme sa zase dozvedeli, že nejaká firma v Poľsku prebaľovala posypovú soľ určenú na údržbu ciest do malých balení a predávala ju ako kuchynskú soľ. Cestárska soľ sa tak dostala do chleba, mäsových výrobkov či rybích konzerv. Škandalózna je aj distribúcia kurčiat z krajiny galského kohúta, ktoré sa dostali na trh v mojej krajine. Francúzska hydina tam obsahovala vnútornosti, ktoré v balení byť nemali, mali polámané kosti a žlčník bol roztečený po celom výrobku. Podobná situácia bola s baleniami vločiek, ktoré spôsobovali zvracanie. Takýchto produktov, ktoré nepatria na spoločný trh, sa objavuje stále viac a viac. Preto si myslím, že by sme sa v rámci zdokonaľovania jednotného trhu mali venovať aj zdokonaľovaniu dohľadu nad mechanizmami uvádzania produktov na náš spoločný trh, a to v záujme našich spotrebiteľov.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-035-000" speaker_id="109649" name="Mikael GUSTAFSSON" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Sweden" birth_date="06-03-1966" birth_place="Dragsfjärd" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="SE">
      <p sl="es">för GUE/NGL-gruppen . – Fru talman! Jag tänker inte haka på lovsångerna för den inre marknaden utan mer fokusera på dess brister. EU:s nyliberala ekonomiska politik, EMU, och den inre marknaden sätter i dag principen om varors fria rörlighet före medborgarnas intressen. Det har skapat ett nytt Europa – ett Europa som är präglat av massarbetslöshet, fattigdom och växande klassklyftor, samtidigt som arbetet för en bättre miljö och jämställdhet pressas tillbaka.</p>
      <p sl="es">I betänkandet hänvisas till Krakówdeklarationen där den inre marknaden beskrivs som ”det mest kraftfulla verktyget för att återställa hållbar tillväxt”. Den inre marknaden kan emellertid inte i sig själv skapa en hållbar tillväxt och fler arbetstillfällen. Det är en omöjlighet. För det krävs en helt ny ekonomisk politik som är grön och expansiv, gör investeringar i offentlig sektor och sätter människan före systemet.</p>
      <p sl="es">I punkt 33 sägs att EU ska vara en direkt mänsklig kontakt med ”medborgare och konsumenter via kommissionens representationskontor”. Det är en utmärkt idé! Bjud aktivt in medborgarna, låt män och kvinnor välla in på representationskontoren så att de kan berätta vad de tycker om den inre marknaden och nuvarande åtstramningspolitik – en politik som ödelagt miljontals människors liv och framtid.</p>
      <p sl="es">Den inre marknadens grundprincip och målsättning borde vara människornas och miljöns bästa, inte som nu att gynna storföretagens intressen. Den nuvarande inre marknaden har dessutom rest en hög och bevakad mur mot omvärlden. Resultattavlan för den inre marknaden säger ingenting om alla de tusentals fattiga människor från syd som hoppades på en bättre framtid i Europa men som drunknade i Medelhavets höga vågor.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-036-000" speaker_id="96981" name="Franz OBERMAYR" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Austria" birth_date="25-05-1952" p_group="Non" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="es">Frau Präsidentin! Seit zwanzig Jahren besteht nun der Binnenmarkt mit seinen vier Grundfreiheiten, und der Binnenmarkt hat zweifellos einige Vorteile für Europas Bürger gebracht. Um das ganze Potenzial auszuschöpfen, gilt es, möglichst nahe am Bürger die Probleme zu identifizieren und zu lösen. Dafür sind Stellen wie Solvit ein wichtiges Instrument. Die Mitarbeiter dort arbeiten effizient und schnell. Leider sind die Stellen oft unterbesetzt, und es wäre hier besser, in Personal zu investieren, statt die nächste schwammige EU-Agentur einzurichten, von deren Nutzen die EU-Bürger sehr wenig überzeugt sind.</p>
      <p sl="es">Der Binnenmarkt kann sicher vieles, aber er kann sicher nicht die ultimative Antwort auf die Wirtschaftskrise sein und schon gar nicht, wenn man ignoriert, wo der Binnenmarkt auf seine Grenzen stößt. Ein Beispiel: Scheinselbständige aus dem Osten im Baugewerbe, die in Österreich und Deutschland quasi als Lohnsklaven gehalten werden. Gemäß der Zeitung Frankfurter Allgemeine gilt Frankfurt als die Hauptstadt der Bulgaren-Industrie. Laut Steuerfahndung arbeiten derzeit ca. 10.000 bis 17.000 Scheinselbständige in der hessischen Großstadt. Die Dunkelziffer dürfte noch weit höher sein. Für die Baufirmen hat das sicher große Vorteile. Für den heimischen Arbeiter muss man hier 35 EUR in der Stunde rechnen, für einen Scheinselbständigen in den meisten Fällen günstige 10 EUR. Das kann nicht der Sinn des Binnenmarktes sein, denn hier werden die Grundfreiheiten sowohl zulasten der heimischen Unternehmen als auch zulasten der Arbeitnehmer ausgenutzt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-037-000" speaker_id="96757" name="Raffaele BALDASSARRE" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Italy" birth_date="23-09-1956" birth_place="Lecce" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="es">Signora Presidente, signor Commissario, onorevoli colleghi, condivido pienamente la priorità e gli accenti posti dal collega Busuttil nella sua relazione, che mi auguro quest'Aula adotti con una piena maggioranza, al fine di rafforzare sempre di più il funzionamento del mercato unico, assolutamente strategico nelle politiche di sviluppo dell'Unione europea.</p>
      <p sl="es">Ciò permetterebbe di lanciare un segnale forte ai singoli Stati membri. Infatti, gli ultimi risultati del quadro di valutazione hanno dimostrato come gli Stati membri stiano venendo sempre meno ai loro obblighi in merito alla trasposizione delle normative europee. Per questo motivo, concordo con il collega sulla necessità di dare maggiore forza e flessibilità alle procedure di infrazione, ripensando al contempo il ruolo di SOLVIT come alternativa al ricorso giudiziario.</p>
      <p sl="es">A tale riguardo, ho anch'io delle riserve sul rischio di incorrere in problemi concernenti il rispetto del principio di sussidiarietà nel caso si formalizzi eccessivamente la base giuridica di SOLVIT. Ritengo quindi sia necessario che la Commissione esplori attentamente ogni tipo di soluzione, con l'obiettivo di rafforzare l'operatività del portale senza incorrere nel rischio di arenarsi in cavilli giuridici.</p>
      <p sl="es">Infine, vorrei ricordare che il Trattato di Lisbona ha fortemente ridefinito il ruolo del Parlamento europeo, conferendo a quest'ultimo poteri sostanziali per strutturare e rivedere la legislazione dell'Unione europea. In tal senso è prioritario, ai fini di una più proficua collaborazione con le autorità nazionali, che le conclusioni del quadro di valutazione siano adeguatamente analizzate nel dialogo strutturato tra il Parlamento europeo e i parlamenti nazionali.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-038-000" speaker_id="1907" name="Barbara WEILER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="17-09-1946" birth_place="Düsseldorf" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="es">Frau Präsidentin, Herr Kommissar, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Ich durfte in der letzten Woche bei einer deutsch-französischen Partnerschaftsfeier zum zwanzigjährigen Jubiläum der Vollendung des Binnenmarktes reden. Es war interessant, wie die Gäste darauf reagiert haben. Sie fanden das alle eine Selbstverständlichkeit, und es ist ja auch gut, dass die Bürger dies als Selbstverständlichkeit empfinden. Die vier Grundfreiheiten sind der Kern der Europäischen Union, und wir werden als Parlament, hoffe ich, alle gemeinsam Versuche bekämpfen, neue Schlagbäume, neue Grenzen und Barrieren aufzubauen, wie zum Beispiel die deutsche Regierung und die alte französische Regierung das mit neuen Schlagbäumen versucht haben, denn die Freizügigkeit für Bürger ist uns mindestens so wichtig wie die Freizügigkeit von Kapital oder Gütern.</p>
      <p sl="es">Den Bericht von Herrn Busuttil finde ich gut und hilfreich. Der Binnenmarktanzeiger und auch Solvit und andere Instrumente sind hilfreich, um festzustellen, ob die Regierungen wirklich europäische Gesetze wollen und ob die Defizite auch in der Tat abgebaut werden, wie der Rat es ja eigentlich vereinbart hat. Wir wollen, dass der Binnenmarkt für die Bürger vereinfacht wird. Wir wollen, dass die KMU leichteren Zugang haben, und wir wollen, dass alle Bürger davon profitieren.</p>
      <p sl="es">Die Umsetzung hängt interessanterweise nicht immer von der Größe des Landes ab. Es wurde ja schon erwähnt, dass Malta am besten dasteht, Belgien leider nicht ganz so gut. Interessant ist auch Ihr Antrag, Herr Busuttil, und ich hege sehr große Sympathien für ihn, muss aber sagen, wir haben in Ihrem Bericht ein paar andere Forderungen, die dies auch schon beinhalten, zum Beispiel der Artikel 18 für die Öffentlichkeit oder der Artikel 24, wo wir Entsprechungstabellen fordern, oder auch der Artikel 21, wo es darum geht, dass der Europäische Gerichtshof schneller arbeiten kann. Also vielleicht sollten wir erstmal damit arbeiten.</p>
      <p sl="es">Für die Sozialdemokraten möchte ich noch vier Aspekte hervorheben. Erstens: Die Umsetzung muss korrekt sein, das heißt, es muss kein gold plating sein, aber es darf auch nicht lasch und unzureichend sein. Herr Chatzimarkakis, wenn Sie mal kurz zuhören: Die beiden liberalen Häuser der deutschen Bundesregierung versuchen sich gerade an der Zahlungsverkehrsrichtlinie, und die ersten Gerüchte, die ich gehört habe, lassen nichts Gutes erahnen.</p>
      <p sl="es">Zweiter Punkt: Der Binnenmarkt ist auch eine Bewältigung der Krise, schafft Arbeitsplätze und trägt zum Wachstum bei.</p>
      <p sl="es">Drittens: Für uns sind die Verfahren beim sozialen Schutz von Arbeitnehmern zu schwerfällig, denn uns geht es auch darum – und das ist der einzige Kritikpunkt, Herr Barnier, den ich habe –, dass in diesem Dossier der soziale Zusammenhalt etwas zu kurz kommt. Wir werden darauf pochen, denn wir sind in einer sehr guten Tradition beim sozialen Zusammenhalt.</p>
      <p sl="es">Ich zitiere zum Schluss Ihren früheren Kollegen Jacques Delors, der gesagt hat, der Binnenmarkt arbeitet nach drei Prinzipien: Wettbewerb, der belebt, Zusammenarbeit, die stärkt, und Solidarität, die verbindet.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-039-000" speaker_id="111589" name="Inês Cristina ZUBER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="11-03-1980" birth_place="Évora" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="es">Senhora Presidente, este relatório faz considerações muito interessantes. Diz, por exemplo, que o êxito do Mercado Interno é um motor fundamental para aumentar a competitividade e o crescimento e uma das melhores formas para solucionar a crise económica. Estas considerações podem ser interessantes mas são-no, apenas e somente, na perspetiva do grande capital económico e financeiro.</p>
      <p sl="es">Certamente que estas considerações não tiveram em conta o desenvolvimento económico e social dos países periféricos e dos seus povos. É porque são esses países que sentem hoje, num período de crise, maiores dificuldades decorrentes da sua fragilização económica para a qual muito contribuiu, surpresa das surpresas, a construção do Mercado Interno.</p>
      <p sl="es">O Mercado Interno, ou seja, as políticas de liberalização, privatização e desregulamentação da economia significaram para os países economicamente mais vulneráveis a destruição da sua capacidade produtiva, a diminuição das suas exportações, o aumento das importações em setores como a energia e a alimentação, que os deixaram em situações de extrema dependência externa.</p>
      <p sl="es">Quais foram as consequências do Mercado Interno para países como o meu, Portugal? Um crescente número de empresas encerradas, nomeadamente pequenas e médias empresas, a destruição de milhares de postos de trabalho, o aumento dos níveis de pobreza de exclusão e desigualdades, a perda de direitos dos trabalhadores e a generalização da precariedade nas relações laborais, a privatização de setores de energia, transportes, correios, telecomunicações, banca, seguros, a liberalização de serviços públicos essenciais.</p>
      <p sl="es">É que na perspetiva do Mercado Interno não existe a liberdade das pessoas terem direitos sociais e uma vida digna. Na perspetiva do Mercado Interno, e de quem o defende, só existe liberdade de circulação de mercadorias e capitais. Os trabalhadores dos vários países europeus têm lutado corajosamente pelas suas liberdades, pelos seus direitos sociais e económicos e exigindo um rumo diferente das atuais políticas.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-040-000" speaker_id="102886" name="Ildikó GÁLL-PELCZ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="02-05-1962" birth_place="Szikszó" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="es">Először is szeretném megköszönni Busuttil jelentéstevő úrnak ezt a nagyszerű jelentését, nemcsak azért, mert ez a tiszteletkör, hanem azért is, mert nagyon aktuálisnak és nagyon hasznosnak tartom ezt a jelentést, hiszen egy olyan eszköz fontosságát méltatja, amivel pontosabban, átláthatóbban foglalkozhatunk a belső piac eszközeivel és az előttünk sorakozó feladatokkal.</p>
      <p sl="es">Egyetértek azon képviselőtársaimmal, akik azt vallják, hogy a belső piac nagy múltja és megannyi hozadéka ellenére sajnos még mindig nem működik tökéletesen. A végső célunk pontosan az, hogy ez a piac minden európai polgár számára egyre több előnyt jelentsen úgy, hogy annak előnyét kivétel nélkül minden szereplő élvezhesse.</p>
      <p sl="es">Az előttünk fekvő jelentésben szereplő tábla eredményei ugyan pozitív tendenciát mutatnak, és ez nagyon fontos lépés, de ez semmiképpen sem adhat okot az elkényelmesedésre. Itt az ideje, hogy éppen alaposabban tájékozódjunk afelől, hogy melyek azok a pontok, ahol továbbra is elmaradásban vagyunk, és ahol további erőfeszítésre van szükség. Ez a jelentés ebben nyújt számunkra segítséget, és rávilágít arra is, hogy a kedvező átfogó mutatókkal nem szabad eltakarni a részleteket, nem szabad eltakarni azokat a problémákat, amelyek még ma is fennállnak.</p>
      <p sl="es">Hogy egyet említsek, ilyen például a közbeszerzés, ami az európai GDP mintegy 15–20%-át teszi ki. Ha ezeket a piacokat maradéktalanul meg tudjuk nyitni – és itt az európai jogszabályokat megfelelően tudjuk alkalmazni –, akkor a kormányok jelentős megtakarításokat tudnak elérni a jövőt illetően. Világosan kell látnunk, hogy Európa akkor lesz versenyképesebb, ha éppen a szigorú költségvetési politikák mellett a gazdasági növekedés megteremtésére is elegendő figyelmet fordít.</p>
      <p sl="es">Szeretném kiemelni továbbá, hogy a Bizottság által is kezdeményezett SOLVIT megerősítése rendkívül fontos. Rendkívül fontos, hogy lássuk, hogy a jogszabályok átültetése területén milyen deficitjeink vannak. De ez önmagában még nem elegendő. Szükség van az egyablakos ügyintézés erősítésére, még több tájékoztató portál és jobb koordinációs mechanizmusok létrehozására, valamint nagyon nagy szükségünk van az egymást fedő eszközök kiiktatására is. Feladatunk tehát az, hogy érvényt szerezzünk a jogszabályoknak, mégpedig oly módon, hogy megfeleljünk az emberek elvárásainak a munkaalkalmak, a növekedés és a biztonság területén.</p>
      <p sl="es">Meggyőződésem, hogy nem azért van szükség ezekre az eredménytáblákra, hogy kipipáljunk egy feladatot, hanem azért, hogy pontosan értsük azt, hogy éppen most hol tartunk. Méltatom a tagállamok eddigi eredményeit, és ösztönzöm őket – a jelentéstevővel együtt – a határozottabb koordinációra és az átláthatóság további növelésére.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-041-000" speaker_id="96915" name="Sergio Gaetano COFFERATI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Italy" birth_date="30-01-1948" birth_place="Sesto ed Uniti " p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="es">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, signor Commissario, siamo tutti convinti dell'importanza del mercato interno che, nella costruzione dell'Europa, ha assunto nel corso di questi vent'anni addirittura il carattere di uno degli aspetti identitari dell'Unione. Allo stesso modo siamo convinti che nel mercato interno sia insita la potenzialità di dare un contributo robusto alla crescita dei singoli paesi e dell'insieme dell'Unione. Per queste ragioni, proprio perché condividiamo l'assunto, occorre prestare grande attenzione ad alcuni aspetti che, non a caso, sono stati riassunti già nell'odierna discussione.</p>
      <p sl="es">A mio parere, il primo di questi aspetti è che il vero nemico del mercato interno oggi è la crisi. È la crisi a mettere in discussione il valore del mercato interno agli occhi di molti cittadini ed è la crisi a togliere potenzialità al valore aggiunto che il mercato interno rappresenta. Pertanto, come affermato da più parti, anche in quest'Aula, occorre concentrarsi sulla priorità della crescita, perché senza crescita il nostro lavoro – quello relativo al mercato interno – diventa oggettivamente più difficile.</p>
      <p sl="es">Il processo di crisi che sta coinvolgendo i nostri paesi produce in verità un altro effetto negativo: fornisce cioè giustificazioni infondate ad alcuni paesi per applicare difformemente ciò che il Parlamento europeo, la Commissione e il Consiglio decidono.</p>
      <p sl="es">Come è già stato ribadito, ci troviamo di fronte a due problemi. L'uno riguarda i ritardi nel recepimento da parte degli Stati membri, ritardi non imputabili alla complessità dei provvedimenti, ma spesso frutto di un'errata scelta politica. L'altro riguarda le alterazioni, i difetti, nel recepimento. Troppe volte ci si discosta sia dal testo che dalle stesse intenzioni. Su alcuni capitoli, poi, la difformità è assai rilevante: vengono registrati i valori medi – ed è giusto che sia così – ma se si guarda il dato disaggregato di dove avvengono gli scostamenti più consistenti, si ha la sensazione di un'Europa che cerca di usare le risorse di cui dispone in maniera a volte un po' troppo furbesca. Occorre dunque che gli strumenti necessari per dare consistenza al mercato interno siano rivisti e rafforzati.</p>
      <p sl="es">Si è parlato delle sanzioni per quanto concerne l'applicazione non corretta o tardiva delle decisioni: ma personalmente vorrei anche sottolineare l'importanza di SOLVIT. Mi rendo conto della delicatezza nella ricerca della base giuridica: ma uno strumento che ha dimostrato la propria validità non può esser lasciato nelle condizioni in cui versa attualmente.</p>
      <p sl="es">Vorrei ora rilevare un'ultima cosa al relatore: visto che ci troviamo in questa fase necessitata di difficoltà prodotta dalla crisi e dalle condizioni esterne, non capisco la ragione per la quale sia stata avanzata l'ipotesi del Procuratore del mercato interno, cioè di un soggetto terzo, che ci porterebbe a una discussione prolungata nel tempo quando invece abbiamo bisogno di decidere rapidamente con il massimo di unità possibile, quell'unità che si era evidenziata e che questa proposta rischia di mettere in discussione.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-042-000" speaker_id="97016" name="Angelika WERTHMANN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Austria" birth_date="07-11-1963" birth_place="Schwarzach" p_group="Non" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="es">Frau Präsidentin, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Zurzeit spüren wir überall in der Europäischen Union die Wirtschaftskrise. Um wieder auf dem Pfad des Wachstums zu schreiten, müssen wir uns auf den Binnenmarkt fokussieren, das wichtigste Instrument.</p>
      <p sl="es">Es sollte ein Binnenmarkt für Bürger und Unternehmen gleichzeitig sein. Daher sind Synergien zwischen den nationalen Behörden zu unterstützen, und diese sollten mehr Engagement an den Tag legen, um Rechtsvorschriften ordnungsgemäß und in der Frist umzusetzen. Die Mitgliedstaaten müssen ihren Verpflichtungen nachkommen, und Transparenz und Effizienz sind dringend gefragt.</p>
      <p sl="es">Der Vorteil muss Bürgern und Unternehmen klar vermittelt werden. Solvit trägt hierzu bei. Dem Kollegen Busuttil vielen Dank für diesen wirklich sehr guten Bericht!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-043-000" speaker_id="28223" name="Andreas SCHWAB" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="09-04-1973" birth_place="Rottweil" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="es">Frau Präsidentin, meine Damen und Herren, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Ich war über einige Meinungsbeiträge hier in der Diskussion schon etwas überrascht, als beispielsweise der Kollege Gustafsson von der Linken, der jetzt leider nicht mehr da ist, gesagt hat, dass der Binnenmarkt die Menschen in die Armut getrieben habe und nur großen Konzernen diene. Da kann ich nur sagen: Soll er mal zu mir in den Wahlkreis kommen! In meinem Wahlkreis gibt es gar keine großen Betriebe. Mein Wahlkreis lebt von diesem Binnenmarkt, bei dem es ganz viele kleine und mittlere Unternehmen gibt, die von diesem Binnenmarkt profitieren. Sie hätten in einer Welt ohne den Binnenmarkt bei weitem nicht dieselben Absatzchancen. Deswegen kann ich jedenfalls von meinem Wahlkreis deutlich sagen: Diese Auffassung ist grob falsch.</p>
      <p sl="es">Zum Zweiten hat Frau Kollegin Weiler in der Diskussion darauf hingewiesen, dass nach ihrer Auffassung die Umsetzung der Richtlinie über den Zahlungsverzug auch in Deutschland etwas hänge. Ich kann Ihnen nur sagen, Frau Kollegin Weiler: Wir werden alles tun – egal, wer in Deutschland regiert –, darauf zu achten, dass die Richtlinien, die in diesem Hause beschlossen werden – mit demokratischer Mitwirkung des europäischen Mitgesetzgebers, des Rates und damit eines deutschen Bundesministers –, auch in Deutschland so umgesetzt werden, wie sie umzusetzen sind.</p>
      <p sl="es">Zuletzt darf ich auf einen Punkt zurückkommen, der in dieser Diskussion bisher nur sehr wenig Raum gefunden hat, der sich aber im Bericht des Kollegen Busuttil findet. Wenn wir zu mehr Verordnungen kommen – und die Kommission hat ja dankenswerterweise in der Binnenmarktakte einige Vorschläge gemacht, wo wir mit dem Rechtsmittel der Verordnung im europäischen Binnenmarkt gesetzgeberisch tätig werden –, nehmen wir zwar den Mitgliedstaaten den Spielraum zur Umsetzung, aber wir schaffen dafür Einheitlichkeit bei der Rechtsanwendung. Das scheint mir doch etwas zu sein, was wir in Zukunft viel stärker ins Auge fassen sollten, wenn es uns gelingen soll, das Umsetzungsdefizit in diesem Binnenmarkt zu verringern.</p>
      <p sl="es">Deswegen, lieber Kommissar, lieber Michel, darf ich nochmals daran erinnern, dass die EVP-Fraktion ausdrücklich Wert darauf legt, dass wir sehr genau prüfen, an welchen Stellen wir mit dem Mittel der Richtlinie und an welchen Stellen wir mit dem Mittel der Verordnung tätig werden sollen, um die besten Ergebnisse in diesem Binnenmarkt zu erzielen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-044-000" speaker_id="37312" name="Christel SCHALDEMOSE" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Denmark" birth_date="04-08-1967" birth_place="Odense" m_state="DK">
      <p sl="es">Fru formand! Da jeg var ung for 20 år siden, var jeg egentlig ikke så begejstret for indførelsen af det indre marked. Jeg mente, at den kun ville gavne kapitalen og ikke så meget menneskene, borgerne. Men sidenhen har jeg heldigvis fået et nyt og andet syn på det indre marked. Jeg har set det i funktion, og jeg må sige, at det indre marked i dag er blevet motoren i EU-samarbejdet. Det indre marked har bidraget til vækst, til jobs og til velstand for EU's borgere.</p>
      <p sl="es">Det er vigtigt, at det også kommer til at ske i fremtiden. Derfor bliver vi nødt til at sikre, at det indre marked kommer til at fungere endnu bedre i fremtiden. Det kræver imidlertid, at vi gør mere, end vi gør i dag. Jeg er faktisk lidt ærgerlig over, at Rådet ikke er til stede for at lytte til debatten, fordi noget af det, der efter min mening er vigtigt, er, at medlemslandene indser, at de har et kæmpestort ansvar for at sikre, at den lovgivning, der laves på det indre marked, bliver gennemført ordentligt.</p>
      <p sl="es">Som hr. Busuttil fortalte, viser der sig at være lande, der gør det rigtig godt. Hvis alle EU's lande gjorde som Malta, ville vi have et ganske velfungerende indre marked. Så for mig at se, handler det altså i stor stil om vilje hos medlemsstaterne. Den skal forbedres.</p>
      <p sl="es">Vi bliver nødt til at gøre det bedre, for hvis ikke vi gør det bedre, så er det, vi mister opbakningen til det indre marked hos borgerne og hos virksomhederne. Allerede i dag gør vi jo grin med de landmænd, som opfylder kravene ved at have bygget nye bure til deres høns, der lægger æg. Vi gør grin med dem, fordi vi samtidig reelt tillader, at der på det indre marked kan købes æg fra høns, som ikke bor i bure, der opfylder kravene. Eller vi skaber mistillid hos forbrugerne, der oplever, at de ikke kan stole på sikkerheden eller på sundheden i de varer, de køber på det indre marked, fordi der er medlemslande, der ikke sikrer, at markedsovervågningen fungerer. Eller vi skaber berettiget utilfredshed hos de arbejdstagere, der oplever, at de bliver udkonkurreret, fordi myndighederne ikke er i stand til at sikre en fair konkurrence.</p>
      <p sl="es">Vi kan gøre det bedre, hvis vi vil gøre det bedre! Efter min mening er resultattavlen et rigtig godt eksempel på det. Den er et redskab til at vise, hvor problemerne er, og hvad vi kan gøre ved dem. Jeg deler faktisk også hr. Busuttils ide om at lave en fast-track-procedure til håndtering af de tilfælde, hvor medlemslande ikke overholder reglerne ordentligt. Det skal gå hurtigt med at få gennemført den EU-lovgivning. Det går ikke hurtigt nok i dag. Der kan også gøres andre ting. Som kommissæren fortalte, er der taskforcen, der rejser rundt til medlemslandenes hovedstæder og hjælper landene til at implementere EU's lovgivning bedre.</p>
      <p sl="es">Derfor siger jeg tak for en god betænkning og tak for indsatsen. Vi kan gøre det bedre, og jeg synes, at det er vigtigt, at vi bruger tyveåret til at vise borgerne, at det indre marked er til for dem og ikke omvendt!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-045-000" speaker_id="96686" name="Mitro REPO" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Finland" birth_date="03-09-1958" birth_place="Heksinki" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="FI">
      <p sl="es">Arvoisa puhemies, rauha ja sosiaalisen oikeudenmukaisuuden tavoittaminen on ollut EU:n johtoajatuksia alusta lähtien ja kaikki tämä on mahdollista toteuttaa vain, jos EU saa omat sisämarkkinansa toimimaan.</p>
      <p sl="es">Euroopan unioni on täynnä lukemattomia mahdollisuuksia, mutta on myös se vaara, että me tuhoamme itse omat mahdollisuutemme. Tässä suhteessa Busuttilin mietinnössä otetaan kantaa todella tärkeään asiaan, lainsäädännön täytäntöönpanoon. Yhä edelleenkään kaikki jäsenvaltiot eivät pane yhdessä sovittuja direktiivejä ja asetuksia täytäntöön sovituissa aikarajoissa. Tällaista tapahtuu etenkin verotukseen ja ympäristöön liittyvissä asioissa.</p>
      <p sl="es">On merkillepantavaa, että lainsäädännön puutteellisesta täytäntöönpanosta eivät kärsi vain kyseisen jäsenvaltion kansalaiset, vaan myös muut EU:n yhteisillä sisämarkkinoilla toimivat jäsenvaltiot. Jos tavoitteenamme on edistää EU:n yhtenäisyyttä, talouskasvua ja sisämarkkinoiden toimintaa, meidän tulisi saada direktiivit ja asetukset käytäntöön nykyistä paljon nopeammassa aikataulussa. Jos jäsenvaltiot eivät ole halukkaita panemaan täytäntöön esimerkiksi ympäristöön liittyviä säädöksiä, miten EU aikoo saavuttaa esimerkiksi Eurooppa 2020 -strategian tavoitteet, mitä tulee resurssi- ja energiatehokkaaseen Eurooppaan?</p>
      <p sl="es">Puutteellisesti toteutettu lainsäädäntö heikentää EU:n uskottavuutta ja kilpailukyvyn ohella myös ennen kaikkea kansalaisten oikeuksia. On myös syytä kysyä, miten me voimme vaatia kansalaisia uskomaan ja myös sitoutumaan EU:n yhteisiin sisämarkkinoihin, jos jäsenvaltiot ja päättäjätkään eri jäsenvaltioissa eivät sitä halua tehdä.</p>
      <p sl="es">EU-lainsäädännöllä tavoitellaan esimerkiksi parempaa toimintaympäristöä kuluttajille ja pk-yrittäjille. Parempaa toimintaympäristöä on kuitenkin vaikea saavuttaa ilman uudistuksia ja yhteistä lainsäädäntöä. Tästä syystä meidän tulisi olla valmiita tarvittaessa jollain tavalla puuttumaan myös niiden jäsenvaltioiden toimintaan, jotka eivät ole halukkaita noudattamaan yhdessä sovittuja pelisääntöjä.</p>
      <p sl="es">Jos sääntöjä rikkovien jäsenvaltioiden toimintaan ei puututa, sisämarkkinoiden tulevaisuus on yhtenäisyyden sijaan sirpaloituminen. Tästä on kyse myös Eurooppaa nyt koskevassa kriisissä. Kyse on moraalista ja etiikasta, siitä, ovatko kaikki jäsenvaltiot suurimmasta pienimpään ihan oikeasti valmiita sitoutumaan yhteisiin tehtyihin päätöksiin.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-046-000" speaker_id="39721" name="Theodor Dumitru STOLOJAN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="24-10-1943" birth_place="Târgovişte" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="es">Doresc să felicit şi eu pe colegul meu, domnul Busuttil, pentru acest raport de iniţiativă.</p>
      <p sl="es">Piaţa unică este un domeniu despre care toate statele membre, fără excepţie, sunt de acord că este un avantaj al Uniunii Europene pentru a reveni la creşterea economică, pentru a crea locuri de muncă. Cu toate acestea, prima condiţie pentru buna funcţionare a pieţei unice este ca toate statele membre să transpună în legislaţiile naţionale regulile europene; or aici, din păcate, cu toate că s-au făcut progrese, avem încă state membre care întârzie această transpunere.</p>
      <p sl="es">A doua condiţie este de a avea o bună calitate a transpunerii normelor europene în legislaţiile naţionale - şi aici trebuie să subliniez că ne lovim de primul obstacol chiar în procesul de elaborare a legislaţiei europene.</p>
      <p sl="es">De câte ori intrăm într-o negociere tripartită Parlamentul European – Consiliu – Comisia Europeană ne izbim de rezistenţa unor state membre în a fi de acord cu elaborarea tabelelor de corespondenţă între prevederile din normele europene şi prevederile din legislaţiile naţionale în care aceste norme sunt transpuse. Aceste tabele de corespondenţă sunt primul pas pentru a asigura o monitorizare competentă a modului în care se respectă calitatea în procesul transpunerii. De aceea cred că trebuie să avem ca regulă ca orice legislaţie europeană să fie însoţită în statele membre de elaborarea acestor tabele de corespondenţă.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-047-000" speaker_id="96925" name="Sylvana RAPTI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Greece" birth_date="10-11-1958" birth_place="Kerkyra" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="es">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, ευχαριστώ το φίλο μου Simon Busuttil για την πολύ καλή δουλειά που έκανε. Είχα ετοιμάσει μια άλλη ομιλία αλλά, δυστυχώς, θα πω άλλα πράγματα και τούτο διότι υπέπεσε στην αντίληψή μου τούτη η τροπολογία, η οποία αλλάζει εντελώς το πνεύμα της έκθεσης. Στην Ελλάδα, έχουμε ένα πάρα πολύ γνωστό τραγούδι, σύμφωνα με το οποίο "ό,τι αρχίζει ωραία τελειώνει με πόνο". Θυμήθηκα αυτό το τραγούδι τώρα, διότι η έκθεση ξεκίνησε μεν πολύ ωραία και έτυχε ευρείας αποδοχής, αφού ψηφίστηκε ομόφωνα στην επιτροπή, αλλά δεν θα τελειώσει καλά, και τούτο διότι η υπόθεση της εσωτερικής αγοράς και ειδικά του πίνακα των αποτελεσμάτων, του λεγόμενου scoreboard, δεν αφορά αριθμούς αλλά ανθρώπους. Αφορά τους ευρωπαίους πολίτες, και μάλιστα σε περίοδο κρίσης.</p>
      <p sl="es">Όταν το Ευρωπαϊκό Κοινοβούλιο συζητά, προβληματίζεται και νομοθετεί, το κάνει για τους ευρωπαίους πολίτες και το κάνει, όχι in vitro, αλλά προβληματίζεται και νομοθετεί in vivo, διότι μας ενδιαφέρει η ίδια η ζωή. Για τον πίνακα των αποτελεσμάτων ξέρουμε ότι αποτυπώνει πόσο σωστά κάθε κράτος μέλος μεταφέρει την ευρωπαϊκή νομοθεσία και πόσο σωστά την εφαρμόζει στην επικράτειά της. Όλοι ξέρουμε ότι υπάρχουν κράτη μέλη που καθυστερούν. Όλοι συμφωνούμε ότι αυτά τα κράτη μέλη πρέπει να δεχτούν επιπλήξεις και, ενδεχομένως, να υποστούν ποινές. Αυτό όμως που πρέπει να εξετάσουμε, πριν να επιβάλουμε ποινή, είναι γιατί καθυστερούν αυτά τα κράτη και τι φταίει ακριβώς. Το γεγονός ότι οι μισές εκκρεμείς υποθέσεις αφορούν τη φορολογία και το περιβάλλον φανερώνει πολλά, διότι, τούτη την εποχή συζητούμε για την οικονομική και την νομισματική ένωση και διότι βλέπουμε πως, όταν αυτά τα δύο δεν συμβαδίζουν, έχουμε προβλήματα και κρίση στην Ευρώπη και απειλείται το ευρώ. Κατατίθεται λοιπόν αυτή εδώ η τροπολογία και ζητά, ούτε λίγο ούτε πολύ, να διορίσουμε εισαγγελέα και να συστήσουμε ακόμη ένα ελεγκτικό σώμα που θα επιβάλλει ποινές για να συνετιστούν τα κράτη μέλη. Φοβούμαι ότι, με παρόμοιες ενέργειες, ούτε η Ευρώπη θα προοδεύσει ούτε η εσωτερική αγορά θα γίνει ελκυστική. Παρακαλώ πάρα πολύ να σκεφτούμε πολύ σοβαρά το θέμα των κινήτρων και των ποινών, διότι αντικατοπτρίζουν αντιλήψεις. Εμείς, ως σοσιαλιστές και δημοκράτες, είμαστε υπέρ των κινήτρων και δεν θέλουμε να πιστέψουμε ότι το ΕΡΡ είναι μόνο υπέρ των ποινών.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-048-000" speaker_id="4538" name="Malcolm HARBOUR" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="19-02-1947" birth_place="Woking" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="es">Madam President, I am very pleased to be here – rather later than I expected, and thank you very much for including me in the speakers’ list. I was sorry to miss Simon Busuttil’s presentation of his report and your response, Commissioner, but I would just say that, as Chair of the committee, I am pleased that so many colleagues are here to support you. We do not all agree on everything, as Mrs Rapti indicated, but nevertheless I think the detailed analysis of the issues in this report is an indication of the depth of knowledge and engagement that my committee has for single market issues. I know you will take it seriously, as I am sure you have already said at the beginning.</p>
      <p sl="es">Unfortunately, because I was not here to hear everybody else’s speeches, I do not know whether I will be duplicating what people have already said. But in my remarks I just want to concentrate on two particular aspects.</p>
      <p sl="es">I will come back in a moment to refer to the question of infringements which Mrs Rapti raised, but first I want to highlight how our monitoring of the effectiveness and impact of the single market can evolve, namely by understanding the level of lost opportunities that still exist.</p>
      <p sl="es">I am reminded of a phrase that was used by one of your distinguished predecessors, Mr Bolkestein, in one of his reports on the single market, which we received annually – and I have been around long enough in the single market to have done a report on that – where he described the single market as a Ferrari motoring along in second gear. At the time I said that it was not necessarily a Ferrari that we wanted, because what we want is not top speed but solidity, reliability and accessibility to everybody; but I think the point was, nevertheless, well made. The problem that we have, colleagues, is that we do not know how many lost opportunities are still out there in the single market, where businesses have tried to sell goods or services in a country (which they are legally entitled to do) and are still frustrated by existing barriers – many of which should have been cast away by the Services Directive and the goods package – so they go off and go to another market, or they take another product.</p>
      <p sl="es">We can never calculate those lost opportunities, but I think the question about attitudes of business to the single market, knowledge of instruments like SOLVIT and the point of single contact, are clear indicators of loss of potential. In this report there is just a short paragraph (but a significant one) where we ask the Commission to include the findings of the Eurobarometer surveys in the annual governance check-up. What I particularly want to ask the Commissioner is whether, in the annual Eurobarometer surveys that are linked into the governance framework for the internal market, we should be including awareness measures about the extent to which companies and individuals know about their rights, SOLVIT and the points of single contact – because if we do not do that, we will have no indication about how the Member States and the Commission are promoting [the single market] together. Similarly, my colleagues have called for the Your Europe platform to be incorporated too so we can have a single powerful brand name and citizens and businesses will know where to go to get information. That is my first point.</p>
      <p sl="es">On the second point, about infringements, I think the core idea that was in the report about fast-track procedures stands. It may well be that ideas about an independent infringement assessment are at too much of an early stage but, to be fair to Mr Busuttil’s amendment, it only says ‘potentially considered’. However, it seems to me that, if people cannot sell a product or a service because of a government not implementing legislation, we have to deal with that quickly. Justice delayed is justice denied.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-050-000" speaker_id="39916" name="Zofija MAZEJ KUKOVIČ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovenia" birth_date="14-05-1955" birth_place="Črna" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="SI">
      <p sl="es">Ob dvajseti obletnici notranjega trga in ob tej resni krizi je vsekakor poročilo gospoda Simona Busuttila še kako dobrodošlo. Končno se moramo zavedati, da manj tekmujemo znotraj Evrope drug z drugim, ampak da se bolj orientiramo na tekmovanje z drugim globalnimi tekmeci, kot je v skupini BRIC.</p>
      <p sl="es">In zato pozdravljam vse te pobude in dajem večji poudarek mogoče samo na intenzivnost komuniciranja. Kajti portali sicer povsod so, so po vseh državah, ampak v te portale, verjemite, tudi ljudje, ki so za to odgovorni, premalo komunicirajo. Premalo komunicirajo vnaprej tudi ustno, tudi z besedami, zato mogoče od malih in srednjih podjetij je samo nekaj procentov tistih, ki sploh ve resno za to, ostali pa so tako rekoč izključeni.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-051-000" speaker_id="96814" name="Elena BĂSESCU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="24-04-1980" birth_place="Constanţa" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="es">Piaţa unică joacă un rol crucial în ieşirea Europei din stagnarea economică. În acest context doresc să subliniez importanţa transpunerii la timp şi a implementării în mod corect a directivelor europene. Prin urmare, consider că monitorizarea constantă a statelor membre este esenţială.</p>
      <p sl="es">Astfel, se va crea un cadru pentru o reglementare mai puternică a pieţei interne. Atât întreprinderile, cât şi cetăţenii vor putea beneficia de o piaţă unică îmbunătăţită. Cel mai recent tablou de bord al pieţei interne arată că doar un număr redus de state membre şi-au îndeplinit obiectivele de transpunere.</p>
      <p sl="es">România nu a reuşit, din păcate, să-şi îndeplinească obiectivul de 1% deşi înregistrase rezultate bune în luna martie. Ţara noastră trebuie să-şi intensifice eforturile de transpunere a normelor Uniunii.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-052-000" speaker_id="96749" name="Andrew Henry William BRONS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="16-06-1947" birth_place="London" p_group="Non" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="es">Madam President, in the early days of what was the EC, the words ‘free trade’ rather than ‘single market’ were used. The word ‘free’ is of course an emotively favourable word that gave the idea an attraction, but misled many about its reality. The freedom enjoyed by this traded good is paid for by that person’s job, or the other firm’s factory. This person’s free movement is that person’s lost job.</p>
      <p sl="es">The rapporteur refers to the alleged need for Member States to transpose and implement the laws of their EU masters. He calls upon the Commission to pursue swiftly infringement proceedings against countries that have failed to remove minor impediments to a single market. He calls rather ominously for greater monitoring of Member States by the Commission.</p>
      <p sl="es">Back in 1973, when the UK joined, many of us warned of the Orwellian double-think that lay behind nice words like ‘free’ and ‘freedom’. We can now hear the chilling and repressive reality falling from the lips of the Eurocrats.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-053-000" speaker_id="96776" name="Róża THUN UND HOHENSTEIN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="13-04-1954" birth_place="Kraków" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="es">Tabela wyników rynku wewnętrznego jest niezwykle ważnym dokumentem i wszyscy powinniśmy się starać, żeby również za jego pomocą wspólny rynek znalazł się w centrum debaty publicznej. Unia Europejska służy obywatelom wtedy, gdy przenosimy dobrze prawo wspólnotowe i w tym celu muszą zgadzać się dane. Transpozycja prawa jest czymś niezwykle ważnym i do tego potrzebne są liczby, oczywiście również zachęty oraz wymiana najlepszych praktyk – np. survey czy też jedna dobra strona informacyjna jak „Your Europe” – żeby właśnie nie było tych straconych szans. Ja się cieszę, że Single Market Forum, które zaproponowałam w moim sprawozdaniu dwa lata temu, nabrało takich rozmiarów, że w tym roku organizujemy Single Market Week. Ale chciałabym, żeby po pierwsze, projekt ten był kontynuowany, żebyśmy co roku mieli Single Market Forum czy Single Market Week i jeszcze bliższą współpracę między Parlamentem a Komisją Europejską w ramach tego projektu. Bo tylko wtedy rynek wewnętrzny rzeczywiście będzie zrozumiały dla wszystkich obywateli i im bliski oraz znajdzie się w centrum debaty. Dziękuję.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-055-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Michel Barnier" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="es">membre de la Commission . − Madame la Présidente, merci à chacune et chacun d'entre vous de vos interventions, de vos propositions. Je remercie en particulier Andreas Schwab, comme Mme Girling tout à l'heure, d'avoir souligné, au début de son intervention, que, quand on parle de marché unique, on parle de cette réserve de croissance.</p>
      <p sl="es">J'ai dit – et là je réponds aussi à M. Cofferati, qui parlait de la crise comme la principale menace du marché unique – au début de ma propre intervention tout à l'heure, quelque chose qui rejoint vos propres interventions. Je le redis: dans cette crise – avec la montée du protectionnisme, du repli national –, on voit que la première victime pourrait être le marché. Parce que si on refractionne l'activité de l'économie européenne, sous l'impulsion de réflexes nationaux, voire nationalistes, du protectionnisme, c'est clair que le marché unique ne résistera pas.</p>
      <p sl="es">Mais en même temps, pour sortir de cette crise, je pense comme vous que ce grand marché intérieur, avec davantage de libertés et moins de fractionnement, c'est notre principale chance. C'est notre première chance pour retrouver la croissance.</p>
      <p sl="es">Cela étant dit, pour bien agir, pour bien faire fonctionner le marché unique, il faut bien comprendre, et je rejoins Malcolm Harbour, qui a appelé à cette bonne connaissance – c'est là l'intérêt du rapport de M. Busuttil et des travaux que nous faisons –, où se trouvent les faiblesses, les mauvaises transpositions, les erreurs, parfois, les insuffisances de contact ou d'information avec les citoyens ou avec les entreprises.</p>
      <p sl="es">Voilà la raison de ce tableau de bord, de cette volonté de transparence que M. Schwab a recommandée. Je voudrais dire à M. Schwab qu'au delà de ce tableau global, qui fait état de tous les textes du marché unique, nous devons, en effet, aller plus loin et regarder, texte par texte, comment cela fonctionne. C'est ce que je vais faire, par exemple, sur l'une des pièces majeures du marché unique, qui ne fonctionne pas bien, et elle ne date que de trois ans. C'est la directive "services" qui couvre 40 % de l'économie européenne, tous les autres secteurs des services étant d'ailleurs couverts par d'autres textes européens. Nous devons aller regarder, dans le cadre du tableau général, texte par texte, brique par brique, comment sont évaluées chacune des directives.</p>
      <p sl="es">Nous avons, Mme Schaldemose le disait, comme Mme Băsescu à l'instant, avec ce tableau, l'occasion d'émettre des préalertes régulières, de pointer du doigt, de distribuer quelques fois de bons ou de mauvais points, mais aussi d'aider les États, de pratiquer ce que Róża Thun évoquait comme un échange de bonnes pratiques.</p>
      <p sl="es">Je veux dire également à M. Stolojan et à M. Schwab qu'il m'importe, comme à eux, que nous ayons les tableaux de correspondance, que les États membres fournissent bien, pour tous les textes, toutes les directives, ces tableaux de correspondance et que, lorsque cela est approprié, nous puissions les publier.</p>
      <p sl="es">M. Repo évoquait les procédures d'infraction. Je suis décidé à utiliser – comme je l'ai déjà fait – ces procédures d'infraction pour obliger les États membres à faire ce qu'ils doivent faire, mais je veux, avant toute chose, épuiser toutes les possibilités de contractualisation, d'incitation. Et nous avons déjà, M. Repo, je veux le dire pour être objectif, amélioré les choses. Par exemple nous avons, grâce aux procédures liées à EU Pilot, réduit très substantiellement le nombre des procédures d'infraction.</p>
      <p sl="es">Je voudrais maintenant réduire aussi la durée des procédures d'infraction. Parmi les outils dont nous avons besoin pour rapprocher le marché unique, pour rapprocher Bruxelles des citoyens et des entreprises, il y a Solvit, cet outil auquel je crois beaucoup. J'ai beaucoup œuvré depuis deux ans pour que, dans chaque État membre, Solvit reçoive – comme l'a souhaité M. Carrera de Campos ou M. Obermayer – les moyens juridiques et techniques dont il a besoin ainsi que le personnel nécessaire, et je continue ce travail avec beaucoup de vigilance.</p>
      <p sl="es">Beaucoup d'entre vous, comme M. Busuttil, mais aussi Mme Weiler ou Mme Rapti, ont évoqué cette idée nouvelle – M. Busuttil – d'un procureur.</p>
      <p sl="es">La Commission a une certaine réserve sur cette idée tout simplement – je crois que M. Busuttil le comprendra – parce que nous considérons institutionnellement, dans le cadre des traités, que nous sommes le gardien des traités et qu'il faut éviter les doublements ou les dédoublements de fonction ou de responsabilité. En revanche, vous êtes en droit, comme c'est votre rôle de législateur, de demander à la Commission de faire son travail. C'est l'objectif de ce rapport, l'objectif d'autres outils dont nous disposons.</p>
      <p sl="es">Je pense que le Parlement a un rôle, parmi toutes ces missions, de veille politique, et que c'est dans le dialogue entre notre institution et la vôtre, avec le concours du Conseil, que nous pouvons améliorer la mise en œuvre. Maintenant je pense, Monsieur Busuttil, que nous devons renforcer le rôle de la Commission et son activité en vue de la bonne transposition de tous ces textes. Je vais proposer de travailler sur certaines idées comme, par exemple, le fait de déterminer les législations ou les secteurs qui sont prioritaires en matière de marché intérieur, là où nous pourrions, après avoir déterminé les secteurs prioritaires les plus efficaces pour la croissance et la compétitivité, avoir un partenariat renforcé avec les États membres et, dans certains cas, aboutir à une tolérance zéro. C'est d'ailleurs, Monsieur Busuttil, l'objectif que vous visez sans doute avec votre amendement.</p>
      <p sl="es">Je voudrais aussi rappeler que nous pourrions proposer que cet exercice sur la bonne mise en œuvre du marché s'inscrive dans le cadre d'un exercice contraignant et plus global, qui est celui du semestre européen, de façon à ne pas se contenter, dans ce semestre, d'une évaluation des performances ou de recommandations en matière budgétaire, mais aussi en matière de compétitivité et de croissance. J'en ai déjà discuté avec mon collègue Olli Rehn.</p>
      <p sl="es">Nous devons faire notre travail, mais nous devons aussi faire un effort de dialogue avec les citoyens et avec les petites et moyennes entreprises. Je voudrais dire à Mme Mazej Kukovič que c'est bien l'idée de cette semaine du marché intérieur, qui nous est venue après le succès du forum du marché intérieur, que votre collègue Róża Thun avait imaginé et auquel beaucoup d'entre vous ont participé.</p>
      <p sl="es">Nous allons essayer d'utiliser tous les nouveaux moyens de communication, notamment les réseaux internet, les réseaux sociaux pour aller le plus près possible des gens. Je vais, comme M. Malcolm Harbour et M. Schwab me l'ont conseillé, avec mon collègue, M. Tajani, tenir compte spécifiquement des petites et moyennes entreprises, dans le dialogue, pour leur apporter directement, en utilisant internet, le contenu de tout ce que nous faisons avec vous, depuis des années et en ce moment même, pour faciliter leur travail. Réconcilier les citoyens et les petites et moyennes entreprises avec le marché intérieur, c'est précisément ce que nous voulons faire, et c'est aussi un des points que M. Baldassarre a évoqué en insistant pour qu'on n'oublie pas les parlements nationaux. Je suis bien d'accord.</p>
      <p sl="es">Quand on parle de liberté et de circulation des marchandises – je réponds en cela à M. Paška –, on parle effectivement de la sécurité de ces marchandises, aussi bien, Monsieur Paška, de celles qui rentrent dans le marché intérieur et qui doivent respecter des normes, notamment en matière de sécurité, que de celles qui circulent à l'intérieur. C'est un sujet dont mon collègue, John Dalli, est naturellement responsable et qu'il suit avec beaucoup d'attention.</p>
      <p sl="es">À l'intérieur de ce grand marché unique, il y a – comme Mme Gáll-Pelcz l'a rappelé à juste titre – une partie de l'économie qui dépend de la commande publique: 15 à 17 %. Je pense en effet que le respect des textes en matière de commande publique et aussi les progrès que nous pouvons faire, notamment avec les marchés publics électroniques, peuvent conduire à des économies extrêmement importantes et positives.</p>
      <p sl="es">L'autre jour, plusieurs d'entre vous étaient là au workshop que nous avons fait au Parlement à Bruxelles avec MM. Tarabella et Arias Echeverría, sur le e-procurement . Nous avons eu des démonstrations qui montrent que si nous parvenons, ensemble, à partir de nos textes à systématiser, à développer de manière générale les marchés publics électroniques, nous pourrions économiser, avec toutes les collectivités locales, près de 100 milliards par an, grâce à cette numérisation et à cette généralisation.</p>
      <p sl="es">Voilà des progrès concrets qui sont inscrits dans le single market act. Je partage l'avis de M. Schwab parce qu'il faut être objectif avec le marché unique, l'intérêt qu'il représente pour les petites et moyennes entreprises. Le travail que nous voulons faire, comme je viens de le dire, est bien d'accélérer, dans tous nos textes, normes comptables, très petites entreprises, marchés publics avec la simplification, l'activité et l'investissement dans les petites et moyennes entreprises.</p>
      <p sl="es">Je voudrais dire à M. Gustafsson, comme à Mme Zuber, que le marché unique, cela ne veut pas dire toutes les politiques européennes. C'est quoi le marché unique? C'est le plancher. C'est la plateforme de base, sur laquelle nous bâtissons des politiques publiques ou privées. Mais naturellement, si le plancher n'est pas fractionné, si le plancher est solide, tout ce qu'on met dessus, en termes d'initiatives privées ou publiques, est plus efficace. C'est précisément comme cela que nous travaillons avec des politiques pour la croissance verte, telles qu'évoquées par M. Gustafsson dans le cadre de la stratégie Europe 2020. C'est comme cela que nous avons travaillé avec les douze leviers qui sont dans le single market act et qui montrent bien l'équilibre que nous souhaitons. Ces derniers retrouvent – je le souhaitais personnellement et beaucoup d'entre vous m'y ont incité – les fondations de l'économie sociale de marché compétitive en tenant compte des trois mots, ou des quatre mots: économie, social, marché, compétitif. Vous trouverez cet équilibre dans les douze leviers que nous allons préserver dans le cadre du single market act II que nous préparons pour la fin de l'été.</p>
      <p sl="es">Je voudrais dire, avec Mme Gáll-Pelcz, que je trouve, en effet, le rapport de M. Busuttil efficace, pour reprendre ses mots. Je pense qu'il faut – comme l'a souhaité M. Schwab, chaque fois, pour être encore plus efficace, que nous le pouvons, et je fais ce travail de screening – voir si nous devons utiliser, comme je le souhaite, le règlement plutôt que la directive. Et je le fais aussi bien dans le domaine des marchés financiers que dans le domaine du single market act et du marché intérieur.</p>
      <p sl="es">C'est dans cet esprit que nous préparons, avec Mme Schaldemose et le Conseil européen, qui a un rôle très important à jouer comme colégislateur, le single market act . Et voilà aussi pourquoi je souhaite que, Parlement, Conseil et Commission, nous puissions trouver le moyen de délivrer, d'agir, sur la quarantaine de textes qui sont dans cette brochure et qui sont maintenant sur votre table depuis plusieurs mois.</p>
      <p sl="es">C'est le temps d'agir en allant plus loin, comme nous allons le faire, en supprimant les entraves que le Président Malcolm Harbour a rappelées. Ces entraves au marché intérieur sont autant d'occasions perdues pour la croissance et pour l'emploi. Je crois franchement que nous n'avons pas le droit, dans le temps de crise où nous sommes, de perdre des occasions.</p>
      <p sl="es">Voilà pourquoi nous devons avoir le bon outil, comme l'a recommandé M. Busuttil, pour mettre en œuvre, avec les États membres, tous les textes du marché intérieur tels qu'ils sont déjà proposés et votés et aussi aller plus loin, secteur par secteur, entreprise par entreprise, comme nous l'avons proposé dans le single market act , pour faire mieux fonctionner ce marché unique.</p>
      <p sl="es">Mesdames et Messieurs, je suis convaincu que c'est là que se trouve la première, la plus proche des réserves de croissance, de compétitivité et d'emploi et nous devons aller la chercher là où elle se trouve.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-056-000" speaker_id="28120" name="Simon BUSUTTIL" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Malta" birth_date="21-03-1969" birth_place="Attard" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="MT">
      <p sl="es">rapporteur . − Madam President, let me start by thanking Commissioner Barnier and all those colleagues who have spoken in this very interesting debate – all those who have, almost unconditionally, supported my report, as well as those who have expressed some reservations, in particular about the amendment that is to be presented. I will come back to that in a moment.</p>
      <p sl="es">At the very beginning of this debate, Commissioner Barnier said we are facing a paradox: on the one hand, we all – or almost all of us – understand the potential of the internal market; on the other hand, we know that the internal market often ends up as the first victim of a protectionist tendency when things are going badly. This is, indeed, a paradox and it is the hurdle that we need to overcome.</p>
      <p sl="es">In my report I mention three ways of overcoming this paradox. The first is through transposition. We need to transpose internal market legislation on time and correctly. If we do not do that, we have a problem. Secondly, we need to implement laws effectively. If we do not implement laws, it is no use having them in the first place. Thirdly, we need to provide citizens and enterprises with the tools to find remedies when things go wrong.</p>
      <p sl="es">Some colleagues have mentioned their reservations on the amendment that is to be presented. Let me quickly go through it in order to put their minds at rest. The amendment reads as follows: ‘calls on the Commission to put in place a fast-track infringement procedure and to consider’ – I emphasise ‘consider’ – ‘establishing an independent body within the Commission responsible for prosecuting cases of internal market infringements and pursuing infringement proceedings after obtaining the approval of the College of Commissioners’.</p>
      <p sl="es">This amendment seeks to develop the concept of fast-track infringement proceedings. We want to give concrete meaning to this proposal. It would free the Commission from the undue political pressure that we all know it often faces when it tries to negotiate better implementation, or better transposition, with Member States at the initial stages of infringement proceedings – often with the result that the infringement proceedings are delayed for too long. So this is not about sanctions – as Ms Rapti understood it to be – but rather about depoliticising the process and making it quicker. It is certainly not ominous: it is about making the internal market work.</p>
      <p sl="es">As to the timing and the question ‘why now?’ – now is the right time because, if we do not act now, we really have lost the plot.</p>
      <p sl="es">In conclusion, I agree with all those colleagues who say that Europe’s major strength is the internal market. The question is how to ensure that we make the internal market work for all of us. I believe that we should seize the opportunity of the 20th anniversary of the internal market to muster the political will to address the remaining weaknesses of the market, in order to achieve a truly single internal market that can deliver the growth and economic prosperity that all our citizens want.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-057-000" speaker_id="39317" name="Anni PODIMATA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Greece" birth_date="08-10-1962" birth_place="Athina" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="es">Η συζήτηση έληξε.</p>
      <p sl="es">Η ψηφοφορία θα διεξαχθεί αύριο Τρίτη 22 Μαΐου 2012 στις 12 το μεσημέρι.</p>
      <p sl="es">Γραπτές δηλώσεις (άρθρο 149)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-058-000" speaker_id="28275" name="Małgorzata HANDZLIK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="01-01-1965" birth_place="Bielsko-Biała" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="es">na piśmie . – Tabela wynikow rynku wewnetrznego, S. busuttil A7-0153/2012 Obywatele, a więc konsumenci i przedsiębiorcy, są kluczowym komponentem rynku wewnętrznego i to właśnie o nich należy myśleć tworząc prawo czy przekazując informację. Tymczasem, często mają oni problemy z uzyskaniem właściwych informacji i nie wiedzą, jakie tak na prawdę możliwości rynek wewnętrzny im oferuje. Często spowodowane jest to nieumiejętnie przekazywaną informacją. Doceniam prace Komisji w tym względzie, jednak ilość portali, które oferują informację często jest tak przytłaczająca, że obywatele gubią się i w efekcie nie znajdują informacji, która jest im potrzebna. Dlatego też tak istotna jest koordynacja narzędzi informacyjnych. Wskazywałam na problem ze skutecznym przekazywaniem informacji o jednolitym rynku już niejednokrotnie. W kontekście dyrektywy usługowej na przykład, sytuację miały poprawić pojedyncze punkty kontaktowe, tymczasem jak się okazuje nie funkcjonują one w pełni. Państwa członkowskie powinny wdrożyć unijne przepisy tak, aby końcowy beneficjent, jakim jest obywatel mógł z praw, które w Parlamencie przyjmujemy, korzystać. Tabela wyników rynku wewnętrznego stanowi dobre narzędzie do motywowania państw członkowskich, aby dokonywały sprawnie transpozycji prawa. Ostatnia tabela rynku wewnętrznego pokazała niestety, że tendencja, jeżeli chodzi o wdrażanie prawa jest negatywna w porównaniu z latami ubiegłymi. Dlatego też powinniśmy wysłać jasny sygnał państwom członkowskim, że potencjał rynku wewnętrznego może zostać w pełni wykorzystany tylko dzięki ich rzeczywistemu zaangażowaniu</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem15" title="15. Viajes a Canadá sin necesidad de visado para todos los ciudadanos de la UE y Acuerdo Económico y Comercial Global entre la UE y Canadá (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-060-000" speaker_id="39317" name="Anni PODIMATA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Greece" birth_date="08-10-1962" birth_place="Athina" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="es">Το επόμενο σημείο της ημερήσιας διάταξης είναι η δήλωση της Ευρωπαϊκής Επιτροπής με τίτλο: "Απαλλαγή από την υποχρέωση θεώρησης για όλους τους πολίτες της EE που μεταβαίνουν στον Καναδά και η συνολική οικονομική και εμπορική συμφωνία ΕΕ - Καναδά".</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-061-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Cecilia Malmström" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="es">Member of the Commission . − Madam President, the issue of visa non-reciprocity continues to be a significant irritant in EU-Canada relations. Canada continues, as you know, to maintain the visa requirement for the citizens of Bulgaria and Romania, and also reintroduced it for Czech citizens over two years ago. This is an issue we have raised numerous times in the course of the contacts we have with Canada, on every relevant occasion and at all levels, in order to try to find a solution in partnership with the Member States affected.</p>
      <p sl="es">The EU is the number one source region for asylum applications in Canada. This is of course a serious concern, and we know it could have potential negative effects on the successful conclusion and ratification of several important agreements with Canada, such as the Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement (CETA) and the Strategic Partnership Agreement.</p>
      <p sl="es">Visa-free travel between the EU and Canada does not fall within the scope of the CETA negotiations, and CETA has not been directly used as a way of putting pressure on Canada. However, the EU negotiators have repeatedly, in the margins of the negotiations, made it clear to their Canadian counterparts that this issue is important for the EU, and decisive for the Member States concerned. It has been pointed out to the Canadian negotiators that such measures are in contradiction with the spirit of an agreement like the CETA, which tries to bring the EU and Canada more closely together.</p>
      <p sl="es">The Commission welcomes the draft asylum reform proposed in Canada. Once this is adopted and in force, it should act as a deterrent to unfounded applications and lead Canada to lift the visa requirement for Czech citizens. We are ready to explore with Canada, in close cooperation with the Member States concerned, possible additional measures to help reduce unfounded asylum applications, and we plan to set up a joint working group on this issue. In the case of Romania and Bulgaria, full accession to the Schengen area will be an important factor with regard to Canada’s position on visas. The Commission will shortly present its seventh visa reciprocity report. This will include the Canadian issue and will set out the future approach.</p>
      <p sl="es">Our previous report, in 2010, concluded that the EU was ‘confronted with the limits’ of the existing reciprocity mechanism. In the ongoing negotiations on the amendment of Regulation No 539/2001, the Commission fully supports improvements to the reciprocity mechanism to ensure solidarity among the Member States, provided that these are legally and institutionally sound and do not conflict with the Commission’s right of initiative.</p>
      <p sl="es">A better reciprocity mechanism should enable the EU to exert quicker and more sustained influence over relevant third countries. All existing countries would be re-examined by the Commission under this new, more efficient mechanism. The Commission hopes that the legislative negotiations on all aspects of the proposal will proceed quickly, allowing agreement to be reached in the course of the Danish Presidency.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-062-000" speaker_id="33982" name="Marian-Jean MARINESCU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="11-08-1952" birth_place="Râmnicu Vâlcea" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="es">în numele grupului PPE . – Între Uniunea Europeană şi Canada există relaţii cu statut special. Cu toate acestea, cetăţenii a trei state membre au nevoie de viză pentru a intra în Canada. Această situaţie subminează politica europeană comună a vizelor, politică ce se bazează pe reciprocitate şi este menită să asigure un tratament egal pentru toţi cetăţenii Uniunii.</p>
      <p sl="es">Statele membre participă în mod egal la acordul global, economic şi comercial cu Canada. Acest acord este determinant pentru viitorul relaţiilor economice dintre Uniunea Europeană şi Canada şi va stabili viitorul cadru juridic pentru dezvoltarea acestor relaţii. În cadrul acestui acord, Canada tratează în mod egal toate statele membre. Când este, însă, vorba de acordarea vizelor de intrare în Canada sau de egalitate de tratament atunci când vorbim de eliminarea vizelor, Canada nu este la fel de coerentă. Se aplică un standard dublu şi se utilizează criterii care nu sunt suficient de clare şi de transparente.</p>
      <p sl="es">Noua legislaţie referitoare la sistemul canadian de azil descurajează cererile de azil din ţările Uniunii. Este un argument în plus că menţinerea vizelor pentru cele trei state membre este nejustificată. Comisia va cere în curând, în cursul acestui an, avizul conform al Parlamentului pentru acordul global, economic şi comercial cu Canada. Lipsa unui tratament egal pentru toţi cetăţenii Uniunii în ceea ce priveşte călătoriile fără viză în Canada creează evidente reticenţe pentru vot şi nu este exclus să se ajungă în situaţia nedorită ca Parlamentul European să nu acorde avizul său. Reamintesc că recent Comisia LIBE a votat o procedură automată de utilizare a clauzei de reciprocitate în cazul statelor terţe care menţin vize pentru cetăţenii europeni.</p>
      <p sl="es">Este obligaţia Comisiei să găsească o soluţie la situaţia actuală privind vizele impuse cetăţenilor români, bulgari şi cehi. Cer Comisiei ca în cursul negocierilor pentru acordul global economic să susţină, ca şi prioritate, eliminarea vizelor pentru toţi cetăţenii europeni. Este datoria Comisiei să asigure un tratament egal pentru toţi cetăţenii europeni.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-063-000" speaker_id="96859" name="Ioan ENCIU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="14-04-1953" birth_place="Odorheiul-Secuiesc" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="es">în numele grupului S&amp;D . – Acordul CETA care este în acest moment în negociere reprezintă un pas înainte în ceea ce priveşte relaţiile comerciale şi economice dintre Uniunea Europeană şi Canada. Cu toate acestea, el este şi simbolul unui mare paradox şi al unei incoerenţe grave din partea Uniunii Europene.</p>
      <p sl="es">Prin acest acord, bunurile şi serviciile produse în România, Bulgaria şi Cehia vor circula liber în Canada, însă fără ca cetăţenii acestor state să aibă acelaşi drept. Cu alte cuvinte, bunurile produse în România, Bulgaria sau Cehia sunt, din păcate, mai importante decât înşişi cetăţenii acestor state membre. Este o situaţie anormală şi discriminatorie, care nu poate fi acceptată şi care demonstrează şi neputinţa Comisiei Europene pentru asigurarea de drepturi egale pentru cetăţenii europeni. Parlamentul European trebuie să amintească permanent Comisiei şi Consiliului că fără solidaritate între statele membre, Uniunea Europeană nu poate funcţiona în condiţii optime.</p>
      <p sl="es">În acelaşi timp, putem vorbi şi de o lipsă a spiritului de bună cooperare din partea Canadei. Dacă în cazul Republicii Cehe motivul invocat are tendinţe discriminatorii la adresa unei etnii, în cazul României Canada păstrează în mod artificial o rată de refuz ridicată pentru a justifica neincluderea în programul de scutire de vize. Numeroşi cetăţeni români, şi aş cita aici numai pe cei care au fost de acord să li se facă public numele: Maria Dalcu, Cosmin Drăgoi sau Nicolae Ion, ne-au adresat plângeri faţă de modul nejustificat în care consulatele canadiene le-au refuzat cererile de viză. Cazurile sunt cu mult mai numeroase şi mă fac chiar să pun la îndoială buna credinţă a autorităţilor canadiene implicate.</p>
      <p sl="es">Desigur, există şi semnale pozitive din partea autorităţilor canadiene cu care am avut ocazia să mă întâlnesc în cadrul mai multor delegaţii oficiale. În cursul celei mai recente vizite la Ottawa, la începutul acestei luni, am primit asigurări atât din partea ministrului federal al emigraţiei, cât şi a deputaţilor din Parlamentul Federal că problematica vizelor va fi rezolvată odată cu adoptarea în luna iunie a noii legi privind imigraţia. Cu toate acestea, progresele reale sunt foarte lente, şi chiar dacă noua lege va intra în vigoare nu este clar când şi dacă vizele vor fi eliminate pentru România, Bulgaria şi Cehia, întrucât alte condiţionalităţi vor putea fi folosite pentru a bloca în continuare accesul fără viză a cetăţenilor celor trei ţări în Canada.</p>
      <p sl="es">Vreau să subliniez încă odată că problematica vizelor nu trebuie să fie lăsată pe planul doi nici de către Canada şi nici de către Comisia Europeană, ci trebuie să fie o prioritate pe agenda relaţiilor bilaterale. Aşa cum am mai spus, bunurile şi serviciile nu pot fi mai importante decât propriii cetăţeni. Este rolul nostru de reprezentanţi ai acestor cetăţeni europeni să ne asigurăm că drepturile lor primează faţă de orice alte considerente de ordin economic. De aceea, vreau să închei prin a spune foarte clar că ratificarea Acordului CETA poate depinde şi de progresul înregistrat în ceea ce priveşte ridicarea vizelor pentru cetăţenii români, bulgari şi cehi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-064-000" speaker_id="34234" name="Antonyia PARVANOVA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Bulgaria" birth_date="26-04-1962" birth_place="Dobrich" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe - Vice" m_state="BG">
      <p sl="es">on behalf of the ALDE Group . – Madam President, I warmly welcome today’s debate, which is jointly addressing the issues of visa-free travel for all EU citizens and the EU-Canada economic and trade agreement, and I would like to start by congratulating the colleagues who have taken this initiative.</p>
      <p sl="es">Not only are we addressing an issue which is of key interest and which directly affects European citizens from Bulgaria, Romania and the Czech Republic, but we are also touching on the values of our Union and the principles on which we would like the Commission to stand firm as part of its negotiating mandate.</p>
      <p sl="es">I am confident that the Commission will continue negotiating a comprehensive economic and trade agreement with the Canadian authorities, taking due account of our international commitments when it comes to trade and economic exchanges, as well as our rules and priorities for our own single market and our consumers.</p>
      <p sl="es">The Commission, as guardian of the Treaties, and representing the interests of the Union in this negotiation, has a duty to make sure our economic and market rules are respected and upheld in any international agreement that is concluded.</p>
      <p sl="es">But let us not forget that our Union is not only about trade and economic exchange or about the free movement of goods and capital. It is also and mainly about people – about the citizens of Europe – and I hope that the Commission will put the core principle of European citizenship on the same level as our economic interests.</p>
      <p sl="es">We should not forget, either, the existing common EU visa policy. Together with MEPs from Romania and the Czech Republic, I have already sent a letter to Prime Minister Harper expressing our hope that by the date of completion of negotiations for either or both of the bilateral agreement and the comprehensive economic and trade agreement, scheduled for the first quarter of next year, the visa situation for Romanian, Czech and Bulgarian citizens will be resolved.</p>
      <p sl="es">Looking at the situation today, we still have reason to be concerned. As you know, any future EU-Canada economic and trade agreement will have to be approved by this House, and we have made clear to Prime Minister Harper that we are not ready to compromise on the principle of equal treatment for all European citizens.</p>
      <p sl="es">We are also aware that other points in the negotiations might be problematic, notably with regard to trade, preferential markets or energy and environment, for example. We are not denying, or forgetting about, these crucial issues but are simply asking for a fair and comprehensive negotiating strategy on the Commission’s part – one which takes into consideration the concerns and warnings voiced by the European Parliament.</p>
      <p sl="es">So let us be clear and consistent and let us not conclude an agreement which would imply different levels of rights for European citizens according to whether they come from France, the UK or Germany, or from Bulgaria, Romania or the Czech Republic, for example.</p>
      <p sl="es">As an elected Member of the European Parliament who comes from Bulgaria, I do not ask for any exemption or special consideration. I am simply standing up for equal treatment for all European citizens, regardless of their Member State of origin.</p>
      <p sl="es">Finally, I would be grateful if the Commission could clarify whether this principle will indeed become a ‘red line’ for the EU when it is concluding negotiations with the Canadian authorities.</p>
      <p sl="es">Could you, Commissioner, also inform us about your cooperation with Commissioner De Gucht on this matter, as we believe it is crucial that both citizens’ rights and trade considerations should be pursued on the same path, towards, we hope, a successful outcome?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-066-000" speaker_id="96912" name="David CAMPBELL BANNERMAN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="28-05-1960" birth_place="Bombay " p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="es">on behalf of the ECR Group . – Mr President, I am alarmed at the tendency of the European Union to trespass into areas of national sovereignty where it does not belong; this is another example of that trend. It is the rightful business of the Canadian Government – and not us – to decide who it lets into its country, and why.</p>
      <p sl="es">Canada is not discriminating against us Europeans: it introduced similar restrictions for Mexicans, even though Mexico is in the North American Free Trade Agreement. Canada has successfully lifted the requirement for temporary visas where conditions are met. It has done so for Estonia, Latvia, Poland, Slovakia, Lithuania and Hungary.</p>
      <p sl="es">There seems to be serious confusion in the Commission’s stance in two regards.</p>
      <p sl="es">Firstly, there is confusion as to whether such visa matters belong in free trade agreements. They do not; just as ‘Mode 4’ worker access is not appropriate in the draft EU/India free trade agreement, so traveller visa matters do not belong in this Canadian free trade agreement. Border issues like this are a matter for Member States.</p>
      <p sl="es">The second point of confusion is about the European Union being a country. Yes, it aspires to be a country, but it is not one yet. So it is not the business of this place to force Canada to treat every EU nation equally, as if we were one country. That is a matter for individual nation states working through their own embassies.</p>
      <p sl="es">The Canadians have laid down fair and reasonable criteria, including low immigration violation rates, low asylum claims, high integrity of travel documents and good cooperation on removals. Those are reasonable terms.</p>
      <p sl="es">If this principle is breached, however, every EU Member State can expect the EU to start dictating all its border matters, and many EU Member States may well dislike losing control of their own borders to EU diktats. France and Spain have suspended Schengen on occasion, as has Spain this month, and the Dutch have tried to block Bulgaria and Romania. So in conclusion, Mr President, this is a line in the sand; a legal and political border that the EU must not cross.</p>
      <a text="(The speaker agreed to take a blue-card question under Rule 149(8) of the Rules of Procedure.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-067-000" speaker_id="34234" name="Antonyia PARVANOVA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Bulgaria" birth_date="26-04-1962" birth_place="Dobrich" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe - Vice" m_state="BG">
      <p sl="es">blue-card question . – Mr President, I would like to put a question to Mr Campbell Bannerman. In explicitly mentioning Mexico as an example, does he see any similarities between Bulgaria, Romania and Mexico and, if so, could he mention some of them? Or does he see that Bulgaria and Romania actually have more similarities with the rest of the European Union?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-068-000" speaker_id="96912" name="David CAMPBELL BANNERMAN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="28-05-1960" birth_place="Bombay " p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="es">blue-card answer . – Ms Parvanova, I think the point you are missing is that they are all nation states. The objection I have is to pretending that the EU is one country and saying that we are trying to force equality on Canada as if the EU were one country. By all means let the national embassies argue with the Canadian authorities and do it for themselves, but I do not think the EU should be acting this way, and certainly not within free trade agreements. I am on the Committee on International Trade, and too much leeway is being given to items which are not to do with trade and jobs. Europe desperately needs trade and jobs at this point.</p>
      <a text="(The speaker agreed to take a blue-card question under Rule 149(8))"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-069-000" speaker_id="96859" name="Ioan ENCIU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="14-04-1953" birth_place="Odorheiul-Secuiesc" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="es">Întrebare de tip „cartonaş albastru” . – Aş vrea să-l întreb pe onorabilul nostru coleg: în cazul acesta, de ce nu încheie Canada un acord comercial cu fiecare stat membru în parte?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-070-000" speaker_id="96912" name="David CAMPBELL BANNERMAN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="28-05-1960" birth_place="Bombay " p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="es">Blue-card answer . – The answer is that, as part of being a member of the European Union, every member country, such as Britain, has to hand over the negotiation of free trade agreements to the EU. I personally think that Britain should be outside the European Union and negotiate its own free trade agreements, as do Norway and Switzerland – and we would get a better result. That is the reason that is driving it. I am in favour of trade and of helping Europe get better jobs – I think we all are here – but I think there are better ways of doing it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-071-000" speaker_id="28497" name="Gerard BATTEN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="27-03-1954" birth_place="London" p_group="Europe of Freedom and Direct Democracy Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="es">on behalf of the EFD Group . – Mr President, the Czech Republic, Bulgaria and Romania are threatening the EU-Canada trade agreement unless Canada lifts its visa requirement for visitors from those three countries. Canadians do not need visas to visit EU countries, whereas Canada has imposed visa restrictions on these three EU Member States. This is because of a previous influx of people from those countries who outstayed their welcome.</p>
      <p sl="es">Canada takes the quite reasonable view that not all EU countries are the same, and that some pose a particular risk when it comes to unwanted visitors and guests. The Canadians want to pick and choose who they admit and who they do not. However, this realistic view of the world falls foul of the EU ideological view that the EU is in fact one country, and to discriminate against one of its regions is not permissible.</p>
      <p sl="es">The Canadian Government already has a very generous system of allowing visa-free entry for 24 EU Member States, but perhaps it has looked at my constituency, London, and seen what a completely unrestricted open-door immigration policy actually delivers. They will not get the visitors and migrants they want – the decent, hard-working and law-abiding – they will also get the down-and-outs, the deadbeats and the criminals. In Marble Arch, the very centre of London, we now have migrants living on the street, with all the unpleasant social and sanitary consequences that involves, which I will leave to your imagination.</p>
      <p sl="es">This is what indiscriminate, visa-free travel can deliver. The Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement put in jeopardy by Canada’s reluctance to open its doors to all comers is reputedly worth a potential USD 12 billion per annum, and would boost two-way trade by 20%.</p>
      <p sl="es">What does the world need now? Does it desperately need increased trade? Does it desperately need increased economic activity, jobs and increased prosperity? I think we would all agree that it does. Does it desperately need even more uncontrolled and unlimited migration? Most rational people would think that it does not. Let the Canadians choose who they want to let into their country, and on what terms. Let Canada and Europe get on with increasing the trade between them that can help us all out of the dire economic situation that we find ourselves in.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-072-000" speaker_id="96852" name="Cornelia ERNST" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="es">im Namen der GUE/NGL-Fraktion . – Herr Präsident! Also erstens gibt es entweder, einheitliche EU-Visa-Regelungen und einen verbindlichen Gegenseitigkeitsmechanismus für alle Mitgliedstaaten, dann muss auch die Kommission als Hüterin der Verträge hart dafür kämpfen, dass dies umgesetzt wird. Oder nicht, dann duldet die Kommission im Übrigen seit vielen Jahren schon ein Zweiklassensystem der EU-Bürger, und das ist etwas völlig Inakzeptables für uns als Fraktion. Wir verlangen von der Kommission unverzüglich und vor Abschluss des Abkommens mit den Kanadiern, dieses Problem zu klären. Ansonsten muss der Gegenseitigkeitsmechanismus gelten. Das ist das Erste.</p>
      <p sl="es">Zugleich müssen wir uns aber auch ernst nehmen, und da frage ich: Wird denn nun wenigstens mit der neuen Visa-Verordnung der Gegenseitigkeitsmechanismus gestärkt? Ist das so? Kann verhindert werden, dass künftig solche Praktiken wie in Bezug auf Kanada tatsächlich nicht mehr auftreten? Und da kann ich nur sagen: Mitnichten. Herausgekommen ist doch, dass die Visa-Politik weiterhin als Druckmittel gegen Migration dient.</p>
      <p sl="es">Zum dritten Punkt: Reden wir doch, bitte schön, einmal über die Bevölkerungsgruppe, um die es häufig geht, wenn wir von Tschechien, Bulgarien und Rumänien sprechen. Das sind Roma. Sehr viele Roma sind nach Kanada gegangen, und die Tschechische Republik argumentiert, Kanada sei doch selber schuld daran. Kanada habe ja jahrelang durch seine großzügige und tolerante Asylpolitik Anreize für hohe Einwanderungsquoten geschaffen. Das ist die Argumentation von Kanada, und dagegen unternehmen sie nichts. Im Gegenteil, sie unterstützen das sogar noch, indem sie sagen: Ja, wie können denn EU-Bürger überhaupt in Drittstaaten gehen und Asyl beantragen! Ja warum wohl? Weil die Roma in der EU miserable Lebensbedingungen haben, eine Situation, die wir seit vielen Jahren kennen, die von Diskriminierung und Ausgrenzung nur so strotzt, so dass man sich nicht wundern muss, dass zum Beispiel Leute nach Kanada gehen. Für mich ist diese Sache auch eine Art Lex Roma, und insofern muss, wer wirklich etwas in der Frage verändern will, wer Auswanderung verhindern will, die Lebensbedingungen im eigenen Land verbessern. Darum sollten wir uns kümmern.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-073-000" speaker_id="28255" name="Andreas MÖLZER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Austria" birth_date="02-12-1952" birth_place="Leoben" p_group="Non" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="es">Herr Präsident! Im Rahmen des Handelsabkommens EU-Kanada stellen Visaerleichterungen zweifellos einen weiteren Schritt dar, die von gemeinsamen Wurzeln und Werten geprägten langjährigen Beziehungen zu intensivieren. Auch wenn prinzipiell im Falle Kanadas sicher mit hohen Sicherheitsstandards gerechnet werden kann, sollten die Visaskandale der vergangenen Jahre und die allzu häufige Verwechslung von Visafreiheit mit Niederlassungsfreiheit, wie sie etwa der Anstieg serbischer Asylanträge um 700 % sichtbar macht, als warnende Beispiele gelten.</p>
      <p sl="es">Während auf der einen Seite sogar eigene Visa-Warndateien beschlossen werden, ist auf der anderen Seite bekanntlich Sparen angesagt. Gerade in sensiblen hoheitlichen Bereichen wie der Visavergabe können Privatisierungen allerdings der Manipulation Tür und Tor öffnen. Schließlich sind 2004, 2008 und 2010 unzählige, durch korrupte Ortskräfte ausgelöste Visabetrugsfälle aufgeflogen. Die EU sollte also meines Erachtens in diesen Bereichen besonders sensibel sein und auf größtmögliche Sicherheit achten.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-074-000" speaker_id="28120" name="Simon BUSUTTIL" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Malta" birth_date="21-03-1969" birth_place="Attard" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="MT">
      <p sl="es">Is-sitwazzjoni li qegħdin niddiskutu llum m'aħniex qed nesperjenzawha għall-ewwel darba. Għandna ċittadini ta' pajjiżi terzi, bħall-Kanada, illi jistgħu jidħlu fil-pajjiżi kollha tal-Unjoni Ewropea mingħajr viża filwaqt li ċittadini ta' numru ta' pajjiżi tal-Unjoni Ewropea għad għandhom bżonn viża biex jidħlu f'dawn l-istess pajjiżi. Jiġifieri hawnhekk, għandna kwistjoni ta' nuqqas ta' reċiproċità u mhux kwistjoni ta’ jekk l-Unjoni Ewropea hija jew m’hijiex pajjiż wieħed kif qalu xi kollegi.</p>
      <p sl="es">Il-każ tal-lum jirrigwarda l-Kanada u ċ-ċittadini tar-Repubblika Ċeka, il-Bulgarija u r-Rumanija. Però din l-istorja diġà rajniha mal-Istati Uniti u għadna qed narawha anke ma’ pajjiżi oħra bħall-Brażil, pereżempju, li għadhom qed ikarkru saqajhom biex ineħħu l-obbligu tal-viża għal ċerti pajjiżi fosthom Malta, il-Litwanja u l-Latvja. Dawn is-sitwazzjonijiet juru li m’aħniex qegħdin nieħdu ċ-ċittadinanza Ewropea bis-serjetà biżżejjed u għandna nirranġaw dan in-nuqqas. Sfortunatament, l-Unjoni Ewropea qed tkun wisq timida u mhijiex tasserixxi ruħha kif hemm bżonn fejn hemm sitwazzjoni ta’ nuqqas ta’ reċiproċità.</p>
      <p sl="es">Bħalissa, kif intqal, l-Unjoni Ewropea qegħda tinnegozja trattat ekonomiku u ta’ kummerċ mal-Kanada. Fl-istess ħin, għandna l-Kanada li għadha qed tiddiskrimina kontra ċ-ċittadini tal-Bulgarija, ir-Rumanija u r-Repubblika Ċeka. Jiena naqbel illi l-Kummissjoni għandha tagħmilha ċara li dan mhux aċċettabbli. Fejn pajjiżi terzi mhumiex juru rieda tajba, bħala l-aħħar miżura, l-Unjoni Ewropea għandu jkollha l-possibilità li terġa’ tintroduċi l-obbligu tal-viża għal dawn il-pajjiżi meta jiġu biex jidħlu fl-Unjoni Ewropea. Fil-fatt għadna kif ħadna vot dwar dan fil-Kumitat LIBE f’dawn l-aħħar ġimgħat fejn daħħalna l-idea ta’ mekkaniżmu ta’ sospensjoni. Min-naħa tagħhom ovvjament l-Istati Membri għandhom jgħinu lill-Unjoni Ewropea u juru solidarjetà ma’ dawk il-pajjiżi li qegħdin jiġu diskriminati.</p>
      <p sl="es">Għaldaqstant, nispiċċa billi ngħid illi jekk aħna stess ma niħdux iċ-ċittadinanza u l-politika estera bis-serjetà, ma nistgħux nippretendu li l-pajjiżi terzi jittrattawna bħala grupp magħqud. Għall-kuntrarju, aktar ma nuruhom illi aħna magħquda aktar allura nikkonvinċuhom sabiex jittrattaw lil kulħadd l-istess għal dik illi hija l-kwistjoni tal-viża. U hu għalhekk illi jiena naqbel illi l-Kummissjoni għandha tieħu azzjoni mill-aktar fis fuq dan il-każ u l-każijiet l-oħra kollha pendenti fejn hemm nuqqas ta’ reċiproċità għall-viża.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-075-000" speaker_id="36281" name="Silvia-Adriana ȚICĂU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="14-11-1970" birth_place="Galaţi" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="es">Există numeroase acorduri bilaterale între Canada şi state membre ale Uniunii Europene în domeniul ştiinţei şi tehnologiei, acorduri care implică instituţii guvernamentale, centre universitare de cercetare, fundaţii private, sectorul privat. Totodată, Uniunea Europeană şi Canada trebuie să-şi intensifice cooperarea în domeniul comunicaţiilor electronice şi al tehnologiei informaţiei.</p>
      <p sl="es">Subliniez că, în domeniul transporturilor, Parlamentul European a aprobat încheierea a trei acorduri între Uniunea Europeană şi Canada: un acord-cadru privind transportul aerian, un acord privind siguranţa aviaţiei civile şi un acord privind registrul cu numele pasagerilor, toate aceste acorduri fiind considerate ca exemplare pentru fiecare categorie de acorduri în parte.</p>
      <p sl="es">Aceste acorduri facilitează crearea unei pieţe unice a transportului aerian între Uniunea Europeană şi Canada, în care investiţiile ar putea circula liber şi în care companiile aeriene europene şi canadiene ar putea furniza servicii aeriene fără niciun fel de restricţii, inclusiv pe pieţele interne ale celor două părţi.</p>
      <p sl="es">Acordul-cadru privind transportul aerian cuprinde o eşalonare treptată a drepturilor de trafic şi a oportunităţilor de investiţii, precum şi cooperarea la scară largă cu privire la o serie de aspecte printre care siguranţa, securitatea, aspectele sociale, interesele consumatorilor, mediul, gestionarea traficului aerian, ajutoarele de stat şi concurenţa.</p>
      <p sl="es">Toate aceste acorduri bilaterale şi mai ales un acord economic şi comercial cuprinzător dintre Uniunea Europeană şi Canada se bazează pe un spirit de încredere şi cooperare între părţi. Acelaşi spirit de încredere şi cooperare trebuie, însă, să se manifeste şi în privinţa asigurării regimului de călătorii fără viză în Canada pentru toţi cetăţenii Uniunii Europene.</p>
      <p sl="es">Solicităm ca cetăţenii României, Bulgariei şi Cehiei să beneficieze, încă din acest an, de regimul de călătorii fără viză în Canada. Solicităm ca încheierea unui acord economic şi comercial cuprinzător între Uniunea Europeană şi Canada să se realizeze doar în condiţiile în care toţi cetăţenii Uniunii Europene, deci şi cetăţenii României, Bulgariei şi Cehiei vor beneficia în mod nediscriminatoriu de regimul de călătorii fără viză în Canada.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-076-000" speaker_id="96802" name="Jacek WŁOSOWICZ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="25-01-1966" birth_place="Skalbmierz" p_group="European Conservatives and Reformists Group" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="es">Panie Przewodniczący! W grudniu minęło już dziesięć lat od spotkania, jakie odbyli w Ottawie ówczesny przewodniczący Rady Rasmussen i kanadyjski premier Chrétien. Zadeklarowali wtedy oni wspólne działania na rzecz pogłębienia więzi pomiędzy Unią Europejską i Kanadą. Wiele w tym czasie wydarzyło się na arenie międzynarodowej. Traktat europejski przeszedł dwie ogromne przemiany. Euro w tym czasie stało się wspólną walutą wielu krajów w Europie. Nastąpiło również największe rozszerzenie Unii Europejskiej w historii.</p>
      <p sl="es">Wspólne wartości obywateli Unii Europejskiej i Kanady dały siłę i wzmocniły podstawy wzajemnej współpracy, której zakres poszedł dużo dalej, niż przewidywał pierwotny projekt. Pojawiły się projekty z dziedziny prawa własności, prawa konkurencji i zamówień rządowych. Nie wszystkie nowe płaszczyzny udało się w międzyczasie uregulować, ale jak widać trwają dalsze prace w celu zapewnienia pełnego wdrożenia istniejących już umów. Uważam więc, że potrzeba nowego tchnienia, świeżego powietrza – jak widzę, niezbędnych kroków do podjęcia w stosunkach gospodarczych pomiędzy Unią Europejską i Kanadą w obecnym stuleciu. Dlatego z zadowoleniem przyjmuję postęp dotychczasowych prac w tym zakresie, w zakresie ruchu bezwizowego równego dla obywateli wszystkich państw Unii Europejskiej.</p>
      <p sl="es">Oczywiście pamiętam, iż nie wszyscy obywatele Unii są traktowani jednakowo. Wyjaśnienia strony kanadyjskiej wydają się być jedynie przeciąganiem czasu zamiast podjęcia jednoznacznej decyzji. My, Polacy, takiego traktowania doświadczamy w kontaktach z sąsiadem Kanady – Stanami Zjednoczonymi – niestety jesteśmy traktowani na granicy amerykańskiej jak obywatele Unii Europejskiej, ale drugiej kategorii. Uważam, iż negocjowane porozumienie gospodarczo-handlowe pomiędzy Unią i Kanadą musi zawierać rozwiązania nie tylko z zakresu gospodarki, ale również regulujące sprawy obywatelskie. Jeżeli pozwolimy na nierówne traktowanie obywateli poszczególnych państw Unii Europejskiej, to przyznamy, iż wspólna polityka zagraniczna, która obejmuje również sprawy wizowe, nie istnieje i najlepiej zrezygnujmy z wydawania na nią dużych kwot. Ponadto należy jeszcze pamiętać, iż to, o co się upominamy, czyli możliwość bezwizowego wjazdu na obszar Kanady, jedynie zrównoważy wzajemne prawa obywateli Unii i Kanady, bo Kanadyjczycy przecież takie prawo mają.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-077-000" speaker_id="96858" name="Marie-Christine VERGIAT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="France" birth_date="23-09-1956" birth_place="Roanne" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="FR">
      <p sl="es">Monsieur le Président, je vais parler –j'espère que vous ne m'en voudrez pas, Madame Malmström – uniquement de l'accord économique et commercial global entre le Canada et l'Union européenne.</p>
      <p sl="es">Je crains qu'il en soit de cet accord comme d'ACTA. Le moins que l'on puisse dire, c'est que ces négociations sur l'AECG manquent de transparence. Ces négociations ont débuté en 2009 et nous en sommes au douzième round de négociation. Pourtant, nous ne pouvons pas dire que nous soyons très bien informés du contenu de ces négociations. Le site de la Commission, lui-même, est bloqué au neuvième round. Il ne contient aucune information réelle et les informations les plus pertinentes nous parviennent du Canada. Pire, d'une résolution à l'autre, le point de vue du Parlement européen ne semble guère être pris en compte.</p>
      <p sl="es">Cet accord est le plus ambitieux jamais négocié avec le Canada, voire avec n'importe quel autre État dans le monde. Il est basé sur une approche fondée sur une liste dite négative de la libéralisation des services. Or, la plupart des services publics ne semblent pas avoir été exclus des négociations. Qu'adviendra-t-il des services en matière de santé, d'éducation, d'électricité, de télécommunications, d'eau potable et même de culture, si seule l'approche économique et commerciale prévaut de chaque côté de l'Atlantique. Seuls semblent être pris en compte les intérêts des grandes entreprises publiques qui veulent conquérir de nouvelles parts de marché, au mépris de l'intérêt général, de l'intérêt public des populations. Cette vision du monde a pourtant déjà fait suffisamment de dégâts pour que l'on cesse la fuite en avant. Mais non, rien n'y fait. Les points de vue des experts chargés d'étudier l'impact de ces accords semblent être pour le moins divergents. Les uns parlent de la création de 80 000 emplois au Canada, les autres de la suppression de 30 à 150 000 emplois. Le même type d'étude ne semble pas avoir été publié pour l'Union européenne, et c'est bien dommage. L'impact de cet accord pourrait aussi avoir de lourdes conséquences pour les collectivités locales et leurs marchés publics, qui, pour l'essentiel, semblent avoir été tenues à l'écart.</p>
      <p sl="es">Pourrions-nous avoir un état précis de cet accord et des études d'impact aussi précises sur ses conséquences? ACTA devrait nous servir de leçon; il n'en est rien, je le regrette.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-078-000" speaker_id="97968" name="Andrey KOVATCHEV" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Bulgaria" birth_date="13-12-1967" birth_place="Sofia" m_state="BG">
      <p sl="es">Г-н Председател, уважаема г-жо Malmström, уважаеми колеги, общата външнотърговска политика на Европейския съюз трябва да докаже, че Европа има силен глас в света и че Европейските институции могат да защитят интересите на всички граждани на Европейския съюз, за разлика от това, което моят колега от Обединеното кралство явно не иска - да има такъв силен Европейски съюз. Съжалявам, че той не е вече тук в залата.</p>
      <p sl="es">Аз съм за по-нататъшното задълбочаване на европейската интеграция, водеща до по-ефективна, силна общностна наднационална външна политика, външнотърговска политика и политика за сигурност. Която страна не иска да има така интеграция, то тя е свободна и е суверенно право да напусне Европейския съюз, но не постоянно да бойкотира желанието на другите страни, които искат да има такава интеграция.</p>
      <p sl="es">Обратно на темата - Канада е важен наш съюзник и икономически партньор. Желаното от двете страни всеобхватно икономическо и търговско споразумение, което в момента е в процес на договаряне, е замислено да бъде основен инструмент за улесняване на търговията между партньорите във взаимен техен интерес.</p>
      <p sl="es">Съществуващите обаче визови ограничения за гражданите на България, Чешката република и Румъния при пътувания до Канада трябва да отпаднат. В хода на преговорите европейските институции трябва да си поставят тази задача като приоритет, което ще доведе до реално улеснение и либерализация на търговските отношения между Европейския съюз и Канада.</p>
      <p sl="es">Търговското споразумение има за цел либерализация на търговията с услуги, предимно пътнически и транспортни, като неговият текст трябва да съдържа насочени към премахването на пречките, които затрудняват достъпа до този пазар на услуги, стъпки. Изискванията за притежаване на виза е точно такава пречка.</p>
      <p sl="es">Аз смятам, г-жо комисар, че има директна връзка между търговското споразумение и визовия режим и тези пречки трябва да отпаднат. Благодаря, г-жо комисар, за Вашата позиция, очаквам в оставащите кръгове на преговорите Комисията да продължава да поставя този въпрос пред канадските ни партньори, особено в светлината на предстоящите промени в канадското миграционно законодателство, гарантиране на принципа на реципрочност и разбира се дебатираното търговско споразумение.</p>
      <p sl="es">Безвизовото пътуване до Канада за всички граждани на Европейския съюз е ключово условие, чието изпълнение ще доведе и до реално улесняване на търговията между Европейския съюз и Канада. Аз споделям също и мнението на моите колеги, които преди това казаха, че има риск в нашия парламент да не бъде ратифицирано това споразумение, ако тези условия не бъдат изпълнени.</p>
      <p sl="es">Осигуряването на безвизово пътуване и гарантиране на реципрочност за всички граждани на Европейския съюз трябва да е приоритет на Европейските институции в отношенията, особено със стратегическите ни партньори като Съединените щати, Канада и Австралия.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-079-000" speaker_id="97009" name="Kriton ARSENIS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Greece" birth_date="03-08-1977" birth_place="Thessaloniki" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, I heard and I share the concerns of colleagues on the visa issue, and I would also like to draw attention to another possible problem regarding this agreement.</p>
      <p sl="es">For the first time since the Lisbon Treaty allowed us to do so, we have concluded EU agreements on investment issues. It seems that the proposal will include provision for investor-State dispute settlement. This will mean that not only States but also individual investors can sue EU States over what they regard as obstacles to their investments. This might seriously reduce our powers here in this House, and also in the national parliaments, to regulate on environment-related, social and labour issues.</p>
      <p sl="es">It is proposed to maximise economic profit and benefits, but our own EU assessment – the economic, social and environmental assessment – says there is no solid evidence to suggest that investor-State dispute settlement will maximise economic benefit in CETA beyond simply serving as one form of enforcement mechanism, just as State-State settlement is also an enforcement mechanism. It goes on to say that a well-crafted State-State dispute settlement mechanism might be a more appropriate enforcement mechanism in CETA. So our own assessment says we should move in another direction.</p>
      <p sl="es">The idea of an investor-State settlement mechanism was introduced in the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) because Mexico’s courts were considered to be corrupt, but in the end the mechanism was used mainly against Canada. Twenty-eight cases have been taken against Canada under NAFTA, and out of them eight have been concluded officially. Four have been lost – 50% have been lost.</p>
      <p sl="es">I would like to mention very briefly the case of Ethyl Corp versus Canada. Canada decided to ban, for health reasons, a gasoline additive, and the Ethyl company took Canada to the NAFTA tribunal. It made Canada pay CAD 16 million in compensation, apologise and withdraw the ban. I believe that this is not the kind of regulation we can accept in this agreement.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-080-000" speaker_id="96848" name="Mariya GABRIEL" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Bulgaria" birth_date="20-05-1979" birth_place="Gotse Delchev" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats) - Vice" m_state="BG">
      <p sl="es">Г-н председател, уважаема г-жо комисар, още на 9 юни 2010 г. с колеги от Европейския парламент внесохме въпрос до Европейска комисия относно визите за Канада за български, румънски и чешки граждани.</p>
      <p sl="es">Преди това, по време на последната среща на върха на Европейския съюз и Канада, беше поет ангажимент да бъдат премахнати оставащите пречки за постигане на безвизов режим за пътуване за всички граждани на Европейския съюз. Оттогава минаха близо две години, но визовият режим все още в сила, ограничавайки свободното движение на гражданите на тези страни.</p>
      <p sl="es">Според Европейския парламент в рамките на Европейския съюз има само една категория граждани и със сигурност категория "втора ръка" не съществува.</p>
      <p sl="es">Преговорите на Комисията с Канада относно Всеобхватното икономическо и търговско споразумение ще определят бъдещата правна рамка на икономическите отношения между Европейския съюз и Канада.</p>
      <p sl="es">Ключов елемент от икономическите и търговските споразумения е степента на улесняване на пътуванията за търговските партньори. Понастоящем обаче този елемент не функционира при използване на пълния си капацитет, тъй като Канада изисква визи за гражданите на Румъния, Чешката република и България. Следователно е важно подобно споразумение да бъде договорено, базирайки се на визова реципрочност.</p>
      <p sl="es">Въвеждането на безвизово пътуване за гражданите на всички държави членки на Европейски съюз трябва да бъде приоритет по време на оставащата част от преговорите. Премахването на визите ще спомогне за изграждането на тесни връзки в полза и на Канада, и на Европейския съюз, като едно неделимо цяло.</p>
      <p sl="es">Трябва да бъде постигната справедливост, защото за съжаление сме свидетели на едностранна справедливост: канадските граждани могат да пътуват свободно във всички двадесет и седем страни членки, докато в същото време налага ограничение за някои пълноправни членки на Европейския съюз.</p>
      <p sl="es">Убедена съм, че премахването на визовите изисквания ще помогне за укрепване на сътрудничеството в бизнеса и търговията, за насърчаване на културния и научния обмен и ще позволи по-солидни връзки между Канада и Европа.</p>
      <p sl="es">Канада е страна партньор на Съюза в много области, така че заедно трябва да се ангажираме с премахване на пречките, които ни възпрепятстват за постигането на общата цел за създаване на зона за свободно движение. Постигането на тази обща ни цел означава премахване на ограниченията и укрепване на принципа на реципрочност, които два елемента могат силно да допринесат за доброто и на канадските, и на европейските граждани, с които чрез това споразумение в крайна сметка пътуваме в един кораб.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-081-000" speaker_id="96715" name="Pavel POC" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Czechia" birth_date="26-05-1964" birth_place="Havlíčkův Brod" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="CZ">
      <p sl="es">Pane předsedající, Listina základních práv a svobod zakládá Evropskou unii na nedělitelných a všeobecných hodnotách lidské důstojnosti, svobody, rovnosti a solidarity. Hlava III Listiny hovoří o rovnosti před zákonem a zákazu diskriminace. Evropské smlouvy hovoří o evropském občanství. Evropská komise se ráda nazývá strážkyní smluv, možná by bylo dobré, aby byla výrazně aktivnější při snaze zabezpečit evropským občanům rovný přístup k základním principům evropských smluv a nevytvářela svou nečinností evropské občany „druhé kategorie“.</p>
      <p sl="es">Kanadou byla v červenci roku 2009 zavedena jednostranná vízová povinnost pro občany České republiky, dosud bez jakéhokoliv recipročního opatření Evropské unie. Údajným důvodem pro zavedení této vízové povinnosti bylo velké množství žadatelů o azyl z České republiky. Ovšem v kontextu skutečnosti, že poté další členské státy začaly Kanadu „zásobovat” větším počtem žadatelů o azyl bez jakéhokoliv opatření z kanadské strany, nemohu ignorovat dosavadní váhavost a nedůsledný přístup Komise v této věci. Jsou snad pravdivé fámy o účelové, neformální dohodě mezi paní komisařkou a jejím kanadským protějškem, která má zabránit tomu, aby byly další členské státy vystaveny stejné diskriminaci jako moje země? Hodila snad Komise část občanů Evropské unie jednoduše přes palubu? Nevím a doufám, že ne. Každopádně věřím, že Evropská komise vyslyší konečně všechny výzvy a zasadí se o ukončení vízové povinnosti části evropských občanů cestujících do Kanady.</p>
      <p sl="es">S váženými kolegy Parvanovou a Bodu jsme se 18. října 2011 obrátili na kanadského premiéra Harpera osobním dopisem, upozornili jsme jej na možné politické souvislosti tohoto jednostranného zavedení vízové povinnosti a schvalovacího procesu souhrnné hospodářské a obchodní dohody (CETA). Dopis dodnes zůstal bez reakce. Pokud se tato situace urychleně nevyřeší, nedivil bych se potížím s ratifikací dohody CETA nejen v Parlamentu České republiky.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-082-000" speaker_id="28397" name="Agustín DÍAZ DE MERA GARCÍA CONSUEGRA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Spain" birth_date="27-09-1947" birth_place="Daimiel " p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">Señor Presidente, el debate de esta tarde no es nuevo ni es un problema exclusivo de Rumanía, la República Checa y Bulgaria, sino que afecta a todos los Estados de la Unión.</p>
      <p sl="es">Hoy son estos tres los países concernidos, pero en otras ocasiones podría tratarse de cualquier otro, como así ha ocurrido. De hecho, esta Cámara, en su Declaración del 8 de marzo de 2011, ya solicitó a la Comisión el establecimiento de un nuevo mecanismo que garantizara la plena reciprocidad para todos los Estados, asegurando así que, si un país tercero incumple la reciprocidad del régimen de visados, todos los Estados miembros establecerán la obligación del visado para los ciudadanos de dicho país.</p>
      <p sl="es">Los principios de reciprocidad y solidaridad deben guiar la política comunitaria de visados, respetándose también en aquellos otros debates, como el caso que nos ocupa, acerca del Acuerdo económico y comercial global entre la Unión Europea y Canadá. Solo así conseguiremos una política de visados fuerte, rigurosa, creíble, solidaria y comunitaria.</p>
      <p sl="es">Del mismo modo, soy también consciente de la importancia de las relaciones exteriores de la Unión y de cada uno de sus países; por ello es necesario encontrar un equilibrio entre el respeto de los principios de reciprocidad y solidaridad y las relaciones comerciales europeas.</p>
      <p sl="es">Este problema, como saben, está debatiéndose desde hace prácticamente un año en el seno de la Comisión LIBE, a través de una propuesta destinada a modificar el Reglamento (CE) nº 539/2001 del Consejo, por el que se establece la lista de terceros países cuyos nacionales están sometidos a la obligación de visado para cruzar las fronteras exteriores y la lista de terceros países cuyos nacionales están exentos de esa obligación. Yo soy el ponente de esta iniciativa legislativa.</p>
      <p sl="es">El objetivo de esta propuesta es precisamente dotar a la Unión de un mecanismo eficaz y realista que solucione conflictos como el que actualmente sufren rumanos, checos y búlgaros con Canadá. Hace una semana comenzamos la fase de trílogos negociadores con el Consejo, pero tengo un fuerte mandato en materia de reciprocidad.</p>
      <p sl="es">La Comisión LIBE está comprometida y exige esa reciprocidad. La postura de las tres instituciones y el Parlamento está en fase de aproximación, pero todos somos conscientes de la urgencia y de la necesidad de encontrar un acuerdo que satisfaga los intereses concernidos. No creo, señora Comisaria, que podamos alcanzar este acuerdo con la Presidencia danesa.</p>
      <p sl="es">Ya saben que el Parlamento solo dice «sí» o «no» ante un acuerdo internacional. Yo diré «no» y recomendaré el «no» a mi grupo político si Canadá no exime de la obligación de visado a checos, búlgaros y rumanos, antes de la votación.</p>
      <p sl="es">Señor Presidente, el argumento del señor Enciu es un argumento muy sólido e impecable.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-083-000" speaker_id="39722" name="Sebastian Valentin BODU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="07-12-1970" birth_place="Constanţa" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="es">Dezbaterea de astăzi reprezintă „semifinala” unei lupte al cărei punct final îl va constitui eliminarea vizelor pentru cetăţenii români, cehi şi bulgari, vize impuse de către autorităţile canadiene pentru un motiv constant: rata ridicată a solicitărilor de azil venite din partea unor cetăţeni est-europeni, în special aparţinând unor anumitor minorităţi, odată ajunşi în Canada cu viză turistică.</p>
      <p sl="es">Ca membru al delegaţiei interparlamentare UE – Canada, cu fiecare ocazie avută, inclusiv prin scrisori adresate oficialităţilor canadiene, am susţinut necesitatea modificării procedurii de azil pentru cetăţenii europeni, astfel încât abuzul constant de această procedură să dispară.</p>
      <p sl="es">În urmă cu câteva luni, Canada a adoptat în sfârşit o nouă legislaţie privind imigraţia, legislaţie prin care, pentru cetăţenii statelor democratice, termenul de soluţionarea a cererii de azil a fost redus de la câţiva ani la câteva săptămâni. Am sperat că, odată eliminată problema azilanţilor abuzivi, Canada să renunţe la vize, nemaiexistând motive pentru menţinerea acestora. Din păcate însă, constat cu regret că oficialii canadieni nu şi-au schimbat deloc discursul în această chestiune, astfel încât ultima posibilitate de a modifica această atitudine este apelul la solidaritatea europeană.</p>
      <p sl="es">În a doua jumătate a acestui an va intra spre aprobare în Parlament îndelung-negociatul acord de liber-schimb UE - Canada, acord care în prezent nu conţine nicio prevedere privind eliminarea vizelor. Prin prezenta dezbatere, subsemnatul, împreună cu ceilalţi iniţiatori ai întrebării adresate Comisiei vrem să trimitem un semnal puternic atât negociatorilor europeni - de a considera prioritară problema vizelor, cât şi guvernului canadian, astfel încât Parlamentul European să nu fie pus în situaţia de a respinge acordul de liber-schimb pe motiv de inexistenţă a unui regim de liberă circulaţie a persoanelor.</p>
      <p sl="es">După cum se ştie, Parlamentul European este foarte sensibil la probleme ce ţin de drepturile omului, aşa cum a dovedit-o de foarte multe ori, în mod surprinzător pentru mulţi, iar în cazul acordului de liber-schimb este evident că nu putem vorbi de liberă circulaţie a bunurilor, capitalurilor şi serviciilor în lipsa unei libere circulaţie a persoanelor.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-085-000" speaker_id="96654" name="Jaroslav PAŠKA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="20-06-1954" birth_place="Banská Štiavnica" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group - Vice" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="es">Myslím si, že všetci máme záujem na čo najlepších vzťahoch s Kanadou, ktorú považujeme za vyspelú, civilizovanú a demokratickú krajinu. Rovnako som presvedčený, že všetci rešpektujeme práva kanadskej administratívy na to, aby si sama určovala podmienky pre vstup osôb z iných krajín, ktoré prichádzajú na jej územie.</p>
      <p sl="es">Na druhej strane si treba uvedomiť, že dohoda o hospodárskej a obchodnej spolupráci, ktorá má upraviť spoluprácu Kanady s Úniou, sa bude vzťahovať aj na Českú republiku, Rumunsko, Bulharsko a ktorákoľvek z týchto krajín bude môcť namietať proti uzavretiu dohody, pokiaľ sa bude cítiť diskriminovaná prístupom Kanady k jej občanom. Preto chcem veriť, že pripravovaná reforma azylového práva Kanady odstráni obavy Kanaďanov zo zneužívania ich sociálneho systému občanmi niektorých európskych krajín a otvorí cestu pre bezvízový styk všetkých občanov Európskej únie s Kanadou.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-086-000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán KELLY" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Ireland" birth_date="26-04-1952" birth_place="Killarney" m_state="IE">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, I too am a member of the EP Delegation for Relations with Canada. I find the experience rewarding, and I find the Canadians upfront and honourable. For that reason it is a pity that we have this logjam, which we must work our way through.</p>
      <p sl="es">For that reason, I would be loath to use what I would regard as the ‘nuclear option’ of withdrawing visa-free travel for Canadians at this point in time. That is something we should hold as a bargaining tool. I think that, with our shared history and culture, we should be able to get through this difficulty and come to an understanding so all 27 Member States would have the same rights with regard to travel to Canada.</p>
      <p sl="es">Also, I think that the trade agreement is of paramount importance and, particularly at a time of recession, we do need to work at ensuring that we have every opportunity to grow our economy. Certainly, having a country like Canada in a position to have a free trade agreement with us offers huge opportunities for us. So I think the message here is that we should negotiate and come to an agreement with people who share a history, a culture and democratic principles with us.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-087-000" speaker_id="96981" name="Franz OBERMAYR" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Austria" birth_date="25-05-1952" p_group="Non" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="es">Herr Präsident! Grundsätzlich ist ein umfassendes Wirtschafts- und Handelsabkommen mit Kanada durchaus zu begrüßen. Ich möchte gleich zur Einschränkung der Visafreiheit kommen. Es sollte doch jedem souveränen Staat selbst überlassen werden, für wen er Reiseerleichterungen verabschiedet. Es steht dementsprechend auch Rumänien oder Bulgarien offen zu entscheiden, welchen Staatsbürgern sie die Einreise in ihr Land erschweren oder auch erleichtern.</p>
      <p sl="es">Für sinnvoll halte ich auch die Asylpolitik von Kanada, die zwischen Antragstellern aus demokratischen und undemokratischen Ländern durchaus unterscheidet. Denn Asylant kann schon von der Definition her nur jemand sein, der aus einem Land kommt, in dem er verfolgt wird, was auf demokratische EU-Staaten wohl kaum zutrifft. Die EU sollte sich vielmehr ein Beispiel an der Asylpolitik Kanadas nehmen. Kanada war und ist grundsätzlich ein großzügiges Einwanderungsland. Nur, wenn man negative Erfahrungen mit sogenannten Touristen hat, die dann untertauchen, die die Gastfreundschaft über Gebühr in Anspruch nehmen und das mit einer Niederlassungsfreiheit verwechseln, dann verstehe ich, dass man auch in Kanada durchaus Bedenken gegen diese Form von Einwanderung hat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-089-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Cecilia Malmström" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="es">Member of the Commission . − Mr President, I would like to thank all the Members for this very important debate. Canada is a country with which we have a special relationship. It is a friend and an ally on many issues, and it is in both Canada’s interest and our interest that we try to deepen the relationship in all possible ways. That is why this visa issue is so frustrating, and I share your frustration here.</p>
      <p sl="es">Of course the Commission is doing everything it can to make sure that there will be full visa freedom between Canada and the EU, in both directions. I have, on numerous occasions, raised this issue with the Canadian authorities, indeed with the Minister himself, and so have my colleagues in the Commission and many of the Commission officials. We hope that the issue between Romania and Bulgaria, on the one hand, and Canada, on the other, can be solved very soon when Romania and Bulgaria enter the Schengen cooperation system. Meanwhile the immigration bill should enter into force by the end of this year, so there should be a possibility of breaking the deadlock.</p>
      <p sl="es">This is an issue we are following very, very closely and we have made clear to our Canadian counterparts that visa reciprocity is a key issue for us in the Commission, for Member States, for the European Parliament and for our citizens. We have also made clear that it may influence the ratification of the CETA process. However this is not part of the formal negotiating mandate.</p>
      <p sl="es">I think the message from this plenary has been very clearly heard, and we will continue on the Commission side to push this issue. It will also be part of the discussion on a new EU-Canada framework agreement, and we will set up a working group with the countries concerned, the Commission and the Canadian authorities. I am confident we can achieve a solution to this problem, and I hope we will do so very soon.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-090-000" speaker_id="23820" name="László SURJÁN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="07-09-1941" birth_place="Kolozsvár" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="es">A vitát lezárom.</p>
      <p sl="es">Írásbeli nyilatkozatok (149. cikk)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091-000" speaker_id="23840" name="Richard FALBR" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Czechia" birth_date="29-09-1940" birth_place="Chester" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="CZ">
      <p sl="es">písemně . – Když poslouchám stále stejně znějící lamentace na téma, jak Kanada dělá z občanů tří zemí EU, tj. Bulharska, Česka a Rumunska, občany druhé kategorie, nemůžu se ubránit dojmu, že pláčeme dobře, ale na špatném hrobě. Tyto tři země by si měly udělat pořádek doma, aby nedocházelo k hromadnému exodu menšinového obyvatelstva, které se díky sociální politice prováděné v těchto třech zemích ocitá v nesnesitelných a neřešitelných životních podmínkách.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091-250" speaker_id="111027" name="Svetoslav Hristov MALINOV" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Bulgaria" birth_date="19-01-1968" birth_place="Dupnitsa" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="BG">
      <p sl="es">в писмена форма. – Има нещо дълбоко символично в това, че поводът за дебата относно премахването на канадските визи за българи, румънци и чехи се оказва предстоящото търговско споразумение между Канада и Европейския съюз. Търговските споразумения винаги търсят взаимната изгода и са максимално прагматични. Ето защо разговорът за принципи и ценности по време на търговски преговори често се смята за проява на лош вкус. Призовавам да нарушим добрия тон и да запитаме канадските си партньори: Смятате ли, че има „първа“ и „втора“ категория европейци? Как иначе да си обясним вашия съзнателен отказ да третирате като равноправни всички европейски граждани?</p>
      <p sl="es">Европейският съюз винаги се е гордеел с това, че е „съюз на ценности“. Равенството на държавите членки пред Договорите е прогласено в чл. 3 на Договора от Лисабон. То трябва да се защитава, защото неговото незачитане засяга самия фундамент на Съюза. Разполагаме с достатъчно механизми, за да изискаме прилагането на принципа на визовата реципрочност спрямо Канада. Осигуряването на безвизово пътуване за всички европейски граждани трябва да бъде приоритет на всички европейски институции. Канада трябва да премахне визовите си ограничения за България, Румъния и Чехия. Призовавам членовете на ЕП да не забравят това, когато търговското споразумение между ЕС и Канада се върне в тази зала за нашето одобрение.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091-500" speaker_id="28352" name="Zuzana ROITHOVÁ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Czechia" birth_date="30-01-1953" birth_place="Praha" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="CZ">
      <p sl="es">písemně . – Vítám debatu k otázce vízové reciprocity s Kanadou v souvislosti s vyjednávanou obchodní dohodou mezi EU a Kanadou, jsem však nemile překvapena, že k ní dochází až poté, co jsem spolu s kolegy musela v této věci předložit otázku k ústnímu zodpovězení. Jsem stále zaražena přístupem Evropské komise, která dělá to, co vyhovuje kanadské straně, a účinně nebrání diskriminaci dotčených států. Na nebezpečí neschválení mezinárodních smluv s Kanadou upozornil EP již před dvěmi lety v písemném prohlášení, které jsem iniciovala. Nejedná se o planá varování, jelikož český parlament již kvůli této situaci blokuje smlouvu v oblasti letectví. Čeští poslanci zvažují, že budoucí obchodní dohodu budou blokovat tak dlouho, jak dlouho bude trvat vízová nereciprocita, která slaví v červenci třetí výročí. Nepovažuji za účinné svolat pracovní skupinu, pokud jde o problém velkého přílivu nepodložených žádostí o azyl, jelikož jádro problému tkví v kanadském azylovém zákoně, nikoliv v členských státech EU. Navíc pracovní skupina mezi Kanadou a ČR za účasti EK již byla sestavena v roce 2009 a k žádnému postupu nedošlo. Apeluji na EK, aby podpořila pozměňovací návrh navržený mnou a kolegy k nařízení o vízové povinnosti třetích zemí jako účinný, viditelný a rázný tlak na Kanadu, jinak EU hrozí budoucí komplikace v evropsko-kanadských vztazích.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem16" title="16. Intervenciones de un minuto (artículo 150 del Reglamento)">
    <intervention id="1-093-000" speaker_id="23820" name="László SURJÁN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="07-09-1941" birth_place="Kolozsvár" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="es">A következő napirendi pont a fontos politikai kérdésekkel kapcsolatos egyperces felszólalások.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-094-000" speaker_id="26851" name="Nikolaos CHOUNTIS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Greece" birth_date="17-09-1953" birth_place="Lagadia Arkadias" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="es">Αγαπητοί συνάδελφοι, κύριε Πρόεδρε, όπως γνωρίζετε, η χώρα μου η Ελλάδα βρίσκεται σε προεκλογική περίοδο. Πριν δύο μέρες, επισκέφτηκε την Ελλάδα ο Πρόεδρος του Ευρωπαϊκού Κοινοβουλίου. Κατά τη διάρκεια της συνάντησής του με τον Πρόεδρο της Δημοκρατίας, ο Πρόεδρος της Ελληνικής Δημοκρατίας δέχτηκε τηλεφώνημα από την κυρία Μέρκελ, η οποία συνέστησε να πραγματοποιηθεί δημοψήφισμα μαζί με τις εκλογές, με το ερώτημα εάν αποδέχεται ο ελληνικός λαός τα μέτρα του μνημονίου ή εάν επιθυμεί να εγκαταλείψει το ευρώ. Ο κύριος Schulz είδε την οργή και την ανεπιφύλακτη καταδίκη τέτοιων παρεμβάσεων από όλες τις πολιτικές δυνάμεις. Θα περίμενε συνεπώς κανείς ότι, αντί να προπαγανδίζει θέσεις τις οποίες έχει απορρίψει ο ελληνικός λαός, θα επέλεγε αντιθέτως να πράξει το καθήκον του και να προβεί σε μια δημοκρατική δήλωση με την οποία θα τόνιζε ότι πρέπει να αφεθεί απερίσπαστος ο ελληνικός λαός να αποφασίσει δημοκρατικά. Δεν το έπραξε. Παρόμοιες συμπεριφορές και παρεμβάσεις πλήττουν ωστόσο τη συνοχή της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης και πλήττουν τη δημοκρατία, όχι μόνο στην Ελλάδα αλλά και στην Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση. Αναμένω από τον Πρόεδρο του Ευρωπαϊκού Κοινοβουλίου να τοποθετηθεί σχετικά με τούτο το ζήτημα δημοκρατίας.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-095-000" speaker_id="23746" name="Vytautas LANDSBERGIS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Lithuania" birth_date="18-10-1932" birth_place="Kaunas" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="LT">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, colleagues, recently we all witnessed the doubtful management and misconduct of our parliamentary work when a document duly adopted by plenary was later partly cancelled in a discussion of the Conference of Presidents.</p>
      <p sl="es">This happened with the resolution on EU-Azerbaijan negotiations. No parliamentary rule states that, once adopted, a document can afterwards be changed in substance by another Member of Parliament.</p>
      <p sl="es">Deletion of the relevant part of the text was announced as having been made allegedly in accordance with Rule 216, which refers to something different, namely to possible corrigenda to literal or linguistic errata when discovered in a text after the vote.</p>
      <p sl="es">As this was not the case, the corrigendum – as distributed in a breach of due procedure – looks unlawful when the resolution in the form in which Parliament voted on it was lawful and legitimate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-096-000" speaker_id="96918" name="Derek VAUGHAN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="02-05-1961" birth_place="Merthyr" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, I speak to welcome the Connecting Europe Fund, which is proposed for the new financial framework post-2013. Right across Europe there are still many large infrastructure projects that are needed to boost economic growth. This investment is, of course, needed now more than ever.</p>
      <p sl="es">Indeed, in my own country – Wales – transport infrastructure is still needed, for example electrification of the railway between London and West Wales, which is so vital for our economy. The UK Government proposes to fund that electrification only as far as Cardiff. I would urge them to fund it at least as far west as Swansea because of its importance to the West Wales economy. But if they are refusing to do that, they should work with others, including the Welsh Government, to ensure that the project goes ahead. They should put in place a Plan B, which should include bidding for Connecting Europe funds when they become available.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-097-000" speaker_id="96922" name="Izaskun BILBAO BARANDICA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Spain" birth_date="27-03-1961" birth_place="Bermeo" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">Señor Presidente, en el País Vasco, la asociación Eurobask dedicó el pasado 9 de mayo a aprobar un manifiesto en el que los europeístas vascos renovamos nuestro compromiso con el proyecto europeo.</p>
      <p sl="es">Necesitamos una Europa que ponga a la ciudadanía en el centro del proyecto de integración en vez de a los mercados; que defienda una alternativa a la gestión de la globalización, liderando organismos multilaterales capaces de regular el mercado financiero.</p>
      <p sl="es">Queremos un gobierno económico europeo que devuelva al sistema financiero a su misión tradicional de apoyar la eficacia de la economía productiva como generadora de bienestar social. Eso requiere compaginar la reducción de la deuda y el aumento de la competitividad con el máximo impulso de la I+D+I, orientado especialmente hacia la economía baja en carbono y las energías renovables.</p>
      <p sl="es">Necesitamos liberarnos de dependencias, acelerar el crecimiento y el empleo y establecer nuevos instrumentos de cohesión; más diálogo, más política exterior común y un rotundo «no» a los discursos que criminalizan a las minorías y a la inmigración: seres humanos iguales en derechos frente a los recortes etnicistas.</p>
      <p sl="es">En definitiva, una nueva Europa que vuelva a ser referencia en formación y modelo social; una Unión para vivir, útil y justa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-098-000" speaker_id="111823" name="Nikos CHRYSOGELOS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Greece" birth_date="13-05-1959" birth_place="Athina" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="es">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, για να αντιμετωπιστεί η δημοσιονομική κρίση στην Ελλάδα εφαρμόζονται μέτρα που προξενούν την αντίδραση της κοινωνίας ενώ θα μπορούσε αντιθέτως να προωθείται μια πολιτική πολύ πιο ισορροπημένη από κοινωνική άποψη. Αναφέρω ένα παράδειγμα το οποίο απουσιάζει παντελώς από το νέο μνημόνιο για την προσαρμογή της ελληνικής οικονομίας. Πρόκειται για την εξάρτηση της χώρας από τις εισαγωγές ορυκτών καυσίμων πετρελαίου. Η Ελλάδα, όπως και άλλες χώρες που αντιμετωπίζουν βαθιά κρίση σήμερα, εξαρτώνται απολύτως από εισαγωγές πετρελαίου, οι οποίες όμως επιβαρύνουν πολύ την οικονομία τους και αυξάνουν σημαντικά το έλλειμμα του εμπορικού ισοζυγίου τους. Το ετήσιο κόστος εισαγωγής πετρελαίου, μόνο για τη λειτουργία των μονάδων παραγωγής ηλεκτρικής ενέργειας στα μη διασυνδεδεμένα νησιά, ξεπερνάει τα 300 εκατομμύρια ευρώ. Θα έπρεπε συνεπώς το μνημόνιο να δίνει μεγάλη έμφαση στην ενεργειακή αποδοτικότητα και στην αποδοτικότητα στη χρήση των φυσικών πόρων, διότι θα μπορούσε με τον τρόπο αυτό να βελτιώσει τα δημοσιονομικά της χώρας και να δημιουργήσει θέσεις εργασίας αναζωογονώντας την οικονομία. Νομίζω λοιπόν ότι μία από τις αλλαγές που πρέπει να γίνουν στο μνημόνιο πρέπει να αφορά μια τέτοια πολιτική.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-099-000" speaker_id="38610" name="Slavi BINEV" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Bulgaria" birth_date="10-12-1965" birth_place="Sofia" p_group="Non" m_state="BG">
      <p sl="es">Г-н председател, колеги, имунитетът ми е потъпкан. Подложен съм на политически преследвания, а медиите в България мълчат. Причината: казвам истината.</p>
      <p sl="es">След среща между симпатизанти на създадения от мен политически Съюз "ГОРД" полицията задържа нашите съмишленици, а аз и останалите бяхме третирани като престъпници. Защо? Заради подкрепата към "ГОРД".</p>
      <p sl="es">Именити българи, подкрепили "ГОРД", биват мачкани и унижавани, защото са против управлението. Премиерът е лично отговорен за репресиите срещу нас, но му липсва доблест и други му вършат мръсната работа. Европа пренебрегва сигналите ми, а това окуражава диктатора Борисов.</p>
      <p sl="es">Управлението краде народа и се гаври с противниците си, няма демокрация. Опасявам се, че бездействието на европейските институции може да коства както доброто име, така и живота на моите съмишленици, моите близки, дори на мен.</p>
      <p sl="es">Призовавам обединена Европа и лидерите на европейските партии за незабавни действия и ясно становище. Ако уважавани хора потвърдят, че управляващите ги притискат, защото ме подкрепят, ще се намесите ли или с моите съмишленици да търсим политическо убежище?</p>
      <p sl="es">Ако Брюксел не ни защити от диктатора, то накъде да се обърнем - към Москва, Вашингтон, а може би към Пекин? Това е ситуацията в България</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-100-000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán KELLY" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Ireland" birth_date="26-04-1952" birth_place="Killarney" m_state="IE">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, the Fiscal Stability Treaty will be put to the vote in Ireland in a referendum on 31 May, but I want to take this opportunity to denounce the undemocratic nature of the debate.</p>
      <p sl="es">There is a severe distortion of the democratic process following the McKenna judgment, which stipulates that the ‘yes’ and ‘no’ sides of any referendum campaign must be given equal weight in terms of air time during the campaign. This creates a perverse incentive for all sorts of shady interests to campaign against any referendum, often on spurious grounds. Added to this is the absurdly undemocratic nature of allowing vested interests with no democratic mandate – such as Declan Ganley, a failed European Parliament candidate in 2009 – a disproportionate platform on the national airwaves.</p>
      <p sl="es">Tonight Mr Ganley will be given a similar platform, along with the Deputy Prime Minister, an Tánaiste Eamon Gilmore, on the popular current affairs programme, ‘The Frontline’. Mr Ganley, alongside the Russian economist Constantin Gurdgiev, has set up an asset management company in Switzerland called St Columbanus AG. This company would clearly stand to benefit from any financial instability in Ireland caused by a ‘no’ vote. As it states on its own website: ‘The firm provides a safe haven for assets in the midst of the continuing global financial crisis, a service that appears increasingly important in the current European context of fragile peripheral economies, and an unstable eurozone banking sector’.</p>
      <p sl="es">I think giving this platform to Mr Ganley is totally undemocratic, particularly when you consider that 11 of the 12 Irish MEPs who are in favour of the referendum are virtually ignored.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-101-000" speaker_id="39319" name="Maria Eleni KOPPA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Greece" birth_date="01-03-1963" birth_place="Athina" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="es">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, οι εκλογές της 17ης Ιουνίου θα είναι για την Ελλάδα οι πιο κρίσιμες της μεταπολεμικής περιόδου. Οι πολίτες καλούνται να επιλέξουν εάν θέλουν μια κυβέρνηση υπεύθυνη, η οποία μπορεί να βγάλει τη χώρα από την κρίση, ή εάν προτιμούν να υποκύψουν στο λαϊκισμό και στις εύκολες υποσχέσεις. Σ' ένα τόσο κρίσιμο πλαίσιο με τέτοια δραματικά διλήμματα, οι παρεμβάσεις απ' το εξωτερικό λειτουργούν αρνητικά και πυροδοτούν αντιδράσεις ακόμα και από εκείνους που θέλουν να ακούσουν. Το πλέον πρόσφατο παράδειγμα είναι η πρόταση της κυρίας Μέρκελ προς την ελληνική πολιτική ηγεσία για διεξαγωγή δημοψηφίσματος με το ερώτημα "ναι ή όχι στο ευρώ", την ίδια ημέρα με τις εκλογές. Πρόκειται για μια άποψη εκτός τόπου και χρόνου, διότι μια υπηρεσιακή κυβέρνηση δεν μπορεί να προτείνει δημοψήφισμα, διότι η Βουλή που μόνη της μπορεί να αποφασίσει κάτι τέτοιο έχει διαλυθεί ενόψει εκλογών και, τέλος, διότι πουθενά δεν γίνονται δημοψηφίσματα επειδή το απαιτούν κάποιοι εταίροι. Όταν προτάθηκε δημοψήφισμα από την κυβέρνηση του ΠΑΣΟΚ μερικούς μήνες πριν, με πολύ πιο συγκεκριμένο ερώτημα, υπήρξαν αρνητικές αντιδράσεις διεθνώς, στις οποίες πρωτοστάτησε η κυρία Μέρκελ. Κάθε παρόμοια παρέμβαση είναι απολύτως αντιπαραγωγική αυτή τη στιγμή. Καλούμε την Επιτροπή και το Συμβούλιο να απέχουν από κάθε ενέργεια που δίνει την εικόνα παρέμβασης στα εσωτερικά κυρίαρχης χώρας. Από την Ευρώπη, η Ελλάδα χρειάζεται μια ενιαία φωνή στήριξης και όχι υποδείξεις και απειλές.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-102-000" speaker_id="97018" name="Theodoros SKYLAKAKIS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Greece" birth_date="18-10-1959" birth_place="Athina" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="es">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, τον τελευταίο καιρό γίνεται εκτεταμένη συζήτηση για έξοδο της Ελλάδας από το ευρώ. Ορισμένοι μιλούν ακόμη και για έξοδο από την Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση. Δυστυχώς, είναι πάρα πολλοί αυτοί που μιλούν και είναι πάρα πολλά αυτά που λένε, με κίνδυνο να προκαλέσουν κρίση πριν ακόμη φτάσουμε στις εκλογές του Ιουνίου. Μιλούν χωρίς να λαμβάνουν υπόψη ούτε τις οικονομικές, ούτε τις κοινωνικές και τις γεωπολιτικές συνέπειες μιας τέτοιας υπόθεσης.</p>
      <p sl="es">Θεωρώ ότι θα ήταν καλύτερο να μη χωρίζουμε τους Έλληνες, αναλόγως της ψήφου τους, σε δύο παρατάξεις, υπέρ και κατά της Ευρώπης. Πρέπει να συνειδητοποιήσουμε ότι επρόκειτο, κατά βάση, για ψήφο αντίδρασης στο πολιτικό σύστημα που έφερε την Ελλάδα σε αυτό το τραγικό σημείο. Πρέπει να προσπαθήσουμε να βοηθήσουμε την παραγωγική Ελλάδα, η οποία αξίζει να έχει καλύτερη τύχη από εκείνη που της επιφυλάσσεται μέχρι στιγμής. Τα τελευταία δύο χρόνια, υπήρξε προβληματική διαχείριση της πραγματικά παραγωγικής Ελλάδας. Η ανεργία χτύπησε κυρίως τον ιδιωτικό τομέα και για το γεγονός αυτό δεν είναι άμοιρη ευθυνών η ευρωπαϊκή πλευρά.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-103-000" speaker_id="99416" name="Nikolaos SALAVRAKOS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Greece" birth_date="15-02-1946" birth_place="Kalamata" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group" m_state="GR">
      <p sl="es">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, την ισορροπία μεταξύ λιτότητας και ανάπτυξης των ευρωπαϊκών οικονομιών καλούνται να βρουν οι ευρωπαίοι ηγέτες, τόσο υπό την πίεση του εκλογικού αποτελέσματος στη Γαλλία και στην Ελλάδα, όσο και υπό το ανήσυχο βλέμμα των αγορών. Τα αυστηρά μέτρα λιτότητας συνεχίζουν να δημιουργούν νέους ανέργους και ευρύτερα προβλήματα κοινωνικής συνοχής σε ολόκληρη την Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση. Τα εκλογικά αποτελέσματα τοπικών ή εθνικών εκλογών ανά την Ευρώπη, όπως αυτές που πραγματοποιήθηκαν στην Ιταλία, στη Γερμανία και στη Γαλλία, αντιπροσωπεύουν μια γενικευμένη αντίδραση στην πολιτική της αυστηρής λιτότητας. Είναι βέβαιο ότι απαιτείται χαλάρωση του γερμανικού προτύπου δημοσιονομικής πειθαρχίας και άμεση ανάπτυξη της οικονομίας για να ξαναβρούν οι ευρωπαϊκές κοινωνίες την ισορροπία τους και για να διασφαλίσουν την συνοχή τους, η οποία απειλείται. Απειλείται επίσης το νόμισμα κύριε Πρόεδρε. Πρέπει να σεβαστούμε τα περιθώρια ανοχής των ευρωπαίων πολιτών. Με βάση την αρχή της ευρωπαϊκής αλληλεγγύης, πρέπει να εξετάσουμε το ενδεχόμενο μιας πιο ρεαλιστικής λύσης, που θα περιλαμβάνει έκδοση ευρωομολόγων, την ενίσχυση της Ευρωπαϊκής Τράπεζας και την έκδοση νέου χρήματος.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-104-000" speaker_id="28514" name="Kyriacos TRIANTAPHYLLIDES" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Cyprus" birth_date="03-09-1944" birth_place="Palaihori" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="CY">
      <p sl="es">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, χαιρετίζω τα συμπεράσματα του Συμβουλίου Γενικών Υποθέσεων της 14ης Μαΐου 2012 σχετικά με την ειρηνευτική διαδικασία στη Μέση Ανατολή, με τα οποία επαναλαμβάνεται η προσήλωση της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης στη λύση δύο κρατών και εκφράζεται ανησυχία ότι αυτή η λύση υπονομεύεται από τον εποικισμό και από την κατεδάφιση οικιών και άλλων υποδομών στην ούτω καλούμενη περιοχή C. Την ίδια στιγμή, διπλωμάτες στην περιοχή καταγγέλλουν ότι τουλάχιστο 62 υποδομές που περιλαμβάνουν δεξαμενές ύδρευσης και υγειονομικά συστήματα που είχαν χρηματοδοτηθεί από την Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση και τα κράτη μέλη της κατεδαφίστηκαν από το Ισραήλ το 2011, επιπλέον των εκατοντάδων οικιών και αγροτικών και κτηνοτροφικών εγκαταστάσεων. Στη διάρκεια των τελευταίων δέκα ετών, οι ισραηλινές κατοχικές δυνάμεις έχουν καταστρέψει χρηματοδοτηθέντα από την Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση έργα αξίας 50 εκατομμυρίων ευρώ. Αυτή τη στιγμή, 110 υποδομές έχουν παραλάβει διατάγματα κατεδάφισης από τις ισραηλινές αρχές και κινδυνεύουν να σωριαστούν σε ερείπια από στιγμή σε στιγμή. Οι υποδομές αυτές και τα έργα που ήδη καταστράφηκαν έχουν ανεγερθεί με το υστέρημα του ευρωπαίου φορολογούμενου. Ερωτώ το Συμβούλιο και την Επιτροπή: σε ποιες ενέργειες προτίθενται να προβούν για να προστατεύσουν τα έργα που οικοδομήθηκαν με χρήματα των ευρωπαίων πολιτών;</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-105-000" speaker_id="96987" name="Ricardo CORTÉS LASTRA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Spain" birth_date="23-09-1969" birth_place="Castro Urdiales" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">Señor Presidente, estimados colegas, cada vez son más los casos que conocemos en España de bebés robados o, como ellos prefieren que se les llame, niños apropiados: entre 200 000 y 300 000 bebés entre los años 40 y principios de los 90.</p>
      <p sl="es">Auténticas tramas, en las que estaban implicados religiosas, médicos y funcionarios; en sus inicios, tramas cargadas de ideología, donde se robaba a los hijos de presas políticas y mujeres republicanas para dárselos a familias conservadoras. Estas tramas pronto se convirtieron en tramas puramente económicas, como atestigua Fernando Tena, un sociólogo y experto en este drama histórico.</p>
      <p sl="es">Se creían con la autoridad moral para decidir sustraer los bebés a madres sin recursos y dárselos a familias convencionales. Ahora, hace cerca de un año, se ha comenzado a ver la luz gracias al incansable trabajo de las asociaciones de niños robados, a las que quiero expresar mi máximo respeto y animar a que continúen su trabajo.</p>
      <p sl="es">Exijo al Gobierno de España que vele por que se haga justicia en cada uno de los casos y a la Unión Europea que continúe con sus esfuerzos en la lucha contra la trata y el tráfico de personas.</p>
      <p sl="es">Termino, señor Presidente, con una frase: el tiempo apremia. Hay muchos padres y madres que no van a tener la oportunidad de encontrar a sus hijos.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-106-000" speaker_id="96749" name="Andrew Henry William BRONS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="16-06-1947" birth_place="London" p_group="Non" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="es">Mr President, trying to rescue a country from debt by driving its population into austerity and unemployment is not so different in principle from the 19th century British policy of locking up the indebted in debtors’ prisons.</p>
      <p sl="es">However, borrowing yet more to increase aggregate demand is hardly going to reduce debt. Quantitative easing will increase aggregate demand without increasing debt but, if not matched by increased production, it does tend to be inflationary. We must work from the principle that what is physically possible must be financially possible. If we have infrastructure work that needs to be carried out, and building workers who are unemployed, the latter must be employed to carry out the former.</p>
      <p sl="es">Can inflation be avoided? Yes, if full payment for the work is delayed until the project is complete, is in use and has added to our stock of goods and services. Created money is not inflationary if it is matched, in quantity and in time, by an increase in goods and services.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-107-000" speaker_id="110984" name="Joseph CUSCHIERI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Malta" birth_date="20-02-1968" birth_place="Attard" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="MT">
      <p sl="es">Fl-ewwel ta’ Mejju madwar l-Ewropa ġie kkommemorat Jum il-Ħaddiem. Dan il-jum ifakkarna fil-kisbiet ekonomiċi u soċjali tal-ħaddiema. Minħabba l-kriżi ekonomika, dawn il-kisbiet ekonomiċi u soċjali qed jitnaqqru u jiġu attakkati minn gvernijiet bla ruħ soċjali li qed jimponu miżuri ta’ awsterità u ta’ dixxiplina fiskali mingħajr ma jagħtu każ il-problemi u d-diffikultajiet eżaġerati li qed joħolqu lill-ħaddiema u lill-familji. Il-kriżi ekonomika u finanzjarja saret kriżi soċjali. Hemm bżonn li aktar minn qatt qabel nisimgħu lill-ħaddiema u nagħtuhom vuċi. Il-ħaddiema Ewropej iridu t-tkattir tal-opportunitajiet tax-xogħol, żieda fl-investiment u azzjonijiet li jistimulaw ix-xogħol speċjalment għaż-żgħażagħ. Dan huwa d-dritt tagħhom. Ir-rata tal-qgħad fl-Ewropa hija l-ogħla waħda fl-aħħar ħmistax-il sena b’aktar minn 24 miljun persuna bla xogħol. Il-miżuri ta’ awsterità u ta’ dixxiplina finanzjarja mill-Kunsill Ewropew mhumiex is-soluzzjoni għal dan il-qgħad. U hu għalhekk li naqbel u nippromwovi l-proposta tal-Parlament Ewropew għall-garanzija Ewropea għaż-żgħażagħ li tiżgura d-dritt li kull żagħżugħ fl-Unjoni Ewropea jiġi offrut impjieg, apprendistat, taħriġ addizzjonali jew taħlita ta’ xogħol u taħriġ wara perjodu massimu ta’ erba’ xhur bla impjieg. Fil-kuntest politiku, soċjali u ekonomiku Ewropew li qed ngħixu fih illum, din il-garanzija tista' sseħħ billi tiġi ffinanzjata mill-Fond Soċjali Ewropew.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-108-000" speaker_id="113487" name="Alda SOUSA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="04-08-1953" birth_place="Porto" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="es">Senhor Presidente, em 17 de junho, o povo grego vai a votos: é o seu futuro, a sua vida que vão escolher. É desta liberdade que se constrói a Europa. São, portanto, inaceitáveis as declarações de Trichet na reunião do G8. Na prática, o antigo presidente do Banco Central Europeu propôs que um povo possa perder o direito ao voto, que um governo democraticamente eleito, mas que recusa austeridade, possa ser substituído por uma constelação de comissários de Bruxelas.</p>
      <p sl="es">É igualmente inaceitável a chantagem do Tratado Orçamental. Para nós, a Europa é democracia, é solidariedade entre os povos. Não é, nem pode ser, o empobrecimento forçado das populações. É, por isso, que pergunto a todos vós, deputados e deputadas, se estão dispostos a aceitar este regime colonial.</p>
      <p sl="es">Da parte dos cidadãos europeus, a resposta será certamente pela democracia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-109-000" speaker_id="96845" name="Corneliu VADIM TUDOR" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="28-11-1949" birth_place="Bucureşti" p_group="Non" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="es">Zi şi noapte pe planetă se întâmplă grozăvii care şochează. Câinii violenţei au fost dezlegaţi şi nu-i mai poate opri nimeni. Cele mai expuse victime sunt oamenii lipsiţi de apărare. Iată, de pildă, cazul unui tânăr român, Virgil Cristian Pop, în vârstă de 38 de ani. Aflat într-o închisoare din Lecce, Italia, el a fost ţinut şase luni la izolare, unde a fost bătut crunt, după care a intrat în greva foamei. Din păcate, nimeni nu l-a crezut, a fost total ignorat, iar bietul om după cincizeci de zile de grevă a murit.</p>
      <p sl="es">Aceeaşi lipsă de omenie o dovedesc şi forţele de represiune, care îi stâlcesc în bătaie pe demonstranţii ecologişti, sau antiglobalizare, sau împotriva înarmării, sau galeriile sportive. Aproape zilnic asistăm la scene scandaloase. Nişte batalioane de asalt formate din poliţişti şi jandarmi echipaţi ca nişte extratereştri calcă în picioare femei şi bărbaţi, tineri şi bătrâni, care nu au arme, ci cel mult câte o floare, iar aceste gorile şi dresorii lor politici numesc aceasta democraţie şi asigurarea ordinii publice. Însă de-a lungul istoriei popoarele au avut întotdeauna dreptate, nu slugile potentaţilor care acţionează ca nişte kapo sub hipnoză. Din păcate Hitler şi Stalin n-au murit, ci doar s-au reîncarnat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-110-000" speaker_id="97050" name="Antigoni PAPADOPOULOU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Cyprus" birth_date="08-07-1954" birth_place="Morfou" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="CY">
      <p sl="es">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, οι ελεύθερες και δημοκρατικές εκλογές στη Γαλλία, Φιλανδία, Ολλανδία και Ελλάδα έχουν καταδείξει την αυξημένη διαμαρτυρία των πολιτών ενάντια στην αυστηρή λιτότητα και τις αποτυχημένες συνταγές των διαρθρωτικών μεταρρυθμίσεων και της αυστηρής δημοσιονομικής πειθαρχίας που ακολουθήθηκαν μέχρι σήμερα σε ευρωπαϊκό επίπεδο. Ο νέος αέρας αλλαγής στη Γαλλία και αλλού αναζωογονεί την ελπίδα πως θα τερματιστούν επιτέλους οι νεοφιλελεύθερες πολιτικές και πως η Ευρώπη θα ξαναμπεί στη λογική της ανάπτυξης, της απασχόλησης και της πραγματικής κοινωνικής αλληλεγγύης. Εύχομαι η Ελλάδα να αποκτήσει σύντομα, στις 17 Ιουνίου, κυβέρνηση και να παραμείνει στο ευρώ, γιατί τυχόν αποχώρησή της θα έχει αρνητικές αλυσιδωτές επιπτώσεις στις χώρες του ευρωπαϊκού Nότου, στην ευρωζώνη και στη συστημική σταθερότητα του ευρωπαϊκού χρηματοπιστωτικού συστήματος. Οι ωμοί εκβιασμοί της κυρίας Μέρκελ και άλλων αξιωματούχων σε βάρος του ελληνικού λαού είναι επιεικώς απαράδεκτοι και αχρείαστοι.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-111-000" speaker_id="96706" name="João FERREIRA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Portugal" birth_date="20-11-1978" birth_place="Lisboa" m_state="PT">
      <p sl="es">Senhor Presidente, em Portugal, nas últimas semanas, consumou-se mais um retrocesso social e civilizacional. Com o patrocínio da União Europeia e do FMI e com a assinatura dos partidos nacionais que aceitam, defendem e implementam um autêntico pacto de agressão ao país e ao seu povo.</p>
      <p sl="es">As alterações à legislação laboral atingem conquistas históricas dos trabalhadores e desferem mais um rude golpe numa já fragilizada democracia. Facilitação dos despedimentos, redução das indemnizações, redução do pagamento suplementar e dos dias de descanso, redução dos dias de férias e supressão de feriados, ou seja, trabalho forçado e gratuito, tentativa de generalização de contratos precários e de desarticulação da contratação coletiva.</p>
      <p sl="es">Serão milhões de euros mais que por esta via serão extorquidos aos trabalhadores portugueses. Ao mesmo tempo que se promove a eliminação de mais postos de trabalho, que poderão superar os 90 mil, numa altura em que o desemprego atinge já níveis históricos.</p>
      <p sl="es">Não é tarde para romper com este caminho. É agora a hora de o fazer. Vão afirmá-lo uma vez mais os milhares de pessoas que voltarão a encher as ruas de Lisboa já no próximo sábado.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-112-000" speaker_id="23820" name="László SURJÁN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="07-09-1941" birth_place="Kolozsvár" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="es">A napirendi pont ezzel lezárul.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem17" title="17. Estrategia de Seguridad Interior de la Unión Europea (breve presentación)">
    <intervention id="1-114-000" speaker_id="23820" name="László SURJÁN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="07-09-1941" birth_place="Kolozsvár" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="es">A következő pont a Rita Borsellino által az Állampolgári Jogi, Bel- és Igazságügyi Bizottság nevében készített jelentés az Európai Unió belső biztonsági stratégiájáról (2010/2308(INI)) (A7-0143/2012)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-115-000" speaker_id="96916" name="Rita BORSELLINO" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Italy" birth_date="02-06-1945" birth_place="Palermo" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="es">relatrice . − Signora Commissario, signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, mi accingo a presentare la mia relazione d'iniziativa sulla sicurezza interna dell'Unione europea con una certa emozione. Ricorre infatti in questi giorni, e precisamente il 23 maggio, il ventennale dell'uccisione del giudice Falcone, di sua moglie e della sua scorta.</p>
      <p sl="es">Proprio a tutte le vittime delle mafie, della criminalità organizzata e del terrorismo desidero dedicare l'approvazione di questa relazione e in particolare a Melissa Bassi, la giovane vittima dell'attentato di sabato scorso in una scuola di Brindisi, dove sono state ferite anche altre sei ragazze. Il movente dell'atto è ancora ignoto ma è evidente che si innesta in un clima crescente di tensione e di insicurezza determinato dalla crisi, che organizzazioni o singoli possono essere tentati di sfruttare a fini di eversione violenta. Un pensiero va anche alle vittime del terremoto in Emilia Romagna, perché anche le calamità naturali sono oggetto della sicurezza interna dell'Unione.</p>
      <p sl="es">Il testo che domani voteremo sottolinea l'importanza di una strategia coerente dell'Unione in materia di sicurezza e per questo desidero ringraziare la Commissione europea per l'importante sforzo compiuto nella sua elaborazione.</p>
      <p sl="es">Come abbiamo a più riprese evidenziato nella relazione, la sicurezza deve essere sempre garantita nel pieno rispetto dello Stato di diritto e dei diritti fondamentali, che sono parte integrante e inscindibile di questa strategia. Anche per questa ragione assume particolare importanza il ruolo che le Istituzioni dell'Unione europea devono avere nella definizione e nell'attuazione della strategia, in particolare nel quadro post Lisbona.</p>
      <p sl="es">In questo quadro è necessario un ruolo appropriato del Parlamento europeo, sia in fase di elaborazione delle priorità della strategia che in fase di valutazione. Si tratta di un ruolo derivante dal potere di legislatore a pieno titolo che il Parlamento ha assunto in materia di sicurezza. Ma si tratta anche di un elemento essenziale per assicurare un adeguato controllo democratico che il Parlamento europeo deve avere insieme ai parlamenti nazionali. Proprio per questo ci impegneremo per istituire un rapporto regolare tra il Parlamento europeo e i parlamenti nazionali – un ciclo politico parlamentare legato alla relazione annuale della Commissione in questa materia e che termini proprio con una relazione parlamentare annuale sullo stato di attuazione della strategia di sicurezza interna.</p>
      <p sl="es">Pensiamo che sia necessario che l'Unione abbia chiara l'entità delle minacce alla sicurezza interna, cosa che oggi non è. Chiediamo quindi che Europol, con il sostegno delle Istituzioni e delle altre agenzie, possa svolgere un'analisi globale delle minacce da affrontare a livello di Unione, basandosi su una metodologia più solida e trasparente e sul contributo di informazione degli Stati membri.</p>
      <p sl="es">Con riferimento ai cinque obiettivi prioritari individuati dalla Commissione europea, sosteniamo che non si debba trattare di una lista esaustiva e che probabilmente l'ordine delle priorità avrebbe potuto essere meglio strutturato. La lotta contro il terrorismo, la criminalità organizzata e le mafie sono e devono rimanere per noi priorità chiave di una strategia di sicurezza interna. L'Unione deve però non solo saper reagire, ma anche prevenire e interpretare cosa si muove in Europa: ce lo hanno dimostrato i fatti di Utøya, ce lo dimostrano i fatti di Brindisi. Dobbiamo saper individuare in fase precoce i segnali di radicalizzazione violenta dell'imbarbarimento del clima sociale e dell'estremismo violento.</p>
      <p sl="es">La cooperazione giudiziaria è la grande assente della strategia di sicurezza delineata dalla Commissione e occorre colmare questa lacuna. L'azione congiunta delle magistrature è vitale in Europa per contrastare la criminalità e il terrorismo e potenziarla è una priorità, così come sono prioritarie anche la lotta alla corruzione e alla criminalità ambientale, economica e aziendale.</p>
      <p sl="es">Pur condividendo l'accento posto sulla lotta contro la criminalità informatica, non ci è però parsa giustificata la scelta della Commissione di inserire la tutela dei diritti di proprietà intellettuale fra le priorità della sicurezza. Come insegna il caso ACTA, si tratta di un tema non puramente securitario, molto complesso, che riguarda i diritti delle persone e che necessita di un dibattito più approfondito.</p>
      <p sl="es">Concludo ringraziando tutti i relatori ombra che hanno contribuito alla stesura di questa relazione, oltre ai funzionari dei gruppi politici e la mia assistente personale.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-117-000" speaker_id="96654" name="Jaroslav PAŠKA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="20-06-1954" birth_place="Banská Štiavnica" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group - Vice" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="es">Vnútorná bezpečnosť Európskej únie je atakovaná mnohými hrozbami, ktoré sa vďaka našej politike otvorených hraníc rýchlo šíria po celej Európe. Asi najväčším aktuálnym problémom vnútornej bezpečnosti Únie je stále sofistikovanejšia organizovaná trestná činnosť. Masívny prílev ekonomických emigrantov z chudobných krajín Ázie či Afriky, ale aj veľké rozdiely v životnej úrovni niektorých regiónov Únie generujú využiteľný potenciál pre organizovanie nelegálneho trhu s čiernou prácou, prostitúciou či rozsiahlymi podvodmi na sociálnych systémoch bohatších krajín. Nemôžeme teda prehliadať previazanosť vnútornej bezpečnosti s politickými a bezpečnostnými turbulenciami v našom okolí, a preto by sme mali sa usilovať o komplexnú bezpečnostnú politiku Európskej únie a mali by sme formulovať tento systém tak, aby v ňom boli obsiahnuté zjavné súvislosti medzi zahraničnými impulzmi a vnútornými dôsledkami pre bezpečnosť Európskej únie. Myslím, že taký komplexný prístup je základnou podmienkou pre úspešnú bezpečnostnú politiku vo vnútri Európskej únie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-118-000" speaker_id="96814" name="Elena BĂSESCU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="24-04-1980" birth_place="Constanţa" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="es">Crearea unui spaţiu de libertate, de securitate şi de justiţie se numără printre obiectivele principale ale Uniunii. Pentru realizarea sa este nevoie de măsuri concrete, care să asigure un grad sporit de siguranţă individuală pentru fiecare cetăţean. Comunicarea Comisiei reprezintă un prim pas în acest scop prin identificarea celor cinci domenii-cheie şi prin acţiunile specifice pe care le propune, însă este nevoie de eforturi suplimentare pentru combaterea crimei organizate şi a infracţionalităţii în general. De multe ori, în spatele unor infracţiuni minore în aparenţă, cum ar fi furtul din buzunare sau din maşini, de care sunt afectaţi atâţia cetăţeni, se poate afla o reţea criminală internaţională. În acest context, susţin implicarea mai mare a Europol în analiza şi gestionarea principalelor riscuri de securitate internă conform articolului 6.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-120-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Cecilia Malmström" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="es">Member of the Commission . − Mr President, I would like to join Mrs Borsellino in fiercely condemning this weekend’s atrocities in Brindisi. This is something that we can never defend. Whatever the causes behind this, the great symbolism that it was the school named after Mrs Falcone is of course something that we must reflect upon. The girl came from a village that I visited only two weeks ago, to learn how the community works against the Mafia and works to confiscate the goods of organised crime. This is a barbaric act that we must all condemn.</p>
      <p sl="es">Let me also thank you for your report. I think you have done excellent work. I would also like to thank the shadow rapporteurs. It really contributes to the development of the Internal Security Strategy. We fully share your view that the Internal Security Strategy should be a shared agenda for all the institutions and the agencies, with clear roles and responsibilities and a common goal. The security of citizens is at the heart of all our efforts.</p>
      <p sl="es">The Internal Security Strategy provides the best platform to respond to security threats, encompassing both policy-setting and operational cooperation, which is now taking shape in a cycle on serious and organised crime. In this context, we very much welcome the idea of the ‘parliamentary policy cycle’, involving the European Parliament, as well as national parliaments, in a joint debate on the state of play with regular reports from the Commission. The Commission is currently working on the second implementation report of the Internal Security Strategy, which will be published by the end of the year.</p>
      <p sl="es">Implementing the Internal Security Strategy is about keeping promises on the five objectives. There is no ranking between those objectives, which are fighting and preventing serious and organised crime, terrorism and cybercrime, management of our external borders, and building resilience to natural and man-made disasters.</p>
      <p sl="es">We have achieved quite a lot since the first publication: for instance the report on confiscation of goods, the establishment of the radicalisation awareness network, the proposal on EU PNR, and the proposal to establish a cyber centre. We are also preparing, for the end of this year, reforms of Cepol, Europol and Eurojust, which would – as you call for – improve the cooperation between police agencies, but also on a national level. We will also present proposals on improving our protection against critical infrastructure and by the end of the year we will hold a conference gathering our experience and building on one year of the establishment of the radicalisation awareness network, with some ideas and policies presented from that network.</p>
      <p sl="es">This second report will assess the state of play of the previously promised actions, including the policy cycle, but we are also looking at the opportunities that security can offer in responding to the economic and financial crisis, because of course this is also key in establishing an environment where people, investors and companies feel safe and secure.</p>
      <p sl="es">I believe that Mrs Borsellino’s report is a very valuable milestone in Parliament’s involvement in the Internal Security Strategy and I look forward to working with you on this matter.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-121-000" speaker_id="23820" name="László SURJÁN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="07-09-1941" birth_place="Kolozsvár" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="es">A vitát lezárom.</p>
      <p sl="es">A szavazásra 2012. május 22-én, kedden kerül sor.</p>
      <p sl="es">Írásbeli nyilatkozatok (149. cikk)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-122-000" speaker_id="96707" name="Ágnes HANKISS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="07-03-1950" birth_place="Budapest" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="es">írásban. – Mint a belbiztonsági stratégia árnyék-jelentéstevője köszönetet kell mondanom Borsellino asszonynak azért a nyitottságért és rugalmasságért, amellyel a néppárti felvetéseket fogadta. Sikeres kompromisszumaink bizonyítják, hogy ha szakmai alapon, előítéletek nélkül foglalkozunk a belbiztonság problémáival és kihívásaival, akkor képesek vagyunk közös nevezőt találni, és a politikai ellentétek fölé emelkedni.</p>
      <p sl="es">A belbiztonsági stratégia fontos eszköz a bűncselekmények számos formája elleni hatékony fellépéshez. Fókuszában áll a nemzetközi szervezett bűnözés különböző formái elleni küzdelem, úgymint a maffia-típusú vagy a „fehérgalléros” bűnözés és pénzmosás elleni küzdelem, valamint az európai terrorelhárítás megerősítése.</p>
      <p sl="es">Elengedhetetlen a közös fenyegetettségértékelési rendszer kidolgozása, valamint a kritikus informatikai infrastruktúrák hatékony védelméhez szükséges tagállami gyakorlatok jobb összehangolása. Az EU kiberbiztonságának szavatolásához nélkülözhetetlen az unión belüli állami és magánszektor, valamint a polgári és katonai szereplők közötti együttműködés. Ezt a célt szolgálja a megalakuló kibervédelmi központ is. Sürgető feladat az európai kritikus infrastruktúrák meghatározásának befejezése. A külső határok védelme, nem utolsósorban a természeti és ember okozta katasztrófák megelőzése és elhárítása is közös fellépést igényel.</p>
      <p sl="es">Az említett célok eléréséhez megkerülhetetlen, hogy arányos költségvetési forrásokat rendeljünk hozzájuk, törekedni kell arra, hogy a 2014–2020-as költségvetésben megfelelően szerepeljenek a belbiztonsági stratégiában foglalt intézkedések.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-123-000" speaker_id="96823" name="Petru Constantin LUHAN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="19-03-1977" birth_place="Jud. Suceava" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="es">în scris. – În prezent, securitatea internetului reprezintă una din cele mai importante priorităţi politice pentru Uniunea Europeană. În mod evident, internetul este o infrastructură critică, iar perturbarea sa ar putea duce la pierderi substanţiale şi riscuri privind siguranţa cetăţenilor.</p>
      <p sl="es">Tocmai de aceea consider că Directiva 2008/114 ar trebui să îşi extindă domeniul de aplicare, prin includerea tehnologiilor informaţiilor şi comunicaţiilor şi recunoaşterea lor ca sector critic. Consider ca fiind urgentă crearea, la nivel european, a reţelei de alertă privind infrastructurile critice şi includerea în sistemul de avertizare a serviciilor financiare, a sistemelor de sănătate, alimentaţie şi furnizare a apei, cercetarea nucleară şi industrie.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem18" title="18. Enfoque de la UE acerca del Derecho penal (breve presentación)">
    <intervention id="1-125-000" speaker_id="23820" name="László SURJÁN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="07-09-1941" birth_place="Kolozsvár" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="es">A következő pont a Cornelis de Jong által az Állampolgári Jogi, Bel- és Igazságügyi Bizottság nevében készített jelentés a büntetőjog uniós megközelítéséről (2010/2310 (INI)) (A7-0144/2012)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-126-000" speaker_id="96748" name="Dennis de JONG" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Netherlands" birth_date="22-05-1955" p_group="Confederal Group of the European United Left - Nordic Green Left" m_state="NL">
      <p sl="es">Rapporteur . − Voorzitter, strafrecht is niet zomaar een onderwerp. Straffen betekenen inperking van de fundamentele rechten van de verdachten en veroordeelden. Daar moet je voorzichtig mee omgaan. Natuurlijk is het gerechtvaardigd om onder bepaalde omstandigheden fundamentele rechten in te perken, maar daar moeten wel goede gronden voor zijn, zoals vastgelegd in de internationale mensenrechteninstrumenten en het Handvest van de grondrechten.</p>
      <p sl="es">Grosso modo zijn er twee bedreigingen. In de eerste plaats zijn wij dat zelf, de politici. De media besteden, meer dan vroeger, uitgebreid aandacht aan sprekende misdrijven. Advocaten staan soms nog vaker voor de camera dan politici, en ook het Openbaar Ministerie en de rechterlijke macht bedienen zich tegenwoordig van een leger aan voorlichters. Politici willen hier nog wel eens op inhaken door nieuwe wetten af te kondigen met ofwel een uitgebreidere of nieuwe delictsomschrijving, of een hogere strafmaat. Als ze er dan ook nog eens in slagen om hun Europese collega's ervan te overtuigen dat die wetgeving in heel Europa moet worden ingevoerd, hebben ze in hun ogen succesvol gereageerd. Maar zo moet het dus niet.</p>
      <p sl="es">Strafrecht is niet bedoeld om op korte termijn succesjes te boeken. Voordat je nieuwe delictsomschrijvingen overeenkomt of straffen verhoogt, moet je goed hebben nagedacht over de consequenties. Worden hier inderdaad meer misdadigers door opgepakt en geresocialiseerd, en is de publieke opinie op langere termijn nog steeds geïnteresseerd in die strengere straffen, of ging het hier om een incidentele schok in de samenleving, die ook door betere handhaving van het bestaande recht zou kunnen worden opgevangen?</p>
      <p sl="es">De tweede bedreiging komt helaas uit Brussel. We zijn hier gewend om ruim gebruik te maken van de bevoegdheden die via de reeks van Verdragen aan de EU zijn gegeven. Het Verdrag noemt een aantal delicten waar een minimumharmonisatie voor de hand ligt. Daarnaast mag de EU ook minimumharmonisatie bedrijven van delicten als dat voor de uitvoering van al geharmoniseerd EU-beleid noodzakelijk is. Dit geeft eigenlijk ontzettend veel ruimte, en ik kan me bij ieder delict wel een reden voorstellen om dat dan ook maar Europees te gaan regelen.</p>
      <p sl="es">Hetzelfde Verdrag toont echter ook respect voor nationale tradities en culturele verschillen, die juist in het strafrecht naar voren komen. De noodremprocedure, waarin speciaal door het strafrecht is voorzien en waarbij een lidstaat zich kan verzetten tegen harmonisatie als die in strijd zou zijn met de fundamentele beginselen uit hun grondwet, is hiervan de procedurele weerslag.</p>
      <p sl="es">Tussen beide onderdelen, de ruime bevoegdheden en de terughoudendheid en het respect voor nationale tradities, zit een spanning. Daarom mogen we op het gebied van het strafrecht niet dezelfde weg bewandelen als op andere terreinen: stukje bij beetje, hier en daar ongecoördineerd harmoniseren, zonder dat daar heel duidelijke overtuigende redenen voor aan te wijzen zijn.</p>
      <p sl="es">In mijn verslag wordt nu duidelijk gemaakt dat men op het gebied van strafrecht niet aan symboolpolitiek mag doen, geen politieke hypes dus. Voordat je tot harmonisatie overgaat, moet er eerst een toetsingskader zijn doorlopen dat de meerwaarde van harmonisatie via statistisch materiaal bewijst en bovendien duidelijk maakt dat er buiten het strafrecht geen andere, minder indringende oplossingen voorhanden zijn. En daarnaast blijven de mensenrechten bepalend. Ook hieraan zal steeds uitdrukkelijk moeten worden getoetst.</p>
      <p sl="es">Even belangrijk is de bewaking van consistentie en coherentie. Daarvoor zullen alle EU-instellingen speciale maatregelen moeten nemen, inclusief het Europees Parlement. De Commissie LIBE heeft geen recht van coördinatie, maar verbrokkeld strafrecht is een slecht strafrecht.</p>
      <p sl="es">Ik dank alle collega's uit de Commissie LIBE voor hun overweldigende steun voor dit verslag. In een interinstitutionele werkgroep zullen we deze regels hopelijk samen met de Commissie en de Raad verder moeten uitrollen. Ik heb er vertrouwen in dat we er met elkaar in zullen slagen dat toekomstige regels over strafrecht alleen worden ingevoerd als het echt moet en dat deze verder van hoge kwaliteit zullen zijn.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-128-000" speaker_id="96761" name="Axel VOSS" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="07-04-1963" birth_place="Hameln" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="es">Frau Präsidentin! Zunächst möchte ich dem Kollegen Cornelis de Jong recht herzlich danken für sein Engagement, das er hier an den Tag gelegt hat. Er hat das sehr gut und sehr ausgewogen gemacht, und ich finde es super, dass wir uns in kleinen Schritten den inhaltlichen Dingen genähert haben. Insofern muss ich ihm recht geben, und es ist schön zu sehen, dass eigentlich in jedem Mitgliedstaat das Strafrecht unterschiedlich gewachsen ist und wir deshalb eben auch unterschiedliche Annäherungen brauchen, und es ist nun einmal das stärkste Argument, was wir hier haben, um dem einen oder anderen bestimmte Grundrechte zu beschneiden, und deshalb sollten wir da auch sehr vorsichtig herangehen – in Verfahrensfragen, aber auch im materiellen Strafrecht.</p>
      <p sl="es">Deshalb, meine ich, lohnt es auch, einmal darüber nachzudenken, ob man nicht in diesem Sinne auch ein Konzept entwickelt, damit wir nicht zuerst mit der Europäischen Ermittlungsanordnung starten und uns erst dann mit den Grundsätzen auseinandersetzen, sondern es eigentlich anders herum starten sollte. Von daher möchte ich doch bitten, dass wir konzeptioneller an so etwas herangehen und nicht das Letzte zuerst machen und das Erste eigentlich erst zum Schluss.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-129-000" speaker_id="96736" name="Jan Philipp ALBRECHT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Germany" birth_date="20-12-1982" birth_place="Braunschweig" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="DE">
      <p sl="es">Frau Präsidentin! Sehr geehrte Frau Malmström! Ich möchte in das gleiche Horn blasen wie Herr Voss. Ich glaube, es ist wirklich dringend notwendig, dass wir – das wird auch aus dem guten Bericht von Herrn de Jong deutlich – endlich eine koordinierte Strategie brauchen, wie wir das Strafrecht so ausgestalten und harmonisieren, dass es eben nicht nur immer in den Bereichen vorangeht, in denen es kurzfristig Interessen gibt, sondern dass man sich auch langfristig damit auseinandersetzt, ein kohärentes Strafrechtssystem zu haben.</p>
      <p sl="es">Vielleicht wäre es wirklich eine gute Idee, wenn Sie sich auch mit Ihrer Kollegin aus dem Justizressort gemeinsam Gedanken machen, wie man das gemeinsam voranbringen kann, denn gerade gegenüber dem Rat haben wir immer wieder Schwierigkeiten, diesen Verbund beider Perspektiven deutlich zu machen. Wir werden mit der Ermittlungsanordnung, mit den Mindeststandards im Strafverfahren erleben, dass natürlich auch immer wieder Schwierigkeiten auftreten, die Perspektiven von Parlament und Rat zusammenzubringen. Da könnte die Kommission sicherlich eine wichtige und vermittelnde Rolle spielen. Darum würde ich Sie bitten.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-130-000" speaker_id="28497" name="Gerard BATTEN" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="United Kingdom" birth_date="27-03-1954" birth_place="London" p_group="Europe of Freedom and Direct Democracy Group" m_state="GB">
      <p sl="es">Madam President, this report confirms what I have been warning my constituents in London about, and the British people generally, for some years, which is that the EU intends to create its own system of criminal law.</p>
      <p sl="es">This project is already very well advanced and very comprehensive and I have written about it in a report of my own, Freedom, Security &amp; Justice? or The Creation of a European Union Police State .</p>
      <p sl="es">We do not need an EU system of criminal law in England. We have something called the common law which has taken a thousand years to evolve. We have safeguards under Magna Carta, the Bill of Rights and habeas corpus, which are being swept away under this new system. They are being set aside. A British citizen can now be sent off to any corner of the European Union on the strength of a piece of paper with vague accusations. They can be imprisoned for months or years. The English and Scottish courts have abdicated their duty to protect their own citizens from arbitrary arrest and imprisonment.</p>
      <p sl="es">Your system of EU criminal law would do for our liberties what the European single currency has done for your economies.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-131-000" speaker_id="2307" name="Hubert PIRKER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Austria" birth_date="03-10-1948" birth_place="Gries" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="es">Frau Präsidentin! Wir befassen uns heute damit, wie Sicherheit in der Europäischen Union auf Dauer gewährleistet werden kann. Das war im letzten Bericht so, und das ist eigentlich hier indirekt auch die Zielsetzung. Wir können uns alle Strategien von Frau Kommissarin Cecilia Malmström wünschen – wenn es nicht gelingt, diese Strategien umzusetzen und gleich dazu parallel auch das Strafrecht europaweit umzusetzen, dann ist jede Initiative und all diese Strategie zahnlos.</p>
      <p sl="es">Daher bin ich dafür, dass wir alles unternehmen, damit eben auch das Strafrecht europaweit harmonisiert wird – freilich mit Rücksichtnahme auf nationale Traditionen, aber nichtsdestoweniger muss es die Zielsetzung sein, mithilfe eines harmonisierten Strafrechts das umzusetzen, was wir im Sicherheitsbereich an Initiativen, an Vorleistungen in diesem Bereich vom Grenzschutz über die Bekämpfung des organisierten Verbrechens bis hin zu Cybercrime entwickelt haben.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-132-000" speaker_id="96654" name="Jaroslav PAŠKA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="20-06-1954" birth_place="Banská Štiavnica" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group - Vice" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="es">Súhlasím s tým, že v Lisabonskej a Maastrichtskej zmluve boli zadefinované isté predpoklady na to, aby sme mohli pristúpiť k tvorbe spoločného európskeho trestného práva. Chcel by som však upozorniť na to, že táto cesta bude veľmi zložitá, komplikovaná a veľmi citlivá. V Európe máme viacero tradícií, či už spoločenských, ale i justičných, na ktorých bolo právo v jednotlivých krajinách alebo regiónoch budované. Zaznela tu už výhrada od môjho kolegu z Veľkej Británie, ktorý upozornil na to, že britské ostrovné právo má iný spôsob riešenia problémov, že tam platia pravidlá precedensov, zatiaľ čo v európskej kontinentálnej časti platia zase iné pravidlá. Moja krajina napríklad využíva rakúsko-uhorský právny základ. Som presvedčený, že Švédsko alebo severské krajiny používajú úplne iné pravidlá. Takže z toho vyplývajú isté rozdiely v právnych systémoch, ktoré budeme musieť veľmi citlivo zvažovať. A ja osobne som veľmi skeptický, že sa nám to podarí v dohľadnom čase.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-134-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Cecilia Malmström" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="es">Member of the Commission . − Madam President, I would like to thank the rapporteur very much for having taken the initiative to prepare a report on this issue. It links in perfectly with the communication on EU criminal policy that the Commission published last September, and I am really glad to see that this communication has achieved its goal in launching a debate inside and outside the institutions. This was our aim in the Commission: to summarise for the first time the principles guiding legislation on criminal law so as to strengthen the enforcement of EU policies under the new legal framework of the Lisbon Treaty. Mr de Jong’s report very much follows that objective, and I am really grateful for that.</p>
      <p sl="es">Clear and transparent rules on when to use European criminal law are crucial, and we fully share the view of the rapporteur that any legislation at EU level must fully respect the principles of subsidiarity and proportionality. We know – and it has been clear from the debate here – that criminal law is a sensitive area, with quite substantial differences between the different Member States. This has to be taken into account. Because of that, it is crucial that we ensure full respect of the rights guaranteed by the Charter of Fundamental Rights and the European Convention on Human Rights for all EU criminal law legislation. We need to understand each other’s systems better in order to be able to assess how we can bring them closer together where this is necessary, while respecting the different legal systems and traditions in all Member States.</p>
      <p sl="es">EU criminal law to strengthen the enforcement of EU policies is only needed in selected areas, but it can provide significant added value. We have seen this for example in the context of environmental crime, where two important directives were adopted in 2008 and 2009. These were the first instruments adopted on criminal law in the ordinary legislative proposal. The fruitful cooperation between the Commission and Parliament on these files has set an example for future work.</p>
      <p sl="es">We also see the importance of common EU rules when it comes to discussing proposals for criminal law measures to fight insider dealing and market manipulation. It is clear that the EU financial markets can only have investors’ confidence and trust if we send a strong signal in the form of common rules.</p>
      <p sl="es">In addition to rendering EU policies effective through the introduction of criminal law measures, the Treaty establishes ten ‘euro crimes’ that are both serious and have a cross-border dimension, justifying the need to legislate common minimum rules on definitions of offences and sanctions. Much has been achieved in relation to the latter in the post-Lisbon period, specifically with the adoption of directives on the fight against trafficking in human beings as well as the fight against sexual exploitation of children. Negotiations are being finalised regarding the Cybercrime Directive, and the newly-adopted proposal on the harmonisation of confiscation laws is about to be negotiated.</p>
      <p sl="es">All these initiatives have so far contributed to the development of Treaty provisions contributing, inter alia, to a pragmatic interpretation of the concept of common minimum rules in both areas, and they are important frames of reference for further development of criminal law at EU level.</p>
      <p sl="es">Putting in place a coherent EU criminal policy requires further reflection and discussion on many legal issues. The European Commission has just set up an expert group which will meet for the first time in June, and we will be happy to report once they have met. It will be composed of experienced academics and practitioners in the field. This expert group will be a forum to discuss the challenging and difficult questions which arise when the EU considers criminal law measures and advises on the best way forward.</p>
      <p sl="es">We fully share the approach set out in the resolution. For instance, our criminal law communication also supports the idea of simpler language to guide EU legislators when they draft criminal law provisions.</p>
      <p sl="es">So the Commission’s communication last year, and this report – which has received considerable support here – are the starting point for the shaping of a common EU criminal policy, and I look forward to working with Parliament and moving further towards a common goal: a true area of freedom, security and justice.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-135-000" speaker_id="96639" name="Isabelle DURANT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Belgium" birth_date="04-09-1954" birth_place="Bruxelles" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="BE">
      <p sl="es">Le point est clos.</p>
      <p sl="es">Le vote aura lieu mardi 22 mai 2012.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem19" title="19. Perspectivas para las mujeres en Turquía de cara a 2020 (breve presentación)">
    <intervention id="1-137-000" speaker_id="96639" name="Isabelle DURANT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Belgium" birth_date="04-09-1954" birth_place="Bruxelles" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="BE">
      <p sl="es">L'ordre du jour appelle le rapport d'Emine Bozkurt sur les femmes en Turquie à l'horizon 2020 [2011/2066(INI) ] (A7-0138/2012).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-138-000" speaker_id="28171" name="Emine BOZKURT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Netherlands" birth_date="09-08-1967" birth_place="Zaandam" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="NL">
      <p sl="es">rapporteur . − Madam President, it is a great pleasure to be presenting to you today my third report on the situation of women in Turkey, which presents a strategy towards 2020 and is inspired by the gender aspect of Europe 2020. In preparing my report I spoke to various Ministers, Members of Parliament, women’s NGOs and many others, such as young university students. Of all these meetings, the one that affected me the most was the meeting I had with Arzu, a woman who was staying in the shelter. Her story has helped me in evaluating the law on the protection of women from violence. I will come back to that.</p>
      <p sl="es">In my report I have made a call for zero tolerance for violence against women. The report indicates what needs to be done about violence and stresses that, without good implementation, even the best laws cannot protect women, so I put forward suggestions to ensure that the law is strictly applied. More shelters are needed. The existing shelters should be made safer, and the personnel must be better trained. There should be vocational courses offered to women in the shelters. This is important, because many of the women who have been victims of violence are housewives or, like Arzu, have lost their jobs because their ex-husbands also attacked them at their places of work. Arzu was continually beaten up by her husband even after obtaining a divorce. The law which was in effect at that time did not protect victims who were not married. It must be made clear to Turkey that the law protects women, regardless of the relationship between the victim and the perpetrator.</p>
      <p sl="es">Many positive developments are also taking place in Turkey. The Ankara Prosecutor’s Office has established a specialised bureau dealing solely with violence against women, which is very successful. We need more of these in Turkish cities and rural areas.</p>
      <p sl="es">The gender gap in primary education has been closed, but there are worries concerning the new education reform. The new system should not jeopardise the successes achieved so far concerning the schooling of girls. The percentage of women in the labour market has risen to around 30%, but more needs to be done on issues such as childcare and maternity leave to further increase this ratio. Trade union activities should also be made more accessible for women.</p>
      <p sl="es">In my report I ask for a new law on political parties and elections which would establish a temporary mandatory quota system ensuring the fair representation of women in electoral lists. In order to successfully make the necessary changes, a change in mentality is needed. Women are not only mothers or members of a family, they are individuals. This must be made crystal clear.</p>
      <p sl="es">The Commission is actively engaged in improving women’s rights in Turkey. Last week, during the launch of the positive agenda, Commissioner Füle once more highlighted the importance of women’s rights within the positive agenda, as well as the importance of Chapter 23 negotiations on this subject. Indeed, in order to give the EU more leverage in the area of women’s rights, Chapter 23 negotiations should be opened. I want strongly to underline the importance of the Commission and Turkey continuing to promote of women’s rights in Turkey and to place women’s rights at the heart of the accession negotiations.</p>
      <p sl="es">Finally, I would like to thank everyone, especially the shadow rapporteurs, who have contributed to the drafting of this report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-140-000" speaker_id="96814" name="Elena BĂSESCU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="24-04-1980" birth_place="Constanţa" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="es">Măsurile luate până în prezent de autorităţile turce demonstrează angajamentul lor pentru apărarea şi promovarea drepturilor femeilor, însă este nevoie de eforturi suplimentare pentru implementarea legislaţiei adoptate, mai ales în domenii precum violenţa domestică. Crearea unui serviciu specializat în cadrul biroului Procurorului general reprezintă un pas înainte în acest scop.</p>
      <p sl="es">În acelaşi timp trebuie să se acorde atenţie măsurilor de informare şi prevenire. În acest context, salut crearea Comisiei speciale pentru egalitate de gen în cadrul Ministerului educaţiei. Ea dovedeşte conştientizarea de către guvernul turc a nevoii de a combate stereotipurile şi de a produce o schimbare durabilă de mentalitate. Nu în ultimul rând, mă bucur că a crescut numărul de femei în parlamentul turc, dar nu susţin recomandările din raport privind instituirea unui sistem de cote.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-141-000" speaker_id="97050" name="Antigoni PAPADOPOULOU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Cyprus" birth_date="08-07-1954" birth_place="Morfou" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="CY">
      <p sl="es">Madam President, Turkey, as a candidate country, is obliged to abide by the acquis communautaire. It must respect human rights, including women’s rights and gender equality. It must implement legislative reforms and empower women in social, economic and political life so as to reach the objectives of Europe 2020.</p>
      <p sl="es">Turkey still has a long way to go. According to progress reports on Turkey for 2010 and 2011, Turkey needs to implement the existing legal framework in order to fight honour killings, forced marriages and violence against women, and to combat female illiteracy, discrimination, stereotypes and the very low female participation rate in the Turkish labour force and in political life.</p>
      <p sl="es">We therefore call on Turkey to implement comprehensive reforms, to fulfil the Copenhagen criteria for the sake of its own modernisation and to establish a climate of mutual understanding and respect with all EU Member States, thus making it possible to exchange best practices on gender equality with all of those States for the benefit of its own female citizens.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-142-000" speaker_id="97017" name="Ulrike LUNACEK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Austria" birth_date="26-05-1957" birth_place="Krems a.d. Donau" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="es">Madam President, first of all, on behalf of our Green shadow rapporteur Marije Cornelissen who cannot be here and who asked me to speak, let me thank the rapporteur and the other shadows in the Committee on Women’s Rights and Gender Equality for a very good report, which I think will be helpful to you, Mrs Malmström, and others in the Commission in promoting women’s rights in Turkey, more than has been done up till now.</p>
      <p sl="es">Legislation in Turkey is rather good at several levels, but implementation is lacking, especially when it comes to domestic violence against women. For example, it is still a fact that two or three women are killed every day in Turkey in the domestic area by their husbands or families. More has to be done there, in order to punish the person who was the perpetrator, but also family members who silently look on and do not speak out.</p>
      <p sl="es">One fact that also hinders women’s empowerment in Turkey is the low employment rate of women: only 24% of women are employed. That has been a fact for a number of years, so that is an area where more investment is needed. I find it very important to have a national action plan to combat violence against women. Other countries, for example Spain, have shown over the last few years what can be done; that is something that I hope can be achieved. Education for women is important. It has improved but not yet enough. I also think it would be important to open Chapter 23.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-143-000" speaker_id="96654" name="Jaroslav PAŠKA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="20-06-1954" birth_place="Banská Štiavnica" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group - Vice" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="es">Veľmi oceňujem túto správu, pretože problematika, ktorá je tu riešená, je naozaj veľmi závažná. Najmä preto, že Turecko sa uchádza o vstup do Európskej únie a z tohto dôvodu by sme mali veľmi pozorne sledovať, aké sú práva a postavenie žien v tejto krajine. Správa je veľmi prehľadná a veľmi stručná a konštatuje, že právne predpisy sú viac-menej v poriadku, ale aplikácia do reálneho života je problematická. Najmä tá pasáž, kde sa hovorí o tom, že manželia, priatelia a rodinní príslušníci denne zavraždia najmenej dve ženy, je, povedal by som, šokujúca. Takisto aplikácia právnych predpisov v oblasti vzdelania alebo účasti žien v zamestnaní alebo politike je veľmi výpovedná. Hovorí o tom, že naozaj účasť žien na takomto živote – reálnom, hospodárskom – je veľmi slabá. Chcel by som sa zamerať na opatrenia, ktoré by sme mali presadzovať ako Európska únia a možno aj ako spoločenské organizácie. Predovšetkým by sme mali apelovať na politikov, aby boli osobnými príkladmi a správali sa podľa toho, ako sa od nich žiada. Potom, aby sme využívali médiá, televíziu, rozhlas na to, aby viacej presadzovali práva žien a chránili ženy. A samozrejme, ten apel na spoločenské povedomie by sa mal premietať aj v tej politike, ktorá sa vykonáva v regiónoch, a to je, myslím si, najdôležitejšie – dostať túto politiku k ľuďom, do regiónov.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-144-000" speaker_id="28178" name="Miroslav MIKOLÁŠIK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="11-09-1952" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="es">Turecko zlepšilo svoj legislatívny rámec pre práva žien, avšak prenášanie legislatívy do každodennej praxe nie je na uspokojivej úrovni. Násilie voči ženám preto zostáva jedným z najpálčivejších problémov v Turecku. Za šokujúce považujem štatistiky, že až 39 % žien sa počas svojho života stretlo s fyzickým násilím, pričom dve až tri ženy denne padnú za obeť svojim manželom, iným rodinným príslušníkom alebo priateľom. Miera zamestnanosti žien predstavujúca približne 24 % úzko súvisí s pretrvávajúcimi rozdielmi medzi mužmi a ženami v stredoškolskom a vysokoškolskom vzdelávaní. 14-percentný podiel poslankýň v tureckom parlamente taktiež možno považovať za odraz spoločenskej reality. Vítam správu o súčasnej situácii a perspektíve žien v Turecku, ktorá systematicky zhodnotila právny stav a realitu poznačenú násilím páchaným na ženách, ale aj skutočnú účasť žien na trhu práce alebo v politike.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-146-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Cecilia Malmström" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="es">Member of the Commission . − Madam President, I would like to thank the rapporteur, Ms Bozkurt, for this report. It is really good and well balanced. As is rightly emphasised, the issue of women’s rights is a major challenge on Turkey’s road to the European Union and it certainly merits a special report. The unanimous voting in the committee shows the strong support received from shadow rapporteurs and others, so thank you very much, Ms Bozkurt, for your work.</p>
      <p sl="es">As you mentioned, Commissioner Füle was in Turkey last week and he discussed women’s rights with a range of civil society representatives. Protecting women’s rights in Turkey, promoting gender equality and combating violence against women remain major challenges. The legal framework guaranteeing women’s rights and gender equality is broadly in place and has been further reinforced by the recent law to protect women and family members from violence, and the Commission agrees that this is an important step forward. But, as all of you have underlined, the legal framework is not enough: it needs to translate into political, social and economic reality for women everywhere in Turkey.</p>
      <p sl="es">Legislation needs to be implemented consistently across the country. Further training and awareness-raising on women’s rights and gender equality are needed, particularly for the police. Of course, as was also underlined in the report, serious problems remain with so-called ‘honour’ killings (which is a horrible term because there is nothing honourable in such brutality), as well as early enforced marriages and domestic violence against women.</p>
      <p sl="es">The report calls upon us in the Commission to make the issue of women’s rights central to the negotiations with Turkey, and it mentions in this respect progress on the negotiation chapter devoted to the judiciary and fundamental rights. As you know, the positive agenda in EU-Turkey relations, which was endorsed by the Council in December, includes the judiciary and fundamental rights among its main features. During his visit to Turkey, Commissioner Füle launched concrete work on this positive agenda. I am happy to report that he chaired the first meeting of the working group on judiciary and fundamental rights with Justice Minister Ergin, with the aim of fostering reforms in Turkey in this crucial area. He also had a separate meeting with the Minister on the same day to underline these issues.</p>
      <p sl="es">Commissioner Füle told the Minister that steps need to be taken to implement the new law on violence against women and to improve the real-life situation of women in Turkey as regards political representation and access to education and employment. While we need to combat violence against women as a matter of urgency, we also need to keep a focus on all the other aspects – and that is precisely what this resolution does.</p>
      <p sl="es">Madam President, honourable Members, we share the same concerns about women in Turkey. The issues mentioned here in the debate are indeed grave; some of the stories are compelling; and there is a lot to be done. Reforms need to be further accelerated.</p>
      <p sl="es">As I said, Commissioner Füle met civil society representatives and they assured him that they see the European Union as a vital source of support for their cause. We have legislation guaranteeing equality; we have standards protecting women against violence; and that is why the accession process is so important with regard to reforms on vital issues such as women’s rights, and the implementation of those reforms.</p>
      <p sl="es">We must continue to encourage the progress of reform. Our leverage and influence in Turkey will be all the more credible and all the stronger if our commitments – as outlined in 2005 when we launched the accession negotiations – remain unambiguous.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-147-000" speaker_id="96639" name="Isabelle DURANT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Belgium" birth_date="04-09-1954" birth_place="Bruxelles" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="BE">
      <p sl="es">Le point est clos.</p>
      <p sl="es">Le vote aura lieu mardi 22 mai 2012.</p>
      <p sl="es">Déclarations écrites (article 149)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-147-500" speaker_id="26829" name="Siiri OVIIR" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Estonia" birth_date="03-11-1947" birth_place="Tallinn" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="EE">
      <p sl="es">kirjalikult . – Türgi kui ELi kandidaatriik on kohustatud järgima ühenduse väärtusi ja õigustikku. On positiivne, et naiste õigusi käsitlev seadustik on suurelt jaolt kehtestatud. Täna ollakse staadiumis, kus neid ka juba rakendatakse. On positiivne, et tööle on asunud pere-ja sotsiaalpoliitika ministeerium, parlamendis on moodustatud soolise võrdõiguslikkuse komisjon, vastu on võetud riiklikke tegevuskavu jms. Need ei ole pelgalt sõnad ega paberid, vaid kõik asjaomased ministrid teevad koostööd ja viivad ellu projekte, millega jõustatakse naiste elustandardi parandamist käsitlevaid õigusakte. Tõsisemaid probleeme on täna Türgis naistevastane perevägivald. Selles osas on õigusaktid veel lünklikud. Positiivne on aga see, et ühiskonna teadlikkus selles osas üha kasvab. Vastutustundlikult on käitunud meedia, kelle roll ühiskonna mõttelaadi muutmisel on hindamatu. Raportöör Emine Bozkurt on valmis saanud asjakohase ja asjatundliku raporti.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-148-000" speaker_id="96770" name="Joanna Katarzyna SKRZYDLEWSKA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="17-02-1977" birth_place="Łódź" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="es">na piśmie. – Sprawozdanie autorstwa Emine Bozkurt w sprawie przyszłości kobiet w Turcji jest niezwykle ważne ze względu na fakt, że w dokumencie tym poruszone zostały istotne kwestie, takie jak walka z przemocą wobec kobiet, zabójstwa honorowe, zjawisko wymuszanych małżeństw, a także eliminowanie analfabetyzmu wśród kobiet. Zwalczanie przemocy wobec kobiet jest jednym z głównych wyzwań stojących przed Turcją.</p>
      <p sl="es">Z zadowoleniem przyjmuję plany zwiększenia liczby ośrodków pomocy dla kobiet oraz utworzenia telefonicznych linii zaufania. Chciałabym jednak zaznaczyć, że oprócz zwiększania ilości środków doraźnych należy także podjąć wzmożone wysiłki mające na celu zmianę mentalności społecznej. Prowadzenie kampanii informacyjnych, poruszanie tematów równości płci w trakcie edukacji szkolnej oraz wdrożenie polityki zerowej tolerancji dla przemocy wobec kobiet, szczególnie w przypadku zabójstw honorowych i zmuszania do samobójstw honorowych, to niezbędne elementy w procesie zmiany statusu kobiet w Turcji.</p>
      <p sl="es">Z zadowoleniem przyjmuję fakt, że dysproporcje na tle płciowym na poziomie edukacji podstawowej zostały prawie całkowicie zlikwidowane, co na pewno przyczyni się do wyeliminowania negatywnego zjawiska, jakim jest analfabetyzm wśród kobiet. Apeluję jednak, aby zwrócono większą uwagę na szkolnictwo ponadpodstawowe, w dostępie do którego w dalszym ciągu istnieją znaczne różnice między kobietami i mężczyznami.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-149-000" speaker_id="96774" name="Jarosław WAŁĘSA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Poland" birth_date="13-09-1976" birth_place="Gdańsk" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="PL">
      <p sl="es">na piśmie . – Strategia Europa 2020 ma na celu przywrócić stan gospodarki sprzed kryzysu. Do zapewnienia konkurencyjnego rynku niezbędny jest udział kobiet w gospodarce. Turcja jako kraj kandydujący do Unii Europejskiej zobowiązana jest do przestrzegania praw człowieka oraz dalszego przeprowadzania i monitorowania wdrażania reform legislacyjnych. Należy cieszyć się ze stopniowo dokonującej się transformacji roli kobiety, jednak trzeba podjąć ogrom pracy w celu znormalizowania ich uczestnictwa szczególnie w społeczeństwie, gospodarce i polityce.</p>
      <p sl="es">Największym wyzwaniem dla Turcji jest zlikwidowanie przemocy wobec kobiet. Z danych ONZ z 2012 roku wynika, że 39% kobiet na jakimś etapie swojego życia doświadczyło przemocy. Niemniej w ostatnim czasie zauważalny jest wzrost poziomu świadomości tego problemu, o czym świadczy uruchomienie telefonicznej linii zaufania dla ofiar. Niezbędna jest jednak restrukturyzacja systemu ośrodków pomocy oraz prowadzenie polityki zerowej tolerancji dla przemocy wobec kobiet. Zauważalna jest poprawa poziomu wykształcenia kobiet, a ministerstwo edukacji podejmuje próby likwidowania języka seksistowskiego oraz stereotypów dotyczących ról społecznych w podręcznikach szkolnych.</p>
      <p sl="es">Rząd turecki postanowił wpłynąć na bardzo niską – 30% – stopę zatrudnienia kobiet poprzez wdrażanie reform. Przykładem zmian prawnych może być wprowadzenie poprawek do ordynacji wyborczej, która określałaby obowiązkowe minimum udziału kobiet w parlamencie krajowym, co pozwoliłoby na zwiększenie obecnej 14% reprezentacji w Wielkim Zgromadzeniu Narodowym Turcji. Wyżej wymienione działania dają nadzieję na zwiększenie roli kobiety w społeczeństwie tureckim.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-149-500" speaker_id="23894" name="Anna ZÁBORSKÁ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="07-06-1948" birth_place="Zürich" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="es">písomne – Samozrejme, aj ja plne podporujem výzvu, aby Turecko urobilo viac pre ochranu žien pred násilím. Zvlášť treba venovať pozornosť ženám – matkám, ktoré sú najviac zraniteľné. Táto správa je však viac o ideologických predsudkoch spravodajkyne, než o skutočných problémoch Turecka. Tak napríklad pre deti vo veku 0 až 5 rokov sú vraj lepšie štátne jasle, než starostlivosť milujúcej matky (bod 30). Samotné materstvo je vraj rodovým stereotypom a tureckí novinári by mali byť vyškolení k tomu, aby o ženách ako matkách mlčali (bod 66). Matky nepatria ani do čítaniek (bod 33). Pre prípad, že by rodičia s takýmto vyučovaním nesúhlasili, treba zakázať alternatívne vzdelávanie (bod 35). Ženy patria do fabrík a na polia, lebo žena – traktoristka je predsa viac, než žena, ktorá sa stará doma o deti (bod 46). Naozaj ide o – citujem – „zásadnú zmenu spôsobu myslenia“.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem20" title="20. Refuerzo de los derechos de los consumidores vulnerables (breve presentación)">
    <intervention id="1-151-000" speaker_id="96639" name="Isabelle DURANT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Belgium" birth_date="04-09-1954" birth_place="Bruxelles" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="BE">
      <p sl="es">L'ordre du jour appelle le rapport de María Irigoyen Pérez sur la stratégie de renforcement des droits des consommateurs vulnérables [2011/2272(INI) ] (A7-0155/2012).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-152-000" speaker_id="105192" name="María IRIGOYEN PÉREZ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Ponente" nationality="Spain" birth_date="01-10-1952" birth_place="Soria" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="ES">
      <p sl="es">Señora Presidenta, permítame, antes que nada, agradecer a todos mis colegas y, sobre todo, a las ponentes en la sombra la ayuda prestada para la elaboración de este informe, que ha hecho que salga muchísimo más reforzado.</p>
      <p sl="es">Todos sabemos que este año se cumple el vigésimo aniversario de la puesta en marcha del mercado único, que debe ser motor de la actividad económica y del crecimiento en Europa, clave para salir de la crisis y lograr los objetivos de la Europa 2020. En estos ocho años la construcción del mercado interior hay que hacerla compatible con su desarrollo, con un marco amplio de protección de los consumidores, con crecimiento y derechos que generen dinamismo y confianza, con transparencia –principio básico de la democracia y buen gobierno a la que esta tarde ha hecho referencia el Comisario Barnier– y con la cooperación entre la Comisión y el Parlamento.</p>
      <p sl="es">Es tiempo ahora de desarrollar el marco regulador relativo a la protección y la capacitación de los consumidores y, singularmente, de los consumidores vulnerables. Sabemos que la diversidad de las situaciones de vulnerabilidad, tanto las endógenas como las exógenas, dificulta la adopción de un instrumento legislativo global. Esto nos obliga a tratar el problema de la vulnerabilidad desde un análisis transversal que tenga en cuenta las distintas necesidades, capacidades y circunstancias de los consumidores.</p>
      <p sl="es">La Comisión, siendo consciente de las deficiencias actuales, ha centrado su estrategia en mejorar la información y la educación de los consumidores. Siendo una propuesta ambiciosa, no es suficiente para proteger a los consumidores vulnerables, porque su vulnerabilidad nace precisamente de su falta de asertividad y de comprensión de la información que reciben, o de las opciones disponibles, o de su desconocimiento de los sistemas de reclamación y compensación existentes, especialmente en el caso del consumo transfronterizo y en línea.</p>
      <p sl="es">Es por todo ello que, para solucionar las deficiencias, es decir, los problemas, es necesario adoptar una estrategia de refuerzo de los consumidores vulnerables y que tanto la Comisión como los Estados miembros introduzcan en sus legislaciones medidas específicas para garantizar una protección adecuada, que vaya más allá de la mera información, especialmente en aquellas materias donde se registra el mayor número de denuncias de los consumidores: el sector financiero, cuya complejidad implica que, en potencia, cualquier consumidor puede llegar a ser vulnerable.</p>
      <p sl="es">Por ello se pide a la industria de los servicios financieros que redoble los esfuerzos para proporcionar información comprensible, veraz, abundando en explicaciones claras y usando un lenguaje directo sobre la naturaleza de los productos y servicios que ofrece; al sector de la alimentación, en relación con la publicidad de los alimentos con alto contenido en grasas, sales y azúcares, informando a los niños y a los jóvenes, quienes son los más sensibles a la publicidad de estos alimentos; al sector del transporte, que sigue teniendo a menudo dificultades cuando viajan las personas vulnerables; al sector de la energía y las telecomunicaciones, donde la falta de transparencia provoca en algunos casos una dificultad añadida para los consumidores, por ejemplo, en el sector de la energía, a la hora de determinar la tarifa que más se ajusta a sus necesidades; en el acceso a la justicia, donde los consumidores pueden encontrar dificultades para acceder a los mecanismos existentes.</p>
      <p sl="es">Por ello se pide a la Comisión y a los Estados miembros -y permítame que haga una llamada de atención al Ministro de Justicia español, señor Gallardón, para que no retroceda en los derechos y vaya en sentido opuesto a la marcha de estos tiempos de dificultad- que pongan la inteligencia y el buen gobierno a favor de una resolución alternativa de litigios en materia de consumo.</p>
      <p sl="es">Por último, quisiera decir que cualquiera de nosotros somos susceptibles de convertirnos en consumidores vulnerables y agradecer a todos los ponentes alternativos la ayuda prestada para reforzar este informe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-154-000" speaker_id="96814" name="Elena BĂSESCU" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Romania" birth_date="24-04-1980" birth_place="Constanţa" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="RO">
      <p sl="es">Consider că este necesar să existe un nivel ridicat de protecţie pentru toate categoriile de consumatori, iar o atenţie suplimentară ar trebui acordată celor vulnerabili. Politica UE se axează pe protejarea şi promovarea drepturilor consumatorilor. Aceasta prezintă probleme importante în vederea consolidării pieţei unice precum şi pentru realizarea obiectivelor Strategiei Europa - 2020. Astfel, o strategie de garantare a siguranţei şi de consolidare a drepturilor consumatorilor este binevenită.</p>
      <p sl="es">Atrag atenţia asupra faptului că statele membre ar trebui să adopte măsuri specifice în vederea asigurării unei protecţii adecvate. În România, liberalizarea preţurilor la gaze şi energie presupune stabilirea consumatorilor vulnerabili în vederea protejării acestora de impactul ajustării de preţuri. Numărul lor este estimat între 1,15 şi 1,4 milioane.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-155-000" speaker_id="96718" name="Olga SEHNALOVÁ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Czechia" birth_date="25-10-1968" birth_place="Kromĕříž" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="CZ">
      <p sl="es">Paní předsedající, zpráva o strategii k posílení práv zranitelných spotřebitelů se věnuje široké škále otázek, kdy stávající situace na jednotném trhu nezaručuje evropským spotřebitelům dostatečnou ochranu.</p>
      <p sl="es">Zranitelným spotřebitelem je každý občan, který má ztížený přístup k informacím nezbytným pro vykonání příslušného nákupu, tedy svého rozhodnutí, nebo který informacím, jež jsou mu dostupné, jednoduše správně neporozumí. Ať už se jedná o prodej zboží na předváděcích akcích, uplatňování práva na reklamaci či nákup výrobků, které jsou v rámci jednotného trhu prodávány ve zdánlivě stejném balení, ale s leckdy odlišným složením, vždy se jedná o případy, kdy jsou spotřebitelé díky informační propasti nedostatečně chráněni. Proto považuji myšlenku zranitelného spotřebitele za opodstatněnou, protože spotřebitelská agenda musí tedy účinně řešit i tyto důležité otázky.</p>
      <p sl="es">Na závěr bych chtěla poděkovat zpravodajce Maríi Irigoyenové Pérezové za velmi kvalitně odvedenou práci na této zprávě.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-156-000" speaker_id="28178" name="Miroslav MIKOLÁŠIK" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="11-09-1952" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="es">Kategória zraniteľných spotrebiteľov alebo spotrebiteľov v zraniteľnej situácii si vyžaduje špeciálnu pozornosť príslušných orgánov a vypracovanie stratégie na ich ochranu. Súhlasím s prístupom spravodajkyne, ktorá uprednostnila nezameriavať sa na vytvorenie novej definície tzv. zraniteľného spotrebiteľa, ktorá by sa mohla stať dvojsečnou zbraňou. Podľa môjho názoru by politické a legislatívne nástroje mali pôsobiť preventívne na predchádzanie situáciám, kde je zraniteľnosť spotrebiteľov často a úmyselne zneužívaná. Zlepšovanie aj povedomia a informovanosti spotrebiteľov o svojich právach však treba doplniť aj zlepšením informovanosti o bezpečnosti tovarov a služieb. Pokiaľ ide o bezpečnosť výrobkov, špeciálne informačné kampane by mali byť zamerané na tehotné ženy a deti. Zároveň sa pripájam k výzve adresovanej Komisii, aby začlenila ochranu detí medzi hlavné priority spotrebiteľskej agendy a vypracovala analýzu vplyvu zavádzajúcej a agresívnej reklamy najmä na deti a dospievajúcich, ktorých zdravie pravidelne padá za obeť takýmto reklamám.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-157-000" speaker_id="96654" name="Jaroslav PAŠKA" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Slovakia" birth_date="20-06-1954" birth_place="Banská Štiavnica" p_group="Europe of freedom and democracy Group - Vice" m_state="SK">
      <p sl="es">Úvodom by som chcel oceniť túto správu, pretože naozaj si myslím, že je potrebné chrániť deti a staršie osoby pred rizikami trhu. V tejto súvislosti by som sa zameral na praktické riešenie, ktoré by sa dalo hneď v súčasnosti aplikovať. Na školách máme po celej Európe automaty, v ktorých sa predávajú sladké nápoje, sladké pečivo. Tieto automaty sú spravidla umiestnené pred jedálňami, ako príklad môžem uviesť Európsku školu, ktorá je v Bruseli, kde je to presne takto zorganizované. Možno keby sme prijali nariadenie, smernicu, ktorá by tieto produkty z automatov odstránila a nahradila ich napríklad ovocím, určite by to tým deťom prospelo. Rovnako by som mohol upozorniť na konkrétne riešenia, ktoré by sme mohli urobiť v súvislosti s certifikáciou potravín, pretože treba sprísniť dohľad a možno aj tie inštitúcie, ktoré v súčasnosti pracujú v jednotlivých krajinách a nefungujú celkom dobre. Mohol by som pripomenúť dioxínovú aféru v Nemecku, keď boli otrávené vajíčka, mäso a mäsové produkty. Tiež by som mohol spomenúť nedávnu aféru z Poľska s cestnou soľou, ktorá sa mala používať na posýpanie a údržbu ciest, bola však prebaľovaná a predávaná ako konzumná soľ a dostala sa do mäsa, rybacích konzerv a podobne. Takže podobné prípady by sa nestávali, keby sme mali lepšiu a menej deravú legislatívu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-159-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="John Dalli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="es">Member of the Commission . − Madam President, I am very pleased to note the considerable interest that Parliament clearly attaches to consumer issues. This is evidenced in several own-initiative reports that have been very helpful to the Commission in the preparation of the Consumer Agenda – our new consumer strategy – which we are presenting tomorrow.</p>
      <p sl="es">I would like to thank, in particular, the rapporteur, Mrs Irigoyen Pérez, and the shadow rapporteurs for their valuable work on this latest own-initiative report. Your input will contribute towards developing further actions for protecting and strengthening the rights of vulnerable consumers. The Commission wholeheartedly agrees that it is important to address the vulnerability of consumers, and this will be reflected in the Consumer Agenda.</p>
      <p sl="es">This initiative will present a coherent, strategic vision for consumer policy for the years to come, focusing on concrete measures that put consumers at the centre of the Single Market. Special attention will be paid to those markets also identified by the Parliament report as being particularly problematic for consumers. This includes financial services, energy, transport, telecommunications and the digital market.</p>
      <p sl="es">I would agree with Parliament’s view that it is not possible to encapsulate vulnerability in a single definition. Instead, we need to identify the various factors that can contribute to consumer vulnerability in specific markets or in particular circumstances. To this end, research and innovation have an important role to play. We are fully committed to mainstreaming the issue of vulnerability into market surveys and consumer studies, including consumer behaviour studies.</p>
      <p sl="es">As also pointed out by Parliament’s report, the concept of ‘vulnerable consumer’ has only been introduced relatively recently in European legislation. However, we already have in place provisions that safeguard the interests and rights of groups of consumers that can be considered more vulnerable in a structural sense – children, elderly people and people with disabilities.</p>
      <p sl="es">I can assure you that the Commission is constantly looking to improve these measures. I fully acknowledge that we also need to anticipate market developments and innovation to make sure that these also deliver benefits for vulnerable consumers.</p>
      <p sl="es">Let me briefly outline just some of the initiatives that the Commission has already brought forward and which focus on the specific areas highlighted by the report. These initiatives include: revising the General Product Safety Directive; evaluating the implementation of the Consumer Credit Directive; looking into ways of tackling the problem of over-indebtedness; and assessing the functioning of the Unfair Commercial Practices Directive, especially in the digital and financial markets.</p>
      <p sl="es">We will also further monitor and assess the application of the rules of the Audiovisual Media Services Directive in order to strengthen their effectiveness, in particular with regard to the protection of minors, across different audiovisual media environments. We are bringing forward a proposal on web accessibility. We have set up a Working Group across the Commission services on the exchange of best practices across Member States and long-term solutions and appropriate non-policy solutions that better target vulnerability in the area of energy.</p>
      <p sl="es">Finally, the Commission is launching guidelines on the application of the regulation on the rights of disabled persons and persons with reduced mobility when travelling by air.</p>
      <p sl="es">If vulnerable consumers are to be properly protected, Member States, businesses and intermediaries, such as consumer NGOs, also have an important role to play. There is a need for close cooperation and the active involvement of all the main stakeholders. We must collectively remain constantly vigilant to market and societal changes that increase the risk of exclusion for certain groups or individuals.</p>
      <p sl="es">To conclude, may I say once again that I very much appreciate the valuable report that Parliament has produced, and which I know will make an important contribution to the Commission’s work.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-160-000" speaker_id="96639" name="Isabelle DURANT" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Belgium" birth_date="04-09-1954" birth_place="Bruxelles" p_group="Group of the Greens/European Free Alliance" m_state="BE">
      <p sl="es">Le point est clos.</p>
      <p sl="es">Le vote aura lieu mardi 22 mai 2012.</p>
      <p sl="es">Déclarations écrites (article 149)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-160-500" speaker_id="4746" name="Sergio BERLATO" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Italy" birth_date="27-07-1959" birth_place="Vicenza" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="es">per iscritto . – L'appartenenza all'Unione europea garantisce ai cittadini un elemento di protezione poiché stabilisce un livello equivalente di sicurezza di diversi beni di consumo e introduce misure a protezione degli interessi generali del consumatore contro le pratiche sleali delle imprese, la pubblicità ingannevole e le clausole contrattuali abusive. Tuttavia, i consumatori vulnerabili o, in situazione di vulnerabilità, rappresentano un sottoinsieme della categoria generale dei consumatori che richiedono speciale protezione e una strategia specifica da parte delle autorità. Ritengo che la creazione di una strategia per il rafforzamento dei diritti dei consumatori più vulnerabili possa contribuire non solo alla loro inclusione sociale, ma anche a garantire un mercato interno più dinamico e competitivo. Convengo con il relatore sull'importanza di migliorare l'informazione dei consumatori affinché abbiano maggiore coscienza dei loro diritti, ma sottolineo anche che la pratica ha dimostrato come, di fatto, la vulnerabilità di molti consumatori derivi dalla mancata comprensione dell'informazione ricevuta o dalla loro ignoranza sulle prassi di reclamo e rimborso esistenti. Sollecito l'attenzione della Commissione affinché consideri l'opportunità di adottare misure legislative specifiche a garanzia di un'adeguata tutela dei consumatori vulnerabili che superino la mera informazione e che siano in armonia con il programma dei consumatori 2014-2020.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-161-000" speaker_id="102886" name="Ildikó GÁLL-PELCZ" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Hungary" birth_date="02-05-1962" birth_place="Szikszó" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="HU">
      <p sl="es">írásban . – Nem beszélhetünk hatékony fogyasztóvédelemről akkor, amikor a fogyasztók továbbra is azt érzik, hogy ki vannak szolgáltatva az egyes vállalkozásoknak, amikor nem értik a szerződési feltételeket, vagy amikor jogvitájuk során alig remélhetnek védelmet.</p>
      <p sl="es">Ugyanakkor úgy gondolom, hogy a hatékony fogyasztóvédelem nem létezhet együttműködő és fogyasztóbarát vállalkozások nélkül. Itt szeretném jelezni, hogy ennek megerősítésére hamarosan benyújtok egy írásbeli nyilatkozatot egy fogyasztóbarát, vállalkozásbarát védjegy megteremtése érdekében, ugyanis mint azt a fogyasztói panaszok is mutatják, a fogyasztók még mindig saját bőrükön érzik azt az egyensúlytalanságot és teljes kiszolgáltatottságot, mely a fogyasztói és a vállalkozói oldal között fennáll fogyasztói érdeksérelem esetén. Ezen pedig elsősorban – de nem kizárólagosan – a jogszabályok olyan mértékű és minőségű módosítása segíthet, amilyenre egyelőre nem került sor.</p>
      <p sl="es">Végül, de nem utolsósorban nem mehetek el szó nélkül a fogyasztók tudatossága mellett, amely az erős és hatékony fogyasztóvédelem alapja. Tudatosság nélkül nincs megelőzés, prevenció nélkül pedig nem létezhet védelem. Ezért – kezdve már a fiatalok oktatásától egészen az idősebb korosztály segítéséig – szükséges, hogy a fogyasztók tudják, hogy jogvita esetén mely szervezetektől remélhetnek segítséget.</p>
      <p sl="es">Perez asszony saját kezdeményezésű jelentése példaértékű, hiszen egy nagyon érzékeny, sürgősen kezelendő területet érint. Köszönöm szépen a jelentéstevő rendkívül időszerű megállapításait, pozitív szavazatommal én mindenképp támogatom e jelentést!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-160-750" speaker_id="96760" name="Tiziano MOTTI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Italy" birth_date="07-02-1966" birth_place="Reggio Emilia" p_group="Group of the European People's Party (Christian Democrats)" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="es">per iscritto. – Presidente, voglio intervenire a proposito della proposta di risoluzione del Parlamento europeo che mira a rafforzare i diritti dei consumatori vulnerabili. Considero importante definire con chiarezza chi sono i consumatori vulnerabili, perché se da un lato vengono considerati tali coloro che hanno una disabilità mentale, fisica o psicologica, per la giovane età o per l`età più avanzata, dall`altro non dobbiamo dimenticare anche coloro che si trovano in uno stato temporaneo di vulnerabilità dovuto a situazioni contingenti. In tutti i casi dobbiamo sempre e comunque fornire al consumatore tutti i mezzi necessari per garantire che possa prendere le decisioni giuste e farsi valere. Questo include dare tutte le informazioni riguardanti i prodotti in maniera accessibile e comprensibile, spiegare sempre tutte le opzioni a disposizione del consumatore, come per esempio i sistemi esistenti di reclamo e di rimborso. Un cenno a parte meritano i bambini e gli adolescenti che sono soggetti spesso alla pubblicità ingannevole ed aggressiva che dovrebbe essere maggiormente controllata, penso per esempio a quella relativa ai prodotti alimentari destinati all`infanzia. Un ultimo punto che voglio ricordare è l`importanza di un accesso facile alla giustizia per chi ha diritto di ricevere un indennizzo per un danno subito.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-161-500" speaker_id="38602" name="Vladko Todorov PANAYOTOV" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Bulgaria" birth_date="07-05-1950" birth_place="Pavlikeni" p_group="Group of the Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe" m_state="BG">
      <p sl="es">in writing . – The EU and its internal market provide the highest protection in the world to its consumers. Thanks to strict principles, the internal market has created many fair and secure opportunities for producers as well as for consumers. As the rules of the internal market are evolving along with its fast development, the concept of the vulnerable consumer and the necessity to set up special protection are assuming more and more importance in the political agenda. Indeed, in order for the internal market to stay fair and secure, it is crucial to highlight the vulnerability of some consumers and to tackle disloyal practices which aim to take advantage of this vulnerability. But types of vulnerability are various and take different shapes which can be very subtle and therefore hard for the legislator to delimitate. This report does not point out a clear definition or specific sanctions but it carefully outlines and enumerates what can be considered to be the consumer’s vulnerability. It is a big step towards a better understanding of this concept and thus a big step towards taking over this issue.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-162-000" speaker_id="96865" name="Debora SERRACCHIANI" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Italy" birth_date="10-11-1970" birth_place="Roma" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="IT">
      <p sl="es">per iscritto . – Tutti i consumatori sono suscettibili di diventare vulnerabili nel corso della loro vita sia per cause endogene, inerenti all'individuo e alla sua condizione culturale e psicofisica, sia per cause esogene, inerenti alla oggettiva difficoltà di accesso alle informazioni. Da qui nasce la necessità di una maggiore e speciale protezione per i consumatori vulnerabili, che tenga conto delle loro pecularietà. Particolare attenzione va data ai disabili e alle persone a mobilità ridotta, soprattutto nel settore dei trasporti, mentre devono essere migliorati i diritti dei passeggeri garantendo la trasparenza delle informazioni e delle tariffe nel momento dell'acquisto di un biglietto.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-162-500" speaker_id="111014" name="Josef WEIDENHOLZER" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" nationality="Austria" birth_date="06-03-1950" birth_place="St. Florian am Inn" p_group="Group of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament" m_state="AT">
      <p sl="es">schriftlich . – Ein größtmögliches Ausmaß an öffentlicher Sicherheit herzustellen ist ein wichtiges Ziel europäischer Politik. Die ISS Strategie ist eine wesentliche Voraussetzung für eine effektive Verbrechensprävention und zeigt auch, dass die europäischen Institutionen in der Lage sind, wichtige Bedrohungspotentiale zu erkennen und strategische Optionen zu entwickeln. Deren Umsetzung bedarf allerdings eines steten Bemühens, das vor allem auch eine stärkere Einbindung der nationalen Sicherheitsbehörden erfordert. Der Ausbau eines effektiven Systems innerer Sicherheit darf allerdings nicht losgelöst von der gesellschaftlichen Entwicklung in Europa gesehen werden. Die sozialwissenschaftliche Forschung hat wiederholt, jüngst etwa durch die bahnbrechenden Arbeiten von Richard Wilkinson und Kate Picket, darauf aufmerksam gemacht, dass ein hohes Ausmaß an sozialer Sicherheit zu einer niedrigeren Kriminalitätsrate führt. Eine Strategie der EU zur inneren Sicherheit sollte daher diese Grundvoraussetzung berücksichtigen und darauf explizit hinweisen. Vor allem, weil auch andere Politikbereiche über diese Zusammenhänge Kenntnis erlangen sollten. Die gegenwärtige Fiskalpolitik etwa konterkariert mit ihren Maßnahmen, die immer auch eine Reduktion sozialer Leistungen nach sich ziehen, genau diesen Zusammenhang.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem21" title="21. Orden del día de la próxima sesión"/>
  <section id="creitem22" title="22. Cierre de la sesión"/>
</text>
